<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4156</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4156Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4156" type="letter">
        <head>4156. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LockerEdwardHawke">Edward Hawke Locker</ref>, <date when="1824-03-13">13 March 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Edward Hawke Locker Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c.<lb />
               Seal: red wax<lb />
               MS: Huntington Library, LR 326. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: W. A. Speck, &#8216;Robert Southey&#8217;s Letters to Edward Hawke Locker&#8217;, <title>Huntington Library Quarterly</title>, 62.1&#8211;2 (1999), 162&#8211;163 [in part].<lb />
               Note on MS: This letter is written on a sheet of paper printed at the head with the following: TO BE/ PUBLISHED/ BY/ SUBSCRIPTION, IN THREE VOLS. OCTAVO,/ PRICE, &#163;2. S2./ (The money to be paid on delivery,)/ A CHRONOLOGICAL HISTORY OF THE/ WEST INDIES,/ BY CAPTAIN THOMAS SOUTHEY, COMMANDER/ ROYAL NAVY. [Tom Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827) was finally published by Longmans.]</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-03-13"> 13 March. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>  My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">You will do me a great kindness if you can procure some subscriptions for what will be a very respectable book, made with great care upon a plan which I suggested, &amp; with a good deal of my assistance. The subject includes the whole of the islands, Spanish, French &amp;c. &amp; therefore can only be treated in that chronological form which is common enough in the French language, but of which Andrewes,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">James Pettit Andrews (1737&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of Great Britain, Connected with the Chronology of Europe from Caesar&#8217;s Invasion to the Accession of Edward VI</title> (1794&#8211;1795), no. 166 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> I think, has given the only English specimen. A great body of facts will be brought together in the only practicable order, &amp; I shall intersperse general views</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What you say of my Book,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> both from yourself, &amp; from the Bishop of Durham,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Shute Barrington (1734&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Durham 1791&#8211;1826.</note> gratifies me as it ought to do. It would not be difficult for me to give references in some future edition; but I really felt that the scale of the work seemed neither to require nor justify it. A sketch of our Church History was all that the limits of the work (tho extended to thrice the original design) would allow: &amp; in that, I thought that while the inferences were my own the facts were too notorious to stand in need of any vouchers. This ground I have for trusting <del>that</del> it may be useful, that I am sure it would have been most essentially so to me, if such a work had been put into my hands in my youth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am persuaded that it might be of considerable use if there were a Professor of English History in each of our Universities &amp; if the divinity students were examined as to their knowledge of the ecclesiastical, &#8211; &amp; all other in the <del>civil</del> political part. Our institutions are depreciated because they are not understood.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I past <del>four &amp; twen</del> six &amp; thirty hours at Cambridge during my travels. It is to be hoped that what they are doing there will excite a spirit of emulation at Oxford; &#8211; the sight of such buildings rising in every direction<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The expansion of undergraduate numbers after 1815 led to new buildings being erected in Cambridge by, among others, King&#8217;s, Trinity, St John&#8217;s, Corpus and Peterhouse Colleges.</note> gave me, tho an Oxonian, a feeling of English delight, such as I have seldom experienced. Still the enlargement of the old Universities appears to me less desirable than the foundation of a new one in these northern parts, &#8211; at Durham, or at Hexham.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Durham University was founded in 1832, though Southey would have preferred it to be based at Hexham.</note> And if we had a Prime Minister with <ref type="m" target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Percevals</ref> principles &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Percevals</ref> warmth of heart, I should not despair of seeing such a measure effected However nothing is to be despaired of. Give peace in our time O Lord,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A quotation from the morning and evening service in the Church of England&#8217;s <title>Book of Common Prayer</title> (1662).</note> &amp; <del>xx</del> we may then obtain every thing which is desirable. The better spirit is prevailing, &amp; we must not relax in our endeavours to keep it up.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeWilliamHart">The Bp of Barbadoes</ref> acts like <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberReginald">Reginald Heber</ref>, solely from a sense of duty.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hart Coleridge became Bishop of Barbados and the Leeward Islands in 1824, while Reginald Heber became Bishop of Calcutta in 1823.</note> He is the only child of an infirm &amp; aged mother, who was left a widow when he was an infant.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hart Coleridge was the only child of Luke Herman Coleridge (1765&#8211;1790), a surgeon and brother of Samuel Taylor Coleridge, and Sarah Hart (c. 1770&#8211;1830).</note> He &lt;<del>xxxx</del>&gt; had a respectable fortune, &amp; was in the high road to preferment. What a set of people he is going among! As a diocese Botany Bay would be a Paradise in comparison.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Botany Bay was a penal settlement in New South Wales, founded in 1788. At this time, all of Australia was part of the Diocese of Calcutta and did not receive its own bishop until 1836. Southey was a long-standing opponent of the slave trade and held a low view of the planters of the West Indies. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Present my kind regards to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LockerEleanor">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Locker</ref>, </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">&amp; believe me my dear friend</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">  Yours most truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">  Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>