<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4165</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4165Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4165" type="letter">
        <head>4165. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ClercqWillem">Willem de Clercq</ref>, <date when="1824-04">[c. early] April 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: S &amp; P de Clercq/ Amsterdam/ for/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Willem de Clercq<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmarks: Engel[illegible]; F 24/ 40<lb />
               Endorsement: Keswick April 1824/ R Southey/ ontv. d% d<hi rend="sup">y</hi>o/ beantw: 17 d<hi rend="sup">y</hi>o<lb />
               MS: University of Amsterdam, Special Collections, OTM hs RA F LXXIII A 10. ALS, 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.<lb />
               Dating note: The endorsement indicates that Southey&#8217;s letter had been received before 17 April 1824, when de Clercq replied to it. Allowing for the international mail service the letter probably dates from early April. We have therefore placed it at the start of the month. </p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-04">April. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>  Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  Accept my thanks for your obliging letter, &amp; for your Essay upon the character of the Cid,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Willem de Clercq, &#8216;De Cid, Voorgesteld als Het Ideaal van den Held der Middeleeuwen&#8217;, originally published in <title>Magazijn voor Wetenschappen, Kunsten en Lettern</title>, 3 (1824), 192&#8211;244.</note> &#8211; a subject which cannot fail to interest me. Ruydiez de Bivar<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Rodrigo Diaz de Vivar (c. 1043&#8211;1099), the Castilian nobleman and military leader known as &#8216;El Cid&#8217;.</note> was indeed what you describe him, &#8211; the model of knighthood in the ruder age of chivalry. A few generations later we have the character a little more refined (&amp; but little) in our Richard Coeur de Lion.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard I (1157&#8211;1199; King of England 1189&#8211;1199; <title>DNB</title>).</note> You find it in perfection in the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, in the Black Prince,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward &#8216;the Black Prince&#8217; (1330&#8211;1376; <title>DNB</title>), Prince of Wales 1343&#8211;1376 and heir to the English throne.</note> &amp; in a still higher degree in the Portugueze hero Nuno Alvares Pereira,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">St Nuno Alvares Pereira (1360&#8211;1431), the Portuguese general who secured Portugal&#8217;s independence from Castile. In later life he became a Carmelite friar and was beatified in 1918 and canonised in 2009.</note> from whom <del>I cannot be</del> it appears to me highly probable that the character of Amadis was drawn; that romance (as I have <hi rend="ital">proved</hi>) having been written by one who was his countryman &amp; fellow soldier<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had translated the medieval Iberian romance <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803) and had argued that its original author was Vasco de Lobeira (d. 1403), who had fought with Alvares Pereira at the Battle of Aljubarotta (1385).</note>. A full account of this most admirable man will be given in my History of Portugal.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s unfinished &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your literature Sir, is little known in England, not because it is despised, but because the language is difficult, &amp; books in it only rarely &amp; accidentally to be obtained. My knowledge of Dutch is merely such as <del>xx</del> enables me to understand the plain straight forward style of Aitzema,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieuwe van Aitzema (1600&#8211;1669), <title>Sakem van Staet en Oorlogh in emde Omtrent de Vereenigde Nederlanden</title> (1655&#8211;1671), with the continuation by Lambert van den Bos (1610&#8211;1698), <title>Historien onses Tyds</title> (1685&#8211;1699), no. 214 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Valentyn<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Fran&#231;ois Valentijn (1666&#8211;1727), <title>Oud en Niew Oost-Indien</title> (1724&#8211;1726), no. 2892 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; Pieter Bor.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Pieter Christiaensz Bor (1559&#8211;1635), <title>Histoire der Nederlandtsche Oorlogen</title> (1679), no. 463 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> A little I have read of Jacob Cats,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacob Cats (1577&#8211;1660), <title>Alle de Wercken</title> (1726), no. 687 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> a little of Vondel;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Joost van den Vondel (1587&#8211;1679), 17 volumes of whose works were no. 3091 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> enough to show me that the former must in his own country be the most delightful of <hi rend="ital">household poets</hi>, &amp; that the latter was truly a master of his art. It appears to me more than likely that Milton was excited by the perusal of Vondel to undertake both his Samson Agonistes, &amp; his Paradise Lost.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey considered Vondel&#8217;s <title>Lucifer</title> (1654), <title>Adam in Ballingschap</title> (1664) and <title>Samson of Heilige Wraeck</title> (1660) to be influences on John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Paradise Lost</title> (1667) and <title>Samson Agonistes</title> (1671).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Permit me now to solicit some information from you concerning your literature, which may be useful to me in my various pursuits. In my History of Brazil<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> I have made use of Nieuhoff,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Johan Nieuhof (1618&#8211;1672), <title>Gedenkweerdige Brasiliaense Zee-en-Lant-Reise</title> (1693), no. 1934 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Aitzema, &amp; J. de Laet&#8217;s Historie van de West Indische Compagnie<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Joannes de Laet (1581&#8211;1649), <title>Historie ofte Jaerlyk Verhael van de Verrichtinghen der Geoctroyeerde West-Indische Compagnie</title> (1644), no. 1671 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> (in the second edition of my first volume, &#8211; which contains many important additions.)<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The second edition of the first volume of the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1822).</note> What other books are there in your language which relate to your war in Brazil? &#8211; I am writing the History of the late great war in the Peninsula.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> Have any memoirs concerning it been published in Du[MS missing]e One German one I have obtained,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Der Feldzug von Portugall, in den Jahren 1811 and 1812, in Historischer und Medizinischer-Hinsicht Beschrieben, von einem Artze der Franzosischen Armee von Portugall</title> (1816). Southey had bought this work on his continental tour in 1817.</note> &amp; only one, &#8211; [MS missing]k<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">A pencil annotation in the left-hand margin reads &#8216;work&#8217;.</note> of a surgeon in Massena&#8217;s army,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Andr&#233; Massena (1758&#8211;1817) commanded the invasion of Portugal in 1810&#8211;1811.</note> printed at Stutgard. &#8211; I am collecting materials for the Life of George Fox, &amp; the Rise &amp; Progress of Quakerism.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write his proposed life of George Fox (1624&#8211;1691; <title>DNB</title>), founder of Quakerism.</note> The best history of the Quakers was published both in Dutch &amp; English by Sewel.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Willem Sewel (1653&#8211;1720; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Histori van de Opkompste, Aanwas en Voortgang der Christenen bekend by den naam van Quakers</title> (1717), translated as <title>The History of the Rise, Increase, and Progress of the Christian People called Quakers</title> (1722), no. 2639 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> There is also a Latin one by Gerard Croese.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Gerard Croese (1642&#8211;1710), <title>Historia Quakeriana</title> (1695). Southey possessed the English translation of 1696, no. 393 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> What other works have you upon this subject? The early Quakers were much connected with Holland, &amp; I should think some curious materials must exist in your language. A year or two hence, it is not unlikely, that I may cross the channel &amp; look for them, &#8211; for I have long been desirous of seeing your country.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey visited the Low Countries in 1825 and 1826.</note> Meantime I avail myself eagerly of the opportunity which you have afforded me for opening a literary communication with it. And I trust you will believe that I do not put questions of this kind more freely, than I should gladly answer any which you may wish to propose in return.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How much I am gratified by M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Bilderdyjks translation of Roderick, by the affecting poem which she has addresst to me,<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Katherina Bilderdijk, n&#233;e Schweickhardt (1776&#8211;1830), <title>Rodrigo de Goth, Koning van Spanje</title>, 2 vols (The Hague, 1823&#8211;1824), I, pp. i&#8211;xii, no. 2701 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, where it was described as &#8216;<hi rend="ital">red morocco, gilt leaves</hi>&#8217;. This was a translation of Southey&#8217;s <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> &amp; by the commendations of such a person as <ref type="m" target="people.html#BilderdijkWillem">her husband</ref>, &#8211; it would be difficult to express. I have written to make my acknowledgements, &amp; to enquire thro what channel I may transmit a small packet.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey intended to send the Bilderdijks a copy of Richard Westall (1765&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths, by R. Southey. Illustrated with Engravings from the Designs of R. W.</title> (1824), nos 2627&#8211;2628 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">   My address, Sir, is <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, Cumberland, &#8211; where I should be truly happy to see you, should you ever visit this most beautiful part of England</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">I remain Sir<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent2">            your obliged &amp; obedient servant<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3">  Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>