<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4168" type="letter"><head>4168. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Susannah Rickman</ref>, <date when="1824-04-07">7 April [1824]</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman<lb/>
               Endorsement: R Southey to SR <lb/>
               MS: The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Wilson Library, James Saxon Childers Papers. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Dating note: The year is derived from the content; see Southey to Susannah Rickman, 12 April 1824, Letter 4172.</note></head>
            
            
          <opener>  <salute>My dear Madam</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">  One of those mishaps has occurred concerning <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Berthas</ref> journey which are always likely <del>when</del> in complicated affairs. The Lady<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Tolson (dates unknown). She was from a Cumberland family and had set up business in High Holborn, London, as a ‘linen-draper, dealer and chapwoman’. Declared bankrupt on 8 July 1826, she started a new business in Regent Street as a ‘milliner and dress maker’ only to go bankrupt again on 16 May 1828.</note> who was to take charge of her as this day, had an Aunt;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> &#38; that Aunt died the other day; so that her departure <del>was</del> &#60;is&#62; put off till Monday next. At any other time such a delay would have been of no consequence whatever: but falling as it does in the Passion Week,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The week leading up to Easter Sunday; in 1824 this was 11–18 April.</note> by a curious infelicity of circumstances every person who could have received <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> on her arrival, is likely to be out of town. There was a forlorn hope of obtaining convoy for her tomorrow but it has failed. And now, unless we should hear from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> that she has devised something, – the expedition must of necessity be postponed till another opportunity can be found.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  The only consolation for this is that she would not have been in the best condition for undertaking such a journey to day; having hardly recovered from a very prevalent catarrh which, I am sorry to say, has taken me by the nose also.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> With kindest remembrances from <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> who has allowed me to write for her while she is occupied with a guest –</p>
           <closer> <salute rend="indent1">I remain</salute>
         <salute rend="indent2">   Dear Madam</salute>
           <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs most truly</salute>
           <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey</signed></closer>
           <postscript> <lb/>
            <p rend="indent0"><date when="1824-04-07">Wednesday 7 April.</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
