<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4170Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4170" type="letter">
        <head>4170. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>,<date when="1824-04-09"> 9 April 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: xxxx To Miss Caroline Bowles <lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 3p. <lb />
               Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 55&#8211;56 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-04-09">9 Apr. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">   Nearly a fortnight has elapsed since I received your letter with the notices which I requested.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles had sent Southey information about her first cousin Paul Henry Durell Burrard (1790&#8211;1809), Ensign in the 1st Foot Guards, who was mortally wounded at the Battle of Corunna (1809). Southey used this to compose &#8216;Lines. To the Memory of a Young Officer, Who was Mortally Wounded in the Battle of Coru&#241;a. By Robert Southey, Esq. Poet Laureate&#8217;, <title>The Literary Souvenir; Or, Cabinet of Poetry and Romance</title> (London, 1826), pp. [341]&#8211;344.</note> They are exceedingly affecting, &#8211; so much so indeed as to make me feel how flat &amp; unprofitable any composition must appear when compared with the plain narration of such circumstances. However what I am contemplating will not be liable to any such comparison, &#8211; otherwise I might well be deterred from the attempt. &#8211; In my youth, the more striking <del>xxx</del> a story appeared to me, the stronger was my inclination to clothe it in verse; whereas in later years the feeling that circumstances affecting in themselves are more likely to be marred than rendered more so by versifying them, has repeatedly withheld my hand. &#8211; But for this subject, it will not be out of mind till I see how to cast it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The vexatious part of your prosecution is the expence:<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles&#8217;s outhouses had been burgled and she was worried about the prospect of prosecuting the offenders at Winchester Assizes.</note> otherwise I should be hardly be sorry for so flagrant an instance of the egregious absurdity &amp; injustice of our laws, such as they are in practice. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">        Since your letter arrived I have been engaged at one time with the prevalent catarrh (- not my annual visitor, or it would not have left me so easily, or so soon) &#8211; &amp; afterwards with an unexpected guest.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Wade Browne (1796&#8211;1851), only son of Wade Browne and later a country gentleman at Monkton Farleigh in Somerset. He had been travelling in the Near East.</note> &#8211; I send you now a few more stanzas,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Stanzas for Bowles and Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Robin Hood&#8217;. The resulting incomplete work was published in <title>Robin Hood: a Fragment. By the Late Robert Southey, and Caroline Southey. With Other Fragments and Poems By R.S. and C.S.</title> (London, 1847), pp. [1]&#8211;36.</note> &#8211; the next batch will probably conclude the canto &#8211; Send me some in return, &#8211; &amp; take up the story where you will; &#8211; in the next canto if you like it, &#8211; with the infancy &amp; childhood of the orphan, &#8211; &amp; conclude it with the return of the few forlorn survivors who bring home their Lords heart. I shall proceed with the better will when I am assured that you are at work</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Such resemblances in sound as that between <hi rend="ital">faith</hi> &amp; <hi rend="ital">fate</hi>, I <del>xxx xxx</del> gladly avail myself of, when they occur without the appearance of being sought for. The use of alliteration in our poetry is as old as that of rhyme, indeed it supplies the place of rhyme in <del>that</del> one form of verse, &#8211; that in which Pierce Ploughmans Vision is written.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">William Langland (c. 1332&#8211;c. 1386; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Piers Ploughman</title> (c. 1370&#8211;c. 1390), written in unrhymed alliterative verse. Southey possessed an edition from 1550, no. 1414 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> Like every other artifice in versification it has been overdone, &amp; thereby rendered disgusting. I was a great offender in this way in my boyhood, before I learnt the use of my tools. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">    You asked me why <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara C.</ref> did not rather begin with Joinville or Du Guesclin<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean de Joinville (1224&#8211;1317), <title>Livre des Sainte Paroles et des Bons Faiz de Nostre Saint Roy Looys</title> (c. 1305&#8211;1309), a work on Louis IX (1214&#8211;1270; King of France 1226&#8211;1270); and <title>La Vie Valliant de Bertran du Guesclin</title> (c. 1380&#8211;1392), a rhymed chronicle of the life of Bertrand du Guesclin (c. 1320&#8211;1380), a Breton knight in the Hundred Years War.</note> than with Bayard<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Sara Coleridge&#8217;s translation, <title>The Right Joyous and Pleasant History of the Feats, Gests, and Prowesses of the Chevalier Bayard, the Good Knight without Fear and without Reproach</title> (1825).</note> &#8211; Because Bayards<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Pierre Terrail, Seigneur de Bayard (1473&#8211;1524), French knight.</note> is a popular name, &#8211; &amp; Joinville had been translated about fifteen years ago by Johnes of Hafod,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Johnes (1748&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of John Lord de Joinville, Grand Seneschal of Champagne, Written by Himself: Containing a History of Part of the Life of Louis IX</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; villainously enough Heaven knows, never man having more liking for such works, with less taste.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">A Lady has translated Roderick into Dutch verse, &amp; dedicated it to me in verse also.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Katherina Bilderdijk, n&#233;e Schweickhardt (1776&#8211;1830), <title>Rodrigo de Goth, Koning van Spanje</title>, 2 vols (The Hague, 1823&#8211;1824), I, pp. i&#8211;xii, no. 2701 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, where it was described as &#8216;<hi rend="ital">red morocco, gilt leaves</hi>&#8217;. This was a translation of Southey&#8217;s <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#BilderdijkWillem">Her husband</ref> is the most eminent man of his age as a poet &amp; critic &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BilderdijkWillem">Bilderdijk</ref> by name &amp; the translation appears to be very well done: that is &#8211; I can see it is true to the original, &amp; the husband assures me of its merits in other respects. The dedication would please you, as it does me. She has lost a son at sea,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Julius Willem Bilderdijk (1798&#8211;1818). He died from fever during a journey from China to the Dutch East Indies.</note> I know not whether in battle or by course of nature, &amp; she describes in these verses, how while she hoped for his return, she used to apply that part of the poem about Alphonso &amp; his mother to her own heart.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Rodrigo de Goth, Koning van Spanje</title>, 2 vols (The Hague, 1823&#8211;1824), I, pp. vii&#8211;viii. Alphonso I (c. 693&#8211;757; King of Asturias 739&#8211;757) is a character in Southey&#8217;s <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814). In Book 11 he unexpectedly returns to his mother, having escaped from Moorish territory.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you &#8211; dear Caroline</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>