<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4177Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4177Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4177" type="letter">
        <head>4177. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-04-26">26 April 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS was not available to the editors, but it forms part of an album kept by members of the Goulburn, Goldsmid and associated families, sold at Bonhams, London, 21 March 2018, Lot 24; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856). <lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 414&#8211;416.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
          </address>
          <date when="1824-04-26">April 26. 1824.</date>
          <salute>My dear Harry,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  If <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> should deposit at your house a set of the engravings for &#8220;Roderick,&#8221;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814). Richard Westall, <title>Illustrations of Roderick, the Last of the Goths. A Poem, by Robert Southey, Esq. from the Drawings of R. Westall, R.A.</title> (1824), nos 2627&#8211;2628 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Longman published the latter and purchasers could arrange for the six engravings to be bound into their copy of <title>Roderick</title>. Southey invested in this venture.</note> which I wish to send to my Dutch translatress,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Katherina Bilderdijk, n&#233;e Schweickhardt (1776&#8211;1830), <title>Rodrigo de Goth, Koning van Spanje</title>, 2 vols (The Hague, 1823&#8211;1824), I, pp. i&#8211;xii, no. 2701 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, where it was described as &#8216;<hi rend="ital">red morocco, gilt leaves</hi>&#8217;. This was a translation of Southey&#8217;s <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> will you have the goodness to transmit them to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, whom I have intrusted to pack them up with a copy of the &#8220;Book of the Church,&#8221;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> and despatch the parcel. I had a note from him, the other day, saying he had put a second edition of that book to the press. Whether the engravings are published I do not know.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am profiting by the communication with Holland. A very well&#8211;informed <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClercqWillem">Mr. Willem de Clercq</ref> shows a great disposition to correspond with me, and answer my enquiries de <hi rend="ital">omnibus rebus et quibusdam aliis</hi>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;of all things and some others&#8217;.</note> Oh, that I had such a correspondent at Lisbon, or at Madrid! I find him, however, very useful, and shall request <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> forthwith to procure for me some German works upon the Peninsular War, which he has pointed out.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The bibliography of his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), III, p. 936, suggests that Southey was probably seeking: Hermann von Staff (1790&#8211;1867), <title>Der Befreiungs&#8211;Krieg der Katalonier, in den Jahren 1808 bis 1814</title> (1821&#8211;1827); and Franz Xaver Rigel (1783&#8211;1852), <title>Die Siebenjahrige Kampf auf der Pyrenaischen Halbinsel vom Jahre 1807 bis 1814; besonders miene eigenen Erfahrungen in disem Kriege; nebst Bemerkungen uber das Spanische Volk und Land</title> (1819&#8211;1821), no. 2442 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> You would be amused at his letters, which are written in very odd English; but I wish I could read Dutch as well.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> is to return to Palace Yard this day; we have just heard from her. She has been so unwell in Sussex as to lie in bed one whole day and great part of the next, &#8211; the effect, I suppose, of too much travelling and excitement.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">   In reply to a question, how she liked the South Downs? her answer is, &#8220;To tell the truth, I quite despise them, they are just like little molehills.&#8221; What airs these young mountaineers give themselves! When she is a little older, she will understand that downs are not to be compared with mountains, and learn to enjoy any scenery that is really enjoyable, &#8211; and there is very little natural scenery which is not so.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Having given up all hope of getting Olivares&#8217;s &#8220;History of the War in Catalonia,&#8221;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford&#8217;s &#8216;On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez&#8217;, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221&#8211;223. It mentioned Olivarez&#8217;s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title>, published in four volumes at Seville in 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &amp; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877 and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had then written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832), and Herbert Hill had also offered to help. Southey had then sought the assistance of George Canning. Finally, Southey had written to John Mitford, 12 April 1824, Letter 4171.</note> I have to&#8211;day set upon that part of my subject from such materials as I possess, and the second volume, accordingly, will go to press in a few days.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What will become of Portugal with such a creature as D. Miguel<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Michael I (1802&#8211;1866; King of Portugal 1828&#8211;1834). He was the second surviving son of John VI (1767&#8211;1826; King of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826), but was likely to succeed his father as his elder brother, Peter IV (1798&#8211;1834; King of Portugal March&#8211;May 1826), had become Emperor of Brazil 1822&#8211;1831. Michael was an extreme reactionary and was shortly to be exiled for plotting a coup against his father.</note> for heir&#8211;apparent! He seems very much to resemble Affonso VI.,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Afonso VI (1643&#8211;1683; King of Portugal 1656&#8211;1683). In 1668 he was declared incapable, and power passed to a regency.</note> if there be any truth in such accounts as get into the newspapers. And his brother in Brazil is of the same stamp. Did I tell you that one of this Emperor&#8217;s amusements is <hi rend="ital">to ride negroes with spurs</hi>? With regard both to the Braganzas and the Spanish Bourbons,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Braganzas had been the ruling dynasty of Portugal since 1640, while the Bourbons had ruled Spain since 1700.</note> I fear Jupiter has determined to destroy them; for he has certainly taken away their senses!<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">As in the proverb, &#8216;Whom Jupiter would ruin, he first makes mad&#8217;. Jupiter was the King of the Roman gods and this is a neo-Latinised version from the seventeenth century of a Greek saying. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A little encouragement would make me think seriously of a <title>Book of the State</title>,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write this book.</note> &#8211; tracing the course of political events with the view of showing their effect upon the condition and progress of society.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How is <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref>? how are the children?<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey, Jnr (b. 1817), Charles Gonne Southey (1819&#8211;1861) and Henry Herbert Southey, Jnr (1822&#8211;1829).</note> My love to them. I wish you were all here to enjoy this delicious weather. God bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R.S.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>