<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4181Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4181Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4181" type="letter">
        <head>4181. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1824-05-03">3 May [1824] </date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>
            <lb />
               MS: Huntington Library, RS 450. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> I think has not noticed an ugly custom of the Anglo Saxons, &#8211; which I find in the Saxon Chronicle, &#8211; that of sometimes burning their prisoners alive.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">James Ingram (1774&#8211;1850; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Saxon Chronicle, with an English Translation and Notes, Critical and Explanatory. To which are added Chronological, Topographical and Glossarial Indices; a Short Grammar of the Anglo-Saxon Language; a New Map of England During the Heptarchy; Plates of Coins etc</title> (London, 1823), p. 58. Southey possessed two copies, nos 2593 and 2594 in the sale catalogue of his library. This information was not in Sharon Turner, <title>The History of the Anglo-Saxons from their First Appearance above the Elbe to the Death of Egbert</title> (1820). Southey possessed a second edition of this work from 1807, no. 2876 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#8211; The same thing was done in France, as late as the end of the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century. &#8211; In all ages generosity seems sometimes to have been displayed in war, but Marlborough<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough (1650&#8211;1722; <title>DNB</title>), the British commander in the War of the Spanish Succession.</note> seems to have <del>th</del> been the first General who introduced any thing like humanity.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am more than half inclined to write a view of our civil history, &#8211; upon such a scale &amp; plan as that <del>of</del> which I have given of the Church;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824). He did not write a book on Britain&#8217;s &#8216;civil history&#8217;.</note> with the special object of tracing the changes in the state of society, &amp; setting in a right point of view some things which are grossly &amp; mischievously misrepresented.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> writes in good spirits, full of your kindness, &amp; of the wonders she has seen.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the Demarara trial.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Smith (1790&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>) was sent to Demerara by the London Missionary Society and preached mainly to African slaves. Following the Demerara rebellion of 1823, he was tried before a court-martial in the colony and accused of fomenting discontent among local slaves. Smith was found guilty and sentenced to death. His death in prison in February 1824 produced an uproar in Britain. Southey had asked Rickman to provide him with &#8216;Papers Relating to Proceedings of Court Martial on Trial of J. Smith, Missionary, in the Colony of Demerara, October 1823&#8217; (1824), which Parliament had ordered to be printed. </note> Can you send me the Reports upon our Artisans &amp; Manufactures?<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Reports of Minutes of Evidence from the Select Committee on Artisans and Machinery (1824).</note> &#8211; I much regret that we did not find Morrison<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">James Morrison (1789&#8211;1857; <title>DNB</title>), an immensely wealthy businessman. His main business at this time was a general drapery firm in Fore Street, City of London. Southey had met him in the Lake District in September 1823.</note> when we went to look for him in Fore Street. It is plain that a great change in the whole system of trade is being brought about &#8211; by the employment of large capitals, &amp; I should very much have liked to have seen what the effect is in one <del>po</del> branch. Morrison considers the breaking up of all the small tradesmen as inevitable, &amp; as an evil. Eventual evil I do not see, as such persons would still be employed as agents, &amp; make the same sort of livelihood, without risk. &#8211; But these [MS obscured] wide subjects. Political economy indeed [MS obscured] metaphysics in more than one respect; &#8211; &amp; in none more than this, that who profess to understand it best are generally arrant humbugs.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <lb />
          <p rend="indent0">
            <date when="1824-05-03"> May 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>