<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4185. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 9 May 1824</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4185Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4185. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 9 May 1824</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4185Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4185" type="letter">
        <head>4185. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1824-05-09">9 May 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham,/ Surry<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmarks: E/ 12 MY 12/ 1824; [partial] 10 F NOON/ MY 12/ xx 24<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 242. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-05-09"> 9 May. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have no reason to complain of neglect in <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge ">Canning</ref>, or any one else, upon the score of my commission.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford&#8217;s &#8216;On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez&#8217;, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221&#8211;223. It mentioned Olivarez&#8217;s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title>, published in four volumes at Seville in 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &amp; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877 and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had then written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832), and Herbert Hill had also offered to help. Southey had then sought the assistance of George Canning. Finally, Southey had written to John Mitford, 12 April 1824, Letter 4171.</note> A letter from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Chinnery<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">George Robert Chinnery (1791&#8211;1825), a Treasury civil servant and secretary to George Canning&#8217;s embassy to Portugal in 1815. On 3 February 1824 he was appointed Resident Commissioner in Madrid for the Liquidation of British Claims on the Spanish Government, under the terms of a British-Spanish Convention (1823).</note> to whom he gave that commission, was duly transmitted by him to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, &amp; so to me; my instructions for a specific search at Seville were returned to Madrid thro the same official steps, &amp; the other day I received assurances that a son of Sir J Downies<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Downie (1777&#8211;1826), Assistant Commissary of the British Army in Portugal 1808&#8211;1810. Downie founded the Legion of Extramadura from Spanish irregular forces in 1810 and was made a colonel in the Spanish Army. He was Commander of the Alcazar, the royal palace and military fortress in Seville, 1814&#8211;1826. As Downie had only married in 1810 it is unlikely that a son of his would be enquiring for Southey&#8217;s books in Seville.</note> was going to Seville, &amp; would there enquire for the books; &#8211; that a certain Friar, who knew more concerning books than is commonly known by Friars, would be applied to, &amp; that if the books were not to be found on sale, application would be made to individuals for them. Nevertheless I shall not delay longer, &#8211; &amp; have only laid aside that portion of my subject for the present, that I may provide by a paper in the QR. for my Midsummer bills<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of John Johnson (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263&#8211;311.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">    The slip of the pen concerning Charles 5 has been corrected,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, p. 8, where Charles V (1500&#8211;1558; Holy Roman Emperor 1519&#8211;1556, King of Spain 1516&#8211;1556) was misidentified as the brother, rather than the nephew, of Catherine of Aragon (1485&#8211;1536; <title>DNB</title>), first wife of Henry VIII (1491&#8211;1547; King of England 1509&#8211;1547; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; a slip of the press where Henri <hi rend="ital">4</hi> is put instead of H. <hi rend="ital">3</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, p. 341, where Henry IV (1553&#8211;1610; King of France 1589&#8211;1610) was misprinted for Henry III (1551&#8211;1589; King of France 1574&#8211;1589).</note> There has been a cry on all sides for references. I cannot afford leisure to make them at present. And there has been a less reasonable cry for dates, &#8211; as if in such a book the succession of the Sovereigns was not a sufficient chronological indication. There is a report at Taunton that the book has been bought up, &#8211; because it did not please all parties: &amp; that I have consented to have it thus withdrawn, upon receiving 1000 &#163; for such consent. This is the wise story which the Taunton Bookseller<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly John Poole (c. 1754&#8211;1841), bookseller and printer at Taunton since the late eighteenth century.</note> assured <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt Mary</ref> to be matter of fact, adding that in consequence the work was much more enquired for. Why it should have been set afloat it is impossible to conjecture, but the bookseller must have known that what he was repeating <del>xx</del> was not <del>only</del> &lt;merely&gt; a lie, but an absurd &amp; an impossible lie. It is however as harmless as it is unaccountable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been sitting closely to work, so that my second volume<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> will proceed rapidly when the printing begins. Moreover I have made considerable progress with the Tale of Paraguay,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> &amp; have added two Inscriptions to my Peninsular series<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s inscriptions on the Peninsular War, most of which were unpublished until the eighteen finished poems were collected in <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), III, pp. 122&#8211;156. Southey had just finished &#8216;Lines. To the Memory of a Young Officer, Who was Mortally Wounded in the Battle of Coru&#241;a. By Robert Southey, Esq. Poet Laureate&#8217;. This was published in <title>The Literary Souvenir; Or, Cabinet of Poetry and Romance</title> (London, 1826), pp. [341]&#8211;344. The identity of the other poem that Southey had been working on is less clear; it might have been &#8216;Inscription for a Monument at Arroyo, in Molina. By Robert Southey, Esq., Poet Laureate&#8217;, <title>Friendship&#8217;s Offering. A Literary Album</title> (London, 1827), pp. [147]&#8211;148.</note> (amounting now to 19) &#8211; when the history is compleated I shall probably let <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> publish them in the quarto <del>volume</del> form to accompany it, &#8211; for those persons who may be pleased to purchase verse as well as prose. To unite such a series is a task of singular difficulty.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should have been heartily glad to have seen M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Michell<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Sampson Michell (1755&#8211;1809) was a British sailor who rose to be an Admiral in the Portuguese Navy. His wife, Ann Shears (1765&#8211;1838), was the daughter of a surgeon at Bedminster and a granddaughter of Emmanuel Collins (fl. 1732&#8211;1762), a clergyman, alehouse-keeper, poet and schoolmaster, who had taught Herbert Hill.</note> had she made her visit to Peckham while I was about town. It is to be hoped your household affairs will soon be in order again: of all discomforts that of inhabiting a house which is undergoing a revolution is one of the greatest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> I hope begins by this time to be reconciled to strange scenes &amp; strange places, for so timid &amp; retiring a disposition it was a great trial; but she will be the better for it, &amp; she could not have been committed to kinder keeping. I am sorry however that she &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">her sister</ref> will be absent during <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edwards</ref> visit, &#8211; for we shall miss them in our lake &amp; mountain parties. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> indeed I miss in more ways than one. &#8211; It is a comfort to think that <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edwards</ref> year of servitude is almost over.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hill was a pupil at Westminster School and had passed &#8216;The Challenge&#8217; to become a King&#8217;s Scholar and member of &#8216;College&#8217;, a group of forty boys with their own accommodation, special dress and privileges, including the right to proceed to a Closed Scholarship at Trinity College, Cambridge, or Christ Church, Oxford. However, he had been bullied in his first year in College.</note> It will make a great difference in his situation</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunts</ref> case whatever occupies &amp; amuses her mind is likely to do good, &#8211; &amp; the sea may do this. Change of air I believe to be very often effectual where medicine can do nothing, &#8211; &amp; I wish you had gone with her instead of remaining in dirt, &amp; discomfort, &amp; in the unwholesome stink of the paint.</p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
            RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>