<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4186</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4186Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4186" type="letter">
        <head>4186. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1824-05-10">10 May 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Miss Bowles/ Buckland/ Lymington/ Hampshire<lb />
               Endorsements: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 53 To Miss Caroline Bowles; Keswick. 10 May 1824<lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 4p. <lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Were you to see sometimes how doggedly I sit down to a stanza for the Paraguay tale,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> &#8211; the pen drying half a dozen times before I get thro two lines of it, &amp; the brain dry as the grey-goose quill, &amp; not so easily moistened, &#8211; you would <del>not</del> perceive that want of ideas, &amp; want of fancy &amp; want of power, are no more proofs of incapacity, &#8211; than an empty purse is a proof of poverty, &#8211; our wealth is not always at command. One of these dry fits has come upon me in this first canto,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Bowles were beginning work on &#8216;Robin Hood&#8217;. The resulting incomplete poem was published in <title>Robin Hood: a Fragment. By the Late Robert Southey, and Caroline Southey. With Other Fragments and Poems By R.S. and C.S.</title> (London, 1847), pp. [1]&#8211;36.</note> &#8211; at a time too when I especially wished to get thro it, that I might begin the second upon your groundwork. Bear a part you most assuredly will; &amp; this you will feel when better health brings with it better spirits. Try at some descriptive sketches in the metre, &#8211; such as painters make in a little pocket book to be introduced into their pictures. If after all you like better to write in rhyme, what is done may easily be translated, &#8211; in proof of the practicability &#8211; the first seventy pages of Kehama underwent this metamorphosis.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> &#8211; Something I did this morning &#8211; drily enough, &#8211; but I shall get on, &#8211; &amp; you shall have every fragment.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Gratified I am indeed at what you say of those monumental verses.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s commemoration of Paul Henry Durell Burrard (1790&#8211;1809), an Ensign in the 1st Foot Guards, who was mortally wounded at the Battle of Corunna (1809). He was Caroline Bowles&#8217;s first cousin. Southey&#8217;s poem was entitled &#8216;Lines. To the Memory of a Young Officer, Who was Mortally Wounded in the Battle of Coru&#241;a. By Robert Southey, Esq. Poet Laureate&#8217;, <title>The Literary Souvenir; Or, Cabinet of Poetry and Romance</title> (London, 1826), pp. [341]&#8211;344.</note> This is one of the proper uses of poetry, &#8211; &amp; the impulse which has thus been given is very likely to accelerate the progress of the series.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s inscriptions on the Peninsular War, most of which were unpublished until the eighteen finished poems were collected in <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), III, pp. 122&#8211;156. Southey originally planned to write thirty inscriptions.</note> I have added another since,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The identity of the other poem that Southey had been working on is less clear; it might have been &#8216;Inscription for a Monument at Arroyo, in Molina. By Robert Southey, Esq., Poet Laureate&#8217;, <title>Friendship&#8217;s Offering. A Literary Album</title> (London, 1827), pp. [147]&#8211;148.</note> making the number nineteen, something more than half of what are intended.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I believe the delay of that first letter was occasioned by its arriving in town when <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> had taken flight during the Easter recess.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Parliament was not sitting 16 April&#8211;2 May 1824, over the Easter period, and this suspended Rickman&#8217;s ability to frank mail.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Your adventure with the Satirist is an amusing one.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles had been sent a satirical poem on Southey by a &#8216;Captain of Lancers, who has taken it into his head to turn author&#8217;. She declined to give any opinion on the poem and returned it to the author; see Caroline Bowles to Southey, 5 May 1824, Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), p. 60.</note> I remember writing in a printed satire of this kind, many years ago, these lines from a play of Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Davenant, &#8211; for myself &amp; the friends<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">William Wordsworth</ref>.</note> who were therein abused with me &#8211; </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Libels of such weak texture &amp; composure</l>
          <l rend="indent3">That we do all esteem it greater wrong</l>
          <l rend="indent3">To have our name extant in such paltry verse,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Than in the <del>sland</del> slanderous sense<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir William Davenant (1606&#8211;1668; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Cruel Brother</title> (1630), Act 1, scene 1, lines 193&#8211;196. Southey had written these lines in Richard Mant (1776&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Simpliciad: a Satirico-Didactico Poem</title> (1808), which attacked Southey, Coleridge and Wordsworth as leaders of the &#8216;Anti-Classical School&#8217;; see Southey to Neville White [fragment], 11 March 1810, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 1757.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">  I thank God that as I have among my friends some of the best &amp; wisest of their age, so I have for my enemies the veryest wretches that disparage nature. This Lancer is only a poor coxcomb &#8211; but I have them in all degrees of ass-ishness &#8211; &amp; in all degrees of baseness &amp; villainy, &#8211; from your Officer up to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Juan the Giaour</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you &#8211; </salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">  RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <lb />
          <p rend="indent0">
            <del>
              <date when="1824-05-10">10 May 1824</date>
            </del>
            <note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Deletion of the date is in another hand.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>