<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">4191Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4191" type="letter"><head>4191. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1824-05-27">27 May–26 June 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 7p.<lb/>
               Previously edited or published: Michael Neill Stanton, ‘An Edition of the Autobiographical Letters of Robert Southey’ (unpublished PhD, University of Rochester, 1972), pp. 150–164; <lb/>
               Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 100–113 [with variants; the text draws on a fair copy of the letter and not on the original version sent to May, which we publish here].</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <dateline><date when="1824-05-27">May 27. 1824.</date></dateline></opener>
		   
           <p rend="indent1"> Nearly four years have elapsed since I began this series of reminiscences, &#38; I have only written twelve letters, which bring me only into the twelfth year of my age. Alas this is not the only case in which I feel that the remaining portion of my life, were it even to be protracted longer than there is reason to expect upon the most favourable calculation of chances, must be too short for the undertakings which I have dreamt of compleating. It is however the case in which I can with least inconvenience quicken my speed, &#38; frail as by humiliating experience I know my own resolutions to be I will nevertheless endeavour to send off a letter from this <del>time</del> time forth at the <del>beginning</del> &#60;end&#62; of every month. Matter for one more will be afforded before I take leave of poor old William Williams;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William Williams (d. 1811), Southey’s schoolmaster at Merchants’ Hall School, Bristol, 1782–1786.</note> &#38; that part of it which has no relation to myself will not be the least worth relation.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">It was a good feature in his character that he had a number of poor retainers, who used to drop in at school hours, &#38; seldom went away empty-handed. There was one poor fellow familiarly called D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jones<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified beyond the information provided here.</note> who always set the school in a roar of laughter. What his real history was I know not; the story was that some mischievous boys had played upon him the dreadfully dangerous prank of giving him a dose of cantharides,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A preparation made from the dried bodies of blister beetles. It had many medical uses, including treating smallpox and as an aphrodisiac, but it could be poisonous in larger doses.</note> &#38; that he had lost his wits in consequence. I am not aware that it could have produced this effect, tho it might easily have cost him his life. Crazy however he was, or rather half crazed: &#38; it was such a merry craziness, that it would have been wishing him ill to wish him otherwise. The bliss of ignorance is merely negative; there was a positive happiness in his insanity; it was like a perpetual drunkenness, <del>kept a</del> sustained just at that degree of pleasurable excitement, which in the sense of present enjoyment is equally regardless of the future &#38; of the past. He fancied himself a poet, because he could produce upon demand a rhyme in the sorriest doggerel, &#38; the most celebrated improvisatore<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A performer of improvised poetry. This tradition was especially popular in Italy, where it had developed in the fourteenth century.</note> was never half so vain of his talent as this queer creature whose little figure of some five feet two I can perfectly call to mind, with his suit of rusty black, his more rusty wig, &#38; his old cocked hat. Whenever he entered the school room he was greeted with a shout of welcome, all business was suspended, <del>&#38; if</del> he was called upon from all sides to give us a rhyme, &#38; when the masters countenance offered any encouragement, he was intreated also to ask for half a holyday, which at the price of some <del>rhymes</del> &#60;doggerel&#62; was sometimes obtained. You will readily believe <del>that</del> he was a popular poet.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  <del>It is now become</del> The talent of composing imitative verses has become so common in our days, that it will require some evidence to make the next generation believe <del>that any</del> (what&#62; sort of verses were received as poetry fifty years ago &#60;when any thing in rhyme past current.&#62;. The magazines however contain proof of this; the very best of them <del>containing</del> &#60;abounding in&#62; such trash as would be rejected now by the provincial newspapers Whether the progress of society which <del>has</del> so greatly favours the growth &#38; developement of imitative talent, is equally favourable to the true poetical spirit, is a question which I may be led to consider hereafter. But as I had the good fortune to grow up in an age when poets, according to the old opinion, were born &#38; not made <del>so</del> – &#38; as at the time to which this part of my reminiscences relates, the bent of my nature had decidedly shown itself, I may here make some observations upon the grounds &#38; consequences of that opinion.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> In <del>former</del> the earliest ages certain it is that they who possessed that gift of <del>tongues</del> &#60;speech&#62; which enabled them to clothe ready thoughts in measured or elevated diction, were held to be inspired. False oracles were uttered in verse; &#38; true prophecies delivered in poetry. &#60;There was therefore some reason for the opinion.&#62; A belief akin to this prevails even now among the ignorant, &#38; was much more prevalent in my childhood, when very few of the lower classes could write or read &#38; when in the classes above these those who really were ignorant, knew that they were so. In dark ages slight of hand past for magic, slight of tongue for inspiration; &#38; the ignorant, &#60;when they were&#62; <del>tho</del> no longer <del>so ignorant as</del> to be thus deluded, still looked upon both as <del>something</del> extraordinary &#38; wonderful. The power <del>of</del> especially of arranging words in a manner altogether different from the common manner of speech, ( – a power which has now become as easy &#38; therefore is every day becoming more &#38; more a common acquirement,) appeared to them what it originally was in all poets &#38; always will be in those who are truly such: &#38; &#60;even now&#62; tho there are none who <del>now look upon</del> &#60;regard&#62; its possessor with superstitious reverence, there are still many who regard look upon him as <del>something</del> &#60;one who in the constitution of his mind is&#62; different from themselves. As no madman ever pretended to <del>inspiration</del> &#60;a religious call&#62; without finding some open-eared listeners ready to believe in him, so perhaps no one ever composed verses with facility, who had not in his own little circle some to admire &#38; applaud him. This was even the case with so poor a creature as D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jones. And to the intoxication of conceit which the honest admiration of the ignorant has produced in half crazed rhymers, like him, it is owing that some marvellous productions have found their way to the press.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jones was a doggrelist of the lowest kind. One other such I once met with, when I was young enough to be <del>infinitely</del> &#60;heartily&#62; amused<del>ent</del> with an exhibition which farcical as it was, would now make me mournful. He was a poor engraver by name Coyte,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph William Coyte (fl. 1780s–1810s).</note> very <del>harmless</del> &#60;simple&#62;, very industrious, very poor &#38; completely crazed with vanity because he could compose off-hand upon any subject such rhymes as the Bellmans<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Bellmen were minor parish officials; traditionally, they presented doggerel verses at Christmas, conveying seasonal good wishes to parishioners, in return for donations.</note> used to be. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Bedford’s father</ref> used to relieve him sometimes; I saw him on one of his visits to Brixton, when he was between 40 &#38; 50 years of age; &#38; his countenance &#38; manner <del>would</del> &#60;might&#62; have supplied Wilkie with a subject.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">David Wilkie (1785–1841; <title>DNB</title>), genre painter, especially of humorous and rustic characters. </note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford</ref> (- there never lived a kinder-hearted man,) loved merriment, &#38; played him off, – in which <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> joined &#38; I was not backward. We gave him subjects upon which he presently wrote three or four miserable couplets: <del>&#38;</del> no creature was ever more elated with <del>glory</del> &#60;triumph&#62; than he was at the hyperbolical commendations which he received, &#38; this mingled with the genuine humility which the sense of his condition occasioned, produced a truly comic mixture in his feelings &#38; gesticulations. What with pleasure inspiration &#38; exertion, &#60;&#38; warm weather, for it was in the dog days&#62;, he perspired, <del>like</del> &#60;as profusely, tho I dare say not as fragrantly, as&#62; an Elephant in love; &#38; literally overflowed at eyes &#38; mouth, frothing &#38; weeping <del>with delight</del> &#60;in <del>his</del> a salivation of happiness&#62;. I think this poor fellow published A Cockneys Rambles in the Country, some 12 or 14 years ago,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Cockney’s Adventures During a Ramble into the Country. A True Tale</title> (1811). See Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 20 October 1812, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2160.</note> for such a book I saw advertised by Joseph William Coyte, &#38; I sent for it at the time, – but it was too obscure to be found.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">These are examples of the very <del>lowest</del> &#60;humblest &#38; meanest) rhymesters, who nevertheless felt themselves raised above their companions, because they could rhyme. I have been acquainted with poets <del>of</del> &#60;in&#62; every intermediate degree between D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jones &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, &#38; their conceit has almost uniformly been precisely in an inverse proportion to their capacity. When this conceit acts upon low &#38; vulgar ignorance it produces direct craziness as in the instances &#60;of&#62; which I have been speaking. In the lower ranks of middle life I have seen it, without amounting to insanity, assume a form of such extravagant vanity, that the examples which have occurred within my own <del>kno</del> observation would be deemed incredible if brought forward in a farce. Of these in due time. <del>I will</del> There is another more curious manifestation of the same folly which I do not remember ever to have seen noticed but which is well worthy of critical observation, because it shows in its full extent &#38; &#60;therefore <hi rend="ital">in puris naturalibus</hi>&#62;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">‘in a purely natural state’.</note> a fault which is found in by much the greater part of modern poetry, – the use of words which have no signification when they are used, – &#60;or which if they mean any thing, mean nonsense, – &#62; the substitution of sound for sense. <del>The writers to whom I refer</del> I could show you passage after passage in contemporary writers, – the most popular which when critically, that is to say <del>fairly &#38;</del> &#60;strictly but&#62; justly examined, are as absolutely nonsensical as the description of a moonlight night in Popes Homer<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander Pope (1688–1744; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Iliad of Homer</title> (London, 1715–1720), Book 8, lines 687–697.</note> – Pope himself thought &#60;intended&#62; that &#60;for&#62; a fine description, &#38; did not perceive that it was as absurd as his own song by a Person of Quality.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander Pope, ‘Song. By a Person of Quality’ (1733), a burlesque.</note> Now there have been writers who have possessed the talent<del>xx</del> of stringing together couplet after couplet in sonorous verse, without any connection, &#38; without any meaning – or any <del>like</del> thing like a meaning, – &#38; yet they have had all the enjoyment of writing poetry, supposed that this was poetry &#38; published it as such. I know a man who has done this, &#38; who made me a present of his poem: &#38; yet he is very far from a fool, – on the contrary a lively pleasant companion, &#38; of talents which in conversation are considerably above par.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> The most perfect specimen I ever saw of such verses was a poem called the Shepherds Farewell,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">This poem is difficult to identify with certainty. However, J. Power Hicks in <title>Notes and Queries</title>, s8-III, issue 62, 4 March 1893, 167, suggested it might be <title>The Shepherd’s Festival</title> (n.d., but c. 1789), ‘printed in quarto, written to celebrate the recovery of George III and dedicated to Dr Willis’. The poem consists of 61 four-line stanzas over 23 pages.</note> printed in quarto some five &#38; thirty years ago. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> once had an imperfect copy of it, – I forget the authors name,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The poem <title>The Shepherd’s Festival</title> is anonymous.</note> but when I was first at Lisbon I found out that he was a schoolmaster, &#38; that poor Paul Berthon<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Berthons were a family of Huguenot refugees who became merchants in London and Portugal. Southey had met Paul Berthon (1775–1810) during his stay in Lisbon in 1796. Berthon went into his family’s business, joining the British Factory in Lisbon in 1799.</note> had been one of his pupils. Men of very inferior powers may imitate the manner of good writers with great success as – for example the two Smiths<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Horace (1779–1849; <title>DNB</title>) and James Smith (1775–1839; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Rejected Addresses, or, the New Theatrum Poetarum</title> (1812).</note> &#60;have done:&#62; but I do not believe that any imitative talent could produce genuine nonsense verses like those of the Shepherds Farewell: the intention of writing nonsensically would appear, &#38; show the meaning of the writer, – <del>th</del> pure involuntary unconscious nonsense is inimitable by any effort of sense.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Such writers as these if they were cross examined would be found to <del>believe in something like</del> &#60;imagine that they wrote under the influence of poetical&#62; inspiration, &#38; were Taylor the Pagan<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The philosopher, translator and neo-Platonist Thomas Taylor (1758–1835; <title>DNB</title>). </note> to set about heathenizing <del>a poet</del> one of them &#60;I am persuaded that&#62; he would not find it difficult to made him believe in the Muses.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek mythology, the nine Muses were the inspirational goddesses of literature, science and the arts.</note> In fact when this sort of conceit sets to work, the man is fairly beside-himself; an innate, self-produced <del>feeling not unlike that of</del> inebriety possesses him, – he abandons himself to it, &#38; while the fit lasts is as mad as a March hare. The madness is not permanent, because such inspiration, according to received opinion, only comes on when the rhymester is <del>at work</del> &#60;engaged&#62; in his vocation. But <del>woe to</del> &#60;the case is very different with&#62; him who has the gift of uttering prose with the same facility &#38; the same contempt of reason; for he in good earnest sets up for an inspired messenger, – he has received a <hi rend="ital">call</hi>, &#38; there are not only sects but Societies in this country ready to &#60;accredit him, &#38;&#62; take him into employ, &#38; send him out with a roving commission thro towns &#38; villages – to <del>dis</del> infect others with <del>xxxxxx</del> &#60;the most infectious of all forms of&#62; madness, disturb the peace of families, &#38; prepare the way for another <del>religious</del> attempt to overthrow the Established Church, – another struggle which will shake these kingdoms to their center. </p>
            <p rend="indent1">  D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jones has led me into a long digression, upon which I should not have entered if I had foreseen that it would have extended so far. Another of Williamss visitors &#38; an equally popular one was a glorious fellow, Pullen<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">John Pullen (dates unknown), a leather dresser whose business was at 134 Thomas Street in Bristol.</note> by name, who during the age of buckskin<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">By at least the 1750s, buckskin (i.e. deerskin) had become a fashionable material for clothing in Europe, especially for breeches and gloves.</note> made a fortune as a breeches-maker in Thomas Street. If I could paint a portrait from memory you should have his likeness. Alas that I can only give it in words, &#38; &#60;that&#62; that perfect figure should at this hour be preserved only in my recollections! <hi rend="ital">Sic transit gloria mundi</hi>!<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Thus passes the glory of the world’.</note> His countenance expressed all that can be expressed by human features of thorough-bred vulgarity, pride of purse, prosperity, good living, coarse humour, &#38; <del>coarse</del> &#60;boisterous&#62; good nature. He wore a white tye wig; his eyes were of the hue &#38; lustre of <del>boiled</del> &#60;scalded&#62; gooseberries: &#60;or oysters in sauce&#62; his complection was the deepest extract of the grape; <del>it had grown on the banks of the Douro</del>, he owed it to the Methuen treaty;<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">The Methuen Treaty (1703) between Britain and Portugal stimulated the Portuguese port industry by allowing Portuguese wines to enter Britain at a duty one third less than the duty charged on French wines. The treaty was named after Sir Paul Methuen (c. 1672–1756; <title>DNB</title>), British Minister to Portugal 1697–1704.</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> no doubt had seen it growing in his rides from Porto, &#38; Heaven knows how many pipes<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">A barrel of port; the average size is about 145 gallons.</note> must have been filtered thro the &#60;Pullenian&#62; system, before that fine permanent purple could have been fixed in his cheeks. He appeared always in buckskins of his own making, &#38; in boots; he would laugh at his own jests with a voice like Stentor supposing Stentor<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">A Greek herald in Homer’s <title>Iliad</title>, who possessed a voice more powerful than that of 50 men. </note> to have been hoarse, – &#38; then he would clap old Williams on the back with a hand like a shoulder of mutton &#60;you may imagine how great a man we thought him.&#62; They had probably been boon companions in their youth, &#38; his visits seldom failed to make the old man lay aside the schoolmaster. He was an excellent hand at demanding half-a-holyday, &#38; when he had succeeded always required three cheers for his success, in which he joined with all his might &#38; main. If I were a believer in the Romish Purgatory I should make no doubt that every visit which he made to that school room, was carried to the account of his good works. Some such set off he needed, – for he behaved with <del>strange</del> &#60;brutal&#62; unfeelingness to his son<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> who had offended him, &#38; &#60;who&#62; I believe would have starved had it not been for the charity of <ref type="m" target="people.html#MorganJohnJames">John Morgans</ref> mother,<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> an <del>singular</del> &#60;eccentric&#62; but thoroughly good woman, – &#38; one of those people whom I shall rejoice to meet in the next world. This I heard from her <del>thirteen or fourteen</del> &#60;several&#62; years <del>after later</del> &#60;afterwards&#62;. At this time Pullen was a widower, <del>about</del> between fifty &#38; sixty, – a hale, strong bodied man, upon whom his wine merchant might reckon for a considerable annuity for many years. He had purchased some lands adjacent to the Leppincott property, near Bristol,<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Stoke Bishop, north-west of Bristol. The Lippincotts lived at Stoke Bishop House.</note> in the pleasantest part of that fine neighbourhood. Sir Henry L.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Henry Lippincott, 1st Baronet (1737–1780), a Bristol tobacco merchant and briefly MP for Bristol 20 September–30 December 1780.</note> was elected member for the city at that election in which Burke<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Edmund Burke (1729–1797; <title>DNB</title>), the Irish author, philosopher and politician. He was MP for Bristol 1774–1780.</note> was turned out. He died soon afterwards, – his son was a mere child,<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Henry Cann Lippincott, 2nd Baronet (1776–1829).</note> &#38; Pullen, the glorious Pullen, in the plenitude of his pride, &#38; no doubt in a new pair of buckskins, called <del>one day</del> on the widow,<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Henry Lippincott had married, in 1774, Catherine Jefferies (dates unknown), heiress of her uncle, Sir Robert Cann, 6th Baronet (d. 1765).</note> introduced himself as the owner of the adjacent estate, &#38; upon that score without any farther ceremony <del>he offered himself</del> proposed <del>a union of bene</del> marriage, &#60;as an arrangement of mutual fitness&#62;. Lady Leppincott of course rung the bell, &#38; ordered her servants to turn him out of <del>doors</del> the house. This is a story which would be deemed too extravagant in a novel, &#38; yet you would believe it without the slightest hesitation if you had ever seen the incomparable Breeches Maker.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> These are comic recollections, the next <del>is</del> &#60;are&#62; of a different kind. Williams had two young kinswomen (I think they were his neices) by name Desmoulins, who kept a school in Kings Mead Square at Bath,<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1785 a Miss Desmoulins opened a school at Kingsmead House, Bath; see <title>Bath Chronicle</title>, 30 December 1784.</note> – pretty, interesting women, struggling with ill fortune. His writing master Gadd,<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">Lucy Des Moulins (b. 1758) is recorded as marrying a John Gadd (b. 1755).</note> married the younger, – &#38; I heard several years after that he had been villain enough to debauch the other, – in what farther misery &#38; guilt the tragedy ended I never chanced to learn. M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Esten<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors">Harriet Pye Esten (1761?–1865; <title>DNB</title>) was the illegitimate daughter of Admiral Sir Thomas Pye (1708/9–1785; <title>DNB</title>) and his housekeeper, the novelist Anna Maria Bennett (d. 1808; <title>DNB</title>). She married James Esten (dates unknown) in 1784, and turned to the stage after her husband became embroiled in financial difficulties. </note> the actress, whom you must remember, was connected with these sisters, &#38; was at that time preparing to make her first appearance on the stage, – at the Bristol theatre. The part she had chosen was Letitia Hardy in the Belles Stratagem,<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors">Esten made her debut at Bristol on 19 June 1786 in Nicholas Rowe’s (1674–1718; <title>DNB</title>) <title>Jane Shore</title> (1714). She appeared the next week, 26 June 1786, in Hannah Cowley’s (1743–1809; <title>DNB</title>) <title>The Belle’s Strategem</title> (1780).</note> &#38; in that part she had to dance a minuet-de-la-Cour,<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors">La Menuet de la Cour was a famous minuet choreographed by Maximilien Gardel (1741–1787) and first performed in his ballet, <title>Ninette a la Cour</title> (1777), and on the London stage in 1781.</note> to perfect herself in which, &#38; perhaps for the sake of accustoming herself to figure away before an audience, she came to <del>the</del> &#60;our&#62; school <del>two</del> on two or three dancing days &#38; took <del>a</del> lessons there, – a circumstance too remarkable to be forgotten in a schoolboys life. Walker the Dancing Master<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Thomas[?] Walker (fl. 1750–1790) who, in the <title>British Journal</title> on 2 January 1779, advertised his plan to open a dancing school in Bristol. He had previously worked as a teacher and performer in London, including at the Drury Lane Theatre.</note> was not a little proud of his pupil. That poor man <del>for</del> was for three years the plague of my life, – &#38; I was the plague of his. In some unhappy mood he had prevailed on <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref> to let me learn to dance, persuading himself as well as her that I should do credit to his teaching. It must have been for my sins that he formed this opinion: in evil hour for himself &#38; for me was it formed; he would have had less trouble in teaching a bear, &#38; far better success. I do not remember that I set out with any dislike, or contempt of dancing; but <del>in</del> the unconquerable incapacity which <del>I</del> it was soon evident that I possessed, produced both; &#38; the more he laboured to <del>make me</del> correct an incorrigible awkwardness, the more awkwardly of course I performed. I verily believe the fiddle stick was applied as much to my head as to the fiddle strings &#60;when I was called out&#62;; – but the rascal had a <del>xxx</del> &#60;worse&#62; way than that of punishing me, he would take my hands in his &#38; lead me down a dance, &#38; then the villain would apply his thumb nail against the flat surface of mine, in the middle, &#38; press it till he left the mark there, this species of torture I suppose to have been his own invention, &#38; so intolerable it was, that at last whenever he had recourse to it, I kicked his shins. Luckily for me he got into a scrape by beating a boy unmercifully at another school, so that he was afraid <del>of</del> &#60;to&#62; carry<del>ing</del> on this sort of contest, &#38; giving up at last all hope of ever making me a votary of the graces, or of the dancing Muse,<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editors">Terpsichore, the Greek Muse who was the goddess of dance and chorus.</note> he contented himself with shaking his head &#38; turning up his eyes in hopelessness whenever he noticed my performance. I had always Tom Madge<note n="39" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Madge (1772–1804), son of Stephen Madge (1735–1790), a captain in the East India Company’s service. Thomas Madge served in the Royal Navy but died young after a long illness.</note> for my partner – a poor fellow long since dead whom I remember with much kindness; – he was as active as a squirrel, but every limb seemed to be out of joint when he began to dance; – we were &#60;always placed as&#62; the last couple &#38; went thro our work with the dogged determination of never dancing more when we should once be delivered from the dancing master which resolution I have piously kept even unto this day.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  Williams who read well himself, &#38; prided himself upon it was one day very much offended with my reading, &#38; asked me scornfully who taught me to read. I answered – <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref>. Then said he, give my compliments to <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">your Aunt</ref>, &#38; tell her that my old horse who has been dead these twenty years could have taught you as well. I delivered the message faithfully to her great indignation. It was never forgotten, or forgiven, &#38; probably accelerated the very proper resolution of removing me. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> made known his intention of <del>sending</del> &#60;placing&#62; me at Westminster, his connection with Christ Church naturally led him to prefer this to any other school, hoping that I should get into College, &#38; so be elected off to a studentship.<note n="40" place="foot" resp="editors">Pupils at Westminster School could take ‘The Challenge’, a gruelling oral examination, that resulted in the election of a group of 40 King’s Scholars, who were taught apart from other boys in ‘College’. King’s Scholars could proceed to a Closed Scholarship at either Christ Church, Oxford, or Trinity College, Cambridge. There was no certainty that a King’s Scholar would receive a Fellowship, once he graduated from Trinity College, Cambridge. However, at Christ Church, a King’s Scholar immediately became one of the body of Students, with a modest stipend that was guaranteed for life, if the recipient wished and he obeyed the rules of the College. If they took university degrees in a timely fashion then their stipend would increase. The rules governing Studentships were strict and anyone who married, did not take Holy Orders or accepted a paid occupation had to resign.</note> But as I was in poor health, &#38; moreover had been very ill taught, it was thought advisable that I should be placed for twelvemonths under a clergyman competent to prepare me for a public school.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  Before I take leave of Williams, <del>xxx xx</del> two or three memoranda upon the slip of paper before me must be scored off. There was a washing tub in the play ground, with a long towel on a reel beside it: this tub was filled every morning, for the boarders to perform their ablutions <del>in</del>, – all in the same water: – &#38; whoever wished to wash his hands in the course of the day had no other. I was the only boy who had any repugnance to dip his hands in this pig-trough. – <del>so li</del> There was a large cask near which received the rain water, but there was no getting at the water, for the top was covered, &#38; to have taken out the spiggot would have been a punishable offence. <del>X</del> I however made a little hollow under the spiggott to receive the droppings, – just deep enough to wet the hand there, &#38; then I used to clean my hands with clean water, when they required it. But I do not remember that any one ever followed my example. I had acquired the <del>love</del> &#60;sense&#62; of cleanliness, &#60;&#38; love of it&#62; &#38; they had not.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">A time was remembered when there were wars of school against school, &#38; a great battle which had taken place in the adjoining park, between Williams’s boys, &#38; Foot’s my first Masters.<note n="41" place="foot" resp="editors">William Foot (d. 1781), a Bristol Baptist Minister, who ran a school at the top of St Michael’s Hill.</note> At both schools I heard of this, &#38; the victory was claimed by both, – for it was an old affair, a matter of tradition (not having been noticed <del>by</del> &#60;in&#62; history) long before my generation, or any who were then in the school, – but remembered as an event second only in importance, if second, to the war of Troy.<note n="42" place="foot" resp="editors">As described in Homer’s <title>Iliad</title>.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">  It was fully believed <del>by all th</del> in both these Bristol schools &#38; at Corston, that no bastard could span his own wrist. And I have no doubt this superstition prevailed throughout that part of England.</p>
            <lb/>
           <p rend="indent0"> <date when="1824-06-26">June 26. 1824.</date></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
