<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4192</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4192Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4192" type="letter">
        <head>4192. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1824-05-27">27 May 1824</date>
          </head><p>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 425&#8211;427.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-05-27">May 27. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Neville,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  I had heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> of my little godson&#8217;s perilous state,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Family histories, such as <title>The Homes and Haunts of Henry Kirke White; with some account of the family of White, of Nottingham and Norfolk</title> (London and Nottingham, 1908), p. 260, suggest that Neville White&#8217;s first son, christened Henry Kirke White (d. 1849), was born in 1821, but this information may be inaccurate, as Southey had stood as godfather to him in January 1824.</note> and did not like to write to you under the uncertainty concerning him. Precarious as human life always is, it is peculiarly so in infancy; but, on the other hand, recovery from the very brink of the grave is much more frequent than it is in any other stage of existence. To hope the best, and to be ready for the worst, is our duty in this, as, indeed, in all other cases; and it is a duty which you, I am sure, practise as well as preach. I will hope for good tidings, and shall be anxious to receive them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Now to the business part of your letter. But first, let me thank you for your good&#8211;will and exertions in <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother&#8217;s</ref> behalf, and say that any names which you may procure may be sent to me.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was canvassing subscribers for Tom Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I should very well like to edit Sir T. Browne&#8217;s works, write a biographical introduction, and add such Omniana notes as my stores may enable me to furnish.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Thomas Browne (1605&#8211;1682; <title>DNB</title>) was a doctor and writer on a huge range of subjects. Southey did not edit his works; however &#8216;The Whole Works and Correspondence of Sir Thomas Browne, Knt. M. D. of Norwich&#8217; was advertised as shortly forthcoming with Longmans, e.g. <title>London Courier and Evening Gazette</title>, 2 October 1824. This was an early indication of Simon Wilkin&#8217;s edition, which did not appear until 1835&#8211;1836. Southey acquired a copy and it became no. 376 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> That the speculation will answer to the publishers I am not so sure as Hudson Gurney<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Hudson Gurney (1775&#8211;1864; <title>DNB</title>), an antiquarian and poet from a prominent Quaker family in Norwich. He was a Whig MP for Shaftesbury 1812&#8211;1813, and Newtown, Isle of Wight 1816&#8211;1832. Sir Thomas Browne had been a famous Norwich resident.</note> seems to be; and this you should say to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilkinSimon">Mr. Wilkin</ref>. But the London booksellers must be the best judges upon a question of republication. I should be very far from allowing this concerning a new work. As to terms, I had two hundred guineas for editing the &#8220;Morte Arthur,&#8221;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s edition of Sir Thomas Malory (1415/18&#8211;1471; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Le Morte d&#8217;Arthur</title> (1485) was published as <title>The Byrth, Lyf and Actes of Kyng Arthur</title> (1817).</note> which was what <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> offered, being the sum they were to have given a certain person who was originally announced as editor, but left the book and the booksellers in the lurch, for the sake of decamping with another man&#8217;s wife.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Louis Goldsmid (1789&#8211;1835), a wealthy producer of fine editions of early romances and histories. His edition of <title>Le Morte d&#8217;Arthur </title>was being advertised by Longman up to 1815. Goldsmid had married Louisa Boscawen de Visme (1782&#8211;1862) in 1809 and the couple had three children, all of whom took their mother&#8217;s name.</note> So it is plain that in that sum nothing was allowed for a good name, if mine was not estimated at a better price than his. With that sum, however, I should be content, because I do not think the speculation could afford more; though, if the risk rested with London publishers, I would take all I could get, being richly entitled so to do from them. When I add, that I possess the folio edition of 1686 of Sir T.&#8217;s works,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Works of Sir Thomas Brown, Kt. Doctor of Physick, Late of Norwich</title> (1686). This does not appear in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> and no other, and nothing else of his writings, I shall have said all which, in this step of the business, it can be necessary to say.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is reasonable ground for hoping that a good deal may be recovered. Tenison speaks of other brief discourses, and of memorials which had been collected for writing his life.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Tenison (1636&#8211;1715; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;The Publisher to the Reader&#8217;, <title>Certain Miscellany Tracts. Written by Thomas Brown, Kt, and Doctor of Physick, Late of Norwich</title> (London, 1684) [unpaginated]: &#8216;There still remain other brief Discourses written by this most Learned and ingenious Author &#8230; There is on foot a design of writing his <title>Life</title>: and there are, already, some Memorials collected by some of his ancient Friends.&#8217;</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  One thing, however, must be taken into account in the terms. I had nothing to do with correcting the proofs of the &#8220;Morte Arthur;&#8221; and this is a matter of more importance with Sir Thomas Browne, owing to the peculiarity of his language, than with any other prose writer. Supposing that <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilkinSimon">Wilkin</ref> means to print the work himself, he must get some person who is a scholar (and an ordinary one will not do) to revise the sheets. The time which that task would require I cannot afford. Should this lead to any transmission of materials, the Quaker volume<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified, but for use in Southey&#8217;s planned, but unexecuted, life of George Fox (1624&#8211;1691; <title>DNB</title>), the founder of Quakerism.</note> may come and be returned with them; otherwise it may wait till I see <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref> once more. Express, I pray you, my thanks to its owner for this civility.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  It was a great disappointment to us not to see you. I had fully expected you, and wish <hi rend="ital">very</hi>, <hi rend="ital">very</hi> much you could still come, persuaded as I am that it would be greatly to your good.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  My paper in the last &#8220;Q.R.&#8221; was upon Dr. Dwight&#8217;s &#8220;Travels.&#8221;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752&#8211;1817), <title>Travels in New&#8211;England and New&#8211;York</title> (1821&#8211;1822), no. 881 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (October 1823), 1&#8211;40, published 17 April 1824. </note> There was nothing of mine in the preceding number. I am now reviewing &#8220;Hayley&#8217;s Memoirs:&#8221;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of John Johnson (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263&#8211;311, published 11 March 1825.</note> a poor, insipid book; but it has made me like the man, and he deserves to be treated with respect and kindness.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you, my dear Neville,<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent2">   Yours affectionately,<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3">   ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>