<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4198</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4198Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4198" type="letter">
        <head>4198. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1824-06-07">7 June 1824 </date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand, deletion and readdress in a second hand] London Tenth June 1824/ Miss Bowles/ &lt;78 High Street&gt;/ <del>Buckland</del> &lt;Cheltenham&gt;/ <del>Lymington</del> / Hants/ Fm/ JRickman<lb />
               Stamped: LYMINGTON 98	 <lb />
               Postmarks: FREE/ 10 JU 10/ 1824	<lb />
               Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 59. To Miss Caroline Bowles<lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 4p. <lb />
               Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 62&#8211;64. </p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-06-07">7. June. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I am under the visitation of my annual cold, which condemns me for a great part of every day to idleness. In the morning I do not rise before breakfast, because this visitor rises with me, &amp; very soon afterwards I am fain to lie back on the sopha, &amp; close my eyes, which have no complaint of their own, but are incapable of bearing the light while the membrane which lines the nose &amp; the throat are in a state of such extreme excitability. First I tried repose, &#8211; &amp; that almost long enough to disable me from exertion, by putting me what is called out of condition; &#8211; then I tried exercise, &#8211; &amp; am now again resigned to inaction &amp; a darkened room, with an upper lip which no razor dare approach, &amp; a proboscis half excoriated by the frequent visits of the pockethandkerchief. In 1799 when I had the first of these inveterate cararrhs (which I never failed to have every year since, except when I was in Portugal) &#8211; I write an Ode, upon it being at that time Poet Laureate to the Morning Post<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey quotes here the third stanza of his unpublished &#8216;Ode&#8217;; see Southey to Daniel Stuart, 19 December 1799, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 464. Southey wrote this when he was employed to provide poetry for the <title>Morning Post</title>, but it was not published in the newspaper.</note> &#8211; &amp; it is worthy of being transferred from the rough copy in my desk to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Ediths</ref> magnifico Album. Behold a specimen of it &#8211; </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Weave the warp &amp; weave the woof</l>
          <l rend="indent4">The pocket handkerchief for me; &#8211; </l>
          <l rend="indent3">Give ample room &amp; verse enough</l>
          <l rend="indent4">To hold the flowing sea.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Heard ye the din of trumpets bray &#8211; </l>
          <l rend="indent4">Nose to napkin, &#8211; nostril-force &#8211; </l>
          <l rend="indent3">Hot currents urge their way</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And thro the double fountain take their course.</l>
          <l rend="indent4">Mark the social hour of night</l>
          <l rend="indent3">When the house-roof shall echo with affright</l>
          <l rend="indent4">The sneeze&#8217;s sudden thunder.</l>
          <l rend="indent4">The neighbours rise in wonder,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">A room-quake follows; each upon his chair,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Starts at the fearful sound, &amp; interjects a prayer.</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent0"> Just half my life has elapsed since that Ode was written, &amp; among those parts of my character which remain unaffected by time, the love of nonsense &#8211; as you may perceive is one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Since you heard from me I have scarcely been able to write any thing except a review of Hayleys Memoirs<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of John Johnson (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263&#8211;311, published 11 March 1825.</note> which I went thro doggedly making what I could of materials not very good in themselves, &amp; miserably put together by their author. Having however some gratitude for Hayley for introducing me by his notes to the Spanish poets,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hayley, <title>An Essay on Epic Poetry; in Five Epistles to the Revd Mr. Mason. With Notes</title> (London, 1782), pp. 202&#8211;273, included accounts of the life and work of Lope F&#233;lix de Vega y Carpio (1562&#8211;1635) and Alonso de Ercilla y Zu&#241;iga (1533&#8211;1594), with quotations and translations.</note> &#8211; a good deal of respect for his love of literature &amp; the arts &amp; the country, &#8211; for his total exemption from all envious feelings, his attachment to his friends, &#8211; &amp; above all for his devotion to that poor son,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Alphonso Hayley (1780&#8211;1800; <title>DNB</title>), a sculptor.</note> &#8211; I have spoken of him in a style very different from the prevailing tone of magazines &amp; reviews.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You asked me once about <ref type="m" target="people.html#WollstonecraftMary">Mary Wollstonecraft</ref>. I had never seen her when that Dedication was written.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;To Mary Wollstonecraft&#8217;, <title>Poems</title> (Brisol, 1797), p. [3].</note> I saw her afterwards three or four times when she was M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Godwin; &#8211; &amp; never saw a woman, who would have been better fitted to do honour to her sex, if she had not fallen on evil times, &#8211; &amp; into evil hands. But it is hardly possible for any one to conceive what those times were, who has not lived in them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I wish <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor&#8217;s</ref> book<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title> (1824).</note> may fall in your way, still more do I wish that you could see Landor himself, &#8211; who talks as that book is written, &#8211; as if he spoke in thunder &amp; lightning. Such of the sheets as frightened <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorJohn">the publisher</ref> were sent to me, &amp; I struck out what would either have given most offence here, or endangered his personal safety where he is. How it is received I know not, &#8211; &amp; indeed I know nothing of what is going on in the world of London, except that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> is not yet ball-sick, &amp; &lt;that&gt; poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> I believe is home-sick. The former goes into Devonshire at the end of this month with Lady Malet,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, n&#233;e Wales (1779&#8211;1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; the latter to the neighbourhood of Portsmouth with the Rickmans;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Susannah Rickman</ref>.</note> &#8211; &amp; in case she should pass your way in any of their excursions &#8211; which is by no means unlikely, I shall tell her where <del>you</del> she may hope to <del>see</del> give you a passing call. &#8211; We are parching here for want of rain. &#8211; The &lt;History&gt; <del>H</del>
          <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Deletion and insertion in another hand.</note>of the W Indies is my brother <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom&#8217;s</ref>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Southey, <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827). Southey was seeking to raise subscriptions for its publication.</note> &#8211; I hear to day that <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles</ref> is out of health, &#8211; &amp; depressed by <del>his xxx</del> it. He is at present in London. &#8211; How are you? &amp; is your singing time come &#8211; for come it will. &#8211; Love from all here. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> would be delighted to see you, &amp; your Sultan also, &#8211; being a great admirer of what he used to call <hi rend="ital">oo</hi>dle<hi rend="ital">oos</hi>.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Owls; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 11 November 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3747.</note> Dear friend God bless you</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>