<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">4199Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4199" type="letter"><head>4199. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ParsonsWilliam">William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1824-06-15">15 June 1824 </date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major-General Peachy/ 80. Wimpole Street/ London.<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               MSS: British Library, Add MS 28603. AL; 4p. Berg Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 1p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Note on MSS: The letter survives as two manuscript fragments: the larger four-page fragment in the British Library (which comprises p. 1, and the top three quarters of pp. 3 and 4, including the address leaf); and the smaller one-page fragment in the Berg Collection (which comprises the lower quarter of pp. 3 and 4, including the closing signature).</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-06-15">15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June. 1824</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Your welcome letter of the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> would have been more welcome, if its contents had not led me to infer that you have no intention of visiting the Island this summer. Had you been here last year, you might have obtained full information concerning Jersey from <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Miss Bowles</ref>, who is by the mothers side of Jersey parentage.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles’s mother was Anne Burrard (1753–1817), the daughter of Madeleine Ann Durell (1728–1792) of Jersey. Madeleine Ann Durell’s parents were Jean Durell (1704–1739), Advocate-General of Jersey 1726–1739, and Anne Le Cloche (1709–1789), heiress of Longueville Manor. Caroline Bowles grew up in a household that included her grandmother, Madeleine Ann Durell, and great-grandmother, Anne Le Cloche, both of whom were bilingual in French and English.</note> By <hi rend="ital">her</hi> account I believe it is a delightful place, but where a state of happy &#38; enviable simplicity has of late years been altered without being improved. I am acquainted with only one account of this &#38; the neighbourhood Island, &#38; that account is nearly 200 years old, having been drawn up by Peter Heylyn,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Heylyn (1600–1662; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Survey of the Estate of France and Some of the Adjoyning Ilands</title> (1656), no. 1187 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. This work included an account of the Channel Islands that Heylyn wrote while he was chaplain to Henry Danvers, 1st Earl of Danby (1573–1643; <title>DNB</title>), Governor of Guernsey 1621–1644. It was on Danby’s recommendation to William Laud (1573–1645; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of London 1628–1633, Archbishop of Canterbury 1633–1645, that Heylyn was appointed a chaplain to Charles I (1600–1649; King of Great Britain 1625–1649; <title>DNB</title>) in 1630.</note> &#38; presented by him to Laud then Bp of London. It is historical, political &#38; ecclesiastical, &#38; Laud approved of it so highly that he recommended the Author to be one of the Kings Chaplains. This is a very able book, &#38; I have reason to regret that I had not read it before my Book of the Church<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> was published, – as it contains something of importance which must be inserted in some future edition of that work. – I am not acquainted with any <del>other</del> thing else upon the subject, except that there is an Account of Guernsey &#38; the other Channel Islands, by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Macculloch, in the first volume of the Geological Transactions, published in 1811.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John MacCulloch (1773–1835; <title>DNB</title>), ‘Account of Guernsey, and the other Channel Islands’, <title>Transactions of the Geological Society</title>, 1st series, 1 (1811), 1–22.</note> Probably this is merely a mineralogical paper; it may however be worth while to look at it, &#38; it is a book which you will be sure to find in the library of the Royal Institution.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Library of the Royal Institution of Great Britain (founded 1799) in Albemarle Street, London.</note> There is a new establishment of this kind, called the Metropolitan Literary Institution,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Metropolitan Literary Institution was founded in 1823 at 6 Chatham Place, London. Members could take advantage of a circulating and a reference library and a reading room, and attend lectures by invited speakers. Its Honorary Secretary was James Jennings.</note> &#38; they have been pleased to elect me an honorary member. To a person resident in town this might be of some advantage, &#38; I wish the usufruct could be transferred to some one who might profit by it.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  I am much obliged to you on the score of my brothers[Southey,Tom] book,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was seeking subscribers for Tom Southey, <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827).</note> &#38; should have to send his acknowledgements &#38; kind remembrances, if I had seen him since yours of the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> arrived. For myself, I have been now ten days a close prisoner with my annual catarrh, which has made its attack this year with its usual violence; but as its course has been more rapid than usual, I hope its departure will be proportionally speedier. It laid me up for the greater part of <del>the</del> a week upon the Sopha, in a darkened room, &#38; this is the first day that I have been able to pursue my wonted employments without intermission. It <del>hxxx xxxxx</del> is in my chest that I feel it now, where I trust it is not likely to remain long, – but it will be some time before I shall get into good condition, [MS missing] relaxed.</p>
           <p rend="indent0"> [MS missing] for it leaves me</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> has not written to me since he left England, – but I believe you may learn how to address him from Miss E Charter.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Charter (1782–1860), sister of William Peachy’s first wife, and friend of George Crabbe (1754–1832; <title>DNB</title>).</note> I am sorry to hear that <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles</ref> is out of health. Remember me to him most kindly, – &#38; tell him it will not be long before I shall show myself alive among the poets</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  We miss <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, as you may suppose, very much. As yet <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesThomas">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi></ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes</ref> are the only <del>strangers</del> &#60;Lakers&#62; we have seen. He is a Canon of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls – &#38; was tutor to three of the royal Dukes.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Hughes was tutor to three of George IV’s brothers: Ernest Augustus, Duke of Cumberland (1771–1851; <title>DNB</title>); Augustus Fredrick, Duke of Sussex (1773–1843; <title>DNB</title>); and Adolphus, Duke of Cambridge (1774–1850; <title>DNB</title>).</note> His son, who was of Oriel is the author of a very pleasant book concerning the South of France.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hughes (1790–1857; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Itinerary of Provence and the Rhone, Made During the Year 1819</title> (1822).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">  My library has lately been adorned by a cast from an ivory cup belonging to my friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, which <ref type="m" target="people.html#ChantreyFrancis">Chantry</ref> has pronounced to be the finest thing he ever saw of its kind, the cast indeed is of his making. The artist is not known, but it seems to be of Benvenuto Cellini’s<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Benvenuto Cellini (1500–1571), Italian goldsmith, sculptor and artist.</note> age, &#38; may not improbably be his work. The subject is Silenus &#38; a groupe of Bacchanals.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Silenus was a companion of Dionysus, the Greek god of wine; a bacchanal was a follower of Bacchus, the Roman equivalent of Dionysus.</note></p>
          <p rend="indent1">  I have sent my second vol. of the Peninsular War<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> to the press, – &#38; written a review of Hayleys Memoirs,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of John Johnson (1769–1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263–311, published 11 March 1825.</note> chiefly for the sake of treating a Gentleman &#38; a Scholar – as a Gentleman &#38; a Scholar ought to be treated. Our Ladies join in kindest remembrances to yourself, &#38; with me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref> – </p>
          <closer> <salute rend="indent1"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
         <salute rend="indent2">   yours with sincere regard</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
