<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4200Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4200" type="letter">
        <head>4200. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-06-15">15 June 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 18 JU 18/ 1823<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.330. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-06-15"> 15 June. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Thank you for your arrangement concerning the Herald.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had received a free copy of the daily evening newspaper, the <title>Courier</title>, because of Daniel Stuart&#8217;s association with the paper. Once Stuart sold his remaining shares in 1824 this arrangement ceased. Southey switched to the <title>Morning Herald</title> (1780&#8211;1869), a daily newspaper which at this time was non-aligned between Whigs and Tories. Its editorials were famously short &#8211; half a column.</note> The paper pleases me better than any other Morning Paper, <del>whxx</del> tho it scarcely ever manifests an opinion which I do not disapprove. But it keeps within decent bounds, &amp; the leading paragraph as it is the worst part, has generally the merit of being the most insignificant</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My cold made its appearance as usual with the first fine weather, &amp; I <del>x</del> soon felt the effect of the relaxation which it produced. <del>Last week I went</del> &lt;About&gt; a fortnight ago I went up Skiddaw with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesThomas">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
          </ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes</ref> &amp; was the better for it, but two days after we went with them by way of Watenlath into Borrodale, &amp; tho I carted it for nine miles out of the fourteen, the walk brought on a considerable haemorrhage;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey suffered from a rectal prolapse and haemorrhoids.</note> &#8211; &amp; the next day the cold became so violent that for a whole week I spent the greater part of the day upon the sofa in a darkened room, unable to bear the light. It has got into my chest, at first with great violence; &#8211; now it is quiet there, &amp; I hope that as it has made a quicker passage than usual, it will depart the sooner. To day I am so much better that I have had no occasion to intermit my employments: something I attribute to change of weather, yesterday when the amendment began the first rain falling which we have had for eight or ten weeks.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It appears now beyond all doubt that the books for which I have so long waited &amp; made so many enquiries are not in existence, &amp; that the account of them &amp; their author in Colburnes Magazine must consequently be a mere fiction.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford&#8217;s &#8216;On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez&#8217;, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221&#8211;223. It mentioned Olivarez&#8217;s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title>, published in four volumes at Seville in 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &amp; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877 and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had then written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832), and Herbert Hill had also offered to help. Southey had then sought the assistance of George Canning. Finally, Southey had written to John Mitford, 12 April 1824, Letter 4171.</note> It was signed John Mitford. I know something of one <ref type="m" target="people.html#MitfordJohn">John Mitford</ref> &amp; supposing him to be the author, never doubted the authenticity of the account: &#8211; as indeed who would have suspected a fiction of this kind? &#8211; I have now sent the volume to press,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &amp; am at this time as busy in arranging its materials as a General is in planning the operations of a campaign. My materials are very good; &#8211; but your Portugueze friends ought to get me a series of P. Gazettes for the honour of Portugal. King Joam 6.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John VI (1767&#8211;1826; King of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826).</note> himself would send them if he knew how much I was disposed to <del>xx</del> do him all the service in my power. &#8211; I have got scent of some German memoirs<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The bibliography of his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), III, p. 936, suggests that Southey was probably seeking: Hermann von Staff (1790&#8211;1867), <title>Der Befreiungs-Krieg der Katalonier, in den Jahren 1808 bis 1814</title> (1821&#8211;1827); and Franz Xaver Rigel (1783&#8211;1852), <title>Die Siebenjahrige Kampf auf der Pyrenaischen Halbinsel vom Jahre 1807 bis 1814; besonders miene eigenen Erfahrungen in disem Kriege; nebst Bemerkungen uber das Spanische Volk und Land</title> (1819&#8211;1821), no. 2442 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> by means of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClercqWillem">one of my Dutch correspondents</ref>, &amp; have desired <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to procure them: but of course I do not wait for them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have notice of a few books from Boston &#8211; one of them is Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Churchs account of Philips war,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Church (1674&#8211;1746), <title>The Entertaining History of King Philip&#8217;s War, Which Began in the Month of June in 1675. As also of Expeditions More Lately Made Against the Common Enemy, and Indian Rebels, in the Eastern Part of New-England: with Some Account of the Divine Providence Towards Col. Benjamin Church</title> (1772), no. 590 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library,</note> of all books the one which is of most direct importance for my poem, &#8211; &amp; perhaps the very rarest of all works relating to AngloAmerican history. Another is a very important one in the history of Quakerism.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Roger Williams (1603&#8211;1683), <title>George Fox Digged out of his Burrowes</title> (1676), no. 3122 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> lately sent me Spix &amp; Martins&#8217;s Travels in Brazil.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Baptist von Spix (1781&#8211;1826) and Carl Friedrich Philipp von Martius (1794&#8211;1868), <title>Reise in Brasilien auf Befehl Sr. Majest&#228;t Maximilian Joseph I. K&#246;nigs von Baiern, in den Jahren 1817 bis 1820</title> (1823) was translated by Hannibal Evans Lloyd (1771&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>) and published by Longmans in two volumes as <title>Travels in Brazil in the years 1817&#8211;1820, Undertaken by Command of His Majesty the King of Bavaria</title> (1824), no. 2722 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> They are imitators of Humboldt<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander von Humboldt (1769&#8211;1859), the German polymath and traveller in the Americas.</note> &amp; Animal Magnetists.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Followers of the theories of the German doctor, Franz Mesmer (1734&#8211;1815), that all living beings possessed an invisible natural force that could be used for healing.</note> How is it that Craniology<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">More commonly known as phrenology, the study of the shape of the skull as an indicator of character and intelligence.</note> has so many believers in these kingdoms, which is so demonstrably futile, &#8211; &amp; that Animal Magnetism which seems actually to be treated as a science by the Germans, is known here only as a mere juggle? &#8211; The remaining volumes of this travels are likely to be the most valuable as they relate to a part of the country hitherto unexplored by travellers &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> I suppose will soon take flight for Devonshire, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> for the neighbourhood of Portsmouth. We miss them both very much, but both are enjoying themselves, &amp; in kind hands. &#8211; I wish Ch. Gonne<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Gonne (1800&#8211;1877), a merchant and the brother of Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s wife, Louisa, married Susanna Beale (d. 1843) on 10 June 1824.</note> happy, but it is not possible to think of any person as <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref> without making a comparison which I never yet saw any woman who could bear[Gonne,Mary]. &#8211; Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref> &amp; the children &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">  RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <lb />
          <p rend="indent1"> I have reviewed Hayleys Memoirs<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of John Johnson (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263&#8211;311.</note> &#8211; - Lambton I see has purchased Martins Picture.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">John George Lambton, 1st Earl of Durham (1792&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>), bought John Martin (1789&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Seventh Plague of Egypt</title> (1823) for 500 guineas. The painting had been included in the inaugural exhibition of the Society of British Artists (1824), where it was probably seen by Southey on his trip to London, November 1823&#8211;February 1824. </note> Whatever he may have given for it, it will be worth ten times that sum hereafter. I never saw any picture which imprest me with so high a notion of the painters genius.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>