<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">4201Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4201" type="letter"><head>4201. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1824-06-16">16 June 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: London Nineteenth June 1824/ The Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> N. Lightfoot/ Crediton/ Free/ JRickman<lb/>
               Postmarks: FREE/ 19 JU 19/ 1824; [partial] xx/ 19/ 1824<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 110. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), V, pp.182–183 [in part].</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </placeName></address><date when="1824-06-16">16 June. 1824</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Lightfoot</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> When I sent you <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brothers</ref> Prospectus<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Nicholas Lightfoot, 12 March 18[24], Letter 4154, had contained Southey’s plea for subscriptions for his brother, Thomas Southey’s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies </title>(1827). The latter was published by Longman.</note> I ought to have told you how well aware I was that you would have little chance or opportunity of obtaining names for <del>him</del> it. Thank you for your own. The list increases slowly, but it is increasing, &#38; there appears a fair likelihood of making up the appointed number.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I was very glad to receive your letter, &#38; the satisfactory – &#38; more &#60;than&#62; satisfactory news of <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">John’s</ref> examination; – the result will in all <del>xx</del> probability put a fellowship within his reach;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Prideaux Lightfoot was elected a Fellow of Exeter College in 1824. After being ordained in 1832 he served as Rector of Wootton 1834–1854, before returning to Oxford as Rector of Exeter College 1854–1887. Southey was suspicious of College Fellowships as a long-term career option because Fellows were not allowed to marry.</note> – which tho a bad thing when it unites a man for better for worse to a college life, is at the beginning an honour, &#38; an useful step in life.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> You are likely to see one of my daughters – I am almost sorry to say, long before I shall. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> will set out with Lady Malet,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, née Wales (1779–1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>).</note> for Seaton, upon your coast, about the end of this month, where they will be joined by our friends the Miss Charters.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Louisa Charter</ref>; and Elizabeth Charter (1782–1860), a friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754–1832; <title>DNB</title>). They were the sisters of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, first wife of William Peachy, and nieces of Sir Charles Malet. Peachy had lent the Charter sisters his home on Derwent Island, and they and Lady Malet had travelled from Keswick to London with Southey in November 1823.</note> Their plans as far as I understand them, are, to remain some time at Seaton, &#38; when they break up from thence, Lady M. will make some visits in Somersetshire, &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> makes hers to your friendly abode before she rejoins her. But you shall hear from me as soon as I know of her arrival on the coast. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> is also in London, as a guest with <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> family, when Parliament breaks up<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The parliamentary sitting ended on 25 June 1824.</note> she will accompany them to the neighbourhood of Portsmouth, &#38; the sisters will most probably not return to Cumberland, till they come together which is not likely to be before the beginning of next year. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle (M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hill)</ref> is become so very infirm that there is too much reason for apprehending I may be summoned to London before that time.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I told you my reasons for declining the proposal of being named one of the Royal Literary Associates.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Royal Society of Literature had been founded in 1820. However, its first Annual General Meeting did not take place until 17 June 1823. It resolved to create 20 Associate Fellows, recommended by the Society’s Council. The Associate Fellows were to write a yearly essay and to receive 100 guineas per annum. Southey had made it known that he did not wish to receive this honour.</note> Had it been a mere honour I should have accepted it as a matter of course, &#38; of courtesy. In my situation any individual who pleases may throw dirt at me, &#38; any associated body which pleases may stick a feather in my cap – <del>I am</del> the dirt does not stick, the feathers are no incumbrance if they are of no use, &#38; I regard the one as little as the other. But in this case the feather was clogged with a condition that I was to receive £100 a year for which it was to be my duty every year to write an essay – to be printed if the Committee approved it, in their Transactions.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of the <title>Transactions of the Royal Society of Literature</title> did not appear until 1829.</note> What should I gain by doing that once a year for this Committee, which I may do once a quarter for the QR? &#38; which I could not do without leaving a paper in that Review undone? – with this difference that what I write in the Review is read every where is received with deference, &#38; carries with it weight, – whereas their Transactions cannot by possibility have a fiftieth part of the circulation: &#38; will either excite ridicule, or drop still-born from the press. I would have accepted a mere honour, in mere courtesy, – &#38; I would thankfully have accepted profit, – but when they contrived <del>x</del> so to mix up both as to leave neither one nor the other in my case, all I had to do was civilly to decline the offer.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara Coleridge</ref> has given up her intended visit to Ireland, &#38; is likely to go to London in the course of the Autumn, to be under the care of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gillman<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">James Gillman (1782–1839), the surgeon in Highgate with whom Coleridge had lived since 1816.</note> (with whom <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">her father</ref> resides) for the complaint in her eyes.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> This is certainly the time for drawing money out of the funds &#38; vesting it in land, where that can be done. – I have no cares of that kind. My B of the Ch.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> has been in the press for a second edition some six weeks: &#38; this is all I know concerning it, – save &#38; except that I am eating, drinking, &#38; living upon the said Book at present. But the only two lines which I have received from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> since I left town were to tell me it must go to press again. It is not unlikely that the next new work I undertake may be a Book of the State upon a similar plan.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write a companion ‘Book of the State’.</note> – At present I am closely employed upon the Peninsular War<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> &#38; recovering (I hope) from a very severe attack of my annual cold, which has for 12 days confined me to the house, &#38; during great part of the time to a darkened room. To day I have walked out for the first time, – but it has pulled me down sadly, &#38; has not left me yet. – I am drinking your cider with great satisfaction, – the greater as being yours. My kindest remembrances to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L &#38; my younger friends<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Lightfoot married Bridget Prideaux (1768–1856) on 13 July 1801. Their children were: John Prideaux Lightfoot; Frances Jane Lightfoot (1806–1882), Southey’s god-daughter; Catherine Anne Lightfoot (1808–1898); Bridget Mary Lightfoot (1810–1889); and Nicholas Francis Lightfoot (1811–1881), Vicar of Cadbury 1846–1855, Rector of Islip 1855–1881.</note> – Best regards from all my womankind – with a particular charge that I must not forget to entreat you to visit me again, &#38; see all that you left unseen.</p>
       <closer>    <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear Lightfoot –</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">  Yours affectionately</salute>
         <signed rend="indent3">   RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
