<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4202Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4202Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4202" type="letter">
        <head>4202. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>,<date when="1824-06-18"> 18 June 1824</date>
          </head><p>MS: British Library, Add MS 47887 <lb />
               Previously published: Robert Southey, <title>The Doctor &amp;c</title>, 7 vols (London, 1834&#8211;1847), VII, pp. 582&#8211;596.</p>
        <p rend="center"> MEMOIR OF THE CATS OF <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">GRETA HALL</ref>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent0"> For as much, most excellent Edith May, as you must always feel a natural and becoming concern in whatever relates to the house wherein you were born, and in which the first part of your life has thus far so happily been spent, I have for your instruction and delight composed these Memoirs of the Cats of <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>: to the end that the memory of such worthy animals may not perish, but be held in deserved honour by my children, and those who shall come after them. And let me not be supposed unmindful of Beelzebub of Bath, and Senhor Thomaz de Lisboa,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Cats that Southey had known when he lived in Bath and in Lisbon in 1800&#8211;1801.</note> that I have not gone back to an earlier period, and included them in my design. Far be it from me to intend any injury or disrespect to their shades! Opportunity of doing justice to their virtues will not be wanting at some future time, but for the present I must confine myself within the limits of these precincts. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the autumn of the year 1803 when I entered upon this place of abode, I found the hearth in possession of two cats whom my nephew <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley Coleridge</ref>, (then in the 7th year of his age,) had named Lord Nelson and Bona Marietta. The former, as the name implies, was of the worthier gender: it is as decidedly so in Cats, as in grammar and in law.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Joshua Poole (fl. 1640s; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The English Accidence, or a Short and Easy Way for the More Speedy Attaining to the Latine Tongue</title> (London, 1646), p. 21: &#8216;The Masculine gender is more worthy than the Feminine ...&#8217;.</note> He was an ugly specimen of the streaked-carrotty, or Judas-coloured<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">In Spanish culture, Judas Iscariot, the disciple who betrayed Jesus, was often depicted with red hair, a trait long associated with treachery.</note> kind, which is one of the ugliest varieties. But <hi rend="ital">nimium ne crede colori</hi>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Trust not too much in a beautiful complexion&#8217; (Publius Vergilius Maro (70&#8211;19 BC), <title>Eclogues</title> (c. 39&#8211;38 BC), Eclogue 2, line 17).</note> In spite of his complection, there was nothing treacherous about him. He was altogether a good Cat, affectionate, vigilant, and brave; and for services performed against the Rats was deservedly raised in succession to the rank of Baron, Viscount and Earl. He lived to a good old age; and then being quite helpless and miserable was in mercy thrown into the river. I had more than once interfered to save him from this fate; but it became at length plainly an act of compassion to consent to it. And here let me observe that in a world wherein death is necessary, the law of nature by which one creature preys upon another is a law of mercy, not only because death is thus made instrumental to life, and more life exists in consequence, but also because it is better for the creatures themselves to be cut off suddenly, than to perish by disease or hunger, &#8211; for these are the only alternatives. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are still some of Lord Nelson&#8217;s descendants in the town of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. Two of the family were handsomer than I should have supposed any Cats of this complection could have been; but their fur was fine, the colour a rich carrot, and the striping like that of the finest tyger or tabby kind. I named one of them William Rufus; the other Danayn le Roux, after a personage in the Romance of Gyron le Courtoys.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The second part of <title>Palamedes</title> (c. 1235&#8211;1240), a French prose romance, is devoted to the adventures of the knight Guiron le Courtois and his companion, Danyn the Red, Lord of the Castle of Malaonc.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Bona Marietta was the mother of Bona Fidelia, so named by my nephew aforesaid. Bona Fidelia was a tortoise-shell cat. She was filiated upon Lord Nelson, others of the same litter having borne the unequivocal stamp of his likeness. It was in her good qualities that she resembled him, for in truth her name rightly bespoke her nature. She approached as nearly as possible in disposition, to the ideal of a perfect cat: &#8211; he who supposes that animals have not their difference of disposition as well as men, knows very little of animal nature. Having survived her daughter Madame Catalani, she died of extreme old age universally, esteemed and regretted by all who had the pleasure of her acquaintance. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Bona Fidelia left a daughter and a grand-daughter; the former I called Madame Bianchi &#8211; the latter Pulcheria. It was impossible ever to familiarize Madame Bianchi, though she had been bred up in all respects like her gentle mother, in the same place, and with the same persons. The nonsense of that arch-philosophist Helvetius would be sufficiently confuted by this single example, if such rank folly contradicted as it is by the experience of every family, needed confutation.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The philosopher Claude Adrien Hel&#233;vtius (1715&#8211;1771) viewed the human mind as a blank slate, with no innate ideas or propensities. Therefore people were shaped entirely by their experiences and education.</note> She was a beautiful and singular creature, white, with a fine tabby tail, and two or three spots of tabby, always delicately clean; and her wild eyes were bright and green as the Duchess de Cadaval&#8217;s emerald necklace.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A rather puzzling reference. However, when Southey had lived in Portugal in 1800&#8211;1801 he saw a Corpus Christi procession, in which a wooden statue of St George was decorated with all the jewels of the Cadaval family &#8211; possibly including this emerald necklace; see Southey to Charles Danvers, [15 June 1800], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 531. At this time the head of the family was Miguel Caetano Alvares Pereira de Melo, 5th Duke of Cadaval (1765&#8211;1808).</note> Pulcheria did not correspond as she grew up to the promise of her kittenhood and her name;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">This cat was named after Pulcheria (c. 398&#8211;453; Empress 450&#8211;453), a Byzantine empress famed for her piety. The name also means &#8216;beautiful&#8217; in Latin. </note> but she was as fond as her mother was shy and intractable. Their fate was extraordinary as well as mournful. When good old <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonMrs">Mrs. Wilson</ref> died, who used to feed and indulge them, they immediately forsook the house, nor could they be allured to enter it again, though they continued to wander and moan around it and came for food. After some weeks Madame Bianchi disappeared, and Pulcheria soon afterwards died of a disease endemic at that time among cats. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For a considerable time afterwards, an evil fortune attended all our attempts at re-establishing a Cattery. Ovid disappeared and Virgil died of some miserable distemper. You and <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">your cousin</ref> are answerable for these names: the reasons which I could find for them were, in the former case the satisfactory one that the said Ovid might be presumed to be a master in the Art of Love;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Publius Ovidius Naso (43 BC&#8211;AD 17/18), <title>Ars Amatoria</title> (AD 2) &#8211; &#8216;the art of love&#8217;.</note> and in the latter the probable one that something like Ma-ro &#8211; might be detected in the said Virgil&#8217;s notes of courtship.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Publius Vergilius Maro (70&#8211;19 BC), Roman poet, popularly known as Virgil.</note> There was poor Othello: most properly named,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">This cat was named after the eponymous central character in <title>The Tragedy of Othello, the Moor of Venice</title> (1603).</note> for black he was, and jealous undoubtedly he would have been, but he in his kittenship followed Miss Wilbraham<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Laetitia Wilbraham (1799&#8211;1874), Tom Southey&#8217;s lodger. She married Joseph Harrison Fryer (1777&#8211;1855) of Whitley House, Northumberland, a surveyor, geologist and mining engineer who spent part of each year at Keswick.</note> into the street, and there in all likelihood came to an untimely end. There was the Zombi &#8211; (I leave the Commentators to explain that title, and refer them to my History of Brazil to do it)<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Zumbi (1655&#8211;1695), last leader of the Quilombo dos Palmares, a community of fugitive slaves in Brazil; the name was, therefore, appropriate for a black cat. Southey described the destruction of the community in <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 23&#8211;29. </note>- his marvellous story was recorded in a letter to Bedford:<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 3 April 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3662.</note>- and after that adventure he vanished. There was Prester John,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Prester John was the legendary Christian leader of a realm believed to be in Asia or Africa. The legend was popular from the twelfth to the seventeenth centuries.</note> who turned out not to be of John&#8217;s gender, and therefore had the name altered to Pope Joan.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Pope Joan was an equally fictional female pope from the Middle Ages.</note> The Pope I am afraid came to a death of which other Popes have died. I suspect that some poison which the rats had turned out of their holes, proved fatal to their enemy. For some time I feared we were at the end of our Cat-a-logue: but at last Fortune as if to make amends for her late severity sent us two at once, &#8211; the never-to-be-enough-praised Rumpelstilzchen, and the equally-to-be-admired Hurlyburlybuss. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  And &#8220;first for the first of these&#8221; as my huge favourite, and almost namesake Robert South, says in his Sermons.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert South (1634&#8211;1716; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;A Sermon Preached at Westminster-Abbey, April 30, 1676&#8217;, <title>Twelve Sermons Preached upon Several Occasions</title>, 2 vols (London, 1697), I, p. 397.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  When the Midgeleys&#8217;<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">A family called Midgeley had rented Greta Lodge, next to Greta Hall, leaving in 1823.</note> went away from the next house, they left this creature to our hospitality, cats being the least moveable of all animals because of their strong local predilections; &#8211; they are indeed in a domesticated state the serfs of the animal creation, and properly attached to the soil. The change was gradually and therefore easily brought about. For he was already acquainted with the children and with me; and having the same precincts to prowl in was hardly sensible of any other difference in his condition than that of obtaining a name; for when he was consigned to us he was an anonymous cat; and I having just related at breakfast with universal applause the story of Rumpelstilzchen from a German tale in Grimm&#8217;s Collection,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacob Ludwig Karl Grimm (1785&#8211;1863) and Wilhelm Karl Grimm (1786&#8211;1859), <title>Kinder-und Hausm&#228;rchen</title> (1812), translated as <title>German Popular Stories</title> (London, 1823), pp. 213&#8211;217, by Edgar Taylor (1793&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>). The book was an immense success (including with Cuthbert Southey). Rumpel-Stilts-Kin was an imp who could spin straw into gold.</note> gave him that strange and magnisonant appellation; to which upon its being ascertained that he came when a kitten from a bailiff&#8217;s house, I added the patronymic of Macbum.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">A bum bailiff was a bailiff empowered to collect debts. </note> Such is his history, his character may with most propriety be introduced after the manner of Plutarch&#8217;s parallels<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Plutarch (AD 46&#8211;after AD 119), <title>Parallel Lives</title> comprises 23 pairs of biographies; each pair comprises one famous Greek and one famous Roman.</note> when I shall have given some previous account of his great compeer and rival Hurlyburlybuss, &#8211; that name also is of Germanic and Grimmish extraction.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was mistaken. Hurlyburly is a sixteenth-century English word.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Whence Hurlyburlybuss came was a mystery when you departed from the Land of Lakes, and a mystery it long remained. He appeared here as Mango Capac did in Peru and Quetzalcohuatl among the Aztecas,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Mango Capac was the legendary first Inca ruler, while Quetzalcoatl was an Aztec deity and culture hero. Southey had researched both figures thoroughly for his epic poem, <title>Madoc</title> (1805). Southey discovered the idea that Mango Capac and his sister-wife, Oella, had mysteriously appeared on the shores of Lake Titicaca in the twelfth century from Inca Garcilaso de la Vega (1539&#8211;1616), <title>Comentarios Reales, que tratan del Origen de los Yncas, Reyes que fueron del Peru</title>, 2 vols (Lisbon, 1609), I, f. 80, no. 3800 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library; see <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 3&#8211;4. The legend that Quetzacoatl came to Mexico by sea from an unknown country, landed at Panuco with a band of followers, and instituted a Golden Age, was detailed in Southey&#8217;s note to <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Part Two, Book 9, line 109. His source was Juan de Torquemada (c. 1562&#8211;1624), <title>Monarchia Indiana. De los veinte y un libros rituales y Monarchia Indiana</title>, 10 vols (Madrid, 1723), I, pp. 254&#8211;256 and II, pp. 48&#8211;52, no. 3797 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> no one knew from whence. He made himself acquainted with all the philofelists of the family &#8211; attaching himself more particularly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mrs. Lovell</ref>, but he never attempted to enter the house, frequently disappeared for days, and once since my return for so long a time that he was actually believed to be dead and veritably lamented as such. The wonder was whither did he retire at such times &#8211; and to whom did he belong; for neither I in my daily walks, nor the children, nor any of the servants ever by any chance saw him anywhere except in our own domain. There was something so mysterious in this, that in old times it might have excited strong suspicion, and he would have been in danger of passing for a Witch in disguise, or a familiar. The mystery however was solved about four week&#8217;s ago, when as we were returning from a walk up the Greta, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> saw him on his transit across the road and the wall from Shulicrow, in a direction toward the Hill. But to this day we are ignorant who has the honour to be his owner in the eye of the law; and the owner is equally ignorant of the high favour in which Hurlyburlybuss is held, of the heroic name which he has obtained, and that his fame has extended far and wide &#8211; even unto <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref> in the East, and Escott and Crediton and Kellerton in the West,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">All places that Southey had been to between November 1823&#8211;February 1824. He had visited Neville White at Norwich, Edward Combe at Escott, Nicholas Lightfoot at Crediton and Sir Thomas Acland at Killerton.</note> yea &#8211; that with Rumpelstilzchen he has been celebrated in song, by some hitherto undiscovered poet,<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">The most likely author of &#8216;The Poetic Epistle to Southey from his Cats&#8217;, signed by Rumpelstilzchen and Hurlyburlybuss, was John Marriott (1780&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman, poet and friend of Walter Scott. He was Curate of St James, Exeter, St Lawrence, Exeter, and St John, Broadclyst. Southey had stayed with Marriott on 6 January 1824 on his visit to the West Country. While he was on this trip, Southey received a copy of this poem, which he liked and kept; it was later printed in <title>The Doctor</title>, 7 vols (London, 1834&#8211;1847), VII, pp. 580&#8211;582.</note> and that his glory will go down to future generations. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The strong enmity which unhappily subsists between these otherwise gentle and most amiable cats is not unknown to you. Let it be imputed as in justice it ought, not to their individual characters (for Cats have characters, &#8211; and for the benefit of philosophy, as well as <hi rend="ital">felisophy</hi>, this truth ought generally to be known) but to the constitution of Cat nature, &#8211; an original sin, or an original necessity, which may be only another mode of expressing the same thing:</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Two stars keep not their motion in one sphere,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Nor can one purlieu brook a double reign </l>
          <l rend="indent3">of Hurlyburlybuss and Rumpelstilzchen.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Two stars keep not their motion in one sphere,/ Nor can one England brook a double reign/ Of Harry Percy and the Prince of Wales.&#8217; <title>The First Part of Henry the Fourth</title>, Act 5, scene 4, lines 65&#8211;67.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1"> When you left us, the result of many a fierce conflict was that Hurly remained master of the green and garden and the whole of the out of door premises. Rumpel always upon the appearance of his victorious enemy retiring into the house as a citadel or sanctuary. The conqueror was perhaps in part indebted for this superiority to his hardier habits of life, living always in the open air, and providing for himself; while Rumpel (who though born under a bum-bailiff&#8217;s roof was nevertheless kittened with a silver spoon in his mouth) past his hours in luxurious repose beside the fire, and looked for his meals as punctually as any two-legged member of the family. Yet I believe that the advantage on Hurly&#8217;s side is in a great degree constitutional also, and that his superior courage arises from a confidence in his superior strength, which as you well know is visible in his make. What Bento and Maria Rosa<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Two of Southey&#8217;s servants in Portugal in 1800&#8211;1801.</note> used to say of my poor Thomaz, that he was <hi rend="ital">muito fidalgo</hi>
          <note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Much the gentleman&#8217; or &#8216;very noble&#8217;.</note> is true of Rumpelstilzchen, his countenance, deportment and behaviour being such that he is truly a gentleman-like Tom-cat. Far be it from me to praise him beyond his deserts: &#8211; he is not beautiful, the mixture, tabby and white, is not good (except under very favourable combinations) and the tabby is not good of its kind. Nevertheless he is a fine cat, handsome enough for his sex, large, well-made with good features, and an intelligent countenance, and carrying a splendid tail, which in Cats and Dogs is undoubtedly the seat of honour. His eyes which are soft and expressive are of a hue between chrysolite and emerald. Hurlyburlybuss&#8217;s are between chrysolite and topaz. Which maybe the more esteemed shade for the <hi rend="ital">olho de gato</hi>
          <note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Eye of the cat&#8217;.</note> I am not lapidary enough to decide. You should ask <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>. But both are of the finest water. In all his other features Hurly must yield the palm, and in form also; he has no pretensions to elegance, his size is ordinary and his figure bad: but the character of his face and neck is so masculine, that the Chinese who use the word bull as synonymous with male, and call a boy a bull-child<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 444. Southey&#8217;s source was probably John McLeod (1777&#8211;1820), <title>Narrative of a Voyage, in His Majesty&#8217;s Late Ship Alceste to the Yellow Sea, along the Coast of Corea, and through the Numerous Hitherto Undiscovered Islands to the Island of Lewchew, with an Account of Her Shipwreck in the Straits of Gaspar</title> (London, 1817), p. 158, no. 1834 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> might with great propriety denominate him a bull-cat. His make evinces such decided marks of strength and courage that if cat-fighting were as fashionable as cock-fighting no cat would stand a fairer chance for winning a Welsh main.<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">A cock-fighting tournament in which the winners of bouts were paired until only one survivor was left.</note> He would become as famous as the Dog Billy<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">Billy (d. 1829) was a bull and terrier dog, famed for his rat-killing abilities in contests organised at the Westminster Pit on Duck Lane, Orchard Street, the centre of British blood sports until it was closed in 1830.</note> himself, whom I look upon as the most distinguished character that has appeared since Buonaparte.<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Some weeks ago Hurlyburlybuss was manifestly emaciated and enfeebled by ill health, and Rumpelstilzchen with great magnanimity made overtures of peace. The whole progress of the treaty was seen from the parlour window. The caution with which Rumpel made his advances, the sullen dignity with which they were received, their mutual uneasiness when Rumpel after a slow and wary approach, seated himself whisker-to-whisker with his rival, the mutual fear which restrained not only teeth and claws, but even all tones of defiance, the mutual agitation of their tails which, though they did not expand with anger, could not be kept still for suspense and lastly the manner in which Hurly retreated, like Ajax still keeping his face toward his old antagonist<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors">In Homer&#8217;s <title>Iliad</title>, Ajax is one of the leading Greek warriors besieging Troy. In Book 16, lines 101&#8211;130, he engages in combat with Hector, son of the King of Troy, but is forced to retreat after being disarmed.</note> were worthy to have been represented by that painter who was called the Rafaelle of Cats.<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors">Gottfried Mind (1768&#8211;1814), a Swiss painter, famed for his portrayal of cats, and hence known as the &#8216;Raphael of Cats&#8217;, after Raffaelo Sanzio da Urbino (1483&#8211;1520), the Renaissance painter. </note> The overture I fear was not accepted as generously as it was made; for no sooner had Hurlyburlybuss recovered strength than hostilities were recommenced with greater violence than ever, Rumpel who had not abused his superiority while he possessed it, had acquired meantime a confidence which made him keep the field. Dreadful were the combats which ensued as their ears, faces and legs bore witness. Rumpel had a wound which went through one of his feet. The result has been so far in his favour that he no longer seeks to avoid his enemy, and we are often compelled to interfere and separate them. Oh it is aweful to hear the &#8220;dreadful note of preparation&#8221;<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Henry the Fifth</title>, Act 5, prologue, line 14.</note> with which they prelude their encounters! &#8211; the long low growl slowly rises and swells till it becomes a high sharp yowl, &#8211; and then it is snapt short by a sound which seems as if they were spitting fire and venom at each other. I could half persuade myself that the word felonious is derived from the feline temper as displayed at such times. All means of reconciling them and making them understand how goodly a thing it is for cats to dwell together in peace, and what fools they are to quarrel and tear each other are in vain. The proceedings of the Society for the Abolition of War<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors">The Society for the Promotion of Permanent and Universal Peace (usually known as the Peace Society), a Quaker society dedicated to pacifism and founded in 1816.</note> are not more utterly ineffectual and hopeless. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All we can do is to act more impartially than the Gods did between Achilles and Hector,<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editors">In Homer&#8217;s <title>Iliad</title>, Hector and Achilles were, respectively, the leading heroes of the Trojans and the Greeks. The gods constantly interfered on the side of one or another.</note> and continue to treat both with equal regard. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  And thus having brought down these Memoirs of the Cats of <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref> to the present day, I commit the precious memorial to your keeping, and remain </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">Most dissipated and light-heeled daughter,</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Your most diligent and light-hearted father,</salute>
          <signed rend="right"> ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <lb />
          <p rend="indent">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">
                  <hi rend="ital">Keswick</hi>
                </ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-06-18">18 <hi rend="ital">June</hi>, 1824.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>