<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4208. Robert Southey to [John May], 29 June&#8211;17 July
          1824</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4208Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4208. Robert Southey to [John May], 29 June&#8211;17 July
              1824</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4208Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4208" type="letter">
        <head>4208. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>], <date when="1824-06-29">29 June&#8211;17 July
                  1824</date>
          </head><p>MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus
                  Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 6p.<lb /> Previously edited or published: Michael Neill
                  Stanton, &#8216;An Edition of the Autobiographical Letters of Robert Southey&#8217; (unpublished PhD, University of Rochester, 1972), pp.
                  167&#8211;178; <lb /> Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850),
                  I, pp. 100&#8211;113 [with variants; Cuthbert Southey&#8217;s text draws on a fair copy of the letter and not on the original version sent to
                  May, which we publish here].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1824-06-29"> June 29. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent0">In a former letter I have mentioned M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Sergeant,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was
                  mistaken; he had not previously mentioned Mrs Sergeant (unidentified beyond the information given here).</note> who had been <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tylers</ref> school-mistress. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">My
                  Aunt</ref> kept up an acquaintance with her as long as she lived, &amp; after her death with her two daughters,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> who lived together in a house on Redclift Parade, &#8211; the pleasantest situation in
               Bristol, if there had been even a tolerable approach to it. One of these sisters was unmarried, the other a widow with one son, who was
               just of my age &#8211; Jem Thomas<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> was his name.
                  M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lewis,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Israel Lewis (c. 1761&#8211;1841) was a native of Carmarthenshire. He
                  was later Vicar of Long Ashton 1794&#8211;1841 and Rector of Foxcote 1806&#8211;1841, but at this time he was acting as a Curate at St Mary
                  Redcliffe, Bristol, and teaching. He had previously been under-master at Bristol Grammar School.</note> the clergyman
                  <del>with</del> under whom I was placed <del>either</del> at the end of 1786 or the beginning of 1787, lodged &amp; boarded with
               these sisters. He had been Usher at the Grammar school, &amp; having engaged to educate this boy was willing to take a few more pupils,
                  <del>who should come to him</del> from the hours of ten till two. He had two others when I went to him, Cooper<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cooper (or Cowper) (d. 1805), son of Launcelot Cooper (or Cowper) (d. 1794), a Bristol merchant in
                  the American trade.</note> &amp; Rawlins,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Fawsitt Herbert Rawlins (1772&#8211;1849) was
                  educated at Eton 1785&#8211;1789 and then entered Queen&#8217;s College, Oxford. He became a barrister at the Inner Temple in 1798 and later
                  settled at the family property at Stoke Courcy (Stogursey) in Somerset.</note> both <del>xx</del> my seniors by three or four years.
               The former I used to call Caliban,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A half-human, half-monster character in Shakespeare&#8217;s
                     <title>The Tempest</title> (1611). His mother was the witch, Sycorax.</note> &#8211; he might have played that character without a
               mask, that is supposing he could have learnt the part, <del>but he was</del> for the resemblance held good in mind as well as in
               appearance his disposition being something between pig &amp; baboon. The latter was a favourite with Lewis, his father had formerly
               been a surgeon but had succeeded to an estate of some value;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Rawlins (c. 1748&#8211;1813), who
                  inherited the Rawlins family property at Stoke Courcy (Stogursey).</note> he was little &amp; mannish, somewhat vain of superficial
               talents &amp; with a spice of conceit &lt;both&gt; in his manners &lt;&amp; in his dress&gt;; but there was no harm in him. He took
               an honorary Masters degree at the Duke of Portlands Installation in 1793<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William
                  Cavendish-Bentinck, 3rd Duke of Portland (1738&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>; Prime Minister 1783, 1807&#8211;1809) was installed as Chancellor
                  of the University of Oxford on 4 July 1793. Rawlins was one of five men admitted to the degree of MA on that day (even though he did
                  not have a BA).</note> &#8211; which was the only time I ever saw him after we ceased to be fellow pupils. He married about that time<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1793, Rawlins married Laetitia Louisa Lemaistre (1761&#8211;1797), daughter of Stephen Caesar
                  Lemaistre (d. 1777), Judge of the Supreme Court of Judicature at Bengal. After the death of his first wife, he married Juliana Baker
                  (d. 1849) on 18 January 1803.</note> &amp; died young. Caliban had a sister whom I shall not libel when I call her Sycorax,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne Cooper (or Cowper) (d. 1806), daughter of Launcelot Cooper (or Cowper) (d. 1794), a Bristol
                  merchant in the American trade.</note> for she was a most loathsome person. Wade<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Josiah Wade
                  (c. 1761&#8211;1842), a linen draper, pioneer of accountancy and editor of the <title>Mercantile Gazette</title>, had met Coleridge and
                  Southey in the mid 1790s. His relationship with Southey was significantly cooler than that with Coleridge. The latter stayed with
                  Wade on his final visit to Bristol in 1813&#8211;1814.</note> a Bristol tradesman &amp; a great friend of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">S.T.Cs</ref> married her for her money, &amp; the only thing I ever heard of Caliban in
               after life was a story which reached me of her every where proclaiming that her brother was a very superior man to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coleridge</ref>, &amp; had confuted him &lt;one evening&gt;
               seven &amp; twenty times in one argument. The word which <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> uses as a
               listener, when he is expected to <del>say something xxx</del> throw in <del>xxxx</del> &lt;something&gt; with or without meaning to
               show that he is listening &#8211; is &#8211; or used to be as I well remember &#8211; &#8220;<hi rend="ital">undoubtedly</hi>&#8221;. The foolish woman had
                  <del>given</del> &lt;understood&gt; it &lt;in&gt; its literal meaning, &amp; kept account with her fingers that he pronounced it
               seven &amp; twenty times while enduring the bestial utterances of an <del>creature</del> &lt;animal&gt; in comparison with whom
                  <del>a Satyr or</del> a Centaur would deserve to be called human, &amp; a Satyr rational.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Jem Thomas was a common place lad, with a fine handsome person, but by no means a good physiognomy: &lt;&amp; I cannot
               remember the time when I was not a physiognomist.&gt; He was educated for a surgeon, &amp; ruined by having at his disposal as soon as
               he came of age something between 2 &amp; 3000 &#163; which his grandmother imprudently left to him instead of his mother in trust for him.
               This he presently squandered, &#8211; <del>&amp; th</del> went out professionally to the E Indies, &amp; died there. So much for my three
               companions &lt;among whom it was not possible that I could find a friend&gt; there came a fourth, a few weeks only before I withdrew,
               &#8211; he was a well-minded boy &amp; has made a very respectable man. Harris was his name, &amp; he married Betsy Petrie,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Petrie (dates unknown) was a friend of Southey in Portugal 1800&#8211;1801. She may have been a
                  daughter of Martin Petrie (d. 1805), a merchant who was later Commissary-General to the Army in the Mediterranean and Portugal.
                  Harris is unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> who was once one of my fellow travellers in Portugal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I profited by this years tuition less than I should have done at a good school. It is not easy to remedy the ill
               effects of bad teaching, &amp; the farther the pupil has advanced in it the greater the difficulty must be &lt;of bringing him into a
               better way&gt;. Lewis too had been accustomed to the mechanical movements of a large school, &amp; was at a loss how to proceed with a
                  <del>pupil</del> &lt;boy&gt; who stood alone. I began Greek under him, made nonsense verses, &lt;read Horace&#8217;s Odes&gt;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Quintus Horatius Flaccus (65&#8211;8 BC), <title>Odes</title> (23&#8211;13 BC).</note> advanced a little in
               writing Latin, &amp; composed English themes. <hi rend="ital">C&#8217;est le premier pas qui coute</hi>
          <note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;It is the first step that is the most difficult.&#8217;</note> I was in as great tribulation when I had the first theme to
               write, as when Williams<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">William Williams (d. 1811), Southey&#8217;s schoolmaster at Merchants&#8217; Hall
                  School, Bristol, 1782&#8211;1786.</note> required me to produce a letter. The text of course had been given me, but &lt;how to
               begin,&gt; what to say, or how to say it, I knew not. No one who had witnessed my perplexity upon this occasion would have supposed
                  <del>that these poor brains</del> how much was afterwards to be spun from these poor brains. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">My Aunt</ref> at last in compassion wrote the theme for me. Lewis questioned me if it was my
               own, &amp; I told him the truth. He then encouraged me sensibly enough, <del>&amp;</del> put me in the way of composing the
               commonplaces of which themes are manufactured, &lt;(indeed he made me transcribe some rules, for theme making, a regular receit, as
               for making a pudding.)&gt; &amp; he had no reason afterwards to complain of any want of aptitude in his scholar. For when I had learnt
               that it was not more difficult to write in prose than in verse, the ink dribbled as daintily from my pen as ever it did from John
                  Bunyans.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of John Bunyan (1628&#8211;1688; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Holy
                     War</title> (1682), &#8216;An Advertisement to the Reader&#8217;, lines 11&#8211;14. Southey had used this quotation as an epigraph to his poems
                  &#8216;Jaspar&#8217; and &#8216;Lord William&#8217; in <title>Poems</title> (London, 1799), p. [117].</note> One of these exercises I remember sufficiently
               well to know that <del>its main fault</del> it was too much like poetry, &amp; that the fault was of a hopeful kind, consisting less in
               inflated language than in &lt;poetical&gt; imagery <del>than</del> &lt;&amp;&gt; sentiment. But this was not pointed out, &amp;
               luckily I was left to myself, &#8211; otherwise like a good horse I might have been spoilt by being broken in too soon.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It was still more fortunate that there was none to direct me in my own favourite &lt;<del>xxxxxx</del>&gt; pursuit,
               certain as &lt;it is that&gt; any instructor would have <del>beco to have</del> interfered with the natural &amp; healthy growth of
               that poetical spirit, which was taking its own course.*<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">* [Southey&#8217;s note, to indicate the
                  insertion that follows: &#8216;That spirit was like a plant &#8230; the dews of heaven&#8217;. His note is in the left-hand margin. We have restored
                  it to its place in his narrative.]</note> &lt;That spirit was like a plant which required no forcing, nor artificial culture, &#8211;
                  <del>xx xxxxx</del> only air &amp; sunshine &amp; the rains &amp; the dews of heaven.&gt; I do not remember <del>during</del>
               &lt;in&gt; any part of my life to have been so conscious of intellectual improvement as I was during the year &amp; half before I was
               placed at Westminster; &#8211; an improvement derived not from books or instruction, but from constantly exercising myself in English verse,
               &amp; &lt;from&gt; the development of mind which that exercise produced. I can distinctly trace my progress by help of a list made
               thirty years ago of all my compositions in verse which were then in existence, or which I had at that <del>xxxx</del> time
                  destroyed.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s catalogue of his juvenile poems, now held at Keswick Museum,
                  1996.5.159a.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Early as my hopes had been directed toward the drama, they received a more decided &amp; more fortunate direction from
               the frequent perusal of Tasso, Ariosto &amp; Spenser.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Torquato Tasso (1544&#8211;1595),
                     <title>Gerusalemme Liberata</title> (1581); Ludovico Ariosto (1474&#8211;1533), <title>Orlando Furioso</title> (1516); Edmund Spenser
                  (1552/1553&#8211;1599; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Faerie Queene</title> (1590&#8211;1596).</note> I had read also Mickles Lusiad, &amp;
               Pope&#8217;s Homer.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">William Julius Mickle (1734&#8211;1788; <title>DNB</title>); <title>The Lusiad; Or, the
                     Discovery of India: an Epic Poem</title> (1776); Alexander Pope (1688&#8211;1744; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Iliad of
                     Homer</title> (1715&#8211;1720).</note> If <del>xx</del> you add to these an extensive acquaintance with the novels of the day &amp;
               with the Arabian &amp; mock-Arabian tales,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Arabian Nights Entertainments</title>
                  (1706&#8211;1721), later much reprinted and extended.</note> &#8211; the whole works of Josephus,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Titus
                  Flavius Josephus (c. AD 37&#8211;100). His works included <title>Bellum Judaicum</title> (AD 78), <title>Antiquitates Judaicae</title> (c.
                  AD 93&#8211;94) and <title>Contra Apionem</title> (after AD 94).</note> taken in by me with my pocket money in threescore sixpenny numbers
               &#8211; (which I now possess)<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Whole Works of Flavius Josephus</title> (1785), no. 1446 in
                  the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; such acquaintance with Greek &amp; Roman history as a school boy picks up from his
               lessons &amp; from Goldsmiths abridged histories,<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Oliver Goldsmith (1728&#8211;1774;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Dr. Goldsmith&#8217;s Roman History Abridged by Himself for the Use of Schools</title> (1772); <title>The
                     Grecian History from the Earliest State to the Death of Alexander the Great</title> (1774).</note> &amp; such acquaintance with
               their fables as may be learnt from Ovid<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Publius Ovidius Naso (43 BC&#8211;AD 17/18),
                     <title>Metamorphoses</title> (c. AD 8).</note> &lt;from the old Pantheon&gt;, &amp; above all from the end of Littletons
                  dictionary,<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Adam Littleton (1627&#8211;1694; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Linguae Latinae Liber
                     Dictionarius Quadripartitus: A Latin Dictionary in Four Parts</title> (1673). Later editions were expanded to include
                  chronological tables and information on Rome, including the pantheon of gods.</note> you will have a fair account of the stock upon
               which I began. But Shakespere &amp; Beaumont &amp; Fletcher<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Beaumont (1584&#8211;1616;
                     <title>DNB</title>) and John Fletcher (1579&#8211;1625; <title>DNB</title>), who co-authored around twelve to fifteen plays.</note>
               must not be forgotten: &lt;nor Sidneys Arcadia,&gt;<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Philip Sidney (1554&#8211;1586;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Arcadia</title> (1590&#8211;1593).</note> nor Rowleys Poems<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas
                  Chatterton (1752&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poems Supposed to Have Been Written at Bristol by Thomas Rowley and Others in the
                     Fifteenth Century</title> (1777).</note> &#8211; for Chattertons history was fresh in remembrance, &amp; that story which would have
               affected one of my disposition any where, <del>acted with decided</del> acted upon me with all the force of local associations.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The first of my epic dreams was created by Ariosto. I meant to graft a story upon the Orlando Furioso &#8211; not knowing how
               often this had been done by Italian &amp; Spanish imitators.<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">For instance, Laura Terracina
                  (1519&#8211;c. 1577), <title>Discorso Sopra il Principio di Tutti I Canti di Orlando Furioso</title> (1549) and Lope Felix de Vega y
                  Carpio (1562&#8211;1635), <title>La Hermosura de Angelica</title> (1602).</note> Arcadia was to have been the title &amp; the scene,
               thither I meant to carry the Moors under Marsilius<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>Orlando Furioso</title>, Marsilius
                  is the Moorish King of Spain who participates in the invasion of France and is defeated.</note> after their overthrow in France,
               &amp; then to have overthrown them again by a hero of my own named Alphonso, who had caught the Hippogriff.<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek legend a combination of an eagle and a horse. In <title>Orlando Furioso</title> it plays an important part
                  in the plot; for instance, the knight Ruggiero uses the hippogriff to free the captive heroine Angelica.</note> This must have been
               when I was between nine &amp; ten, &#8211; for some <del>xxx</del> verses of it were written on the cover of my Phaedrus.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Phaedrus (fl. 1st century), <title>Fabulae Aesopiae</title>, a Latin collection of fables.</note> They
               were in the &lt;heroic&gt; couplet <del>as verse</del>. Among <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunts</ref> books
               was the first volume of Bysshe&#8217;s Art of Poetry,<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Bysshe (dates unknown), <title>The Art
                     of English Poetry</title> (1702). This was in three volumes, the first of which discussed metre and types of poetry, the second
                  was a rhyming dictionary and the third an anthology of poetry.</note> which worthless as it is taught me at that age the <del>common
                  law</del> principle upon which blank verse is constructed. I soon learnt to prefer that metre, not because it was easier than rhyme
               (which was easy enough) but because I felt in it a greater freedom &amp; range of language. My second subject was the Trojan
                  Brutus,<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors">Brutus of Troy, legendary founder of Britain. He first appears in the
                     <title>Historia Brittonum</title> (c. AD 828).</note> &#8211; the defeat of K Richard &amp; the union of the two Roses,<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard III (1452&#8211;1485; King of England 1483&#8211;1485; <title>DNB</title>). His defeat in 1485 ended the
                  conflict between the House of York (symbolised by the white rose) and the House of Lancaster (symbolised by the red rose).</note>
               was my third. In neither of these did I make much progress, but with the story of Egbert<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editors">Egbert
                  (771/775&#8211;839; King of Wessex 802&#8211;839; <title>DNB</title>). He established the dominance of Wessex and was thought of by some
                  historians as the first King of England.</note> I was more persevering, &amp; fairly transcribed several folio sheets the sight of
                  <del>which</del> &lt;these&gt; was an encouragement to proceed, &amp; I often looked at them with <del>solitary</del> delight in
               the anticipation of future fame. This was a <del>sacred</del> solitary feeling, for my ambition or vanity (whichever it may deserve to
               be called) was not greater than the shyness which accompanied it. My port-folio was of course held sacred. One day however it was
               profaned by an acquaintance of <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref> who called to pay a morning visit: she
               was shown into the parlour &amp; I who was sent to say <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref> would presently
               wait upon her, found her with my precious Egbert in her hand. Her compliments had no effect in abating my deep resentment at this
                  <del>unf</del> unpardonable <del>impertinence</del> &lt;curiosity&gt;, &amp; tho she was a good natured woman I am afraid I never
               quite forgave her. Determining however never to incur the risk of a second exposure, I immediately composed a set of characters for my
               own use. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In my twelfth &amp; thirteenth years besides these loftier attempts, I wrote three heroic epistles in rhyme, the one
               was from Diomede to Egiale,<note n="39" place="foot" resp="editors">In Homer&#8217;s <title>Iliad</title>, Diomedes was one of the leading
                  Greek warriors and King of Argos. Egiale was his wife. On his return from the Trojan wars, he found she had rejected him and he was
                  forced to flee to Italy.</note> the second from Octavia to Anthony,<note n="40" place="foot" resp="editors">Marcus Antonius (83&#8211;30
                  BC), the Roman general and triumvir 43&#8211;30 BC. He married Octavia (69&#8211;11 BC) in 40 BC, but they separated in 36 BC and divorced in 32
                  BC.</note> the third from Alexander to his father Herod,<note n="41" place="foot" resp="editors">Herod the Great (74/73 BC&#8211;4 BC),
                  the Roman client King of Judea 34&#8211;4 BC. His son and heir was Alexander (35&#8211;7 BC), whom Herod executed for treason. Their story is
                  related in Titus Flavius Josephus (c. AD 37&#8211;100), <title>Antiquitates Judaicae</title> (c. AD 93&#8211;94).</note> &#8211; a <del>xxx</del>
               subject with which Josephus supplied me. I made also some translations from Ovid, Virgil &amp; Horace,<note n="42" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey stated in the catalogue of his juvenile poems, now held at Keswick Museum, 1996.5.159a, that he translated
                  material related to Aristaeus, a Greek god of husbandry and rural crafts, in Publius Vergilius Maro (70&#8211;19 BC),
                     <title>Georgics</title> (29 BC), Book 4, lines 281&#8211;386 and 528&#8211;558, and in Ovid, <title>Metamorphoses</title> (though Aristaeus
                  is scarcely mentioned in this poem); and Horace, <title>Odes</title>, Book 1, Ode 29.</note> &amp; composed a satirical description
               of English manners, as delivered by Omai<note n="43" place="foot" resp="editors">The Tahitian traveller Mai (Omai) (c.1751&#8211;1780), who
                  visited Britain in 1774&#8211;1776. </note> to his countrymen on his return. On the thirteenth anniversary of my birth, supposing by an
               error which appeared to be common enough at the end of the century that I was then <del>only</del> entering &lt;the first year&gt; my
               teens &lt;instead of compleating it.&gt; &amp; looking upon that as an aweful sort of step in life I wrote some verses in a strain of
               reflection upon mortality grave enough to provoke a smile when I <del>then</del> recollect them. Among my attempts at this time were
               two descriptive pieces entitled Morning in the Country &amp; Morning in the Town, in eight syllable rhyme &amp; in imitation of
                  Cunningham.<note n="44" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Cunningham (c. 1747&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), who had a fondness for
                  using Latin verse forms in his poetry.</note> There was also a satirical Peep into Plutos dominions<note n="45" place="foot" resp="editors">Pluto, the ruler of the underworld in classical mythology.</note> in rhyme &#8211; I remember <del>only</del> the
               conclusion only &#8211; &amp; that because it exhibits a singular <del>xxx</del> indication how strongly <del>at that</del> &lt;&amp;
               how&gt; early <del>age</del> my heart was set upon that peculiar line of poetry which I have pursued with most ardour. It described
               the Elysium<note n="46" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek mythology, the abode after death of the heroic and the righteous.</note>
               of the poets, &amp; that more sacred part of it in which Homer, Virgil, Tasso, Spenser, Camoens &amp; Milton<note n="47" place="foot" resp="editors">Homer, the ascribed author of the <title>Iliad</title> and the <title>Odyssey</title>; Luis Vaz de Camoes
                  (1524&#8211;1580), <title>Os Lusiadas</title> (1572); John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Paradise Lost</title> (1667).
                  All three were epic poets.</note> were assembled. While I was regarding them Fame came hastening by with her arms full of laurels,
               &amp; asking in an indignant voice if there was <del>any</del> &lt;no Poet&gt; who would deserve these, upon which I reached out my
               hands &#8211; <del>&amp; awoke</del> snatched at them &#8211; &amp; awoke. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> One of these juvenile efforts was wholly original in its design. It was an attempt to <del>relat</del>
               &lt;exhibit&gt; the story of the Trojan war in a dramatic form, laying the scene in Elysium where the events that had happened were
               related by the souls of the several heroes as they successively descended. The opening was a dialogue between Laodamia &amp;
                  Protesilaus<note n="48" place="foot" resp="editors">In the <title>Iliad</title>, Protesilaus was the first Greek hero to be killed
                  during the Trojan wars. On hearing of his death, his wife Laodamia committed suicide.</note> in couplets, the best rhymes which I
               had as yet written. But I did not proceed far <del>in</del> &lt;probably&gt; because the design was too difficult, &amp; this would
               have been reason enough for abandoning it, if I had not entered with more than usual ardour upon <del>an</del> a new heroic subject,
                  <del>taken</del> of which Cassibelan<note n="49" place="foot" resp="editors">Cassivellaunus (1st century BC), a leader of the
                  Catuvellauni, who coordinated the resistance to the Roman invasion of Britain in 54 BC.</note> was the hero. I had
                  <del>written</del> finished three books of this poem &amp; advanced far in the fourth before I went to Westminster. All was written
               fairly out in my own private characters, &amp; in my best <del>hands</del> &lt;writing&gt;, if one may talk of calligraphy in an
               unknown hand, which looked something like Greek, but more like conjuration from the number of trines &amp; squares which it contained
               These characters however proved fatal to the poem: for it was not possible for me to continue it at school for want of privacy, &amp;
               disuse made the <del>characters</del> cypher so difficult that I could not read it without almost spelling as I went on, &amp; at last
               in very vexation I burnt the manuscript<note n="50" place="foot" resp="editors">In Southey&#8217;s catalogue of his juvenile poems, now held
                  at Keswick Museum 1996.5.159a, all of these early poems are described as &#8216;burnt&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wonder whether Spurzheim<note n="51" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Gaspar Spurzheim (1776&#8211;1832), the German
                  pioneer of phrenology.</note> could at that time have discovered an organ of constructiveness in my <del>xxxxxxx</del> pericranium.
               The Elysian drama might seem to indicate that <del>I possessed</del> &lt;that&gt; the faculty &lt;was there&gt;, but not a trace of
               it was to be found in any of the heroic poems which I attempted. They were all begun <del>with</del> &lt;upon&gt; a mere general
               notion of the subject, without any prearrangement &#8211; &amp; <del>almost without one</del> little preconception of the incidents by which
               the catastrophe was to be brought about. When I sate down to write I had to look as much for the incidents as for the thoughts &amp;
               language in which they were to be clothed. I expected them to occur just as readily, &amp; so indeed, such as they were, they did. My
               reading in &lt;the old&gt; Chivalrous romances has been extensive enough to justify me in asserting that &lt;the greater number
               of&gt; those romances were written just in the same way, without the slightest plan or forethought: &amp; I am much mistaken if many
               of the Italian romantic poems were not composed in the same inartificial manner. This I am sure that it is more difficult to plan that
               to execute well, &amp; that abundance of <del>good poetry</del> &lt;true poetical power&gt; has been squandered for want of a
               constructive talent in the poet. I have felt this &lt;want&gt; in some of the Spanish &amp; Portugueze writers even more than their
               want of taste. The progress of my own mind towards attaining it (so far as I may be thought to have attained it) I am able to trace
               distinctly, not merely by the works themselves, &amp; by my own recollections of the views with which they were &lt;undertaken
               &amp;&gt; composed, but by the various sketches &amp; memoranda &lt;for <del>for</del> four poems&gt;<note n="52" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey completed five long poems: <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796); <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801);
                     <title>Madoc</title> (1805); <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810); and <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                  (1814). He may be omitting the first as insufficiently thought-through and planned. </note> made from the first conception of
                  <del>every poem</del> &lt;each&gt;, till its completion. At present the facility &amp; pleasure with which I can plan a long poem,
               a drama, &amp; <del>a comprehensive</del> &lt;an&gt; historical or biographical work however comprehensive, is ever a temptation to
               me: &#8211; it seems as if I caught the bearings of a subject at first sight, just as <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Telford</ref> sees from an eminence <del>xx</del> with a glance in which direction his road must be carried. But it was long before
               I acquired this power, &#8211; not fairly indeed till I was about five &amp; thirty:<note n="53" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was
                  thirty-five in 1809. He may therefore be suggesting that only the planning of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814)
                  was fully satisfactory.</note> &amp; it was acquired by practice, <del>by the gradual perception of my own defects</del> in the
               course of which I learnt to perceive wherein I had been deficient.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There was one point in which these &lt;premature&gt; <del>early</del> &lt;attempts&gt; <del>exhibited</del>
               &lt;afforded&gt; a hopeful <del>indication</del> &lt;omen&gt;, &amp; that was the industry with which I endeavoured to acquire all
               the historical information within my reach relating to the subject in hand. Forty years ago I could have given you a better account of
               the birth &amp; parentage of Egbert, &amp; the state of the Heptarchy<note n="54" place="foot" resp="editors">A term dating from the
                  early modern period to describe the seven kingdoms which historians believed divided Anglo-Saxon England: Northumbria; Mercia;
                  Wessex; East Anglia; Essex; Sussex and Kent.</note> in his youth, that I could do now, without referring to my books; &amp; when
               Cassibelan was my hero, I was as well acquainted with the division of the Island among its ancient tribes, as &lt;I am now&gt; with
               the relative situation of its counties. It was perhaps fortunate <del>for me</del> that these pursuits were solitary &amp; unassisted,
               by thus working a way for myself I acquired a habit &amp; a love for <del>pursu</del> investigation &amp; nothing appeared
               uninteresting which gave me any of the information I wanted. The pleasure I took in <del>these pursuits</del> &lt;such researches
               &amp; in composition&gt; rendered me in a great degree independent of other amusements &amp; no systematic education could have
                  <del>so well</del> fitted me for my present course of life so well as the circumstances which allowed me thus to feel &amp; follow
               my own impulses.</p>
        <postscript>
          <lb />
          <p rend="right">
            <date when="1824-07-17"> July 17. 1824</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>