<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4210</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4210Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4210" type="letter">
        <head>4210. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">Mary Ann Watts Hughes</ref>, <date when="1824-07-04">4 July 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand] London July seven 1824/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes/ Uffington/ Faringdon/ CW Williams Wynn <lb />
               Postmark: FREE/ 7 JY 7/ 1824<lb />
               MS: Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public Library, Misc 3797. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 430&#8211;432.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-07-04"> 4 July. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>  My dear Madam</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  Your letter brought me the first, &amp; only intelligence that I have received of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsleys</ref> death.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Anne Watts Hughes was misinformed. Elmsley was very ill, but he did not die until 8 March 1825.</note> His place will not easily be filled at Oxford, &amp; in that walk of letters which he had chosen,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Elmsley was a leading classicist. Since 1823 he had been Principal of St Alban Hall, Oxford, and Camden Professor of Ancient History.</note> &#8211; but to his friends it never can be supplied. For myself, it is a loss which will be perceived whether I look backward or forward. Many recollections which used to be chearful ones, must now change their character, &#8211; &amp; I feel myself left with one friend less in the world, at an age when we rarely <del>make ne</del> form new friendships, even if a new friend could ever supply the place of an old one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been very much confined to the house since your departure by that annual visitation of catarrh<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey suffered very badly from hay fever.</note> which was then upon me. It has now taken the form of cough, which is usually its last stage, but this year, the cough seems to lie deeper &amp; take stronger hold than it was wont. Next year, if it be possible for me to break away from my employments, I will leave home at the end of April, &amp; try as the only probable means of escaping it, to make a journey of six or eight weeks, &#8211; into Holland &amp; the North of Germany if I can find a companion</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You were fortunate while you were here in the weather, &#8211; but had you been a month later, you would have seen our wonder of wonders, which tho there is nothing beautiful in it, <del>it</del> is still very well worth seeing, for I believe nothing of the kind has ever been observed else where. What is called the Floating Island has made its appearance.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Floating Island of Derwentwater is a mass of vegetation that rises to the surface every few years. It appeared from 21 June 1824 to the end of September, its first siting since 1819.</note> By good fortune Sedgewick, the Cambridge Professor of Geology<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Adam Sedgwick (1785&#8211;1873; <title>DNB</title>), Fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge, and Woodwardian Professor of Geology 1818&#8211;1873.</note> is here. I went with him to reconnoitre it on Monday last, &#8211; &amp; yesterday he investigated it thoroughly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The bottom of the lake in that part (near <ref type="m" target="places.html#Lodore">Lodore</ref>) is covered with aquatic plants, growing in a soft vegetable mould which is <del>about xxxx</del> hardly a foot thick, &amp; lies upon a bed of peat, &#8211; that bed is six feet in thickness &amp; rests upon a stratum of fine white clay. From time to time a quantity of <del>xxx</del> &lt;gas&gt; is generated (whether in the peat, or below it remains to be discovered) which fills this peat, till it becomes so buoyant that it is seperated from the clay, &amp; then that part of the bottom of the lake floats &amp; rises to the surface. But so great was the accumulation when this took place that it has made a rent in the bottom some fifty yards long, &amp; some six feet deep. Upon probing the gas comes out freely but not so plentifully, on the sides of this chasm, &#8211; as in another portion at some little distance, where instead of forcing for itself a vent, the gas has puffed up the bottom in a convex form. Then when a pole is thrust down, the air rushes out like a jet.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">We have had rain enough in the course of the lake to raise the lake full four feet. The convex part is therefore now under water, &#8211; &amp; probably the two other pieces, or the sides of the chasm will soon subside.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My young ones, thank God, are well, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel&#8217;s</ref> face which has been frightfully swoln, from an inflammation of the ear, is recovering its usual dimensions. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara Coleridge</ref> is still complaining of her eyes, &amp; talking of going to the South to have them cured, &#8211; but in this family every thing is talked of a long while before it is done. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My eldest daughter</ref> has deferred all account of her visit to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls till she returns, &#8211; as <del>certain</del> having <del>too</del> &lt;so&gt; much to say that she dared not begin to write it. She is now on her way to Devonshire. Last week she met <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> W Wynn</ref> at the Caledonian Ball,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Caledonian Ball is a major event in the London Season. In 1824 it was held on 25 June at Almack&#8217;s Assembly Rooms.</note> &amp; thought her looking very ill. She gives a good account of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, who spent the last week with her, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> gives good accounts of herself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">And now my dear Madam present our united regards to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesThomas">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughes</ref> not forgetting mine to your son,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hughes (1790&#8211;1857; <title>DNB</title>), a miscellaneous author, most recently of <title>An Itinerary of Provence and the Rhone made During the Year 1819</title> (1822), which Southey admired.</note> &amp; believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>