<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4212</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4212Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4212" type="letter">
        <head>4212. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>,<date when="1824-07-08"> 8 July 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Sir Walter Scott Bart./ Abbotsford / Melrose<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Endorsement: 109<lb />
               MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 3899. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Wilfred Partington, <title>The Private Letter-Books of Sir Walter Scott. Selections from the Abbotsford manuscripts ... Edited by Wilfred Partington</title> (London, 1930), pp. 80&#8211;82.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-07-08">8 July. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Scott</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes</ref> owed me some reparation for sending me last week an account of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsleys</ref> death, which thank God, has proved to be untrue, &amp; there are hopes of his recovery. She has made good amends for this needless sorrow (a heavy one the loss of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> would be!), by the real pleasure which it has given me to hear from you. The last &lt;letter&gt; which I received was written just after <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">Ticknor</ref> left you, early in 1819,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Walter Scott to Robert Southey, 4 April 1819, John Gibson Lockhart, <title>Memoirs of the Life of Sir Walter Scott</title>, 7 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), VI, pp. 237&#8211;241.</note> &#8211; &amp; the last which I wrote was addrest to you in London to offer <del>xxx</del> a very hearty congratulation upon the honorary addition to your name.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Scott was created a baronet on 22 April 1820. Southey&#8217;s letter of congratulation does not seem to survive.</note> But I hate accounts of every kind, &#8211; so if two or three books of mine since that time have not found their way to you &#8211; as they ought to have done according to my directions &#8211; requiescant in pace.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Rest in peace&#8217;. Southey was referring to his <title>Vision of Judgement</title> (1821) and <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832). </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It was a mortification to me that I did not see you during my Scotch tour five years ago. But I past thro Selkirk at midnight in the mail, to join a party at Edinburgh, whom I brought home with me by the Glasgow road.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey arrived in Edinburgh at 5:15 a.m. on 17 August 1819, having travelled by mail coach from Carlisle. There he met his travelling companions, John and Susannah Rickman, their children, William (1812&#8211;1886) and Frances Rickman (dates unknown) and a Miss Pigott. It is difficult to be sure of her identity, but she might have been Emma Pigott (dates unknown), younger daughter and co-heiress of James Pigott (d. 1822) of Fitz-Hall, Iping, Sussex. She married, in 1824, Edward Brice Bunny (d. 1867) of Speen Hill, Berkshire. Their return journey to Keswick via Glasgow took place from 27 September&#8211;1 October 1819; see <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (London, 1929), pp. 1&#8211;4, 254&#8211;269.</note> I saw a great deal of Scotland during that journey, &amp; was so interested with what I saw that I live in hopes of one day seeing the rest. I had resolution enough to keep a minute journal, which may probably see the light when the booksellers come to pick my bones &amp; make their last meal of me.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (1929).</note> It was worth doing, for <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Telford</ref> was one of my companions so that I saw his piers, his roads &amp; the Caledonian Canal in progress, &amp; had all the information which I could desire concerning them, &amp; the localities every where.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, who is almost always on the move, has lately returned from the south.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth had visited London in March 1824, returning in June after a round of visits to friends in East Anglia and the Midlands.</note> How he is employed I know not, not having seen him since my own return in February last: but we shall probably see another crop of Odes &amp; Sonnets, in due season, &#8211; for the older he grows the more prolific he <del>xx</del> becomes. My springs are not dry, but they have ceased to flow. You remember poor Daniels complaint in his old age, </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">&#8211; Time has done to me this wrong</l>
          <l rend="indent3">To make me write too much &amp; live too long.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Daniel (1562&#8211;1619; <title>DNB</title>). Southey slightly misquotes from Daniel&#8217;s poem, &#8216;To the Prince&#8217;, lines 107&#8211;108, which was prefixed to his play <title>Philotas</title> (1604). The original text reads &#8216;But yeeres hath done this wrong,/ To make me write too much, and liue to long.&#8217;</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1"> Time has brought no such injury to me as yet, but it has made me much more willing to learn than to teach, &amp; the <del>xx</del> eagerness with which I pursue my researches is much greater than the inclination which I feel for composing their results. Were it not that this also is a mode of learning (&amp; sometimes the best) I should find composition but an irksome task. At present I am printing the second volume of the Peninsular War,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &amp; making collections for a longer series of historical works than I shall live to finish.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s unfinished &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> As a proof however that my right hand hath not quite forgotten its cunning,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Psalms</title> 137: 5.</note> I will send you an Ode written upon occasion of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the Kings</ref> visit to your country;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Scotland, an Ode, Written after the King&#8217;s Visit to that Country. By Robert Southey, Esq. Poet Laureat&#8217;, <title>The Bijou: Or Annual of Literature and the Arts</title> (London, 1828), pp. 81&#8211;88.</note> &#8211; one of my annual tasks, &amp; yet written with good will. It must travel to London for a frank. I will send it because it expresses a friendly [MS missing] as well as a British feeling.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  It would give me great pleasure if I could accept your hospitable invitation. There are few things which I should like so well &#8211; but we are looking for a succession of guests who will engage us till the autumn is advanced: &amp; what with indisposition which always lays me up at this time of year (this year more severely than usual) &#8211; &amp; engagements of society &amp; exercise which follow, &#8211; I find myself very much the slave of the desk during the other months.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> unites with me in kindest respects to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">Lady Scott</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Believe me Dear Sir Walter<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent2">  yrs most truly<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3">   Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>