<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4218" type="letter"><head>4218. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowringJohn">John Bowring</ref>,<date when="1824-07-20"> 20 July 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Bowring Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 5. Jeffrey’s Square<lb/>
               Stamped: [illegible]<lb/>
               Postmark: A. NOON 2/ 23 JY/ 1824<lb/>
               Endorsements: Robert Southey/ 20 July 1824; Keswick. 20 July 1824/ Rob Southey/ 23/ 30<title> </title>Aug<lb/>
               MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
         <opener>   <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-07-20">20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> July. 1824</date></dateline>
            
          <salute>  Dear Sir</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> It was not till yester-evening that I received your volume of Spanish poetry,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Bowring, <title>Ancient Poetry and Romances of Spain</title> (1824), no. 338 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> &#38; the obliging note which accompanied it. A most interesting volume it is. Among the pieces which were new to me are those of Gil Vicente,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Bowring translated seven short poems by Gil Vicente (c. 1465–1536), <title>Ancient Poetry and Romances of Spain</title> (London, 1824), pp. 315–321.</note> – there is no <del>volume</del> book in the language which I am so desirous of seeing as the Comedias<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Vicente wrote over forty plays. A posthumous edition of his works, <title>Compilação de Toda as Obras de Gil Vicente</title> (1562), appeared in five volumes, with the comedies occupying volume two and the farces volume four.</note> of that writer but I never could hear of any other copy than one which was said to be in the Royal Library at Lisbon &#38; now in danger of being devoured by insects in Brazil.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Portuguese Royal Library followed the Court to Rio de Janeiro in 1810–1811, to escape the French invasion of Portugal.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">  You have succeeded most happily with the Coplas of Manrique.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Bowring translated ‘Coplas por la Muerte de su Padre’ by Jorge Manrique (c. 1440–1479) as ‘Ode’, <title>Ancient Poetry and Romances of Spain</title> (London, 1824), pp. 235–252.</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> attempted them once, &#38; gave up the attempt in despair. I thought the attempt so hopeless, that I did not venture to make a trial when verse flowed more fluently from my pen than it would at present. But you have shown us <hi rend="ital">el impossible veneido</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">‘the impossible task’.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The same feeling which made you suppress your intended introduction<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">In his ‘Preface’ to <title>Ancient Poetry and Romances of Spain</title> (London, 1824), pp. [v]–vi, Bowring had confessed he did not have sufficient knowledge to write his planned ‘short history of the popular poetry of Spain’.</note> would deter me from entering upon the subject in the Q Review. There are too many chasms in my knowledge of it.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> You have recorded your confident hope of Spanish regeneration.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Preface’, <title>Ancient Poetry and Romances of Spain</title> (London, 1824), p. viii: ‘my hopes of Spanish regeneration, have not been shaken by the disasters which have filled some minds with disappointment, and others with despair.’</note> In our estimate of the Spanish character I believe we are well agreed, &#38; in our wishes for the welfare of the Spaniards, their improvement, &#38; their emancipation from political &#38; ecclesiastical despotism. But the late contest<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Spain had been invaded by France in 1823; the liberal regime was overthrown and royal absolutism restored.</note> was between two parties, both in my judgement, so absolutely bad, that I could not throw away a wish on either side. – Had I been born a Spaniard, I should probably at this hour have been a thorough-paced <hi rend="ital">Liberal</hi>. I am therefore well aware how much may be pleaded in excuse of their errors: but those errors are not the less fatal in their consequences, because so excusable in their cause: &#38; it is my firm persuasion that liberty in the present state of the world has nothing to fear from its enemies, but every thing from its injudicious friends.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> So much evil has been done in Spain, that I can see nothing but evil in long prospective there, &#38; know not even what to hope for. But in Portugal it appears to me that there is a plain &#38; easy course to be pursued, by restoring the old Cortes,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The medieval Portuguese Cortes of three estates had ceased to meet after 1698. A liberal revolution in 1820 created a new constitution in 1822, but royal absolutism was restored in 1823.</note> &#38; administering justice regularly. If this were done &#38; provision made for the liberty of the subject by a Habeas Corpus act,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">In England, the Habeas Corpus Act (1673) guaranteed no imprisonment without trial.</note> it is as much as the Nation is ripe for, &#38; might content all <del>whose</del> who desire the reformation of abuses. The Inquisition<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The Portuguese Inquisition was abolished in 1821 by the liberal regime.</note> might be managed as long as any thing were to be apprehended from the Queens party,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte (1775–1830), Queen Consort of Portugal and one of the key leaders of the absolutist faction in the Portuguese Court.</note> to whom its suppression would afford a popular pretext, – &#38; in a few years quietly &#38; safely abolished.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Should any chance bring you into these parts I should have much pleasure in talking with you upon subjects concerning which we are, I am well assured, perfectly agreed – as to the end which is to be aimed at, however much we may differ about the means to be pursued. Even upon those, time will bring us nearer, whichever may be wrong.</p>
          <closer> <salute rend="indent1"> Believe me Dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">  yrs with sincere good will</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">  Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
