<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4222" type="letter"><head>4222. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#GrantAnne">Anne Grant</ref>, <date when="1824-07-24">24 July 1824 </date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Grant/ at M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Smiths/ Meadowside/ near/ Glasgow<lb/>
               Stamped: [partial] KESW<lb/>
               Postmark: [partial] G/ JU/ 1824/ 403<lb/>
               Endorsements: From/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 24 July 1824; Shown to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Smith 151 Georges/ Street – XXX/ (from Robert Southey Esq)<lb/>
               MS: Maine Historical Society, Dr John S. H. Fogg Collection (Coll. 420). ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 266–267.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1824-07-24"> 24 July. 1824</date></dateline>
            
          <salute>  My dear Madam</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">If I had any influence with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColburnHenry">Colburn</ref>, it could not be better employed than on this occasion. I have never had any communication with him, but once, which was many years ago, when he wrote to request that I would lend him a portrait of myself to be engraved for his magazine, &#38; also communicate to him some particulars of my life.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Henry Colburn, 5 June 1814, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2434. An engraving of Southey appeared, together with a ‘long Memoir’, in Colburn’s <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 1 (January–July 1814), Frontispiece; 566–571.</note> It happened that a most methodistical mis-likeness of me had been exhibited some little time before in the European Magazine,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A ‘Memoir of Robert Southey, Esq.’ and a portrait ‘Engraved by Blood, from an Original Drawing by Edridge in the Possession of G. C. Bedford, Esq.’ appeared in <title>European Magazine</title>, 66 (July 1814), [3]–5.</note> – &#38; as I was willing enough to supersede it by something better, I told <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColburnHenry">Colburn</ref> where he might borrow a bust,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The bust sculpted by James Smith (1775–1813) in October 1813. Colburn borrowed it from Henry Herbert Southey.</note> which was the only satisfactory resemblance that existed: at the same time I stated in as few words as possible the time &#38; place of my birth, &#38; the course of my education saying that this would suffice for his purpose, &#38; that the public had no business to expect any thing more in the way of memoirs while the subject in question was alive. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColburnHenry">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Colburn</ref> however was not satisfied with this. He borrowed the bust, &#38; got someone to attempt the impossible task of making a portrait from it, which he engraved as an original picture: – a miserable looking wretch it is, – something in physiognomy between assassin &#38; hangman. And he produced a long memoir of my private life, evidently written by some person who must once have been my guest, – or he could not have known so much, – &#38; yet <del>could</del> had been in no degree intimately acquainted with me, – or he could not have made so many grossly erroneous statements. Of course I thought myself ill used, but this sort of usage is too common to excite either surprize or anger.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> This has been my whole intercourse with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColburnHenry">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Colburn</ref>. – Campbell<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Campbell (1777–1844; <title>DNB</title>), the Scottish poet and editor of the <title>New Monthly Magazine</title> 1821–1830.</note> is the person who is most likely to have influence with him. But surely you can stand in need of no such interference. There has been but one opinion of all <del>the books which you have published</del> &#60;your writings&#62;, &#38; they are of a character always to excite as much interest as when they were first published.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> As to the form of publication, booksellers ought to be the best advisors. To me the common octavo is the least agreable form in which a book can appear, as being too large to be held conveniently in the hand, &#38; yet not large enough to require a table. The crown octavo is a much pleasanter size; but I believe the other is the more economical way of printing. In either shape two duodecimos <del>volumes</del> may very well be comprised in one volume. – When the Works are published<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne Grant did not publish her collected works.</note> it may be in my power to render them some little service, &#38; that opportunity I will gladly take, – glad indeed of any occasion to show with what sincere respect I regard M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Grant &#38; her writings.</p>
          <closer> <salute rend="indent1"> Dear Madam</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">  Believe me yours very faithfully</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
