<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4225Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4225" type="letter">
        <head>4225. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Peter Elmsley</ref>, <date when="1824-08-05">5 August 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Westminster School. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Nicholas Horsfall, &#8216;Four Unpublished Letters of Robert Southey&#8217;, <title>Notes and Queries</title>, 22.9 (September 1975), 403&#8211;405.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-08-05"> 5 Aug. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Elmsley</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Among all the persons who have rejoiced in your recovery, there is probably no one who has felt the kind of pleasure which has fallen to my lot. I received a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes</ref> telling me you were dead. I thought of you &amp; dreamt of you as of the dead, &#8211; &amp; continued in that belief till there came news from <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> that <del>thxx xxxxx</del> he was going to visit you, &amp; witness the progress of your amendment. Never before did any letter give me so much delight, &#8211; &amp; most <del>likely xx</del> unlikely it is that any one ever will hereafter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  A severe illness is middle life sometimes leaves the constitution in a better state than it found it. The <hi rend="ital">vis medicatrix</hi>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A contraction of &#8216;vis medicatrix naturae&#8217;: literally &#8216;the healing power of nature&#8217;. This is the Latin version of a phrase attributed to Hippocrates (c. 460&#8211;c. 370 BC), Greek physician.</note> in such cases goes to work like a landlord, who having neglected his house till it threatens to fall down, sets about a thorough repair.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> On <del>Thursd</del> the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this month I shall compleat the fiftieth year of my age. My tenement has some ugly flaws in it, tho it has stood pretty well, all circumstances considered. For more than twenty years I have been subject to a severe &amp; obstinate catarrh, beginning with the summer, &amp; lasting ten or twelve weeks: nor have I ever escaped it except the year when I went into Switzerland at the time of its usual visitation.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s visit to the Continent in May&#8211;August 1817.</note> Latterly it has always ended in a cough, &amp; this year that cough has for the first time given me a hint of its hereditary right to fix upon me. &#8211; I am getting rid of it for the present, &amp; have nearly recovered the strength which I had lost. But so surely as the seasons come round, so surely will the affection return, unless I can arm the system against it by a course of exercise &amp; constant change of air at that time. If therefore it be possible, I will pass the <del>months</del> latter end of May, &amp; the six following weeks next year in <del>travelling</del> Holland &amp; the North of Germany.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did indeed make this journey in 1825 and 1826.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am printing the second vol. of the Peninsular War,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &amp; <hi rend="ital">more meo</hi>
          <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;as is my custom&#8217;.</note> writing it &lt;one chapter&gt; while the press is going on with another. Tho this may not be a good method, there are some good reasons for it, &#8211; the best being that it enables me to <del>use</del> &lt;employ&gt; the latest materials which fall in my way, more advantageously than <del>xx</del> &lt;if&gt; they came only in time to be used for correcting a narrative drawn from <del>documents</del> less satisfactory documents. This is a very sufficient reason. My materials are as authentic as I could desire, &amp; as ample as would be desired by any person except myself. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">The D. of Wellington</ref> would not supply me with any papers, for a reason which <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> has probably told you,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey believed that Wellington was reserving his help for Sir William Napier (1785&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of the War in the Peninsula and the South of France from the Year 1807 to 1814</title> (1828&#8211;1840). Napier did indeed receive much assistance from Wellington, but was not given use of his papers.</note> but thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> he will give me any information I may have occasion to ask that can be communicated <del>in x</del>
          <hi rend="ital">viva voce</hi>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;by word of mouth&#8217;.</note> He would have done better in committing his papers to my hands, than in reserving them for a mere military history, &#8211; to which purpose they would have been equally applicable afterwards. But I have from others had so much both of his official &amp; confidential correspondence during those years while he <del>hxx</del> was fighting up hill, &#8211; that perhaps he would be very much surprized to know how well I am acquainted with his views, feelings &amp; opinions. So well indeed am I provided with documents, &amp; with that previous knowledge which is necessary for turning them to account, that I proceed with full confidence &amp; a firm step every where, &#8211; except upon a field of battle: &#8211; there <del>indeed</del> I am as sensible as I ought to be of my own ignorance; &amp; when I have done my best to understand what to my non-military &amp; non-mathematical head <del>xx xxxx</del> &lt;is&gt; unintelligible. I stick to the letter of my authorities &amp; make the reader as wise as myself. When I come to these parts of the story, <del>xx</del> my own situation puts me in mind of a Cat upon a tea table, &#8211; if you ever saw one picking her way among the cups &amp; saucers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Should it please Gods, Men &amp; Booksellers I am thinking of a Book of the State<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write &#8216;The Book of the State&#8217; as a companion to <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> &#8211; to be brought down to the death of Q Anne,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne (1665&#8211;1714; Queen of Great Britain 1701&#8211;1714; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; &amp; connected by an introductory view of the reigns of George 1 &amp; 2, with <del>a xxx</del> the Age of George 3,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">George I (1660&#8211;1727; King of Great Britain 1701&#8211;1727; <title>DNB</title>); George II (1683&#8211;1760; King of Great Britain 1727&#8211;1760; <title>DNB</title>); and George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of Great Britain 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; making thus a summary of our English history upon a scale &amp; in a form likely to be read &amp; remembered. Want of books is the chief obstacle, &amp; there need be no greater. I have lately read three works which would have made one part of my Eccl. Sketch<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> much less imperfect than it is, if I had perused them in time. Cardinal D&#8217;Ossat&#8217;s Letters,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Arnaud D&#8217;Ossat (1537&#8211;1604), <title>Lettres du Cardinal d&#8217;Ossat, avec des Notes Historiques et Politiques de M. Amelot De La Houssaie</title> (1708), no. 851 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Isaac Casaubons Epistles,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Casaubon (1559&#8211;1614), <title>Epistolae</title> (1656), no. 453 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; Peter Heylyns View of Guernsey &amp; Jersey.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Heylyn (1600&#8211;1662; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Survey of the Estate of France and Some of the Adjoyning Ilands</title> (1656), no. 1187 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> One motive with me for undertaking a sketch of our Civil History would be for the opportunity it would afford of introducing there whatever of importance had been omitted in the former work.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> These are speculations, which with many others of a wider scope &amp; perhaps a worthier purpose, &#8211; time &amp; chance may easily frustrate. Meantime &#8211; sufficient for the day is the occupation thereof. How glad should I be to talk with you over the past &#8211; the present &#8211; &amp; the future, &#8211; here at leisure &amp; at rest! &#8211; <del>&amp; I hope this will</del> Whatever enjoyment there may be in meeting in London society (&amp; I am far from undervaluing it,) there is nothing of this kind to be had in crowds. One day I hope to have you again under this roof.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Elmsley had visited Southey at Keswick in September 1805.</note> Pleasure &amp; profit are not always united, but in that case I should find them so; &#8211; for mine is a mind upon which good seed is not wasted &#8211; tho it is sometimes long in springing up &amp; bringing forth fruit.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you Elmsley &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">  yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>