<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4231Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4231Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4231" type="letter">
        <head>4231. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1824-08-13">13 August 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Revd. Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmarks: E/ 18 xx 18/ 1824; [partial]/AUx/ 1824<lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 247. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-08-13"> 13 Aug. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">The traveller</ref> arrived safely this morning, &amp; nothing the worse for the wear. He was so little tired that by way of refreshing himself he took a walk of four miles with us before dinner, &amp; is now amusing himself with his two Welsh nieces<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> on the green.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">   I cannot but think you might derive benefit from warm bathing. It is rheumatism, &amp; not age that cripples you; &#8211; &amp; tho the Caldas<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The hot, sulphurous spring and spa town of Caldas da Rainha in Portugal. Southey had visited on 5 March 1801.</note> are not within reach, Henry[SoutheyHH] could point out to you some baths either natural or artificial which are. The warm salt water bath would be very likely to be beneficial.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You ask me concerning the Q Review. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> is shy of writing to me because he is playing a part about it which he knows I shall not like. He is very much in Barrows<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Barrow, 1st Baronet (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), the Second Secretary to the Admiralty 1804&#8211;1806, 1807&#8211;1845 and a regular contributor to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> hands; &#8211; &amp; I believe the wish of both is that <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> should hold it as long as he possibly can, &amp; that when he can hold it no longer they should find a successor who would conduct it just in the same manner, &#8211; that is to say, who would allow B. &amp; one or two others the same license. -<ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> however is very much hampered here; &amp; his cupidity has invented another difficulty for himself. He pays <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> 1200 &#163; a year, but means to curtail his successor to 1000 &#163;, &#8211; &amp; he has the modesty to propose that <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> shall have a rider of 500 upon his during his life: &#8211; terms upon which it is quite certain that no one who is not absolutely needy &amp; unfit for the situation, will accept it. He is afraid that whenever <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> leaves it the sale will decrease, &#8211; &amp; does not perceive that meantime he is incurring an immediate loss by <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> delays. I have scarcely heard any thing from him since I left town.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am reading Casaubons Epistles,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Casaubon (1559&#8211;1614), <title>Epistolae</title> (1656), no. 453 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> which ought to have been read before the Book of the Church,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> as also should Cardinal D&#8217;Ossats letters,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Arnaud D&#8217;Ossat (1537&#8211;1604), <title>Lettres du Cardinal d&#8217;Ossat, avec des Notes Historiques et Politiques de M. Amelot De La Houssaie</title> (1708), no. 851 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; Peter Heylyns Account of Guernsey &amp; Jersey.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Heylyn (1600&#8211;1662; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Survey of the Estate of France and Some of the Adjoyning Ilands</title> (1656), no. 1187 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Casaubon was among the books which <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> sent me, <del>&amp; is the</del> he refers to it in his Dialogues, &#8211; one of which is between Casaubon &amp; James I.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Dialogue VIII in Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, pp. [93]&#8211;112, where Casaubon converses with James I and VI (1567&#8211;1625; King of Scotland 1567&#8211;1603, King of Great Britain 1603&#8211;1625; <title>DNB</title>). Landor directed his readers to an &#8216;attentive perusal&#8217; of Casaubon&#8217;s letters (p. 96).</note> The Cardinals letters I bought at Norwich P Heylyn had been long in &lt;my&gt; possession &#8211; but I had forgotten that it contained information concerning Laud&#8217;s<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William Laud (1573&#8211;1645; <title>DNB</title>), Archbishop of Canterbury 1633&#8211;1645.</note> system &amp; views which is not to be found elsewhere. If I should compose a Book of the State,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write &#8216;The Book of the State&#8217; as a companion to his <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> the facts which I have found in these works may as well be introduced there, as incorporated in a future edition of the B.C. But this is very doubtful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have nearly got rid of my cold, tho still with some remains of the cough. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> will conduce to my recovery, by inducing me to live more upon the move now that I am able to do it. We are to dine al fresco by the lake side tomorrow &#8211; if the weather as it promises should permit; &#8211; &amp; next week he will be introduced to a nearer acquaintance with the mountains.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Did you see Conde&#8217;s Catalogue?<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Catalogue of the Curious Library of Don J. Antonio Conde, Part the Second. Being an Extraordinary Collection of Spanish Books and Manuscripts, and Oriental Literature Printed and Manuscript</title> (London, 1824). This sale catalogue detailed part of the library of Jos&#233; Antonio Conde y Garcia (1766&#8211;1820), a Spanish scholar and historian.</note> Among the MSS. were the three parts of the Cronica del R D Joam 1 by Gomes Eannes,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Coronica del Rey Dom Joao de boa memoria primero de Portugal deste nome, composta por Gomez Yanez. Acabado de trasladar no anno 1545, 3 vol.&#8217; This was a chronicle by Gomes Eanes de Zurara (c. 1410&#8211;c. 1474) of the reign of John I (1357&#8211;1433; King of Portugal 1385&#8211;1433); see Southey to John Murray, 11 August 1824, Letter 4228.</note> &#8211; of which only one has been printed. I am endeavouring to find who was the purchaser that I know where to borrow it, if possible, as soon as the Peninsular War<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> is off my hands. A copy of the Quatrocientas Preguntas (for which I gave half a guinea in 1803) sold at this sale for seventeen guineas &amp; a half.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Luis de Escobar (c. 1475&#8211;1552/1553), <title>Las Quatrocientas Respeustas a Otras Tantas Preguntas</title> (1550&#8211;1552), no. 3373 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> I saw only one part of the Catalogue, &#8211; it was the richest I ever saw.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the children. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> has a letter from one of his brothers, which travelled with him &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3">  RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>