<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4231" type="letter"><head>4231. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1824-08-13">13 August 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Revd. Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmarks: E/ 18 xx 18/ 1824; [partial]/AUx/ 1824<lb/>
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 247. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note>
            </head>
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1824-08-13"> 13 Aug. 1824</date></dateline></opener>
            
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">The traveller</ref> arrived safely this morning, &#38; nothing the worse for the wear. He was so little tired that by way of refreshing himself he took a walk of four miles with us before dinner, &#38; is now amusing himself with his two Welsh nieces<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> on the green.</p>
         <p rend="indent1">   I cannot but think you might derive benefit from warm bathing. It is rheumatism, &#38; not age that cripples you; – &#38; tho the Caldas<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The hot, sulphurous spring and spa town of Caldas da Rainha in Portugal. Southey had visited on 5 March 1801.</note> are not within reach, Henry[SoutheyHH] could point out to you some baths either natural or artificial which are. The warm salt water bath would be very likely to be beneficial.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">You ask me concerning the Q Review. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> is shy of writing to me because he is playing a part about it which he knows I shall not like. He is very much in Barrows<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Barrow, 1st Baronet (1764–1848; <title>DNB</title>), the Second Secretary to the Admiralty 1804–1806, 1807–1845 and a regular contributor to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> hands; – &#38; I believe the wish of both is that <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> should hold it as long as he possibly can, &#38; that when he can hold it no longer they should find a successor who would conduct it just in the same manner, – that is to say, who would allow B. &#38; one or two others the same license. -<ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> however is very much hampered here; &#38; his cupidity has invented another difficulty for himself. He pays <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> 1200 £ a year, but means to curtail his successor to 1000 £, – &#38; he has the modesty to propose that <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> shall have a rider of 500 upon his during his life: – terms upon which it is quite certain that no one who is not absolutely needy &#38; unfit for the situation, will accept it. He is afraid that whenever <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> leaves it the sale will decrease, – &#38; does not perceive that meantime he is incurring an immediate loss by <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> delays. I have scarcely heard any thing from him since I left town.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I am reading Casaubons Epistles,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Casaubon (1559–1614), <title>Epistolae</title> (1656), no. 453 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> which ought to have been read before the Book of the Church,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> as also should Cardinal D’Ossats letters,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Arnaud D’Ossat (1537–1604), <title>Lettres du Cardinal d’Ossat, avec des Notes Historiques et Politiques de M. Amelot De La Houssaie</title> (1708), no. 851 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> &#38; Peter Heylyns Account of Guernsey &#38; Jersey.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Heylyn (1600–1662; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Survey of the Estate of France and Some of the Adjoyning Ilands</title> (1656), no. 1187 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Casaubon was among the books which <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> sent me, <del>&#38; is the</del> he refers to it in his Dialogues, – one of which is between Casaubon &#38; James I.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Dialogue VIII in Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, pp. [93]–112, where Casaubon converses with James I and VI (1567–1625; King of Scotland 1567–1603, King of Great Britain 1603–1625; <title>DNB</title>). Landor directed his readers to an ‘attentive perusal’ of Casaubon’s letters (p. 96).</note> The Cardinals letters I bought at Norwich P Heylyn had been long in &#60;my&#62; possession – but I had forgotten that it contained information concerning Laud’s<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William Laud (1573–1645; <title>DNB</title>), Archbishop of Canterbury 1633–1645.</note> system &#38; views which is not to be found elsewhere. If I should compose a Book of the State,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write ‘The Book of the State’ as a companion to his <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> the facts which I have found in these works may as well be introduced there, as incorporated in a future edition of the B.C. But this is very doubtful.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I have nearly got rid of my cold, tho still with some remains of the cough. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> will conduce to my recovery, by inducing me to live more upon the move now that I am able to do it. We are to dine al fresco by the lake side tomorrow – if the weather as it promises should permit; – &#38; next week he will be introduced to a nearer acquaintance with the mountains.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  Did you see Conde’s Catalogue?<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Catalogue of the Curious Library of Don J. Antonio Conde, Part the Second. Being an Extraordinary Collection of Spanish Books and Manuscripts, and Oriental Literature Printed and Manuscript</title> (London, 1824). This sale catalogue detailed part of the library of José Antonio Conde y Garcia (1766–1820), a Spanish scholar and historian.</note> Among the MSS. were the three parts of the Cronica del R D Joam 1 by Gomes Eannes,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Coronica del Rey Dom Joao de boa memoria primero de Portugal deste nome, composta por Gomez Yanez. Acabado de trasladar no anno 1545, 3 vol.’ This was a chronicle by Gomes Eanes de Zurara (c. 1410–c. 1474) of the reign of John I (1357–1433; King of Portugal 1385–1433); see Southey to John Murray, 11 August 1824, Letter 4228.</note> – of which only one has been printed. I am endeavouring to find who was the purchaser that I know where to borrow it, if possible, as soon as the Peninsular War<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> is off my hands. A copy of the Quatrocientas Preguntas (for which I gave half a guinea in 1803) sold at this sale for seventeen guineas &#38; a half.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Luis de Escobar (c. 1475–1552/1553), <title>Las Quatrocientas Respeustas a Otras Tantas Preguntas</title> (1550–1552), no. 3373 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> I saw only one part of the Catalogue, – it was the richest I ever saw.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &#38; the children. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> has a letter from one of his brothers, which travelled with him –</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">  RS. </signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
