<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4238" type="letter"><head>4238. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#NicholsJohn">James Nichols</ref>, <date when="1824-08-24">24 August 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ James Nichols Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 22 Warwick Square/ Newgate Street/ London<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298	<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 27 AU 27/ 1824<lb/>
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
               MS: John Rylands Library, University of Manchester, Methodist Archives, MAM PLP 98.8.8. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1824-08-24"> 24 Aug. 1824</date></dateline>
            
          <salute>  Dear Sir</salute></opener>
          <p rend="indent1">  I thank you for your Book<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">James Nichols, <title>Calvinism and Arminianism Compared in Their Principles and Tendency </title>(1824).</note> &#38; for the obliging letter which accompanied it. They reached me yesterday afternoon &#38; when I add that I have gone thro the first volume, you will perceive how much the work has engaged my attention. Had it been published twelve months earlier, – my sketch of our Ecclesiastical History<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> would have been less imperfect than it is, for you have given much information upon points with which I was but ill acquainted.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  You Sir I am sure can understand the pleasure which I feel in finding that an enquiry so diligent as yours into so momentous a subject confirms in all points the opinions in which my mind reposes after its own researches. And I hope our labours, directed as they are to the same end, will obtain the credit of disinterested sincerity as coming from laymen. Let the Church of England continue true to itself, &#38; it will not want zealous defenders.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  I am afraid the form of your work will impede its sale. It is a mass of most valuable Contributions to our Ecc. History, which would have found <del>their</del> &#60;its&#62; way into more hands had it not borne a title which announces controversy rather than history &#38; biography. Some opportunity I shall have of making it known. &#38; will most gladly improve every opportunity that offers. And truly glad shall I be to become personally known to you when next I may visit London, – or whenever you may find your way to this Land of Lakes.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">May I beg you to present my friendly regards to your friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#JacksonThomas">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jackson</ref>, – as a fellow labourer in a good cause</p>
         <closer>  <salute rend="indent2"> &#38; believe me Dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">  Yrs with sincere respect</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">  Robert Southey.</signed> </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
