<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4239Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4239Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4239" type="letter">
        <head>4239. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>,<date when="1824-08-26"> 26 August 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Hale/ near/ Salisbury<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 30 AU 30/ 1824<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 240 1824/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> August/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> September/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Oct.<lb />
               MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 207&#8211;208.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-08-26">26 Aug. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>  My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  Your letter would not have remained a single post unanswered &#8211; if it had been in my power to have replied to it. But I found it yesterday on returning from the first mornings exercise I have ventured to take, &#8211; when I had only twenty minutes for dressing to receive <ref type="m" target="people.html#JebbJohn">the Bishops of Limerick</ref> &amp; New York<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Henry Hobart (1775&#8211;1830), Episcopal Bishop of New York 1816&#8211;1830. He undertook a prolonged visit to Europe in 1823&#8211;1825, in an attempt to improve his health.</note> at dinner, &#8211; &amp; was moreover in a state of great bodily uneasiness. &#8211; My first business this morning is thus to do &#8211; what I was in this manner compelled yesterday to leave undone.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Your excellent mother<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary May, n&#233;e Coppendale (1745&#8211;1824), May&#8217;s mother, had died on 21 August 1824.</note> appears to have been favoured with something like that <hi rend="ital">&#949;&#965;&#952;&#945;&#957;&#945;&#963;&#953;&#945;</hi>
          <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;euthanasia&#8217;, literally a &#8216;good death&#8217;.</note> which in patriarchal <del>xxx</del> times<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The age of the biblical patriarchs, Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, related in <title>Genesis</title> 12&#8211;50, when men lived to a great age and died peacefully.</note> seems to have been the natural &amp; ordinary termination of life, but with which not one in ten thousand, &#8211; even of those who attain to a good old age, is now blest. You have been fortunate in possessing her so long, &#8211; &amp; fortunate even in seeing her depart before the infirmities of age became what they too frequently are, humiliating as well as painful to humanity. This affliction &#8211; deep as it is, &#8211; has occurred in the due course of nature it was neither unforeseen, nor untimely; &#8211; no human care, &#8211; no circumstances could have averted, or delayed it. It is a grief which the heart can endure to remember, &#8211; which has every thing to hallow it &amp; which time will soon ripen so that it <del>will</del> shall lose all its bitterness.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The generation before us is rapidly passing away, &amp; we are already among the elders of this age. &#8211; Neither of my parents compleated their fiftieth year.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">Robert Southey, Senior</ref> had died at the age of 47 and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">Margaret Southey</ref> at 49.</note> I have been very much shaken at the completion of mine. This is the third year in which my annual catarrh has ended in a cough, &amp; this year the cough came on early, lay deep, &amp; keeps still a lingering hold, &#8211; as if laying claim to its inheritance tho not perhaps taking livery &amp; seizin of it as yet. The relaxation which this summer visitation always brings on brought with it this year a most unpleasant symptom, &#8211; that of a h&#230;morrhage from the rectum upon walking even a mile, &#8211; &amp; once indeed in merely walking the room. I was at one time apprehensive that this would entirely have confined me to the house, but a few cautious trials have given me hope. If I can bring myself into a condition that will allow me to leave home, it is my full purpose next spring to try whether I can avert the yearly attack by running away from it, <del>xxx</del> frequent change of air &amp; much exercise &#8211; in a word travelling is the best chance &#8211; &amp; I have almost promised the Bp of Limerick[Jebb] (who came here in the hope of taking me to Ireland with him) &#8211; that I will visit him next May.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not visit Ireland in 1825, but instead made a journey to the Low Countries.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I thought to have finished this in the evening &#8211; but interruptions usual at this time of year leave me only time to say God bless you, my dear friend</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <del>Yrs</del> Yrs most affectionately<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3">  RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>