<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4243Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4243Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4243" type="letter">
        <head>4243. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1824-09-09">9 September 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Major General Peachy/ Sidmouth/ Devonshire<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 28603. AL; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-09-09">9 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have allowed your last letter to remain unanswered longer than it would otherwise have done; partly in the expectation that I might give you some news of your friends the Bishop of Jamaica<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Christopher Lipscomb (1781&#8211;1843), Vicar of Sutton Benger, Wiltshire 1818&#8211;1824, first Bishop of Jamaica 1824&#8211;1842.</note> &amp; Dr Gabell,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Dison Gabell (1764&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), Rector of St Lawrence, Winchester 1788&#8211;1831, Ashow, Warwickshire 1812&#8211;1831, and Binfield, Berkshire 1820&#8211;1831; Headmaster of Winchester College 1810&#8211;1823.</note> whom it gave me some reason to look for: but they have not as yet made their appearance. We have however had that most excellent &amp; able man <ref type="m" target="people.html#JebbJohn">the Bp of Limerick</ref>, who came here partly with the hope of persuading me to accompany him to Ireland, &amp; whom I have promised to visit in the month of May next, for in truth I was not well enough to have gone with him, even if it had suited my arrangements to leave home at this season. On the same day the American Bishop Hobart<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Henry Hobart (1775&#8211;1830), Bishop of New York 1816&#8211;1830. He undertook a prolonged visit to Europe in 1823&#8211;1825, in an attempt to improve his health.</note> dined with us, &#8211; &amp; I could not help wishing that the West Indian Prelate, &amp; the new <ref type="m" target="people.html#BlomfieldCharlesJames">Bishop of Chester</ref>, whom I expect to see here had happened to arrive also, as such a meeting of mitred heads would have been not a little extraordinary in <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We were on Helvellin last week with your friends the Malkins,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Frederic Malkin (1802&#8211;1830), author of <title>The History of Greece from the Earliest Times to its Final Subjection to Rome</title> (1829), and <ref type="m" target="people.html#MalkinArthur">Arthur Malkin</ref>, civil engineer and writer. They were the two younger sons of Benjamin Heath Malkin (1769&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>), the headmaster of the grammar school at Bury St Edmunds 1809&#8211;1828. William Peachy had married secondly in 1812 a widow called Susannah Henry (dates unknown); Mrs Peachy&#8217;s mother was an inhabitant of Bury St Edmunds; see Robert Southey to John Spedding, 12 September 1818, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Letter 3192.</note> &amp; they were with us yesterday evening. I hope it is not so painful for them to engage in conservation, as it is for me to listen to them; they <del>experi</del> appear to labour dreadfully in bringing out their words (especially the elder) &amp; the fear of mistaking what they say renders it more difficult to catch their meaning. &#8211; One of them would bring out a word of seven syllables one day. The misfortune is the more pitiable as they are both young men who would have a great deal to say, if they could utter it with more facility.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have seen very little company this season, &amp; no other person of any note or name, &#8211; except the young Duke of Buccleugh,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Montagu Douglas Scott, 5th Duke of Buccleuch (1806&#8211;1884; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Privy Seal 1842&#8211;1846, Lord President of the Council 1846. </note> &#8211; a youth of very prepossessing manners &amp; appearance. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> has just announced that he shall with me on Saturday next, &amp; I know not that we have <del>xxxxxx</del> any other guest to expect. <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> is in a fair way of being deserted by all its visitable neighbourhood. The Fryers<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Harrison Fryer (1777&#8211;1855) of Whitley House, Northumberland. Fryer was a surveyor, geologist and mining engineer who spent part of each year at Keswick. At this time he was renting Ormathwaite, a large house about a mile and a quarter from Keswick. He married Mary Laetitia Wilbraham (1799&#8211;1874), who had been Tom Southey&#8217;s lodger, in June 1822.</note> remove this week to a house near Cockermouth. Ponsonby<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Ponsonby (1778&#8211;1841) of the Royal Navy, who had rented various properties in the Keswick area. He moved to Springfield, near Whitehaven.</note> has bought a place not far from Whitehaven, &#8211; &amp; the Calverts<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">William Calvert</ref> and his wife Mary (c. 1775&#8211;1834), n&#233;e Mitchinson.</note> will follow their daughter to town<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Calvert (1804&#8211;1890), daughter of William Calvert. She married Joshua Stanger (1801&#8211;1854), son of James Stanger, in 1824 and moved to London.</note> as soon as they can let their land. The place of any of these families is not likely to be supplied, &amp; the loss of them all, &#8211; is not likely to increase your inducements for repairing to the Island, I fear. We are eating your apples &amp; have eaten your melons, &#8211; but we should like them better if they did remind us of your absence</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We miss the elder girls<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha Southey</ref>.</note> too, who tho the house is not empty, have left a void in it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for news when I have told you that the bookbinder is found guilty of forgery, &amp; will go to bind books (if he can find any there) at Botany Bay;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">William Crampton (c. 1785&#8211;1843), a Keswick bookseller, had obtained a copper plate to forge one-guinea banknotes of the Whitehaven Bank of Johnston, Adamson, Hope &amp; Co. He was condemned to death at Carlisle Assizes on 26 August 1824, but recommended to mercy and sentenced to three years&#8217; imprisonment.</note> that Mr MacAdam<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">John Loudon McAdam (1756&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>), a pioneering road-builder and Surveyor-General of Metropolitan Roads from 1820. McAdam was employed to build a new road from Penrith through Keswick to Cockermouth (now the A66). His principal employer was Greenwich Hospital; he persuaded them to combine all roads to their lead mines into a single turnpike trust, the Alston Trust.</note> has introduced a colony of Irishmen to work upon the roads; &amp; that two of our numerous bad subjects are to take their trial for a brutal assault upon Scott the carrier,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Jonathan Scott (1777&#8211;1824), who worked as a carrier between Penrith and Whitehaven, died on 21 September 1824 following an assault. Thomas Ronson and Thomas Edmondson were charged in March 1825.</note> &#8211; you will have heard all that <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> affords at this time: unless it be news to hear that we have enjoyed one of the finest &amp; dryest seasons ever remembered in their parts. All the hay was got in without a drop of rain, &amp; good part of the corn has been equally fortunate.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am closely employed as usual, &#8211; chiefly at present upon the second volume of the Peninsular War,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> wherein I am making the best use I can of good &amp; abundant materials. My <del>Wom</del> Womankind join <del>with me</del> in kind remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref> &amp; yourself &#8211; farewell my Dear Sir</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">&amp; believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">   yrs faithfully</salute>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>