<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4257. Robert Southey to John Murray, 1 October 1824</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4257Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4257. Robert Southey to John Murray, 1 October 1824</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4257Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4257" type="letter">
        <head>4257. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1824-10-01">1 October 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>
            <lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               Watermark: KINGSFORD/ 1814<lb />
               Endorsement: Oct. 1 &#8211;&#8211;&#8211; 1824/ R Southey Esq<lb />
               MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-10-01">1 Oct. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the draft. The Pepys Memoirs<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Memoirs of Samuel Pepys, Esq. F.R.S.: Secretary to the Admiralty in the Reigns of Charles II and James II. Comprising his Diary from 1659 to 1669, Deciphered by the Rev. John Smith, From the Original Short-Hand MS. in the Pepysian Library, and a Selection from his Private Correspondence</title>, (1825), edited by Richard Griffin, 3rd Baron Braybrooke (1783&#8211;1858). This was the first edition of the diary of Samuel Pepys (1633&#8211;1703; <title>DNB</title>). A later edition from 1828 was no. 2208 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey did not write on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> will afford a good subject, &#8211; so will Sir T. Browne,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Thomas Browne (1605&#8211;1682; <title>DNB</title>) was a doctor and writer on a huge range of subjects. &#8216;The Whole Works and Correspondence of Sir Thomas Browne, Knt. M. D. of Norwich&#8217; was being advertised at this time as forthcoming with Longmans, for example, in the <title>London Courier and Evening Gazette</title>, 2 October 1824. This was an early indication of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilkinSimon">Simon Wilkin&#8217;s</ref> edition, which did not appear until 1835&#8211;1836. Southey acquired a copy and it became no. 376 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> which I shall the more willingly undertake, as the edition partly originated in an enquiry of mine concerning his papers. &#8211; You shall have an article upon Bayard<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sara Coleridge&#8217;s translation, <title>The Right Joyous and Pleasant History of the Feats, Gests, and Prowesses of the Chevalier Bayard, the Good Knight without Fear and without Reproach</title> (1825). Unsurprisingly, Southey gave this a glowing recommendation in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (October 1825), 355&#8211;397.</note> as soon as the book is ready. And a life of Baxter<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Puritan clergyman, Richard Baxter (1615&#8211;1691; <title>DNB</title>). It is not clear which of his works Southey was suggesting he review. He may have heard of the forthcoming <title>The Practical Works of the Rev. Richard Baxter with a Life of the Author and a Critical Examination of his Writings</title> (1830), edited by William Orme (1787&#8211;1830; <title>DNB</title>). Southey did not write on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> for which you will not forget to send me the new edition of his works, &#8211; which must now be nearly compleated.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Monastic Orders<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of the Monastic Orders&#8217; was never completed or published.</note> must be treated as Gibbon<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Gibbon (1737&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title> (1776&#8211;1789), no. 1099 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> has managed his subject &#8211; <del>&amp; require</del> the spirit of their history must be seized, &#8211; what is important &amp; interesting brought forward, what is unimportant passed over; &amp; if I were to say that it is hardly inferior to Gibbons subject in variety it would not be saying too much. It <del>embraces</del> includes no slight part of the history of the corruptions of Xtianity, of the conversion &amp; civilization of the Northern Nations, &#8211; of the decline &amp; revival of letters, &#8211; of the Reformation, &#8211; &amp; of the attempts made by the Romish Church to recover what it lost by the Reformation in Europe, &#8211; &amp; to extend its authority in other parts of the world. &#8211; So rich &amp; so various are the materials that if they were properly worked up, I know not whether the statesman, the philosopher, the antiquarian, the poet or the painter would be most interested by the display. And with the truth of history it would unite the wildness of romance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It would require, as far as I can estimate, six octavo volumes of from 4 to 500 pages.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">   My health has been much shaken this summer, &#8211; but I am now, thank God, well recovered, &amp; in full activity</p>
        <p>
          Believe me my dear Sir<lb/>
            Yrs very truly<lb/>
            Robert Southey.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>