<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4258Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4258Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4258" type="letter">
        <head>4258. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-10-04">4 October 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ xx OC xx/ 18x4<lb />
               Endorsement: Confidential./ 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Octo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1824<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 186&#8211;187 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-10-04">4 Oct. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Murray has sent me a draft for the article, saying it will appear in the next number, &amp; not saying a word concerning any desired alteration.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of John Johnson (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. It was published in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263&#8211;311. Southey had hoped it might appear in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (January 1824), published 28 August 1824.</note> His letter states that having conversed with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> &amp; &#8220;some other literary friends&#8221; upon my proposed History of the Monastic Orders<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">This work was never completed.</note> &#8220;he now comprehends its probable interest &amp; popularity&#8221; &amp; shall be happy to come to &#8220;closer quarters upon the subject.&#8221; &#8211; he says something of future papers for the QR asking me to undertake the Pepys Memoirs<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Memoirs of Samuel Pepys, Esq. F.R.S.: Secretary to the Admiralty in the Reigns of Charles II and James II. Comprising his Diary from 1659 to 1669, Deciphered by the Rev. John Smith, From the Original Short-Hand MS. in the Pepysian Library, and a Selection from his Private Correspondence</title> (1825), edited by Richard Griffin, 3rd Baron Braybrooke (1783&#8211;1858). This was the first edition of the diary of Samuel Pepys (1633&#8211;1703; <title>DNB</title>). A later edition from 1828 was no. 2208 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey did not write on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> &amp; Sir Th. Brownes Works,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Thomas Browne (1605&#8211;1682; <title>DNB</title>) was a doctor and writer on a huge range of subjects. &#8216;The Whole Works and Correspondence of Sir Thomas Browne, Knt. M. D. of Norwich&#8217; was being advertised at this time as forthcoming with Longmans, for example, in the <title>London Courier and Evening Gazette</title>, 2 October 1824. This was an early indication of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilkinSimon">Simon Wilkin&#8217;s</ref> edition, which did not appear until 1835&#8211;1836. Southey acquired a copy and it became no. 376 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#8211; &amp; writes in a strain of profound civility, &#8211; requesting a brief <del>xxx</del> sketch of my monastic plan. &#8211; I have told him little more than that it may be included in six octavo volumes, &amp; comprizes matter hardly less varied &amp; extensive than Gibbons Decline &amp; Fall of the Rom. Empire.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Gibbon (1737&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title> (1776&#8211;1789), published in six volumes, no. 1099 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> If he offers me 500 &#163; per volume I will ere long make it my chief employment; but he shall not have it for less, &amp; I am in no haste to proceed with the negociation being at present sufficiently employed &amp; to my hearts content.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The medical practitioner would not have puzzled you, if fortune had permitted us to have been somewhat &lt;more&gt; together during the last ten years. Yet you have heard from me the name of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Daniel Dove,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Dr Daniel Dove was the central figure in Southey&#8217;s <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847).</note> &amp; something I think of the Tristam-ish, Butler-ish plan<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">One inspiration for <title>The Doctor</title> was the stories about &#8216;The Butler&#8217;, a mock-heroic figure, that Bedford and Southey had developed as boys; another was Laurence Sterne (1713&#8211;1768; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life and Opinions of Tristram Shandy, Gentleman</title> (1759&#8211;1767).</note> of his history, which, if the secret be but kept, must I think inevitably excite curiosity as well as notice. I have lately taken a pleasant spell at it &amp; have something more than a volume ready, &#8211; that is to say something more than half of what I propose to publish, following it nor not with as much more according to its sale &amp; my own inclination. One reason why I wished for you here at this time was to &lt;have&gt; shewn it you &#8211; &amp; to have had your help, for you could have excellently helped me, &amp; I think would have been moved in spirit so to do. If I finish it during the winter, of which there is good hope I will devise some pretext for going to town, where I must be while it is printed to avoid the transmission of proofs, by which it would be easy &#8211; from calculation of time, to ascertain how far they had travelled &amp; so of course to discover the author, &#8211; to whom the printers are to have no clue.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>