<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4259Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4259Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4259" type="letter">
        <head>4259. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-10-06">6 October 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand] Portsmouth Tenth Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1824/ Miss Southey/ with M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wade Browne/ Exeter/ Free/ JRickman<lb />
               Stamped: PORTSMOUTH/ OC 10/ 1824/ 73<lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 4p. <lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>  My dear EMay</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The stinking stone was the first thing for which I enquired in Crediton Church.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Southey&#8217;s Common-Place Books</title>, 4 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, p. 252, &#8216;In Crediton Church is one stone remarkable, because it has the smell of a corpse.&#8217;</note> I believe there is nothing wonderful in it: strike a flint, &amp; you will produce a strong smell. The size of the stone may possibly make it remarkable, &amp; at any rate no one should be allowed to indulge that vile English humour of breaking it to carry away a fragment. Our nation is infamous for this &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#LovellRobert">Robert Lovell</ref> has just been groaning over an example of it in Bedes chair, &#8211; certainly the most venerable relic in these kingdoms, which is utterly defaced &amp; half destroyed by those who have cut their names in it, &amp; carried pieces away.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A wooden chair, reputedly that of St Bede (673&#8211;735; <title>DNB</title>), used to be on display in the chancel at St Paul&#8217;s Church, Jarrow. The chair was not only a tourist attraction but also believed to have the property of improving the chance of bearing many children. It is now thought to date to the fourteenth century.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am not certain whether or not I have said to &lt;you&gt; in any former letter, that if your invitation to pass a <del>xxx</del> day or two with the Longmans should be repeated, I wish you to accept it. This I should not do, if you were not disposed to like the female part of the family.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Longman had married Mary Slater (1781&#8211;1842), of Horsham, Sussex, in 1799. Their daughters included: Mary Longman (1801&#8211;1870), who married the publisher Andrew Spottiswoode (1787&#8211;1866) in 1819; and Frances Longman (1807&#8211;1888), who married Reginald Bray (1797&#8211;1879), a solicitor of Shere, Surrey, in 1836.</note> But they appear very likeable persons, &amp; I should like you to be better acquainted with them, because I believe their father has a sort of feeling towards me which is not entirely dependent upon the state of my accounts. Bookseller usually consider author as a goose whom he has to pluck; &#8211; &amp; in that light the <hi rend="ital">firm</hi> in <ref type="m" target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster Row</ref> consider me &amp; deal with me accordingly; but I believe that <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> individually regards me with respect &amp; good will.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  You will not wonder that you are wished for at home now that the winter is approaching, &amp; we are left to ourselves, &#8211; <hi rend="ital">totally</hi> to ourselves it will soon be. Without intending to hurry you, or prevent any visits which you may purpose to make, I suppose, you will think of returning with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> about February, &#8211; that is as soon as the weather becomes mild enough for travelling. There is a bare possibility, (which must neither be built upon, nor mentioned to any one except <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">your Uncle Henry</ref>,) &#8211; that I may go to London at that time, under pretext of bringing you home, &#8211; but in reality to see a favourite book of yours carried thro the press xx with all imaginable secresy &amp; dispatch.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847), which was published anonymously.</note> I have done so much to it within the last three weeks, as to render this possible, &#8211; &amp; in fact easy, if that abominable Tale of Paraguay<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> were not hanging about my neck like a millstone. I get on with it <hi rend="ital">con amore</hi>:<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;with love&#8217;.</note> &amp; yet should proceed with more pleasure if you were here to witness its progress. &#8211; You would have had some nonsense from me ere this, if all my nonsense had not of late been directed into this channel.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Your character of John L.[Lightfoot,JohnP] is not a pleasant one, &amp; I am sorry for it, &#8211; the fault not being <del>one</del> &lt;of that kind&gt; which time is likely to correct. No man can either be happy himself thro life, or make those so who are connected with him, unless he has good principles, good temper, &amp; good health. A woman may be deceived concerning the first, &amp; must take her chance for the last: but if she marries a man of uncomfortable temper it must be her own fault. You have not mentioned Bridget<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Bridget Mary Lightfoot (1810&#8211;1889), daughter of Nicholas Lightfoot.</note> in your letters, &#8211; a wild-eyed girl who took my fancy much. Indeed I liked the whole family. There was a warmth &amp; heartiness in their whole behavior towards me, which one does not always find in the family of an old friend, however close the ties of friendship may be with the master of the house.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  But I must conclude that I may pass the rest of the evening with your friend the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. &#8211;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847).</note> There is a prospect of seeing <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Sir WScott</ref> here for a day, with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref>, so <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> writes to tell me. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> sends his love &amp; a kiss, &amp; the promise of a letter. He was <del>xxxx</del> very unwell last week with one of his bilious attacks, but thank God is perfectly recovered. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Your mother</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">the Venerable</ref> are drinking tea with the Miss Dentons.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Denton (c. 1758&#8211;1820), Vicar of Crosthwaite, Keswick 1786&#8211;1820, had three daughters, two of whom, Elizabeth and Sarah (dates unknown), were renting Greta Lodge at this time and were therefore Southey&#8217;s near neighbours.</note> Our kindest remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Browne</ref> &amp; Mary<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Browne (1810&#8211;1892), daughter of Elizabeth Browne. She later married William Farwell (1806&#8211;1876), Rector of St Martin&#8217;s, Liskeard 1830&#8211;1876.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <lb />
          <p rend="indent1">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-10-06">6 Oct. 1824</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>