<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4261</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4261Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4261" type="letter">
        <head>4261. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1824-10-10">10 October 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ J Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>
            <lb />
               Endorsement: 10 Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1824<lb />
               MS: Huntington Library, RS 453. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 188&#8211;189 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1824-10-10">Oct. 10. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Peninsular War is going on well. 20 sheets of the second vol. are printed.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> The printer<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Davison (1766&#8211;1831).</note> does not hurry me, neither do I hurry the printer; having found by long experience that after letting a narration rest awhile, it is renewed with fresh spirit. It is proceeding well, the best proof of which is that I am well satisfied with it myself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  My literary employments have never in the slightest degree injured my health. For in truth I neither am, nor ever have been a close student. If I do not take sufficient exercise, it is not from any love of the desk, but for the want of a companion or an object to draw me out when the season is uninviting; &#8211; &amp; yet I overcame this <del>xx</del> dislike of solitary walking, &amp; every day unless it be a settled rain, walk long enough &amp; far &amp; fast enough, to require the wholesome process of rubbing down on my return. At no time of my life have I ever applied half so closely to my employments, as you always do to yours. They impose upon me no restrictions, there is nothing irksome in them, &#8211; no anxiety connected with them. &#8211; they leave me master<del>s</del> of my time &amp; of myself. Nor do I doubt but that they would prove conducive to longevity, if my constitution were disposed for it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> With regard to the prudence of working up ready materials rather than laying in more, upon whatever I employ myself I must of necessity be doing both. The work which I am most desirous of compleating is the Hist. of Portugal, as being that for which most preparations have been made, &amp; most time bestowed on it.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had begun research for his &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217; on his visit to the country in 1800&#8211;1801, but it was never finished or published.</note> And when the Peninsular War shall be completed &#8211; by Gods blessing, &#8211; a week will not elapse before it goes to the press, &#8211; for it has been long in much greater forwardness than any work which I ever before began to print.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am however conscious <del>of</del> now of a disposition the reverse of Montaigne&#8217;s who loved he said rather to forge his mind than to furnish it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Michel de Montaigne (1533&#8211;1592), <title>Essais</title> (1580), Book 3, chapter 3, &#8216;Des Trois Commerces&#8217;: &#8216;Meditation is a large and powerful study to such as vigorously can taste and employ themselves therein. I had rather forge than furnish my mind.&#8217; Southey returned to this quotation from Montaigne in <title>The Doctor</title>, 7 vols (London, 1834&#8211;1847), IV, p. 225.</note> Avarice you know is the passion of declining life, &amp; avaricious I confess myself to be of the only treasure I have ever coveted, or ever shall possess. My temper or turn of mind, inclines also to form new projects, &#8211; but it is one thing to perceive what might be done, &amp; another to dream of doing it. &#8211; No doubt wherever <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Telford</ref> is travelling he cannot help seeing a line of road ought to be carried, <del>or</del> a harbour improved, or a pier carried out &#8211; In like manner I see possibilities &amp; capabilities &amp; desirablities, &#8211; &amp; think no more of them</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am sorry to hear of Mitchells<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Mitchell (1779&#8211;1824), Principal Inspector of Roads and Bridges in the Highlands 1810&#8211;1824. Southey and Rickman had met him on their tour of Scotland in August&#8211;September 1819. John Mitchell was a prot&#233;g&#233;e of Thomas Telford, and Telford ensured that Mitchell&#8217;s eldest son, Joseph Mitchell (1803&#8211;1883), succeeded his father as Principal Inspector of Roads and Bridges in the Highlands 1824&#8211;1867.</note> death, an upright, useful, &amp; happy man, &amp; therefore on all accounts worthy of regret. You have been a true friend to his family, &#8211; but to whom are you not a true friend?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Your Chichester travellers<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> have not yet shown themselves &#8211; They will find me, as any visitor will who comes in a wedding garment, always at leisure.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="salute1">  God bless you<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>