<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4263. Robert Southey to Neville White, 13 October 1824</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4263Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4263. Robert Southey to Neville White, 13 October 1824</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4263Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4263" type="letter">
        <head>4263. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1824-10-13">13 October 1824</date>
          </head><p>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 442&#8211;443.</p>
        <opener>
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
          </address>
          <date when="1824-10-13">Oct. 13. 1824.</date>
          <salute>   My dear Neville,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> First, let me thank you for offering to join me in an expedition to Holland, when I may find it possible to undertake one.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Neville White did accompany Southey on his visit to the Low Countries in 1825.</note> Most truly shall I rejoice to have such a companion. I am, however, under something like a promise of going to Ireland, when I take flight next May, in the hope of escaping from my annual visitation,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s hay fever.</note> to visit <ref type="m" target="people.html#JebbJohn">the Bishop of Limerick</ref>, who came hither about seven weeks ago with the hope of taking me home with him. At that time I was not sufficiently recovered to have ventured from home, even if it had suited me on other accounts to have absented myself from my desk. I am now, thank God, once more in good health, and take a good deal of pains in the way of exercise to keep myself so. The want of a companion in these walks is supplied by a book, so that the time is not wholly lost; this habit is with me full five&#8211;and&#8211;twenty years old, and I can read as well when walking as at the fire&#8211;side.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your newspaper amused me, though I was sorry to see how eagerly an ill feeling seizes upon every opportunity of showing itself. The festival<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Norwich and Norfolk Festival, held on 21&#8211;24 September 1824. Occasional fundraising concerts for the Norwich and Norfolk Hospital had been held since 1772, but the Festival of 1824 established the event on a triennial basis. It consisted of six performances in St Andrew&#8217;s Hall. The newspaper that Neville White sent Southey is difficult to identify with certainty. It might have been the <title>Norwich Mercury</title>, 9 October 1824, which contained articles and correspondence about the poor lighting and smell of gas in St Andrew&#8217;s Hall.</note> must have made <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref> all alive, and will, I hope, be renewed as often as is prudent. Perhaps there is no other mode of bringing so many people together for the purpose of enjoyment which is so entirely unexceptionable, even if the charitable application of the money were not considered; and this is a very disinterested opinion, from one who has no faculty, and consequently no taste, for music.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#AmyotThomas">Mr. Amyott</ref>
          <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Amyot was a native of Norwich and had practised as a solicitor there before moving to London in 1806.</note> is an acquaintance of mine, and a very obliging person he is. I am indebted to him for procuring me some Peninsular information some years ago. I am very glad to hear <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilkinSimon">Mr. Wilkin</ref> has commenced printing,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">This refers to an edition of the works of Sir Thomas Browne (1605&#8211;1682; <title>DNB</title>), a Norwich resident, doctor and writer on a huge range of subjects. &#8216;The Whole Works and Correspondence of Sir Thomas Browne, Knt. M. D. of Norwich&#8217; was advertised as forthcoming with Longmans, for example, in the <title>London Courier and Evening Gazette</title>, 2 October 1824. This was an early indication of Simon Wilkin&#8217;s edition, which did not appear until 1835&#8211;1836. Southey did not review this work, though he obtained a copy, no. 376 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> and am very sure that I shall do him more service than I could have done by becoming his editor. The matter of my reviewing the work is settled.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  You ask me concerning the &#8220;Methodist.&#8221; I sent a copy of the letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">the Bishop of London</ref>;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Mark Robinson (d. 1836), a Beverley draper, who was seeking to lead a group of local Methodists into union with the Church of England, had written to Southey on 13 January 1824; see Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 161&#8211;164. Southey had forwarded a copy of his letter to William Howley, the Bishop of London.</note> he thanked me for it, and in a sensible reply observed upon the difficulty of doing anything in the way of a formal negotiation. Meantime individual discretion might do something, and he thought the Methodists might very usefully be encouraged in the colonies, and perhaps in Ireland also. I had a second communication from Mark Robinson, who is a local preacher at Beverley. You will, of course, understand that he knows nothing of my laying the business before <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">the Bishop</ref>. The second letter related to the probability of the church Methodists separating from the Conference,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;Church Methodists&#8217; in Beverley did separate from the main body of Methodists in 1825 and built their own church in the town.</note> and showed a great tendency among them to split into parties. I am inclined to think that Methodism has in this country reached the point in which the main body will not be progressive in numbers, rather maintaining its population than increasing it, and losing as many by defection and schism as it acquires by proselytism and birth. But this rather alters the nature of the danger to the Establishment than diminishes it; for every new sect that branches off has a fresh principle of increase. I asked Mark Robinson to direct me to information concerning some of these sects, &#8211; the Ranters,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A pejorative name for the Primitive Methodists, who had separated from Methodism in 1807&#8211;1811.</note> &amp;c., which he has not yet done. If I could obtain sufficient documents, it is most likely that I should prepare a paper on the subject. God bless you, my dear Neville.</p>
        <p>
          Yours affectionately,<lb/>
           R.S.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>