<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4265</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4265Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4265" type="letter">
        <head>4265. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>],<date when="1824-10-18"> 18 October 1824</date>
          </head><p>Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 242 1824/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.<lb />
               MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p. <lb />
               Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 209&#8211;210.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-10-18">18 Oct. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  An unusual length of time has elapsed without my hearing from you, &amp; it has so happened that during that time I have not heard <hi rend="ital">of</hi> you from any other quarter. A heavy loss <del>xxx</del> such as that which you have sustained<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary May, n&#233;e Coppendale (1745&#8211;1824), May&#8217;s mother, had died on 21 August 1824.</note> hardly appears at first like a reality when the loss is unexpected or untimely this is peculiarly felt &amp; peculiarly painful; &#8211; &amp; tho in your case what has occurred has been in the due &amp; gentle course of nature, still any thing that produces so great a change in the relations of life, &amp; in the daily &amp; hourly thoughts &amp; feelings affects the mind something in this manner. I am anxious to hear from you &#8211; to know how you are, &#8211; &amp; to know also whether you receive more satisfactory accounts from Brazil.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John May was deeply concerned about his foundering business interests in Brazil.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Your goddaughter</ref> has been interrupted in her plans, which were to have left Exeter this day for Taunton, &amp; to have proceeded from thence on the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> for London with Lady Malet.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susannah Malet, n&#233;e Wales (1779&#8211;1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>).</note> But Lady M. has been summoned to Winchester by the very dangerous illness of a son,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Octavius Warre Malet (1811&#8211;1891), eighth son of Lady Susanna Malet. Octavius Warre Malet served in the East India Company before retiring to Somerset in 1864, where he played a leading role in the restoration of Taunton Castle.</note> an inflammation of the lungs having come on just as he was to all appearances recovering from the measles. The last<del>xx</del> accounts of him were more favourable. This leaves <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Edith</ref> at Exeter, in some uncertainty when to get from thence. She is with <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wade Browne</ref>, the widow of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneWade">my poor Ludlow friend</ref>, &#8211; &amp; herself a person for whom I have a very high regard. I suppose she will take the first opportunity that may occur of finding a fit escort in the stage for London; &amp; I expect that she will return with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> in February &#8211; that is, as soon as the depth of the winter shall be past. You will perhaps have heard of her from Ottery,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Ottery St Mary, Devon, home of many of Coleridge&#8217;s relatives.</note> where she past three days. I begin to be impatient for the return of these girls, &#8211; &amp; to feel that at my age I cannot afford to part with them for so long an absence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Having got rid of all remains of cough which my annual catarrh had left behind it, I have brought myself again into tolerable condition, &amp; am endeavouring to keep myself so by very dutiful exercise, which is rendered less irksome by the habit of reading while I walk, if the weather permits. My second volume of the P. War<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> is getting on well both in the press &amp; at the desk. Indeed I am at this time in the best disposition for getting on with the works which I have in hand: &amp; that disposition is increased by the desire of compleating them that I may lay down other foundations, &amp; work up the materials which I have so long been preparing. &#8211; My Colloquies<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> will very soon go to press, &#8211; indeed as soon as I hear from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">William Westall</ref> that the plates are in any state of forwardness.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall produced six sketches of Lake District scenes that were engraved for <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title>, 2 vols (London, 1829): vol. I: &#8216;Druidical Stones near Keswick&#8217;, &#8216;Derwentwater, Bassenthwaite-water, and Skiddaw from Walla Crag&#8217;, and &#8216;Derwentwater from Strand Shagg&#8217;; and vol. II: &#8216;Crosthwaite Church and Skiddaw&#8217;, &#8216;Greta Hall, Derwentwater, and Newlands&#8217;, and &#8216;Tarn of Blencathra&#8217;.</note> They will afford matter for abuse to many persons, for wonder to more, &#8211; but for sober reflection to not a few, &amp; for approbation also I trust. I expect little profit from them, &amp; more credit in future ages than in this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I believe one reason why neither <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> nor <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> write to me is a degree of shame concerning the QR. which <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">G.</ref> is plainly unwilling to <del>xxx</del> withdraw from, tho incapable of carrying it on, &#8211; &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">M.</ref> I suspect is desirous of driving a booksellers bargain about it, &#8211; perhaps even of trying the experiment of doing without an Editor. <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> writes to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Sir Walter Scott</ref> that he knows not where to look for an Editor: &#8211; there is some duplicity in this, after what has past with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John C.</ref> &#8211; which I have made <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> acquainted with. I still think necessity will compel <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> at last to do &#8211; what for his own interest he ought to have done long ago.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle&#8217;s</ref> last letter was written in good spirits, &amp; with a hand which has lost nothing of its firmness. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> spent his holydays with me, &#8211; a fine boy he is, &#8211; one <del>xx</del> concerning whose conduct there need be no apprehension, as far as any indications of youthful character may be trusted.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="salute1"> My best remembrances to your fireside.</salute>
          <salute rend="salute2">   God bless you my dear friend</salute>
          <salute rend="salute3"> Yrs most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>