<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4271Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4271" type="letter">
        <head>4271. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-10-30">30 October 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Grosvenor Charles Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Post-Office/ Dover.<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 2 NO 2/ 1824<lb />
               Endorsement: 30. Octo<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1824<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 191&#8211;192 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-10-30">30 Oct. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>  My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your ill news had reached me some days ago from a brother in law of Davies Gilbert&#8217;s,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Davies Gilbert (1767&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), Cornish engineer, antiquarian and MP for Helston 1804&#8211;1806, Bodmin 1806&#8211;1832. Gilbert was a friend of Thomas Beddoes and early patron of Humphry Davy. His &#8216;brother-in-law&#8217; was probably John Lewis Guillemard (1764&#8211;1844). In 1804 he married Mary Philippa Gilbert (1769&#8211;1850), sister of Davies Gilbert. Guillemard was part of a well-known family of Huguenot silk-weavers and an active member of many learned societies, including the Royal Society, the Royal Geographical Society and the Royal Institution, of which he was Secretary 1811&#8211;1813.</note> to whom I had given a letter of introduction to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>, &#8211; little apprehending in what state it would find him. The tenour of your letter leaves me very little hope, &#8211; tho some there is, from the strength of constitution which he has shewn, &amp; from the uncertain nature of the disease. You had not told me of the apoplectic <del>symptom</del> attack.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are many things worse than death. Indeed I should think any reasonable person would prefer it to old age if he did not feel that the prolongation of his life was desirable for the sake of others, whatever it might be for himself. If the event be dreaded, the sooner it is over the better, if it be desired, the sooner it comes; &#8211; &amp; desired or dreaded it must be. If there were a Balloon-Diligence to the other world, I think it would always be filled with passengers. You will not suppose from this that I am weary of life, blest with enjoyments as I am, &amp; full of employment. But if it were possible for me (which it is not) to regard myself alone, I would rather begin my travels in eternity than abide longer in a world, <del>where</del> in which I have much to do, &amp; little to hope.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">   Something upon this topic you will see in my Colloquies.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> They will go to press as soon as I hear from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> in what forwardness the engravers are.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall produced six sketches of Lake District scenes that were engraved for <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title>, 2 vols (London, 1829): vol. I: &#8216;Druidical Stones near Keswick&#8217;, &#8216;Derwentwater, Bassenthwaite-water, and Skiddaw from Walla Crag&#8217;, and &#8216;Derwentwater from Strand Shagg&#8217;; and vol. II: &#8216;Crosthwaite Church and Skiddaw&#8217;, &#8216;Greta Hall, Derwentwater, and Newlands&#8217;, and &#8216;Tarn of Blencathra&#8217;.</note> &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has announced the second vol. of the War for November,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;In November will be published, The Second Volume of the History of the Late War in Spain and Portugal. By Robert Southey. Printing for John Murray, Albemarle-street&#8217;, <title>Morning Post</title>, 26 October 1824. The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) did not appear until 1827.</note> &#8211; it would require the aid of some other Devils than those of the printing office to finish it before the spring, &amp; this he knows very well, both the ms. &amp; the proof sheets passing thro his hands. Just one quarter is printed, &amp; I am about 100 pages ahead of the printers.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Davison (1766&#8211;1831).</note> Of late I have made good progress in forwarding various works, in the hope of clearing my hands &amp; bettering my finances. I cannot get on <hi rend="ital">fast</hi> with the Tale of Paraguay<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825). It was written in stanzas of nine lines &#8211; eight in iambic pentameter, followed by a final alexandrine line. The rhyme scheme was &#8216;ababbcbbc&#8217;.</note> because of the stanza, but on with it I am getting, &amp; am half thro the third canto, the fourth brings it to its close. A good deal has been done to the Colloquies, &#8211; which will gain me much abuse now, &amp; some credit hereafter: &#8211; &amp; a good deal to the Doctor,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847).</note> which I should very much like to show you. &#8220;You shall see me insult the Public, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford -&#8221; &#8211; &amp; you will see that the Public will wonder who it is that insults them, &#8211; for I think I shall not be suspected.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Did I tell you, or has <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Dogstar</ref> himself told you, that he has bought a slice of Watson Taylors<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">George Watson-Taylor (1771&#8211;1841), very wealthy plantation owner in Jamaica and MP for Newport, Isle of Wight 1816&#8211;1818, Seaford 1818&#8211;1820, East Looe 1820&#8211;1826 and Devizes 1826&#8211;1832. He was also a playwright, poet and antiquarian. In 1819 he bought what is now 15&#8211;16 Cavendish Square for &#163;20,000 and was said to have spent another &#163;48,000 on its decoration. Henry Herbert Southey lived nearby in Queen Anne Street. In the late 1820s the plot was further redeveloped, including the construction of buildings in Harley Street. Henry Herbert Southey took 4 Harley Street as his home.</note> house? &#8211; an advantageous way in which his marriage settlement allows him to invest <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">his wife&#8217;s</ref> fortune. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> returns to London on the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonnes</ref>, &#8211; she will stay in town till the depth of winter is over, &amp; come home with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> in February, when we begin to look wishfully for their return.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">The Megist.</ref> sent me the paper upon Hayley<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of John Johnson (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. It was published in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263&#8211;311. Southey had hoped that it might appear in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (January 1824), published 28 August 1824.</note> the other day, with a note requesting alteration, but expressing himself as if I had written an unqualified panegyric upon Hayley<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hayley (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), poet and biographer.</note> as a Poet, &amp; saying he would rather lose the hundred pounds &#8211; than insert it in its present state. I answered him at length, &#8211; &amp; took a copy of my answer.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to [John Murray], 25 October [1824], Letter 4268.</note> I have not altered a word in the memoir, but have added two passages, containing grains enough of censure to balance any scruples of commendation which a blockhead may fancy he can discover. &#8211; How <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">the Megist.</ref> may feel about the knuckles I know not: but I gave him a wholesome warning about the QR. letting him know <del>xxx</del> of an opinion which has got abroad that he is endeavouring to get it conducted upon cheaper terms, &amp; to keep the management virtually in his own hands. His feelings towards me are of a very mixed nature, there is the pride of purse, &#8211; there is that sort of dislike which <del>he</del> arises from a consciousness that he has dealt with me in the very worst spirit of trade there is that sort of liking to counterbalance it which proceeds from the expectation of getting more out of me &lt;by continuing so to do:&gt;, &#8211; &amp; withal there is a certain degree of reluctant respect.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You are I hope enjoying leisure &amp; fresh air &amp; profiting by both. Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref>. If I had wings I would be with you</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>