<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4272Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4272Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4272" type="letter">
        <head>4272. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1824-10-30">30 October 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 1 NO 1/ 1824<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.335. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-10-30">30 Oct. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> hooping cough has influenced <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughters</ref> movements at Exeter in a manner which may as distinctly be traced as the way in which Jacks building a house led to the marriage at which the Priest all shaven &amp; shorn officiated.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In the nursery rhyme, &#8216;This is the House that Jack Built&#8217;, a whole series of consequences are built up from this first line, including, in the ninth verse, the arrival of a priest &#8216;all shaven and shorn&#8217; to conduct a marriage between the &#8216;man all tatter&#8217;d and torn&#8217; and the &#8216;maiden all forlorn&#8217;.</note> One of Lady Malets sons<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Octavius Warre Malet (1811&#8211;1891), the eighth son of Lady Susanna Malet. Octavius Warre Malet served in the East India Company before retiring to Somerset in 1864, where he played a leading role in the restoration of Taunton Castle.</note> had nearly lost his life at Winchester in consequence of the measles, she was summoned thither in all speed; &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">E May</ref> left in consequence to shape her operations how she could. To day we have heard that Colonel Coleridge<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">James Coleridge (1759&#8211;1836), eldest brother of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and father of John Taylor Coleridge and Henry Nelson Coleridge.</note> takes her under convoy on Friday the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> next, &#8211; he with two Ladies<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> is going to town to visit his daughter,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Patteson (1790&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>), a barrister and later Justice of the King&#8217;s Bench 1830&#8211;1852, had, on 22 April 1824, married Frances Duke Coleridge (1796&#8211;1842).</note> &#8211; &amp; they have taken the whole stage for their journey, &#8211; they start at six in the evening, &amp; reach London about three on the following afternoon when I trust <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> will be safely deposited at <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne&#8217;s</ref>. &#8211; I hope she will get thro all her engagements in or near town, so as to be ready for returning in February, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> with her: &#8211; that is, as soon as the severity of the winter is over. I begin to be a little impatient at losing both for so long a time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> I see announces my second volume for <del>next</del> November<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;In November will be published, The Second Volume of the History of the Late War in Spain and Portugal. By Robert Southey. Printing for John Murray, Albemarle-street&#8217;, <title>Morning Post</title>, 26 October 1824. The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) did not appear until 1827.</note> &#8211; if he had said May, he might have hit the mark. I know not why the publishers are so fond of holding out promises in this way which they know cannot be realized. However it is <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> concern, not mine, &#8211; both the MS. &amp; the proof sheets pass thro his hands, tho that he knows exactly in what forwardness it is: &amp; I hurry myself for no man. A fourth part of the vol. is printed, &amp; I am proceeding steadily, but not so as to weary myself. A writer who pursues his subject when his own attention flags, will make his readers flag also. If I do not see my way clearly to day, I halt till tomorrow, &amp; having other things to turn to, lose no time by the delay. My Dialogues<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> are now so far advanced that they will go to press as soon as I hear the Engravers<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">William Westall produced six sketches of Lake District scenes that were engraved for <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title>, 2 vols (London, 1829): vol. I: &#8216;Druidical Stones near Keswick&#8217;, &#8216;Derwentwater, Bassenthwaite-water, and Skiddaw from Walla Crag&#8217;, and &#8216;Derwentwater from Strand Shagg&#8217;; and vol. II: &#8216;Crosthwaite Church and Skiddaw&#8217;, &#8216;Greta Hall, Derwentwater, and Newlands&#8217;, and &#8216;Tarn of Blencathra&#8217;.</note> are in any forwardness. And I am half thro the third canto of the Paraguay Tale,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825), written in Spenserian stanzas.</note> &#8211; which extends only to four: &#8211; the end being in view, this of course becomes one of my prime objects, &amp; it will be a relief to be rid of it, so difficult is it to satisfy myself in that most difficult of all stanzas. I verily believe that in the same time I could have composed ten poems of <del>the</del> equal length in any other measure; &#8211; but no other would have been so appropriate.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our weather during the present month has been very unfavourable &#8211; premature &amp; severe cold, changes as sudden as they were great, &#8211; violent storms, &#8211; heavy rain, &amp; a heavy unwholesome oppressive atmosphere. To this I attribute a severe but short bilious attack from which thank God <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> is just recovered. Today we have physicked the two girls<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note> &amp; one of the servants. For myself, I take exercise, rub myself down, eat drink &amp; sleep well, &amp; am in as good condition for mental exertion as ever I was, whatever I may be in other respects.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I would have written the Epilogue<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">It is not clear which &#8216;Epilogue&#8217; Southey is referring to here.</note> at <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edwards</ref> desire if I could, &#8211; but I could have planned half a dozen poems of great pith &amp; moment<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Hamlet</title>, Act 3, scene 1, line 85.</note> in less time than it would have cost me to have hammered out what after all I should have been ashamed of.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Scaliger<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Justus Scaliger (1540&#8211;1609), <title>Illustriss. viri Iosephi Scaligeri, Iulii Caes. a Burden f. Epistolae Omnes Quae Reperiri Potuerunt, Nunc Primum Collectae ac Editae</title> (1628), no. 2485 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> has amused me greatly, &#8211; &amp; made me hungry for farther reading of the same kind. I wish I had Erasmus&#8217;s Epistles<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The only edition of the letters of Desiderius Erasmus (1466&#8211;1536) that Southey acquired was <title>Epistolarum D. Erasmi Roterodami Libri XXXI, et P. Melanchthonis Libri IV. Quis Adjiciuntur Th. Mori &amp; Lud. Vivis Epistolae</title> (1642), no. 959 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; which must be full of good matter. If that Royal Society of Literature<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Royal Society of Literature, founded in 1820.</note> (or whatever they call themselves) had been founded upon any intelligible plan or with any views of common sense, it might have done excellent service to literature, by promoting works which never can be executed while Trade presides over the Press. A series of lives of the restorers of literature, &#8211; &amp; a collection of their letters, properly edited, with all necessary notes, are some of the plans which might have been effected by a proper application of their misdirected means. It is vexatious to see good intentions marred by weak heads.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the children &#8211; I shall be glad to have a good account of you. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">The D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
          </ref> has little time for letter writing &amp; less inclination, &amp; when he does write his letters are almost as concise as his prescriptions.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>