<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">4273Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4273" type="letter"><head>4273. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1824-11-01">1 November 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in a different hand] London Sixth Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Nicholas Lightfoot/ Crediton/ Devon/ Free/ JRickman<lb/>
               Postmark: FREE/ 6 NO 6/ 1824/ +<lb/>
               MS: MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 110. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
         <opener>  <address> <placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1824-11-01"> 1 Nov. 1824</date>
            
           <salute> My dear Lightfoot</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">  It is I trust unnecessary for me to say, – (supposing I could say it,) – how much we are obliged to you &#38; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Lightfoot had married Bridget Prideaux (1768–1856) on 13 July 1801.</note> for all your kindness to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>. She will bring away with her many pleasant recollections of Devonshire. In two days more she will have been absent a whole year from home; – I begin to grow a little impatient for her return, &#38; to feel that life is not long enough to afford such long terms of absence. She has yet some visits to make in &#38; near London which will detain her till after Christmas; – &#38; as soon as the depth of winter is past, – that is early in February, I hope to have her &#38; her sister <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, safely packed up to be delivered at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Next summer according to your promise, I shall expect <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">John</ref>, &#38; if you will contrive to join him at Oxford &#38; come with him, <del>x</del> I <del>xxxxx the</del> shall have the more pleasure in looking on to the visit. The older we grow the deeper root our early friendships takes, &#38; the more fruit they bring forth; – &#38; this is one benefit that age – which takes away <hi rend="ital">so much, brings with</hi> it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">You must not believe the newspapers which advertise that my second volume of the Peninsular War is to be published this month.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">‘In November will be published, The Second Volume of the History of the Late War in Spain and Portugal. By Robert Southey. Printing for John Murray, Albemarle-street’, <title>Morning Post</title>, 26 October 1824. The second volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832) did not appear until 1827.</note> It will not be ready before the spring. A quarter only of the vol. is printed &#38; not another quarter ready for the printer.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Davison (1766–1831).</note> I do not hurry myself, &#38; shall not allow myself to be hurried: – the slights of a jaded author would be as perceptible as the pace of a jaded horse. The difficulty of any such composition lies first in the arrangement, &#38; then in the manner of connecting the parts, &#38; passing easily &#38; naturally from one part of the subject to another. If I cannot arrange the order of narration to my satisfaction, or please myself with the manner of transition, I lay the work aside. It is no use to labour at that, which must be done with ease if it be done well. Tomorrow I take it up with a mind refreshed &#38; in another mood, – &#38; the ink which was yesterday clogged in the pen, flows freely.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">You remember what D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Johnson said of the posthumous publication of Bolingbrokes irreligious writings, by Mallet, – that Bolingbroke had loaded a blunderbuss, &#38; being afraid to discharge it himself, had left a rascally Scotchman half a crown to pull the trigger.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Speaking of David Mallet’s (c. 1705–1765; <title>DNB</title>) edition of the <title>Works</title> (1754) of Henry St John, 1st Viscount Bolingbroke (1678–1751; <title>DNB</title>), Samuel Johnson (1709–1784; <title>DNB</title>) declared of Bolingbroke that ‘he was a scoundrel, and a coward: a scoundrel for charging a blunderbuss against religion and morality; a coward because he had not the resolution to fire it off himself, but left half a crown to a beggarly Scotchman, to draw the trigger after his death!’ (James Boswell (1740–1795; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Life of Samuel Johnson</title>, 3rd edn (London, 1799), p. 312).</note> Capt. Medwin is <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> blunderbuss.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Medwin (1788–1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron: Noted During a Residence with his Lordship at Pisa, in the Years 1821 and 1822</title> (1824).</note> I have seen no more of the book than certain extracts in the newspapers.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>New Times</title>, 25–27 October 1824, where Stoddart used the newspaper he edited to comment extensively on Byron and Medwin’s <title>Conversations</title>. In the final article of 27 October 1824, Stoddart paid particular attention to attacking Byron’s <title>The Vision of Judgment</title> (1822), which had parodied Southey’s <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821), and defending Southey against Byron’s ‘vindictive hatred’. The <title>Morning Herald</title> had published extracts of Medwin’s book, for example, on 25 October 1824.</note> Among those which relate to myself is an account of the manner in which his Lordship was affected upon seeing my attack upon the Satanic school in the preface to the Vision of Judgement.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (London, 1821), ‘Preface’, pp. xvii–xxii, where Southey denounced ‘the Satanic School’ of modern poetry, without naming any one poet. However, this was clearly a riposte to Byron’s <title>Don Juan</title> (1819), whose suppressed ‘Dedication’, mocking Southey, had circulated widely. Southey was mistaken in thinking that Medwin reported Byron’s extreme anger at seeing <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821); instead, Medwin stated Byron was infuriated by seeing a copy of Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776, which appeared in the <title>Courier</title> on 11 January 1822 (Medwin, <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron</title>, pp. 221–224).</note> I am vindictive enough to wish he could he could have known in how very different a manner the whole series of his attacks, before &#38; after that time acted upon me. He would have very well understood the reason of the difference – What I said of him was true to the very letter, manly in its expression &#38; righteous in its purport. What he said of me was as false as it was malignant, as cowardly as it was calumnious, &#38; as blackguard as it was base.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I have made considerable progress in my Colloquies,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> &#38; shall send them to press as soon as I learn from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> that the engravers are in any forwardness. You will be very much pleased with these prints, which are to be in the best manner of line engraving.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall produced six prints: ‘Druidical Stones near Keswick’; ‘Derwentwater, Bassenthwaite-water and Skiddaw, from Walla Crag’; ‘Derwentwater from Strandshagg’; ‘Crosthwaite Church and Skiddaw’; ‘Greta Hall, Derwentwater and Newlands’; and ‘Tarn of Blencathra’. Lightfoot had seen all but the last on his visit in 1822.</note> The scenes are all in this neighborhood, – &#38; I believe all, with the exception of the Tarn on Saddleback, known to you. That Tarn we shall visit when you come next. My views of the present state of society, &#38; my speculations concerning its progress, may draw upon me, as usual, a good share of abuse. They may provoke some persons, &#38; perhaps alarm others. But to those who are capable of serious consideration they will present sufficient matter for it, – &#38; there are some, – (not a few – I should hope) who will feel their opinions rectified &#38; their hearts strengthened by them.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">The Laking season is now fairly closed. We have not seen many strangers this year, &#38; now we shall be wholly to ourselves thro the winter. The winter is of course my season of activity. I take an hour upon the sofa, between dinner &#38; tea, reading there for about a quarter of that time, &#38; then indulging in a comfortable – &#38; what I believe to be a very wholesome nap. At six (&#38; we are punctual as the clock) the tea bell wakes me. Two cups of green tea make me alive &#38; active; – up I go to my desk, the candle fixes me to it, &#38; I have then three hours of steady employments, – from one to two of which are pretty frequently occupied in letter writing. But these hours are the most productive part of the day.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Remember me most kindly to your fireside – all here join in remembrances. Say to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">John</ref> that I hold him engaged for next summer – make up your mind to come with him, – &#38; believe me my dear Lightfoot</p>
          <closer> <salute rend="indent1"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RSouthey.</signed></closer>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
