<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4278</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4278Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4278" type="letter">
        <head>4278. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1824-11-13">[13 November 1824] </date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand] London Eighteenth Nov. 1824/ Miss Bowles/ Buckland/ Lymington/ Hants/ Fm/ JRickman<lb />
               Postmark: FREE/ 18 NO 18/ 1824<lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 2p. <lb />
               Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 70&#8211;72 [in part].<lb />
               Note on MS: fol. 1 is absent from the manuscript in the British Library and has not been traced elsewhere. However, Dowden had access to the now-missing fol. 1; his edition is therefore used to supply the copytext for this section of the letter. </p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">KESWICK</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-11-13">
              <hi rend="ital">November</hi> 13<hi rend="sup">
                <hi rend="ital">th</hi>
              </hi>, 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If procrastination is the thief of time, letter-writing is quite as great a one, and I find the two thieves very closely connected. Some unexpected epistle arrives which is neither wanted nor welcome, but which must be answered; or some other demand upon my hours is made, for which I am neither prepared nor willing, and then the intention which had been formed, of writing that evening to you, stands over for the morrow; and when the morrow comes, other interruptions of the same kind occur, and prevent me from passing an hour according to my wishes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">In reply to your letter, thank Mr. St. Barbe<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles St Barbe (1750&#8211;1826), a banker and salt manufacturer of Lymington, Hampshire; or his son, Charles St Barbe (1776&#8211;1849), a banker and antiquary.</note> in what manner seems best to you, for Pope&#8217;s letter,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A letter from Alexander Pope (1688&#8211;1744; <title>DNB</title>), poet.</note> which I shall be very glad to have. Take for your own collection &#8211; as the first which has turned up &#8211; a note of <ref type="m" target="people.html#LambCharles">Charles Lamb&#8217;s</ref>, relating to a review of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth&#8217;s</ref>
          <title>Excursion</title> written by him at my request for the <title>Quarterly</title>, and inserted there, but so mangled by <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> as to be absolutely spoiled.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Lamb&#8217;s review of Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>The Excursion; a Poem</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (October 1814), 100&#8211;111, published 6 January 1815. The note from Lamb might be that of 20 October 1814, published in Edwin W. Marrs Jnr (ed.), <title>The Letters of Charles and Mary Lamb</title>, 3 vols (Ithaca, 1975&#8211;1978), III, p. 115.</note> It will go very well in the frank, and I will send you others as I meet with them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> is now in the very honeymoon of his happiness, having just been breeched; breeching, as I tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref>, being to a boy what marrying is to a young lady, the great thing in life which is looked on to, and I ask her seriously which she thinks the greatest happiness. I wish you could see <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref>; during dinner he lifts up his pin-before to look at the buttons. It is pleasant to see him, and yet the change is not one which brings with it any cheerful thoughts, for it takes away the charm of childhood, and<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;KESWICK &#8230; childhood, and&#8217;: text supplied by Dowden. The remainder of the letter text is taken from the surviving manuscript.</note> what charm is there in this world equal to it!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">Edith</ref> has been just a week in London. Her plans for getting there were sadly deranged, for Lady Malet<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, n&#233;e Wales (1779&#8211;1868), the widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>).</note> was summoned to Winchester by an account that her son<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Octavius Warre Malet (1811&#8211;1891), the eighth son of Lady Susanna Malet and Sir Charles Malet). Octavius Warre Malet served in the East India Company before retiring to Somerset in 1864 and playing a leading role in the restoration of Taunton Castle.</note> there was dangerously ill after the measles. The child, I rejoice to say has recovered. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> is still at Portsmouth where <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is fitting up a house that he has built. I shall have them both home in February; &#8211; by which time we shall have lost our last neighbours, &#8211; for Mary Calvert being married &amp; settled in London,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Calvert (1804&#8211;1890), the daughter of William Calvert. She married Joshua Stanger (1801&#8211;1854), son of James Stanger, in 1824.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">her father</ref> &amp; mother<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Calvert (c. 1775&#8211;1834), n&#233;e Mitchinson, the wife of William Calvert.</note> are about to remove thither. So be it, &#8211; we are enough within doors, &amp; have enough employment there I had rather, for my own part, be without neighbours &#8211; such as neighbours usually are, than with them; &#8211; but it would add greatly to my enjoyment if I had you within reach.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> has sent over another volume of Conversations to the press.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title> (1824), published in two volumes. A third volume appeared in 1828.</note> Differing as I do from him in <del>xxx</del> constitutional temper, &amp; in some serious opinions, he is yet of all men living the one with whom I feel the most entire &amp; cordial sympathy in heart &amp; mind. Were I a single man I should the pleasure of a weeks abode with him cheaply purchased by a journey to Florence, tho pilgrim-like &#8211; the whole way to be performed on foot. &#8211; The title of his book reminds me of <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> Conversations as <del>xxx</del> let off by his Blunderbuss Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Medwin.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Speaking of David Mallet&#8217;s (c. 1705&#8211;1765; <title>DNB</title>) edition of the <title>Works</title> (1754) of Henry St John, 1st Viscount Bolingbroke (1678&#8211;1751; <title>DNB</title>), Samuel Johnson (1709&#8211;1784; <title>DNB</title>) declared of Bolingbroke that &#8216;he was a scoundrel, and a coward: a scoundrel for charging a blunderbuss against religion and morality; a coward because he had not the resolution to fire it off himself, but left half a crown to a beggarly Scotchman, to draw the trigger after his death!&#8217; (James Boswell (1740&#8211;1795; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Life of Samuel Johnson</title>, 3rd edn (London, 1799), p. 312). Southey used this precedent to describe Thomas Medwin (1788&#8211;1869; <title>DNB</title>), author of <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron: Noted During a Residence with his Lordship at Pisa, in the Years 1821 and 1822</title> (1824), as Byron&#8217;s &#8216;Blunderbuss&#8217;.</note> I have only seen some newspaper extracts.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>New Times</title>, 25&#8211;27 October 1824, where Stoddart used the newspaper he edited to comment extensively on Byron and Medwin&#8217;s <title>Conversations</title>. In the final article of 27 October 1824, Stoddart paid particular attention to defending Southey against Byron&#8217;s &#8216;vindictive hatred&#8217; and attacking Byron&#8217;s <title>The Vision of Judgment</title> (1822), which had parodied Southey&#8217;s <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821). The <title>Morning Herald</title> had published extracts of Medwin&#8217;s book, for example on 25 October 1824.</note> &#8211; I fastened his name upon the gibbet, (as I told him,)<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776, published 11 January 1822.</note> &#8211; his friends have now exposed him there in chains. I am told there is no mention of my correspondence with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref>.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">In a letter of 26 June 1820, Shelley had accused Southey of writing a hostile review of <title>Laon and Cythna, or the Revolution of the Golden City</title> (1818; published late 1817) and <title>The Revolt of Islam. A Poem, in Twelve Cantos</title> (1818); see Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 358&#8211;359. Southey responded with his letter to Percy Bysshe Shelley, [c. 29 July 1820], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3517. Shelley replied in a letter to Southey, 17 August 1820, Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 361&#8211;363. Southey to Percy Bysshe Shelley, 12 October 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3538 closed the correspondence.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> probably kept it to himself. Miserable men that they were, both so gifted &#8211; &amp; so guilty!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Since my last I have not composed any verses except a few stanzas of the Paraguay<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> &#8211; which is the plague of my life. But I have been getting on well with the History, &amp; the Dialogues.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) and <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> God bless you my dear friend.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yr faithfully </salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>