<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4279Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4279Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4279" type="letter">
        <head>4279. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1824-11-13">13 November 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmarks: E/ 16 NO 16/1824; 10 F. NOON.10 / NO.16 /182x<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 250. AL; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-11-13"> 13 Nov. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  In the case of a book, half a loaf is not better than no bread. I never yet saw any epitome, or selections from a book that was good for anything, which did not omit things of main consequence, &#8211; &amp; perhaps the very things which would have been to me the most interesting I would have nothing abridged except <del>the Stat</del> Acts of Parliament, &#8211; &amp; Comments on the Bible, &#8211; &amp; if they were cut down to what is either useful or necessary, the Statutes at large<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Statutes at Large was the common term for a published collection of all the laws passed by Parliament, as in Owen Ruffhead (1723&#8211;1769; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Statutes at Large from Magna Carta to 1763</title> (1762&#8211;1765). </note> would be contained in a pocket volume of reasonable type, &amp; Mants Bible lose 99 notes out of an hundred.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Mant (1776&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>) and George D&#8217;Oyly (1778&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>) edited <title>The Holy Bible, According to the Authorized Version; with Notes, Explanatory and Practical</title> (1814).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you had gone to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> you would have found that he merely came to town to be present at the proroguement,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Parliament was prorogued on 4 November 1824 until 6 January 1825.</note> &#8211; &amp; made no stay there. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> &amp; the family will not return there till after Christmas. We heard from them yesterday, when there arrived a gold chain for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Isabel</ref>, in a letter, sent by <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">R.</ref> in <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Berthas</ref> name as her remembrance of her sisters birthday &#8211; another frank bringing at the same time poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Berthas</ref> genuine remembrance &#8211; which was a cornelian cross. This is like <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &#8211; whose hand is as open as his heart.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am now amusing myself with Budaeus&#8217;s Epistles,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Guillaume Bud&#233; (1467&#8211;1540), <title>Lucubrationes Variae</title> and <title>De Asse et Partibus Eius</title> (1557), no. 473 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. </note> &#8211; at least such of them are in Latin, for they are half in Greek, &amp; the Greek is printed that the contractions present quite as great an impediment as the language. His works are among the books which I last received from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>, &#8211; from whom I had a very pleasing letter last week. He has sent over another volume<del>s</del> of Conversations<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Landor&#8217;s <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title> (1824) were not followed by a third volume until 1828.</note> to the press.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> One of the ugliest &amp; dirtiest of all my Spanish books is affording me great amusement at this time &#8211; Obras en Prosa de D Juan de Zavaleta &#8211; Coronista del Rey &#8211; (<del>Charles xxxx 2d</del>) (Carlos 2)<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan de Zabaleta (c.1610&#8211;1670), <title>Obras En Prosa de Don Ivan de Zavaleta. Coronista del Rey Nuestro Senor. Por el Mismo Anadidas</title> (Madrid, 1667), pp. 224&#8211;453, no. 3779 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey here refers to Zabaleta&#8217;s <title>Dia de Fiesta por la Manana</title> (1654) and <title>Dia de Fiesta por la Tarde</title> (1659), describing customs during a Spanish holiday of his times. Zabaleta was a chronicler in the reign of Charles II (1661&#8211;1700; King of Spain 1665&#8211;1700).</note> The book looks as if Mal-lavado<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Ill washed&#8217;; Southey and Hill&#8217;s nickname for a bookseller they had known in Lisbon.</note> had read it. I know nothing more of the author, &#8211; he has all the faults of his age in great perfection, but they were faults which it required some ability to excel in, &#8211; &amp; I have seldom raked in a dunghill where so many pearls were to be found. The valuable part of his writings relates to the manners of his time. In a work which would fill two English octavos he gives <del>xxx</del> the history of a Dia de Fiesta<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;holiday&#8217;.</note> as past by the different classes of men in Madrid. With some caricature, &amp; a great deal of inane sententiousness, it is a more compleat picture of manners than I have any where else seen.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">The Doctor</ref> hears of me today in the shape of a haunch of venison. &#8211; We are living in the midst of tempests. Since Michaelmas<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">29 September 1824.</note> we have had continual rain &amp; storms, with only a short interval of severe cold. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref>, like you has been suffering with rheumatism which he appears to have relieved by using the warm bath, as hot as it could be borne. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> has been cured by the meadow saffron.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Meadow saffron, also known as autumn crocus, although highly toxic was traditionally used for as a remedy for gout and rheumatism. Its side effects were severe, including a slowing of the heart, lethargy, vomiting and diarrhoea. Fatalities were not uncommon.</note> You would be relieved if you were within reach of the Caldas, or if you would try the English Caldas.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The hot, sulphurous spring and spa town of Caldas da Rainha in Portugal. Southey had visited on 5 March 1801. The &#8216;English Caldas&#8217; was the hot springs at Bath.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">   Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> is in a deplorable state &#8211; if indeed he be still alive. As far as I can understand, when he was apparently recovering from a renewed attack of dropsy, a paralytic seizure supervened, <del>xx</del> which at once reduced his mind to a mere wreck. I know not whether there be any hope &#8211; or possibility &#8211; of recovery. &#8211; I lose in him one of my oldest friends.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>