<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4280Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4280Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4280" type="letter">
        <head>4280. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1824-11-17">17 November 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] Seventeenth Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> twenty first 1824/ Miss Bowles,/ Buckland,/ Lymington/ Hants/ Wm Manning<lb />
               Stamped: TO PAY 1<hi rend="sup">D</hi> ONLY; XXX<lb />
               Postmark: C/ 22 NO 22/ 1824<lb />
               Endorsement: To Miss Caroline Bowles/ Keswick 17 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1824 <lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 4p. <lb />
               Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 73&#8211;75.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1">Your news<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles&#8217;s letter to Southey of 13 November 1824 had informed him of the forthcoming work by Sir William Napier (1785&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of the War in the Peninsula and the South of France from the Year 1807 to 1814</title> (1828&#8211;1840); see Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 72&#8211;73. Napier received much assistance from Wellington, but did not have access to the latter&#8217;s papers.</note> is new to me, &#8211; but it does not surprize, &amp; can in no degree injure me.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles was worried that Napier&#8217;s book would reduce the sales of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832), published by Murray.</note> Indeed I do not think it will affect <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray&#8217;s</ref> interest, who is the person interested. For the intended work will prove a military history exclusively. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">The Duke</ref> refused to communicate any paper to me upon the grounds that he reserved them for such a work. He said that I should do as every one who wished to make a popular work would, &#8211; ascribe more to the Spaniards than was due to them. In this, he is mistaken. But <del>he want</del> the truth is he wants a whole length portrait of himself, &#8211; &amp; not an historical picture, in which a great many other figures must be introduced. &#8211; By good fortune I have had access to papers of his &#8211; of a much more confidential nature than he himself (I am very sure) would entrust to any one. And I have only to wish the work which he patronizes may come out as soon as possible, &#8211; that I may make use of it. For my third volume in all likelihood it will come in time; &#8211; &amp; then it will save me some trouble, for I may rely upon its authority in mere military points.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This must be the reason why <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> announces my second volume so prematurely, when only 26 sheets are printed &#8211; out of 100.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;In November will be published, The Second Volume of the History of the Late War in Spain and Portugal. By Robert Southey. Printing for John Murray, Albermarle-street&#8217;, <title>Morning Post</title>, 26 October 1824. The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) did not appear until 1827.</note> I shall neither hurry myself, nor be hurried. And you need not be told that I shall every where speak of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">the Duke</ref> exactly as I should have done, if he had behaved towards me with more wisdom. Let who may write the military history, it is in my book that posterity will read of his campaigns. And if there had been nothing but a military interest in the story, the Devil might have written it for me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Never I pray you, suffer yourself to be annoyed by any thing <del>by anything</del> which concerns, or seems to concern me, as an author. For in that character nothing can annoy me. I go on, as I always have done, in my own way, endeavouring to do what seems best according to my own judgement, with all diligence, &amp; caring very little for any present opinion that may be passed upon my works. Like <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>, I am satisfied if I please ten persons who are competent to pronounce an opinion upon such subjects.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Savage Landor, <title>Gebir; a Poem, in Seven Books</title> (London, 1798), p. ii: &#8216;If there are, now in England, ten men of taste and genius who will applaud my Poem, I declare myself fully content. I will call for a division; I shall count a majority.&#8217; The book was no. 1030 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">You will have received a letter before this time.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Caroline Bowles, [13 November 1824], Letter 4278.</note> But I write these hasty lines to shew you that I am not insensible of your solicitude for what you think concerns me; &#8211; Would that you were within reach: &amp; yet I cannot wish you here at this time, when for the last seven weeks we have had the worst weather that I can remember for two &amp; twenty years.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I want to hear what <ref type="m" target="people.html#BlackwoodWilliam">the Monster</ref> says to you.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Blackwood published Caroline Bowles&#8217;s next volume of poetry, <title>Solitary Hours</title> (1826).</note> That rascally passage concerning <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Sir Walter Scott</ref> which was cancelled in the London Magazine, beyond all doubt must have been written by <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Hazlitt</ref>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Hazlitt had criticised Sir Walter Scott in his review of <title>Peveril of the Peak</title> (1823), <title>London Magazine</title>, 7 (February 1823), 205&#8211;210, describing the book&#8217;s anonymous author as &#8216;intolerant, mercenary, mean; a professed toad-eater, a sturdy hack, a pitiful retailer or suborner of infamous slanders, a literary Jack Ketch, who would greedily sacrifice anyone of another way of thinking as a victim to prejudice and power, and yet would do it by other hands, rather than appear in it himself.&#8217; The passage was hurriedly suppressed as potentially libelous and only a few unaltered copies of this issue of the <title>London Magazine</title> were circulated. The matter might have rested there, but <title>Blackwood&#8217;s Edinburgh Magazine</title>, 16 (October 1824), 439, reprinted a version of the passage. It did not name Hazlitt, attributing these words to &#8216;a celebrated critic&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> is in water as near the scalding point as flesh &amp; blood can bear it, &#8211; about <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref>.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Medwin&#8217;s (1788&#8211;1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron: Noted During a Residence with his Lordship at Pisa, in the Years 1821 and 1822</title> (1824) contained much criticism of Murray, who had published Byron&#8217;s poetry. </note> This it is to have any dealings with a bad man.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you dear Caroline</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <lb />
          <p rend="indent0">
            <date when="1824-11-17">17 Nov. 1824</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>