<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4282Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4282" type="letter">
        <head>4282. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-11-22">22 November 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Grosvenor Charles Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Dover.<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 23 NO 23/ 1824<lb />
               Endorsement: 22. Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1824./ Secret.<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 273&#8211;275.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-11-22"> 22 Nov. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>  My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> A sad account of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> which <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes</ref> sent me about ten days ago is all I had heard of him since your former letter, till that of to day arrived. It came originally from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wynn</ref>, &#8211; &amp; the inference I drew from it was that a paralytic stroke had deprived him of his intellect. Had there been any better tidings I thought <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> himself would have communicated them, &#8211; but all I have seen of his handwriting for some months has been upon your cover this day. What the ground is for hope I cannot tell, as I am quite at a loss to guess even at the nature of the disease, &#8211; but it is plain that <ref type="m" target="people.html#KiddJohn">Kidd</ref> has hoped, &#8211; &amp; the <hi rend="ital">vis vitae</hi>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;vital force&#8217;.</note> appears to have been unusually strong, that even on that ground hope may be entertained</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am convinced that both the will &amp; the power exist in the quarter where you &amp; I wish to find them, &amp; might reasonably look for one &amp; expect to find the other. But I think that <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">he</ref> is not fully aware of his own power, unless it be exerted in the immediate straight course of office, &amp; that his will is palsied by a sort of indolence, &#8211; which makes (or used to make) him always late upon a journey, or in whatever he had to do, &#8211; &amp; always disposed rather to be doing anything else, than that which ought then to be done. If this had not been the case, <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> &#8211; whom it would always have been an honour to have preferred, would not have gone without preferment so long, &#8211; nor have obtained so poor a preferment at last.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Elmsley became Principal of Alban Hall, Oxford, and Camden Professor of Ancient History in 1823. He had turned down the Bishopric of Calcutta, which Wynn had offered him.</note> There are cases in which Procrastination is worse than a thief, &#8211; it is a murderer.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But the kindness of his heart &amp; the steadiness of his attachments are his own, &#8211; the drawbacks are constitutional &amp; accidental: &#8211; a regular political life, to which he has been trained from his youth up, tends to sear all feelings; &#8211; the statesmen of this country are a bad <hi rend="ital">cast</hi>e, &amp; of all that caste the Grenvilles are the coldest the proudest &amp; the most selfish.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The political family of which Wynn&#8217;s uncle, <ref type="m" target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord Grenville</ref>, was the most distinguished member.</note> Nature has been very bountiful to him in his affections &lt;&amp; dispositions&gt;, &#8211; for he had nothing good to inherit on either side.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> His attachment to me I believe to be unabated, many as are the causes which might have weakened or worn it out. Difference of rank &amp; circumstances I do not take into the account, &#8211; because they existed at the beginning, far more than at present &#8211; when I have won for myself (tho not a fortune) a station in society. But there is little sympathy in our taste, &amp; in some of our opinions &#8211; the most decided opposition, &#8211; &amp; that too upon <del>xx</del> points to which he has pledged himself with most warmth: &amp; which I considerable as demonstrably most perilous to the <del>xx</del> vital interests of these kingdoms.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn was strongly in favour of Catholic Emancipation; Southey was vehemently opposed.</note> Yet these differences have not lessened his regard for me, &#8211; nor has any estrangement been produced by long absence, &amp; the unfrequency even of epistolary intercourse. During the last twenty years we have not seen so much of each other as we did in any one month at Oxford.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I had some time ago an instance of the manner in which friendly feelings are neutralized by political considerations. You know that I think not only of a Book of the State,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Book of the State&#8217;, his companion to <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824), was never written.</note> but of a Hist. of English Literature &amp; <hi rend="ital">Manners</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">This project did not result in a book; the surviving notes that Southey put together were posthumously published as &#8216;Collections for the History of Manners and Literature in England&#8217;, <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 439&#8211;578.</note> For both these works I want the publications of the Record Committee,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Commissioners on the Public Records of the Kingdom had been periodically appointed since 1800. They authorised the publication of the <title>Statutes of the Realm</title> (1810&#8211;1825) in nine volumes as well as a large number of medieval records.</note> &#8211; &amp; <del>cannot</del> &lt;could not&gt; afford to buy them, &#8211; when they were to be sold. They are now I believe at the disposal of the Commissioners, &#8211; certainly at somebodys disposal, &amp; I asked <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> if he could get them for me. His reply was that if he did, it would give Mr Hume,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Hume (1777&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>), a radical MP who was much disliked by Southey for his campaigns against public expenditure.</note> or some such person, a handle for attacking him. &#8211; Now I should have thought he would have been well <hi rend="ital">pleased</hi> with an attack <del>against</del> which he might have repelled so triumphantly, &#8211; &amp; I am very sure that he would not have wanted persons who would, even in that house, warmly have approved such a disposal of books, &#8211; which are lying useless in <del>thx</del> some warehouse.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Edith</ref> is now in town, &#8211; tho I fear she will have little chance of seeing you, &#8211; unless you will volunteer to breakfast with her, &amp; agree upon some morning for that purpose. She is at <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonnes</ref> &#8211; 16 York Place.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">   - I can enter into your Canterbury feelings &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesThomas">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughes</ref> having sent me last week Woolnoths Description of that Cathedral,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William Woolnoth (1780&#8211;1837), <title>A Graphical Illustration of the Metropolitan Cathedral Church of Canterbury</title> (1816), no. 2916 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; as an expression on his part <del>xx</del> that I have deserved well of the Church. Talking of the Church I have heard that the Venerable Archdeacon Hook expects <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the Defender of the Faith</ref> to make him a Bishop.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">James Hook (c. 1772&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), Archdeacon of Huntingdon 1814&#8211;1818, Dean of Worcester 1825&#8211;1828 and a noted Anglican polemicist. Southey had known him at school at Westminster and regarded him with disdain.</note> &#8211; When I write to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">his Right Honour</ref> I shall tell him this. &#8211; My best remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref> &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>