<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">4283Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4283" type="letter"><head>4283. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-11-23">23 November 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 3p. <lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener><salute> My dear Thrym</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> I send you a small supply of I’s autographs, on condition that you get a little blank book (it should be a neat one) &#38; transcribe into it, (- not my nonsensicalities – which are fit only for great Albums,) – but the little extracts which are thus disposed of, whereby in process of time you will have a collection of maxims &#38; sayings of no little value. If you do this I shall have a motive for keeping up the supply.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> has an epistle on the stocks, – &#38; so have I. At present I have not time to say much. But will you tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">your Uncle</ref> that a <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashWilliam">brother</ref> of poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nash</ref> has written to me to ask his interest for D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Richard Waring at the ensuing hospital election,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Mere Latham (1789–1875; <title>DNB</title>) resigned as senior physician at the Middlesex Hospital on 16 November 1824. He was a friend and colleague of Henry Herbert Southey. Eight candidates put their names forward, including Richard Waring (d. 1868), a native of Kent, who had qualified from Edinburgh University in 1823 and became a Licentiate of the Royal College of Physicians in 1824. The result was declared on 18 December 1824 and Francis Hawkins (1794–1877; <title>DNB</title>) was successful, holding his post until 1858. Hawkins was Registrar of the Royal College of Physicians 1829–1858 and held various appointments to the royal family.</note> – in communicating which request I shall have done all that befits me to do, – having promised to communicate it, but added at the same time that I took it for granted his interest must be engaged<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to William Nash, 19 November 1824, Letter 4281.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">For yourself I have only two things to say, – that you will do well not to wear any thing at present which can be called willow, whether as relating to the colour of any part of your dress, or the material of a bonnet, – lest it should be supposed to refer to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lathams<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Mere Latham married Diana Clarissa Chetwynd Stapleton (1795–1825) on 14 September 1824. Southey teases Edith May Southey that she should not be seen to wear willow, a custom for those who were grieving, as this might be taken as a sign of mourning that Latham had married another woman. </note> marriage.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  Secondly – that if you are thrown much into company with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> James S.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">James Lowther Senhouse (1794–1844), a cousin of Humphrey Senhouse. He was educated at Westminster and Trinity College, Cambridge (BA 1815) and was ordained in 1822, becoming Perpetual Curate of Sawley, Derbyshire 1823–1844, and Rector of Gosforth, Cumberland 1827–1835. He too had married in 1824, to Elizabeth Brooks (dates unknown), so Southey may be warning Edith May Southey not to be tempted into matrimony, as the serpent tempted Eve in the Garden of Eden to eat from the tree of the knowledge of good and evil (<title>Genesis</title> 3).</note> you would remember Eve, <del>xx</del> take warning by her fate; &#38; not be tempted by a serpent.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> You will use your own judgement about M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fielding.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">There were four Fielding brothers, all fashionable painters of watercolours: Theodore Henry Adolphus Fielding (1781–1851; <title>DNB</title>); Anthony Vandyke Copley Fielding (1787–1855; <title>DNB</title>); Thales Fielding (1793–1837; <title>DNB</title>) and Newton Smith Fielding (1799–1856; <title>DNB</title>). One of the brothers had been giving lessons to Edith May Southey.</note> But I am sorry to hear that any thing ails your sight. If the weakness continues you had better get some advice concerning it while you are in town</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref> may have a copy of any thing<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Any of Southey’s works published by John Murray or Longmans.</note> – of course. And when you return you may copy the portraits of the Apollo &#38; Venus<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Apollo is one of the Greek Olympian deities and Venus the Roman goddess of love. Southey had given these names to two scarecrows in the garden of Greta Hall. Frances Keenan (d. 1838) had sketched these on her visit to Greta Hall in July 1824.</note></p>
          <p rend="indent1">  We are all well thank God, &#38; I am as busy &#38; as nonsensical as ever. I get on with my Danish after supper, &#38; have made good progress in it, – reading those Traditions which we found so flat when we began with them.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Just Mathias Thiele (1795–1874), <title>Danske Folkesagn</title> (1819–1823), though this does not appear in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Flat enough the greater number are; – but some are very strange, &#38; it was very well worth while to collect them. – It is certainly the easiest language I ever attempted to learn, tho of course one has more occasion for a Dictionary<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey possessed Christian Frederik Bay’s (c. 1737–1809), <title>A Complete Vocabulary English and Danish</title> (1806) and <title>Complete English and Danish and also Danish and English Manual-Lexicon</title> (1807), nos 133–134 in the sale catalogue of his library; and Christian Frederik Schneider (1772–1825), <title>Danish Grammar adapted to the Use of Englishmen</title> (n.d.), no. 1231 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> than in any language of the Roman stock.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  Remember me most kindly to Lady M.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, née Wales (1779–1868), the widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#38; your Somersetshire Cousins.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Edith May Southey had no first cousins in Somerset, so these may have been more distant relations of the Southey or Fricker families.</note> You have not forgotten what I said about ordering books at <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>, – where you will please yourself in your choice – Our best love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">Mrs G.</ref> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref> &#38; the children.</p>
          <closer> <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my <hi rend="ital">muy magnifica</hi><note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">‘most majestic’.</note></salute>
             <signed rend="indent2">Yo el Pa.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Literally ‘I the Pa’ in Spanish.</note></signed></closer>
            <postscript><lb/>
              <p rend="indent0"> <address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1824-11-23">23 Nov. 1824</date>    </p></postscript>        
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
