<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4286Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4286Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4286" type="letter">
        <head>4286. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1824-12-03">3 December 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major General Peachy/ at the Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wooll&#8217;s/ Rugby/ Warwickshire<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-12-03">3. Dec. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>   My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">   I am glad to hear that you have disposed of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Charles Henry<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Edward Henry (1807&#8211;1833), the younger of Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons. He had a serious accident on 2 August 1822 that was widely reported in the newspapers (without naming Henry): &#8216;A young gentleman, by way of saluting some friends who were taking their departure, fired off a cannon, which unfortunately burst in consequence of being overloaded, and the fragments severely fractured his skull&#8217; (<title>Glasgow Herald</title>, 12 August 1822). The cannon was kept outside Peachy&#8217;s house on Derwent Island and was fired as part of the annual Keswick Regatta. </note> so well, &amp; so much to your satisfaction. If any disposition to over-task himself in study should appear, his tutor no doubt will be aware that it ought rather to be repressed than encouraged; for tho all danger is long since past, yet a few more years should elapse before the brain be exerted as if it had never sustained an injury.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeWilliamHart">The Bishop of Barbadoes</ref> has had a lucky escape in not having embarked before the late tremendous gale.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Great Storm of 22&#8211;23 November 1824 &#8211; a hurricane-force wind and storm surge that particularly affected the south coast of England.</note> His baggage was not so fortunate, &#8211; the vessel in which that was stowed is among the wrecks, &#8211; tho it has not gone to pieces. The storm was felt here, but I suppose we were only in the skirts of it, for it was by no means the worst that we have experienced since the end of September, till which time we <del>had</del> &lt;have&gt; had the finest, &amp; since, the worst season I remember in this country. At present we are in a white world, &amp; nothing could be more glorious than the silvery splendour of the mountains this day.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have not seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoe&#8217;s</ref> observations on <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowless</ref> Life of Pope;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Roscoe, <title>The Works of Alexander Pope, Esq. with Notes and Illustrations by Himself and Others. To Which are Added, a New Life of the Author, an Estimate of his Poetical Character and Writings, and Occasional Remarks</title>, 10 vols (London, 1824), I, pp. xvi&#8211;xix, severely criticised William Lisle Bowles, <title>The Works of Alexander Pope, Esq., in Verse and Prose, Containing the Principal Notes of Drs Warburton and Warton</title> (1806) for &#8216;imputations on the moral character of Pope &#8230; accompanied by an apparent disposition of Mr. Bowles to detract also from his estimation as a poet&#8217;.</note> but I should suppose that whatever difference of opinion he may entertain, he will have expressed it courteously. With no great respect for <ref type="m" target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoe</ref> as an author I have great respect for his personal character, as an accomplished kind hearted &amp; generous man. As for the matter of controversy,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A huge controversy had been ignited by Bowles&#8217;s <title>The Invariable Principles of Poetry</title> (1819), which claimed that poetic images should be drawn from nature, not art; and that the finest poetry did not deal with the transient manners of society, but with general and enduring themes. Bowles had been very critical of Alexander Pope (1688&#8211;1744; <title>DNB</title>) in this context.</note> it lies in a nutshell; &amp; if the parties were but agreed upon the meaning of the terms which they use, there would be an end of it. &#8211; It would be very gratifying to me to pass a few days under <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles&#8217;s</ref> roof, but I can seldom move from home, inclination &amp; prudence combining to keep me there. <del>if</del> Even if I considered travelling as a luxury, it is one in which I am not rich enough to indulge without especial cause; <del>x</del> inasmuch as that all the while I am absent from home, my only estate (which is time) is lying unproductive. &#8211; I have no intention of seeing the south next year; if I go from home at all (which &lt;for&gt; the hope of escaping my annual attack in the chest it is probable I shall do) &#8211; it will most likely be to visit <ref type="m" target="people.html#JebbJohn">the Bishop of Limerick</ref>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey actually visited the Low Countries in 1825.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">My daughters<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha Southey</ref>.</note> will, I hope, return in February. We heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> to day. She sends good accounts of Lady Malet &amp; the Charters.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, n&#233;e Wales (1779&#8211;1868), the widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), maternal uncle of the Charter sisters, <ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Louisa Charter</ref> and Elizabeth Charter (1782&#8211;1860), friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>). The Charters were the sisters of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, first wife of William Peachy.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Some extracts from Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Medwins book<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Medwin (1788&#8211;1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron: Noted During a Residence with his Lordship at Pisa, in the Years 1821 and 1822</title> (1824).</note> have been transmitted to me, which, little inclined as I am to controversy, require notice on my part; &amp; you will probably see in the course of some ten days an exposure in the Courier of as much of <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> impudent &amp; malignant falsehood as it behoves me to notice.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s Letter to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 8 December 1824, Letter 4289, published 13 December 1824.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The only news of this place is that <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calvert</ref> has let his estates, &amp; is about to remove to London; &#8211; &amp; as the Fryers<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Harrison Fryer (1777&#8211;1855) of Whitley House, Northumberland. Fryer was a surveyor, geologist and mining engineer who spent part of each year at Keswick. He had been renting Ormathwaite, a large house about a mile and a quarter from Keswick. He married Mary Laetitia Wilbraham (1799&#8211;1874), who had been Tom Southey&#8217;s lodger, in June 1822.</note> are already removed to the vicinity of Cockermouth, we lose in him &#8211; literally the last of our neighbours, &#8211; &amp; the only &lt;one with&gt; whom a constant intercourse has been kept up. The young women I am afraid will feel the loss, which I shall not, &#8211; living always in the society best suited to my habits &amp; inclinations.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Ladies desire their best remembrances &#8211; mine accompany them to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>, when you may write to, or rejoin her. I beg my compliments also to Dr Wooll.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wooll (1767&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman and Headmaster of Rugby School 1807&#8211;1828. Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons, James Henry (1803&#8211;1884) and Charles Edward Henry (1807&#8211;1833) were educated at Rugby School.</note> Rugby I hope is proud of having sent forth <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Landor</ref>, &#8211; who notwithstanding some errors of opinion, will undoubtedly be <del>reme</del> regarded hereafter as one of the brightest ornaments both of his age &amp; of his country.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">farewell my dear Sir, &amp; believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">  yours very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">  Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>