<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4287Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4287Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4287" type="letter">
        <head>4287. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-12-05">5 December 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Private collection. ALS; 4p. <lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-12-05"> 5. Dec. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear E May</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  I write rather because there is a frank going off this evening, than for any better reason. However I have two things to say, &#8211; one is that I wish <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Doctor</ref> would order for me two pairs of strong shoes, which may come in your box (N.B. take care this box be a little better corded than the last the corder whereof ought to have been sent to the Treading Mill.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A form of hard labour used in British prisons since 1818. By continuously stepping onto a series of revolving ledges, prisoners turned a shaft that could be used to power machinery.</note>) &#8211; Secondly I advise you &amp; every body else who can do it, to hear <ref type="m" target="people.html#BensonChristopher">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Benson</ref> preach, at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Giles&#8217;s.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Benson was Rector of St Giles-in-the-Fields Church 1824&#8211;1826. He was appointed in May 1824 and his reputation as a preacher grew quickly. Southey had heard him preach in Cambridge in 1820; see Southey to Katherine Southey, 28 May 1820, <title>Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3487.</note> He is so far the best preacher I ever heard <del>that</del> as to admit of no comparison with any other.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> is coming over tomorrow. I have not seen him since my own return from the South.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will probably in the course of the week see a <hi rend="ital">sweet billet</hi> of mine in the Newspapers noticing a few lies of <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> as published by his Blunderbuss Capt Medwin.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 8 December 1824, Letter 4289, published 13 December 1824. This was a reply to material on Southey in Thomas Medwin (1788&#8211;1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron: Noted During a Residence with his Lordship at Pisa, in the Years 1821 and 1822</title> (1824). Speaking of David Mallet&#8217;s (c. 1705&#8211;1765; <title>DNB</title>), edition of the <title>Works</title> (1754) of Henry St John, 1st Viscount Bolingbroke (1678&#8211;1751; <title>DNB</title>), Samuel Johnson (1709&#8211;1784; <title>DNB</title>) declared of Bolingbroke that &#8216;he was a scoundrel, and a coward: a scoundrel for charging a blunderbuss against religion and morality; a coward because he had not the resolution to fire it off himself, but left half a crown to a beggarly Scotchman, to draw the trigger after his death!&#8217; (James Boswell (1740&#8211;1795; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Life of Samuel Johnson</title>, 3rd edn (London, 1799), p. 312). Southey transferred this description of Mallet to Medwin.</note> I shall just say what is needful, &amp; no more.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have accepted a letter of Pope&#8217;s<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander Pope (1688&#8211;1744; <title>DNB</title>); see Southey to Caroline Bowles, 26 November 1824, Letter 4285.</note> for the sake of transferring it to you. The handwriting is so like <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tylers</ref> that I could have taken it for hers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The third canto of the T of Paraguay<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> is finished. And as I never so heartily desired to be at the end of any other composition whether in prose or in verse I shall not be long in getting thro the remaining one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Yesterday I received <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wordsworths</ref> book<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Eikon Basilike, The Portraicture of His Sacred Majestie in His Solitudes and Sufferings </title>(1649), no. 987 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, purported to be the work of Charles I (1600&#8211;1649; King of Great Britain 1625&#8211;1649; <title>DNB</title>). Christopher Wordsworth, <title>&#917;&#7984;&#954;&#8060;&#957; &#914;&#945;&#963;&#953;&#955;&#953;&#954;&#942; Considered and Answered in Two Letters addressed to his Grace the Archbishop of Canterbury</title> (1824) aimed to support the idea that Charles I was the actual author &#8211; not a conclusion endorsed by modern scholars. The book was no. 3042 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> what has for ever put the question to rest. It is impossible for any investigation to be more compleat, &#8211; or more conclusive. &#8211; I have written in it as a motto, Latimer&#8217;s saying &#8220;Well; there is nothing hid but it shall be opened.&#8221;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Watkins (d. c. 1831; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Sermons of the Right Reverend Father in God, and Constant Martyr of Jesus Christ, Hugh Latimer, Some Time Bishop of Worcester</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, p. cliv. Hugh Latimer (c. 1487&#8211;1555; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Worcester 1535&#8211;1539 and Protestant martyr, was a favourite writer of Southey&#8217;s.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">And now when I have told you that it is snorting weather, &amp; that I am about to write a paper for the QR. upon the Church Missionary Society,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (June 1825), 1&#8211;42, on missionary societies was (ostensibly) a review of <title>An Abstract of the Annual Reports and Correspondence of the Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, from the Commencement of its Connexion with the East India Missions, A. D. 1709, to the Present Day</title> (1814); and of the Church Missionary Society&#8217;s (founded 1799) <title>Church Missionary Register</title> (1813&#8211;1824). The Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge (founded 1698) is also an Anglican missionary organisation.</note> &#8211; &lt;I have no more to say&gt; farther than to send as much love &amp; as many kind remembrances as can be inclosed in a frank, to be distributed at your discretion, &amp; to assure you that I remain</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Dear Madam</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">  with the profoundest respect</salute>
          <salute rend="indent1"> your most obedient humble servant</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <lb />
          <p rend="indent0">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Your Mother</ref> my Governess means to write shortly about chains &amp; I know not what.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>