<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4288</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4288Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4288" type="letter">
        <head>4288. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1824-12-06">6 December 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmarks: E/ 8 DE 8/ 1824; [partial] ON. /[illegible]/ 1824<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 251. ALS, 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 451&#8211;452 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-12-06"> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am sorry to learn from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Edith-May</ref>, that the hooping cough still keeps its ground at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>. When the force of this disorder is spent, nothing I believe is more certain, than that change of air contributes to its removal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wordsworth</ref> has just sent me his Enquiry into the question of who wrote &#917;&#7984;&#954;&#8060;&#957; &#914;&#945;&#963;&#953;&#955;&#953;&#954;&#942;?<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Royal Portrait&#8217;, i.e. <title>Eikon Basilike, The Portraicture of His Sacred Majestie in His Solitudes and Sufferings</title> (1649), no. 987 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, purported to be the work of Charles I (1600&#8211;1649; King of Great Britain 1625&#8211;1649; <title>DNB</title>). Christopher Wordsworth, <title>&#917;&#7984;&#954;&#8060;&#957; &#914;&#945;&#963;&#953;&#955;&#953;&#954;&#942; Considered and Answered in Two Letters addressed to his Grace the Archbishop of Canterbury</title> (1824) aimed to support the idea that Charles I was the actual author &#8211; not a conclusion endorsed by modern scholars. The book was no. 3042 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> a question which would now be set for ever at rest, if there were not a political feeling interested in withstanding the truth. The book is in itself so beautiful, &amp; of so much importance in English history, that it was well worth the labour of this minute investigation to establish its authenticity. &#8211; I expected <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">his brother</ref> this morning, but the weather has delayed his coming. I look for him therefore tomorrow.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When I have added that a regimental record of the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> battalion of the 34<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#8211; has been sent me &#8211; by a retired Army Surgeon,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The 2nd Battalion of the 34th (Cumberland) Regiment of Foot was raised in 1804 and disbanded in 1817. It served with distinction in the Peninsular War 1809&#8211;1814. Its surgeon throughout was Edward Thornhill Luscombe (1781&#8211;1830); his &#8216;regimental record&#8217; does not seem to have been published.</note> &#8211; &amp; that it contains a few matters of fact which I might not have found elsewhere, &#8211; you will have heard all I have to relate. &#8211; Unless it be that a Hist. of the Peninsular War under <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">the D. of Wellingtons</ref> especial patronage is coming forth,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir William Napier (1785&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of the War in the Peninsula and the South of France from the Year 1807 to 1814</title> (1828&#8211;1840). Napier received much assistance from Wellington, but not the use of the latter&#8217;s papers.</note> &#8211; for the sake of which <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">the Duke</ref> refused to supply me with any materials. He wished for a history which should be purely military, &#8211; &amp; therein he was right enough, &#8211; that <del>xx</del> is, it is quite proper that such a one should be composed. But I am not so sure that he is right in chusing to have the whole canvass for his own whole length portrait, instead of being the prominent figure in an historical piece. And I am sure that I <del>xxx</del> am in possession of many more of his most confidential papers than he would ever have communicated, even if he had professed to be most communicative. At present my matters are upon the best footing with him, &#8211; as he will answer any questions which I wish to put to him thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>. &#8211; The Printer<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Davison (1766&#8211;1831), printer of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> moves slowly, but I am getting on well. I must however turn my main attention presently to the Budget, which is no more to be overlooked in private than in public affairs. My subject will be the Church Missionary Society,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (June 1825), 1&#8211;42. This was (ostensibly) a review of <title>An Abstract of the Annual Reports and Correspondence of the Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, from the Commencement of its Connexion with the East India Missions, A. D. 1709, to the Present Day</title> (1814); and of the Church Missionary Society&#8217;s <title>Missionary Register</title> (1813&#8211;1824), no. 1962 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. The latter organisation was founded in 1799 by evangelical Anglicans and had been at work in New Zealand since 1814. However, Southey did not write his proposed article on New Zealand.</note> &amp; I shall probably find matter enough for a paper in some preliminary views of the subject &#8211; &amp; in what they are doing in New Zealand, without <del>touching</del> entering into their Proceedings in other quarters, &#8211; reserving that for other opportunity. They have large means at command &amp; are using them wisely.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If any of your catalogues help you to a Breviary<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The liturgical book of the Catholic Church, containing prayers and readings for daily use. A standardised edition was produced in 1568.</note> I wish you would send me one, &#8211; for sometimes I feel the want of it. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">EMay</ref> will be sending off a package ere long.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">My niece</ref> is about to publish a translation of the Memoirs of the Chevalier Bayard,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Sara Coleridge&#8217;s translation, <title>The Right Joyous and Pleasant History of the Feats, Gests, and Prowesses of the Chevalier Bayard, the Good Knight without Fear and without Reproach</title> (1825). Unsurprisingly, Southey gave it a glowing recommendation in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (October 1825), 355&#8211;397.</note> &#8211; which will give me a good subject for a reviewal. I wanted <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> to republish the old translation of Montluc&#8217;s Commentaries which I would have revised, prefaced &amp; annotated, but he declined, &#8211; in my judgement unwisely, Henri 4. used to call this book the Soldiers Bible. I never saw the translation &#8211; which is by Charles Cotton,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Blaize de Lasseran-Massencome, Seigneur de Montluc (c. 1502&#8211;1577) <title>Commentaires de Messire Blaise de Montloc, Mareschal de France</title> (1592), referred to by Henry IV (1553&#8211;1610; King of France 1589&#8211;1610) as &#8216;the soldier&#8217;s Bible&#8217;, <title>Collection Universelle des Memoires Particulieres Relatifs a l&#8217;Histoire de France</title>, 62 vols (Paris, 1785&#8211;1790), XXII, p. xv, no. 1062 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. It was translated into English by Charles Cotton (1630&#8211;1687, <title>DNB</title>), <title>The commentaries of Messire Blaize de Montluc, mareschal of France wherein are describ&#8217;d all the combats, rencounters, skirmishes, battels, sieges, assaults, scalado&#8217;s, the taking and surprizes of towns and fortresses, as also the defences of the assaulted and besieg&#8217;d: with several other signal and remarkable feats of war, wherein this great and renowned warriour was personally engag&#8217;d, in the space of fifty or threescore years that he bore arms under several kings of France: together with divers instructions, that such ought not to be ignorant of, as propose to themselves by the practice of arms to arrive at any eminent degree of honor, and prudently to carry on all the exploits of war</title> (1674).</note> &#8211; Izaak Walton&#8217;s friend &amp; fellow Angler,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Izaak Walton (1593&#8211;1683; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Compleat Angler</title> (1653), to which Charles Cotton contributed. Southey owned an edition from 1824, no. 2976 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &amp; likely therefore to be in a vein of pure English. But the original is one of the most characteristic books I ever perused.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I begin to read Danish with some facility, &#8211; that is such plain prose as I have hitherto attempted. But in truth it is the easiest of all northern languages, &#8211; &amp; the only difficulty lies in its copious vocabulary. My memory is not so retentive of words as it was in youth, &#8211; &amp; perhaps would have been stronger than it is, if I had ventured to rely upon it more, than for the sake of accuracy I thought <del>rigx</del> expedient.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> I hear has advertised my Colloquies under a wrong title, a blunder which would not have happened if he had been more in communication with me.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray&#8217;s advert referred to &#8216;Dialogues on Various Subjects&#8217; being &#8216;in the press&#8217;, rather than <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829). These adverts continued well into 1825.</note> It is of no consequence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the Children</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>