<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">4296Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4296" type="letter"><head>4296. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>,<date when="1824-12-15"> 15 December 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London <lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 18 DE 18/ 1824<lb/>
               Watermark: KINGSFORD/ 1814<lb/>
               Endorsement: 1824–December/ Southey R Esq <lb/>
               MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-12-15">15 Dec. 1824</date></dateline>
            
         <salute>   My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> I am glad to receive your letter, &#38; quite confident I am that you have determined wisely in a matter of no little consequence both to yourself &#38; the public.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray had just appointed John Taylor Coleridge to succeed William Gifford as editor of the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> I can have no hesitation in writing according to your wish to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Croker</ref>, – with whom I am upon such terms that a letter from me would appear as a natural &#38; proper, tho not a common, occurrence. But with <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge ">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Canning</ref> it would be otherwise. The personal civilities which I have received from him, are not much as to place me upon any footing of freedom with him. I can ask him a favour connected with any literary object (for example, to procure those Catalan books – if any such there had been,)<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to George Canning, 2 January 1824, Letter 4115. Southey had read John Mitford’s ‘On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez’, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221–223. It mentioned Olivarez’s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title>, published in four volumes at Seville in 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &#38; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877 and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had then written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832), and Herbert Hill had also offered to help. Southey had then sought the assistance of George Canning and, finally, John Mitford.</note> – because it was paying him a compliment to presume upon his willingness in such a case to grant one. But I am shy of obtruding myself upon a person so high in office; &#38; especially unwilling to arrogate to myself any importance for the part which I may have borne in the QR.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">There is also another motive which would withhold me from addressing him upon this topic. The time cannot be far distant when the Q. R. must take its part upon a most momentous subject, &#38; chuse between <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Canning</ref> &#38; the Church.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Canning favoured Catholic Emancipation.</note> I have always considered it as one of the greatest errors in the management of the Review that it should have been silent upon that subject so long. Something of what is going on, I know; (even at this distance from the sphere of public affairs) more than is publicly known; &#38; the crisis is likely to be accelerated by the rebellion which may at any hour break out in Ireland, – where it cannot be doubted that the intention of a desperate party is to bring on a religious war. Let us take our stand upon the rock of high constitutional principles, &#38; we shall have with us the integrity &#38; the talents &#38; the heart of the country. – But with this hope, &#38; knowing what I know, it would be unfitting in me to do any thing which <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. C.</ref> might suppose that the Q.R. would follow wherever he may lead. – There are other members of the Government to whom I can make such a communication without scruple, &#38; for whose confidence I can answer. </p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I have long been looking wistfully for the books from Germany concerning the Peninsular War.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832). The bibliography of his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), III, p. 936, suggests that Southey was probably seeking: Hermann von Staff (1790–1867), <title>Der Befreiungs–Krieg der Katalonier, in den Jahren 1808 bis 1814</title> (1821–1827); and Franz Xaver Rigel (1783–1852), <title>Die Siebenjahrige Kampf auf der Pyrenaischen Halbinsel vom Jahre 1807 bis 1814; besonders miene eigenen Erfahrungen in disem Kriege; nebst Bemerkungen uber das Spanische Volk und Land</title> (1819–1821), no. 2442 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The Church Missionary Society will furnish more than one interesting subject.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (June 1825), 1–42. This was (ostensibly) a review of <title>An Abstract of the Annual Reports and Correspondence of the Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, from the Commencement of its Connexion with the East India Missions, A. D. 1709, to the Present Day</title> (1814); and of the Church Missionary Society’s <title>Missionary Register</title> (1813–1824), no. 1962 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. The latter organisation was founded in 1799 by evangelical Anglicans.</note> Will you send me their “Proceedings”<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Church Missionary Society’s <title>Proceedings</title> were published annually from 1801 onwards.</note> – which I find announced in the Missionary Register as published in 3 volumes: the Miss: Register for 1823, &#38; 1824; the Abstract of the Annual Reports of the Soc. for Promoting Christian Knowledge;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge is an Anglican missionary organisation founded in 1698.</note> – &#38; Cruise’s New Zealand.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Cruise (c. 1784–1832), <title>Journal of a Ten Months’ Residence in New Zealand</title> (1823). It was reviewed by Sir John Barrow, 1st Baronet (1764–1848; <title>DNB</title>) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (April 1824), 52–65, published 30 December 1824/1 January 1825.</note> My plan is to have one paper upon the Societies connected with the Established Church, – what they have done &#38; are doing; Another upon New Zealand.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The proposed article on New Zealand was not written.</note> Let me have your last Number<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (January 1824), published 28 August 1824.</note> with these (which I have never yet seen) – &#38; the fair sheets of the Pen. War<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> beginning with X.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">Farewell my dear Sir &#38; believe me</salute>
         <salute rend="indent2">   Yours very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">  Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
