<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4300Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4300Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4300" type="letter">
        <head>4300. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1824-12-21">21 December 1824.</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ J.T. Coleridge Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 2. Pump Court / Temple/ London<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 24 DE 24/ 1824<lb />
               Endorsement: 1824/ Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>/ R.S. Greta Hall<lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47553. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: W. Braekman, &#8216;Letters by Robert Southey to Sir John Taylor Coleridge&#8217;, <title>Studia Germanica Gandensia</title>, 6 (1964), 137&#8211;139.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-12-21"> 21 Dec. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> to whom I wrote upon the subject the day before yesterday,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">This letter does not seem to survive.</note> should think it advisable <del>xxx xxxx</del> to prosecute the M. Chronicle for <del>the</del> &lt;its&gt; atrocious attack upon me in the paper of Friday the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> he will have communicated with you, &#8211; for to you it is that I would trust the cause.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 17 December 1824, published a letter headed &#8216;Southey versus Lord Byron&#8217;. It contained a sustained attack on Southey, but he eventually decided not to take legal action.</note> If however he should be of opinion that it is better to let the slander alone, you will in that case not hear from him. The single charge of blasphemous obscenities is that upon which I should rest, as what must be deemed plainly &amp; infamously libellous, &#8211; if justice is ever to be obtained by law.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Has Mr. Southey, or has he not, in one of his publications, raked up and collected together (note upon note, and line upon line) the most salacious, prurient, and filthy witticisms upon the most awful and sacred subjects, upon the Vessel of Incarnation chosen for the redemption of mankind, upon the Salutation of the Angel, upon the formation of our Holy Redeemer in the uterus, and upon the practicability of clergymen baptizing children in the vagina of their mothers&#8217; wombs before they were brought into the world?&#8217; (<title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 17 December 1824).</note> It was not till just now that I could imagine upon what this could possibly be founded, &#8211; but I now perceive that it must be upon &#8211; <hi rend="ital">literally</hi>, an extract from an English Roman Catholic Book of devotions to the Virgin Mary, in the first vol. of the Omniana.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Omniana or Horae Otiosiores</title>, 2 vols (London, 1812), I, pp. 123&#8211;128, quoting a prayer to the Virgin Mary from Arthur Crowder (1588/1589&#8211;1666; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Jesus, Maria, Joseph, or the Devout Pilgrim of the Ever-Blessed Virgin Mary, in His Holy Exercises, Affections, and Elevations, upon the sacred Mysteries of Jesus, Maria, Joseph</title> (Amsterdam, 1657), unpaginated, no. 1515 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> The other charges are quite unworthy of notice when compared to this most devilish one: but should any proceedings be instituted they will make good garnish, &amp; I will then write to you concerning them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> wrote to me last week a sort of official notification that when the little which remained to negotiate should be settled; there was every probability that you would consent to accept the Editorship:<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Gifford was about to retire as editor of the <title>Quarterly Review</title>; he was briefly succeeded by John Taylor Coleridge 1824&#8211;1825.</note> &amp; he asked me in the meantime to write upon the subject to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge ">Canning</ref>, as persons whose confidence it was of great importance to obtain. I readily promised this with regard to the former (&amp; in fact have written)<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey to [John Wilson Croker], 18 December 1824, Letter 4297.</note> but gave him my reasons why I should not address <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge ">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Canning</ref>. In the first place I do not chuse to affect any importance with any one (especially with a person so high in office) upon the score of my supposed influence in the QR. And in the next, as I told <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, the time cannot be far off, in which the QR must make its choice between <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge ">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Canning</ref> &amp; the Church.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The Cabinet was neutral on the question of whether Catholics should be able to hold public office in the United Kingdom, but Canning favoured this measure.</note> For if his scheme of bringing in the Whigs should succeed, the country must be divided upon the Catholick question; &#8211; even if that question be not sooner brought to a crisis by the forth-coming rebellion in Ireland.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">It was widely rumoured during 1824&#8211;1825 that the Cabinet would break up over the question of Catholic relief and that Canning would form a new government in alliance with some Whigs. The &#8216;Catholic question&#8217; was becoming more pressing because of the campaign by the Catholic Association In Ireland.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had begun to apprehend that I had done you some hurt by my interference. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has been plainly out of humour with me ever since I left London: (wherefore, I neither know nor care) &#8211; &amp; upon his writing <del>a very</del> to me some very silly objections to my reviewal of Hayley&#8217;s life &#8211; which I answered at length,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of John Johnson (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263&#8211;311. Southey replied to Murray on 25 October [1824], Letter 4268.</note> I took occasion to speak in strong terms upon the present state of the Review, &amp; to tell him that I would write under no mans correction. At the same time I repeated on what grounds I believed that the Review could not be entrusted to any person so qualified to conduct it as yourself. The only note which I have received from him since was formal &amp; respectful; &#8211; &amp; I suppose he will come round to his usual civility when the crotchet (whatever it be), which has got into his head, shall have got out of it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  But tho I spoke to him roundly <del>about</del> in resentment of the usage which my papers have sometimes received, &#8211; <del>you will</del> to you I say that at any time I will strike out anything which you may desire to have expunged. I have opportunity enough for saying upon my own responsibility any thing which I may think fit to say; &#8211; &amp; am moreover &lt;at all times&gt; likelier to err by being too easily persuaded, than by turning a deaf ear to advice. The first thing you will have from me will be an article upon Sara&#8217;s translation of Bayards Memoirs.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Sara Coleridge&#8217;s translation, <title>The Right Joyous and Pleasant History of the Feats, Gests, and Prowesses of the Chevalier Bayard, the Good Knight without Fear and without Reproach</title> (1825). Unsurprisingly, Southey gave this a glowing recommendation in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (October 1825), 355&#8211;397.</note> The next upon the Church Missionary Society,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (June 1825), 1&#8211;42. This was (ostensibly) a review of <title>An Abstract of the Annual Reports and Correspondence of the Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, from the Commencement of its Connexion with the East India Missions, A. D. 1709, to the Present Day</title> (1814); and of the Church Missionary Society&#8217;s <title>Missionary Register</title> (1813&#8211;1824), no. 1962 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. The latter organisation was founded in 1799 by evangelical Anglicans.</note> &#8211; &amp; I want also, on the publication of poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#BloomfieldRobert">Bloomfields</ref> life, to give his family what help I can thro the Review.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Bloomfield had died in poverty on 19 August 1823. <title>The Remains of Robert Bloomfield</title> (1824) were not reviewed by Southey in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> I had a great respect for that poor man: &amp; can make a paper concerning him to good effect. When you are fairly installed as Sir Editor, I shall be in more frequent communication with you that I ever was with <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>. You shall then know all my intentions, &amp; may depend upon me at any time &#8211; &amp; to any extent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  The Tale of Paraguay is nearly finished &#8211; to my great joy. My second volume of the war will soon be half printed, &amp; my Colloquies will go to press as soon as the prints which are to accompany them are in any forwardness.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825); the second volume of his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832); and <title>Sir Thomas More; or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara&#8217;s</ref> eyes are not worse, nor could it be known by merely looking at them that they ailed any thing. She is thin, but not I think out of health, &amp; certainly not in bad spirits. Bayard no doubt will sell, &amp; my poem will carry off for her the remaining copies of Dobrizhoffer.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825) was based on an incident in Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae Natione</title> (1784), no. 843 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, which Sara Coleridge had translated as <title>An Account of the Abipones, an Equestrian People of Paraguay</title> (1822).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> was with me lately, &#8211; &amp; I was sorry to notice in him a sort of apprehension in case of slight indisposition, &#8211; which has an ill appearance always, &#8211; as seeming to be founded rather in instinct than in any apparent reason. I never saw so old a man for his years, where there had been no intemperance, or violent shock of any kind, to bring on premature old age.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> God bless you</signed>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>