<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">4308Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4308" type="letter"><head>4308. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1824-12-31">31 December 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J.T. Coleridge Esqre/ 65. Torrington Square<lb/>
               Stamped: Bge St West<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>
               Postmark: EVEN/ 3 JA 3/ 1825<lb/>
               Endorsement: 1825/ Jan<hi rend="sup">ry</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>/ R.S. Keswick <lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47553. ALS; 5p.<lb/>
               Previously published: W. Braekman, ‘Letters by Robert Southey to Sir John Taylor <lb/>
               Coleridge’ <title>Studia Germanica Gandensia</title>, 6 (1964), 142–145.</note></head>
            
            
          <opener> <salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> You will not suppose because my letters follow each other so fast at this time, that I am about to become a habitual nuisance, &#38; that a correspondence with me is to be one of the disagreables attached to your Editorship.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Taylor Coleridge had just taken over as editor of the <title>Quarterly Review</title> 1824–1825.</note> – But both my own concerns &#38; yours require that I should write just now.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> You will see <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 17 December 1824, published a letter entitled ‘Southey versus Lord Byron’, which contained a sustained attack on Southey. The latter consulted Turner about possible legal action against the newspaper, but eventually decided not to proceed.</note> – tho he recommends a course which I shall not follow, that of proceeding by information,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">To proceed by information was to bring a formal criminal charge against someone, in this case the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>’s editor and printer, for libel. This would provoke a trial in which Southey could counter the paper’s attack on him under oath in court. However, as this would be a private prosecution, Southey faced the possibility of incurring heavy costs.</note> &#38; involving myself in expence &#38; trouble, for the purpose of giving a solemn denial to charges which most certainly are not believed by the very miscreant himself who has made them. He wishes to avoid any appearance of an attack on my part upon the Press, &#38; the Morning Chronicle, whereas it appears to me that if I have an opportunity of <del>bringing that paper to justice</del> punishing that newspaper for its abuse of the press, I ought just as much to do it in this case, as I would bring a fellow to justice for assaulting me on the highway. Allowing them as large a latitude as they desire for political abuse, I would rest solely upon the charge of impious &#38; blasphemous obscenities.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Has Mr. Southey, or has he not, in one of his publications, raked up and collected together (note upon note, and line upon line) the most salacious, prurient, and filthy witticisms upon the most awful and sacred subjects, upon the Vessel of Incarnation chosen for the redemption of mankind, upon the Salutation of the Angel, upon the formation of our Holy Redeemer in the uterus, and upon the practicability of clergymen baptizing children in the vagina of their mothers’ wombs before they were brought into the world?’ (<title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 17 December 1824).</note> That charge must be founded upon the Extracts in the Omniana. Vol I. p. 123.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>Omniana or Horae Otiosiores</title>, 2 vols (London, 1812), I, pp. 123–128, quoting a prayer to the Virgin Mary from Arthur Crowder (1588/1589–1666; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Jesus, Maria, Joseph, or the Devout Pilgrim of the Ever-Blessed Virgin Mary, in His Holy Exercises, Affections, and Elevations, upon the sacred Mysteries of Jesus, Maria, Joseph</title> (Amsterdam, 1657), unpaginated, no. 1515 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> with regard to the baptism of children before they are born, I cannot remember that I have ever mentioned it (tho very likely I may, as one of the abominations to which Catholic superstition leads) – except in a very curious passage from Feyjoo, which is given in the Annual Review. Vol I. p. 562.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Benito Jerónimo Feijoo (1674–1764), <title>Cartas Eruditas, y Curiosas</title>, 5 vols (Madrid, 1781), I, pp. 94–120, no. 3297 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey had cited, and provided a brief summary of, Feijoo’s opinion on the following theological problem: ‘In 1736, a child was born at Medina Sidonia, with two heads, two trunks, but single below the middle. As the birth was dangerous, one of the feet which made its appearance first was baptised. Upon this two questions arose, and were referred to Feyjoo for solution. Was the child one or two individuals? if two, did the baptism of the foot regenerate both?’ This puzzling issue was dealt with in Southey’s review of Augustin Louis Josse (1763–1841; <title>DNB</title>), <title>El Tesoro Espanol o Biblioteca Portatil Espanola</title> (1802), <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803), 557–566 (562). (Josse’s book was no. 3657 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.)</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">My brother</ref> has both that &#38; the Omniana. So many things are possible in law, that it must be only a lawyer who can determine whether there be any thing in those two passages, upon which a justification for this devilish libel can be set up. Should it appear as clear in law as it is in equity that <del>this</del> &#60;it&#62; is a foul &#38; infamous libel, which any Judge &#38; any Jury must pronounce such, then certainly I would bring an action for damages against the Morning Chronicle, without caring who the author may be: that paper having not only inserted it, but called attention to it in its leading paragraph.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘We refer our Readers to a Letter in another column on the subject of Mr. SOUTHEY’s late extraordinary attack on Lord BYRON’ (<title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 17 December 1824).</note> The rest may be thrown overboard. Let them revile me as an author &#38; a politician till their hearts ache.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was, among many other things, described as ‘a republican and a revolutionist’ at the time of the French Revolution and ‘a pensioned bookseller’s hack’ (<title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 17 December 1824).</note> Their obloquy serves only to show that my opinions have an influence in society, which they know &#38; feel. And if it gives me any feeling, it is that of satisfaction at seeing to what base &#38; unmanly practises they are obliged to descend. But this goes beyond all bounds of political or even personal animosity. There can be no villainy of which a man would not be capable, who is capable of bringing forward such charges upon such grounds. True it is that my character needs no vindication, &#38; I would not lift a finger to vindicate it. But if I have a villain by the throat, I would deliver him over to justice. Nevertheless if you &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> agree in opinion that I had better let the matter alone, I shall without hesitation follow the advice. And it is well to bear in mind that there has more than once been manifested a <del>xxxx</del> &#60;most&#62; reprehensible disposition in the Judges to favour the wrong side, lest they should be suspected of leaning toward the right.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  Now to the business of the Review. I have laid aside Bayard according to your wish, &#38; begun with the Ch. Miss. Society.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sara Coleridge’s translation, <title>The Right Joyous and Pleasant History of the Feats, Gests, and Prowesses of the Chevalier Bayard, the Good Knight without Fear and without Reproach</title> (1825). Unsurprisingly, Southey gave this a glowing recommendation in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (October 1825), 355–397. However, Southey had laid work on this aside in favour of a second article that appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (June 1825), 1–42. This was (ostensibly) a review of <title>An Abstract of the Annual Reports and Correspondence of the Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, from the Commencement of its Connexion with the East India Missions, A. D. 1709, to the Present Day</title> (1814); and of the Church Missionary Society’s <title>Missionary Register</title> (1813–1824), no. 1962 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. The latter organisation was founded in 1799 by evangelical Anglicans. The Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge (founded 1698) is also an Anglican missionary organisation.</note> The change may occasion a weeks delay, but you shall have the paper in time. In this paper my purpose is to treat the subject of missions in general, &#38; give a general view of what the Ch: of England in particular has done &#38; is doing in this way. Therefore I shall be glad of some Reports of the Soc. for propagating the Gospel; – &#38; also of those of the Home Missionary Society, – upon which I am inclined to lay a heavy hand.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Society for Propagating the Gospel in Foreign Parts (founded 1701) is an Anglican society that concentrated on missions to British colonies. The Baptist Home Missionary Society was founded in 1797 to encourage itinerant preaching in Britain, and was heavily criticised by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (June 1825), 1–42.</note> – I care not what Travels you send me, – having abundant notes &#38; references for any part of the habitable earth. Mexico might tempt me into too wide a field, – for if <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> had sent me Bullocks book<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">William Bullock (c. 1773–1849; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Six Months’ Residence and Travels in Mexico; Containing Remarks on the Present State of New-Spain, its Natural Productions, State of Society, Manufactures, Trade, Agriculture, and Antiquities, &#38;c.</title> (1824). The book was published by Murray.</note> I had thought of preparing an important paper upon the former civilization of that country. Perhaps the account of Portugal which he just now advertises<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Marianne Baillie (1788–1831; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Lisbon in the Years 1821, 1822 and 1823</title> (1824), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 378–390, published 11 March 1825.</note> will be a subject <del>that</del> I can treat with more expedition than any other – I would not think of Lord J Russells book,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Lord John Russell (1792–1878; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Affairs of Europe from the Peace of Utrecht</title> (1824–1829), no. 2579 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> or the Annuaire,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Literally a ‘yearbook’. Possibly <title>Annuaire Historique Universel pour 1823</title> (1824).</note> because there are large subjects enough before me – to wit Bayard (which I shall dress up well) – Baxter,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Puritan clergyman Richard Baxter (1615–1691; <title>DNB</title>). It is not clear which of his works Southey was here suggesting he review. He may have heard of the forthcoming <title>The Practical Works of the Rev. Richard Baxter with a Life of the Author and a Critical Examination of his Writings</title> (1830), edited by William Orme (1787–1830; <title>DNB</title>). Southey did not write on the subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> &#38; (which I forgot to mention in my last) the forthcoming edition of Sir T. Browns works,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Thomas Browne (1605–1682; <title>DNB</title>), a doctor and writer on a huge range of subjects. ‘The Whole Works and Correspondence of Sir Thomas Browne, Knt. M. D. of Norwich’ was advertised as forthcoming with Longmans, for example, in the <title>London Courier and Evening Gazette</title>, 2 October 1824. This was an early indication of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilkinSimon">Simon Wilkin’s</ref> edition, which did not appear until 1835–1836. Southey acquired a copy, no. 376 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#38; the Pepys Memoirs.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Memoirs of Samuel Pepys, Esq. F.R.S.: Secretary to the Admiralty in the Reigns of Charles II and James II. Comprising his Diary from 1659 to 1669, Deciphered by the Rev. John Smith, From the Original Short-Hand MS. in the Pepysian Library, and a Selection from his Private Correspondence</title> (1825), edited by Richard Griffin, 3rd Baron Braybrooke (1783–1858). This was the first edition of the diary of Samuel Pepys (1633–1703; <title>DNB</title>). A later edition from 1828 was no. 2208 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey did not write on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Hughes (of Oriel)<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hughes (1790–1857; <title>DNB</title>), a miscellaneous writer and son of Thomas Hughes and Mary Anne Watts Hughes. He had graduated from Oriel College, Oxford, B.A. 1812, M.A. 1815 and had reviewed ‘Washington Irving’s Tales’, i.e. Washington Irving (1783–1859), <title>The Sketch Book of Geoffrey Crayon, Gent.</title> (1820). His review finally appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 473–487, published 11 March 1825.</note> was preparing a paper upon American Literature – in a right spirit. He had begun with Geoffrey Crayon – of whom quite enough has been said, &#38; who may be left quietly to sink to his own level: <del>but the general</del> this paper it is not unlikely you may have had transferred to you; – but the general subject is a good one, &#38; I can help Hughes in the course of an hour or so, to some serviceable notices for it, from my stock of American books. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> should apply to Barron Field for a paper about New Holland &#38; Van Diemens Land;<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Barron Field (1786–1846), ‘The Australian Colonies’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (October 1825), 311–342. Field was a judge in the Supreme Court of New South Wales 1816–1824. New Holland was Australia and Van Diemen’s Land was Tasmania. Southey did not write for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> on the subject of New Zealand.</note> – but let him leave New Zealand for me &#38; the Church Missionaries.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  Concerning the Catholic Question<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">The question of whether Catholics should be allowed to hold public office in the United Kingdom.</note> you doubt whether conceding it will really weaken or strengthen us for the struggle which is sure to follow the concession; – &#38; whether there is any hope of ultimately resisting the present demand. It is this latter &#60;view&#62; which leads many good men at this time to take the wrong side, – <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Wilberforce</ref> for example &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir T Acland</ref>. They both think that because too much has been granted, more must be given. I differ from them most decidedly – in the belief that if the cession be prevented a few years longer, the Catholic Religion will show itself so plainly in its true colours every where, that the broad distinction between Protestants &#38; Papists will place us in perfect safety. But to the first question I answer without any hesitation that the concession would most materially endanger the Church of England. An object which all the enemies of that Church are united in seeking, must be injurious to it. The Dissenters – the Whigs – the Liberals – what care they for the Catholics? they have their own views to serve by aiding them in this question. The immediate consequence of the concession would be – the repeal of the Test Act,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">The Test Act (1673) ensured that only members of the Church of England could hold public office in the United Kingdom,</note> – in go the Dissenters into the Corporations, – &#38; in come their members into Parliament. The Tithes &#38; the Church property &#60;then&#62; become the objects of attack, – &#38; I know not to what extent the evil may not be carried. – By the by you will see ere long a collection of all that has been said against the Church in Parliament during the last session, – put together by a clergyman – a friend of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wordsworth’s</ref>; – that it may clearly be seen what the enemies of the Church are aiming at.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">It is unclear which publication Southey is referring to here.</note> </p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The number of Catholic members who would immediately be returned to Parliament would not be inconsiderable. They would not dream at once of bringing about the reestablishment of their Church; – but they fully expect it sooner or later; their numbers in England have increased seven fold within the last thirty years (so it is stated) – &#38; they know<del>n</del> that whatever weakens the Establishment tends surely to strengthen them. For the spirit of Popery is a stronger spirit than that either of Puritanism or of Infidelity, another consequence is that the King must be allowed the same liberty of conscience as his subjects, &#38; the same liberty of marrying a Roman Catholic if he chuses, – tho we know what that liberty has cost us.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">George IV had already married a Catholic, Maria Fitzherbert (1756–1837; <title>DNB</title>), in 1785, though the marriage was invalid under the Royal Marriages Act (1772). However, Southey may be referring to the marriage of Charles I (1600–1649; King of Great Britain 1625–1649; <title>DNB</title>) to the Catholic Henrietta Maria of France (1609–1669; <title>DNB</title>), which some critics felt had contributed to the civil wars of 1642–1651.</note></p>
          <p rend="indent1">  My principle is the plain one, that no persons ought to be trusted with political power who think it their duty to alter the constitution of the Church. The argument which <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> used in a letter to me some months ago is wholly fallacious – that we ought to do as is done in Russia &#38; Austria with other modes of faith.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">In Austria (since 1781) and Russia (increasingly from 1801 onwards) members of minority faiths could practise their religion in private.</note> There is no similarity in the cases. There are no legislative assemblies there. What is demanded here is not employment in the state, but <hi rend="ital">legislative power</hi>, – legislative power for men who teach that salvation is not to be obtained out of the pale of their own Church, – for whom persecution is strictly a religious duty, – &#38; who yet &#60;claim&#62; to be admitted into power as a right due to them upon the principle of toleration.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> This is a subject upon which I enter in my Colloquies,<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> – where also it is that I think of examining the popular <del>xxxxxxx</del> grounds of unbelief. – The account of Struensee<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Balthasar Münster (1735–1793), <title>A Narrative of the Conversion and Death of Count Struensee</title> (1824), a life of Johann Friedrich Struensee (1737–1772), a German doctor and government minister in Denmark.</note> I have not seen, – nor Davisons work,<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">John Davison (1777–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Discourses on Prophecy, in which are considered its Structure, Use, and Inspiration: being the Substance of Twelve Sermons Preached in the Chapel of Lincoln’s Inn</title> (1824).</note> – but am glad to hear of both – &#38; shall be interested by them.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I shall now write <hi rend="ital">for</hi> you instead of <hi rend="ital">to</hi> you</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">  RS.</signed></closer>
            <postscript>
			<lb/>
            <p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-12-31">31 Dec. 1824.</date></p>
               <p rend="indent1"> I will prepare a short paper upon poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#SayersFrank">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sayers’</ref> works.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">William Taylor, <title>Collective Works of the Late Dr. Sayers; to which have been Prefixed some Biographic Particulars</title> (1823), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 35 (January 1827), 175–220. This was no. 2505 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey’s metrical experiments had been greatly influenced by Sayers’s <title>Dramatic Sketches of the Ancient Northern Mythology</title> (1790) – for example, <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> He has a claim to it – as an old contributor to the Review, – &#38; from me especially, who &#60;have&#62; followed his example of irregular blank verse so largely.</p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
