<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4309" type="letter"><head>4309. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>,<date when="1824-12-31"> 31 December 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 3 JA 3/ 1825<lb/>
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.338. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1824-12-31">31 Dec. 1824</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Harry</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> Thus saith <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">the Bp. of London</ref> – “I shall have very great pleasure in signing <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southeys</ref> certificate, &#38; being instrumental in introducing so respectable a member to the Royal Society.”<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">At this time, anyone wishing to become a Fellow of the Royal Society was obliged to obtain at least three endorsements from existing Fellows on a certificate applying for membership. The Fellows then decided at their weekly meetings whether to elect the candidate. It was not a requirement to be a practising scientist and many Fellows were senior clergy, army or navy officers or lawyers. It was quite common for London physicians to become members and Henry Herbert Southey was elected a Fellow of the Royal Society on 25 April 1825.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I do not know where <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorHenrySir">Henry Taylor</ref> lodges, – but a note will always find him at the Colonial Office.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> has advised me to prosecute the M Chronicle<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was considering taking action over ‘Southey versus Lord Byron’, <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 17 December 1824. He eventually did not do so.</note> in a way which I shall not do; because it would involve me in trouble &#38; expence for the purpose of vindicating my character. Thank God it needs no vindication, but if I can punish that rascally newspaper I should very well like so to do; &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> will consult with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">J Coleridge</ref> upon the propriety of bringing an action for damages<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Turner had advised Southey to bring a private criminal prosecution against the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>; instead, Southey asked him to look into bringing a civil case against the newspaper, asking for damages.</note> They will look at the question in its legal bearings. To me it seems that I have got a scoundrel on the hip, &#38; ought to make use of the advantage.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  <del>That you may not have</del> William<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">William Southey (1824–1871) was born on 16 November 1824. He later served with the East India Company Army, reaching the rank of Lieutenant-Colonel. Despite Southey’s strictures, Henry Herbert Southey named one of his sons ‘Arthur Southey’ (b. 1833).</note> is a good name; &#38; I hold that no persons can truly understand whether a name is good or otherwise, unless they have paid that attention to the collocation of sounds which is necessary in composing verses. Arthur is not a good name, because the first r eats up the second. William is perhaps the most euphonious of all English names.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I am half way thro the last Canto of Paraguay<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> – which you will be glad to hear. Our love to all –</p>
           <closer> <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
         <signed rend="indent3">   RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
