<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4121Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4121Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4121" type="letter">
        <head>4121. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Charles Cuthbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-01-14">14[&#8211;15] January 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Cuthbert Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland<lb />
               Stamped: TAUNTON / 161 <lb />
               Postmark: JA 15/ 1824<lb />
               Seal: red wax<lb />
               Watermark: 1823 <lb />
               Endorsement: Jan 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1824/ R Southey to C C. Southey<lb />
               MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>Taunton. </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-01-14">Wednesday. 14 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear little good boy</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am writing to you from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">Aunt Mary&#8217;s</ref> lodgings. Your kind <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">Aunt</ref> talks a great deal about you. She has given me a seven shilling piece for you, to buy a pair of half boots when you are breeched &amp; she sends also a very pretty broche for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, of garnets &amp; pearls; &amp; two desert spoons for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Bel</ref>; &amp; a garnet necklace for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">E May</ref>, which was Madam Lethbridges,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Lethbridge, n&#233;e Southey (1704&#8211;1789) married the landowner Christopher Lethbridge of Westaway House, Devon (1685&#8211;1746). As a child, Southey&#8217;s aunt, Mary Southey, had spent much time with Mary Lethbridge, who was an older cousin.</note> &amp; upon her death was given to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt</ref> by Lord Somerville.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Southey Somerville, 15th Lord Somerville (1765&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), grandson of Mary Lethbridge and heir of Mary Lethbridge&#8217;s brother, John Cannon Southey (d. 1768).</note> She sends her love to you, &amp; will be very glad to see you &amp; your mother &amp; sisters, &amp; Betty,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Thompson (c. 1777&#8211;1862), the Southey family&#8217;s long-standing servant. She was buried in the Southey family grave.</note> &amp; Anne,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A servant in the Southey household at Greta Hall, Keswick.</note> &amp; every body &amp; every thing about the house when she comes in the early part of the summer.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here are two pretty birds here in two cages, children of a canary bird &amp; a goldfinch. They sing very sweetly. And here is a very comical small frisking whisking Cupn dog, whose name is Tippoo Saib. That was the name of a terrible Sultan in the East Indies,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Tipu Sultan (1750&#8211;1799; Sultan of Mysore 1782&#8211;1799) killed while defending the fort of Seringapatam against the East India Company.</note> who used to throw men to his tygers <del>&amp; xxxxxxxx</del> He was a very cruel tyrant, but at last the English beat him &amp; killed him in battle.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I received the comical verses signed by Rumpel &amp; Hurlyburlybuss,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The most likely author of these verses signed by two of Southey&#8217;s cats at Greta Hall was John Marriott (1780&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman, poet and friend of Walter Scott. He was Curate of St James, Exeter, St Lawrence, Exeter, and St John, Broadclyst. The patron of the latter church was Sir Thomas Acland, who was also a friend of Marriott. Southey had stayed with Marriott on 6 January 1824 on his visit to the West Country. While he was on this trip, Southey received the poem &#8216;The Poetic Epistle to Southey from his Cats&#8217;, which he liked and kept; it was later printed in <title>The Doctor</title>, 7 vols (London, 1834&#8211;1847), VII, pp. 580&#8211;582. </note> at <ref type="m" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir Thomas Aclands</ref>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Acland&#8217;s house at Killerton Park, Devon.</note> Every body there was much amused by them. I came from thence yesterday morning to this place. Tomorrow I go to visit my old schoolfellow <ref type="m" target="people.html#CombeEdward">Combe</ref>; but my next movements depend upon the chance of the coaches, so that I can say nothing certain about them; only that I hope to be in London again on this day week.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not certain that I shall see <ref type="m" target="people.html#PooleThomas">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Poole</ref>. There was a foolish report told him that I was not coming till Thursday, &amp; he is at the sessions at Wells.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Poole, who was a Justice of the Peace, had gone to a sitting of the Court of Quarter Sessions for the county of Somerset in the city of Wells.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">My dear little boy I was very sorry indeed to hear you had had the toothache. When a tooth aches it should be drawn, because tooth drawing hurts for a minute, &amp; then the pain is over: &amp; it is better to have a short pain than a long one, tho the short one be worse <del>xxx</del> while it lasts. Good boys always bear pain bravely, like men. I told you how your god-brother<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Charles John Herries (1815&#8211;1883; <title>DNB</title>), the eldest son of J. C. Herries, and in later life a financier; see Southey to Cuthbert Southey, [18 December 1823], Letter 4102.</note> behaved when he had that sad fall, which knocked his teeth out. It is a great grief to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your Mamma</ref> &amp; to me when any thing is the matter with you: but it would be a greater not to have you a good boy. You know we are both very fond of you, tho <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your Mamma</ref> does not tell you quite so often as I do. The greatest pleasure I have while I am away is to think of getting home again, that I may see <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your dear mother</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Bel</ref> &amp; you, &amp; have my books about me, &amp; live in my own study, &amp; sleep in my own bed, &amp; see the lake &amp; the mountains, &amp; be very happy, &amp; make a noise sometimes, &amp; be a very nonsensical Pappa, as all good Pappas ought to be.</p>
        <lb />
        <p>
          <date when="1824-01-15"> Thursday morning</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So many persons called in upon me yesterday that I could not finish this letter. If I were to go to all the houses whither I am invited, I should never get to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>; so I say no to every body. There came a letter last night from my old tutor at College, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sweet,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Sweet (c. 1754&#8211;1833), Rector of Kentisbury, Devon 1776&#8211;1833. Sweet received his BA from Wadham College, Oxford, in 1775. He married Jane Sweet, n&#233;e Barter (dates unknown) in Exeter in 1777.</note> asking me to visit him &amp; his wife &amp; his twelve children, &amp; offering to send his coach for me. But I cannot go. On Saturday I hope to see <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Miss Bowles</ref>, &amp; Rover her dog, &amp; Donna her cat. &amp; there I shall have a little quiet, &amp; be able to answer some of the letters which follow me wherever I go.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  O Cuthbert I have seen such beautiful cats in Devonshire that it was a pleasure to look at them. There was a Lady<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> at Sir John Kenneways<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Kennaway, 1st Baronet (1758&#8211;1836), made a fortune in the East India Company and became a landowner in Devonshire. Southey knew him through his son, Charles Edward Kennaway, who had visited Southey in the Lake District in 1819&#8211;1820. His home was Escot House, near Ottery St Mary, Devon.</note> who loves cats; &amp; I wrote in her Album this Triad. &#8220;The Three sweet sounds of the Fireside: the chirping of a Cricket: the singing of a Tea-kettle, &amp; the purring of a Cat.&#8221; &#8211; This is a Triad. The ancient Britons used to put most of their wise sayings in Triads,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A rhetorical form in medieval Welsh that grouped objects in threes.</note> &amp; I will make some wise sayings for you in the same manner one of these days, &amp; some comical ones. In the time of the Britons there was no printing &amp; no books, &amp; indeed no paper, so they recorded things in Triads because they could easily be remembered in that form.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I shall hope to receive a letter from home, in London, &amp; if I hear that you are fond of your books it will please me much. I shall bring down some very nice ones for you &amp; your sisters to read. Give my love to all at home, &amp; <del>xxx</del> offer it to Rumpelstilzchen in the shape of a piece of meat, or a little milk. The same also to Hurlyburlybuss.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Good by my dear Cuthbert. Say your prayers regularly, do your lessons well, always do as you are bid, &amp; never be in a passion; &amp; then you will always be good &amp; happy. God bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">your dutiful father</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>