<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3795</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3795Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3795" type="letter">
        <head>3795. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#AttersollAnn">Ann Holmes</ref>, <date when="1822-02-06">6 February 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: A Madame/ Madame St. Ann Holmes/ Hotel Gabriel. Place d&#8217;Armies/ Versailles<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; 212<lb />
               Postmarks: E/ PAID/ 8 FE 8/ 1822; FE 22<lb />
               Seal: red wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb />
               MS: Newstead Abbey. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: <title>Catalogue of the Collection of Autograph Letters and Historical Documents Formed Between 1865 and 1882 by Alfred Morrison</title>, 6 vols (London, 1883&#8211;1892), VI, p. 165.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-02-06">6. Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Madam</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Among all the &#8220;whys &amp; wherefores&#8221; which you may have found to account for my not acknowledging the receipt of a copy of D Carlos,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Russell (1792&#8211;1868; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Don Carlos; or Persecution. A Tragedy, in Five Acts </title>(1822). As Russell was a leading Whig, Ann Holmes may have been doubtful about Southey&#8217;s reaction to this gift. Russell had travelled widely on the Continent and spent the months November 1820&#8211;January 1821 and June&#8211;September 1821 in Paris, so he may well have met Ann Holmes there.</note> &amp; replying to the letter which you sent with it, &#8211; the true cause, I dare say, never occurred to you; &#8211; it is simply this, &#8211; that I never received either book or letter. My sentiments, Heaven be praised, are too tolerant, too kindly, too charitable (I will not call them <hi rend="ital">liberal</hi>, abused as that word is) &#8211; to keep me at a distance from any one because of any difference in opinions religious or political. What your opinions may be I know not; &#8211; mine are before the world, for those who like them, in private I obtrude them upon no one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If the Chev<hi rend="sup">r</hi> de Sagrie<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Pierre Hippolite Amillet de Sagrie (1785&#8211;1830), <title>Roderic, Dernier Roi de Goths</title> (1821), no. 2700 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This was a translation of Southey&#8217;s <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814). Sagrie did not translate any more of Southey&#8217;s works.</note> thinks it worth his while to bestow any more time upon the translation of any of my works, I will very willingly communicate to you for his use such facts &amp; dates relating to my own life as may serve his purpose.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A translation of Roderick in three small volumes was sent me August last by the translator, who signs himself <ref type="m" target="people.html#BruguiereAntoine">B<hi rend="sup">on</hi> de Sorsum</ref>.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Antoine Andr&#233; Brugi&#232;re, Baron de Sorsum, <title>Roderick, le Dernier des Goths</title> (1820), no. 2697 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library; see Southey to Antoine Andr&#233; Brugi&#232;re, Baron de Sorsum, 30 October 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3743.</note> Is it then a third translation of which you speak?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Am&#233;d&#233;e Pichot (1795&#8211;1877), French novelist, historian and prolific translator, began a translation of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), but abandoned the project once the two other versions in French appeared.</note> In looking over this which on the whole I liked as well as could be expected, I fell upon one odd mistake, &#8211; the motes in the sunbeam (in the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> book) are translated <hi rend="ital">papillons de nuit</hi>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Papillons de nuit are moths: <title>Roderick, le Dernier des Goths</title>, 3 vols (Paris, 1820), I, p. 175, mis-translated <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 8, line 106. Southey drew attention to this mistake in his <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), IX, pp. x&#8211;xiii.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Westall has made some drawings from this poem,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Westall (1765&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>) produced a set of six illustrations. These were published by Longman as <title>Illustrations of Roderick, the Last of the Goths. A Poem, by Robert Southey, Esq. from the Drawings of R. Westall, R.A.</title> (1824), nos 2627&#8211;2628 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Purchasers could arrange for the engravings to be bound into their copy of <title>Roderick</title>, which was also published by Longman.</note> which I have not seen but which are described to me as very beautiful, &#8211; having been done <hi rend="ital">con amore</hi>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;for love&#8217;.</note> They are now in the engravers hands.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall used a number of engravers for this project, including Charles Heath (1785&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref>, I have little doubt, will return to the charge.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">In the &#8216;Appendix&#8217; to &#8216;The Two Foscari&#8217;, <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy. Cain, A Mystery</title> (London, 1821), p. 328, Byron had cautioned: &#8216;I am not ignorant of Mr. Southey&#8217;s calumnies on a different occasion, knowing them to be such, which he scattered abroad on his return from Switzerland against me and others.&#8217; Southey had visited Switzerland in his continental tour of May&#8211;August 1817. The &#8216;calumnies&#8217; Byron believed Southey to have later spread were rumours that Byron and Shelley had engaged in a &#8216;League of Incest&#8217; during their residence in Switzerland in 1816. Southey had responded by writing to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776. His letter was published in the <title>Courier</title> on 11 January 1822.</note> I have the great advantage of being right, &amp; of being master of my temper. He can neither irritate nor injure me. The single charge which malice can bring against me is that I was a republican, or rather an Utopian at twenty, &amp; that as I grew older I grew wiser: modifying my speculative opinions both political &amp; religious, as I acquired more knowledge, but retaining always the moral principle with which I set out in life. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Byron</ref> is not fool-enough to believe that this is any impeachment of my character, <del>tho</del> but he is dishonest enough to join in the cry of a set of cut throats; &#8211; they deserve no better name, &#8211; for cut-throats they would be, as surely as Marat, Chaumette, Hebert<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-Paul Marat (1743&#8211;1793), Jacobin journalist; Pierre Gaspard Chaumette (1763&#8211;1794), President of the Paris Commune; and Jacques H&#233;bert (1757&#8211;1794), ultra-radical journalist. All were extremists and advocates of the Reign of Terror (1793&#8211;1794).</note> &amp;c &amp;c, if they every attained the same power. I despise these wretches too much ever to notice them, otherwise than collectively &amp; as regards the public weal. But if he persists in his ruffian-like attacks I will bestow upon him such farther chastisement as he deserves, well knowing that as I have the better cause, so also have I the stronger arm.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I write in haste, rather than lose a post, &#8211; because I have to clear myself from an appearance of gross incivility</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">farewell therefore Madam</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">  &amp; believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent4">    Your obliged</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">  Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>