<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4127</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4127Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4127" type="letter">
        <head>4127. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1824-01-27">27 January 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand] London Twenty Eighth Jany/ 1824/ Miss Bowles/ Buckland/ Lymington/ Hants/ Fm/ JRickman<lb />
               Postmark: FREE/ 28 JA 28/ 1824<lb />
               Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 43 To Miss Caroline Bowles<lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 4p. <lb />
               Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 49&#8211;50.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-01-27">27 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Till now I have not had five minutes during which I could quietly put pen to paper since we parted. I breakfasted in the Close at Winchester<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey breakfasted with Elizabeth Heathcote (1773&#8211;1855) and Alethea Bigg (1777&#8211;1847), two sisters of Catherine Hill who shared a house at 12 Cathedral Close, Winchester.</note> on the morning after, saw the Cathedral &amp; the College, &#8211; found room in the Coach at noon &amp; reached London at night. The next day I secured places in the <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref> mail for Friday evening, &#8211; &amp; dined among &#8220;strange women&#8221;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Women who flattered Southey: <title>Proverbs</title> 5: 3, &#8216;For the lips of a strange woman drop as an honeycomb, and her mouth is smoother than oil&#8217;.</note> at Lady Malet&#8217;s,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, n&#233;e Wales (1779&#8211;1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>). Her house was at 100 Gloucester Place, London.</note> &#8211; a situation something worse than that of Daniel in the Lion&#8217;s den.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Daniel</title> 6, where Daniel is thrown into a lions&#8217; den, but survives through divine intervention.</note> &#8211; Your note in the travelling frank reached me before I left town, &amp; after a parcel had been sent off which I hope reached you without mishap, tho with no better packing than <del>xxx</del> my hands, (awkward at such work) could give it. You have there all my poems which have as yet been printed in that form.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had sent Caroline Bowles a specially bound copy of his <title>Minor Poems</title> (1823).</note> How many more such volumes may be added to them depends as much upon you as on myself.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had proposed that he and Caroline Bowles should write a poem on the legendary figure Robin Hood. The completed sections were published as &#8216;Robin Hood&#8217; in <title>Robin Hood: a Fragment. By the Late Robert Southey, and Caroline Southey. With Other Fragments and Poems By R.S. and C.S.</title> (London, 1847), pp. [1]&#8211;36.</note> Many I hope &amp; trust, &#8211; very many, &#8211; to your benefit &amp; mine, &#8211; to our mutual delight, &#8211; to our lasting remembrance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">We arrived here safely on Saturday morning, Sunday I heard <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville</ref> officiate in a little village Church of which he is curate.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Neville White had been Perpetual Curate of Great Plumstead, five miles east of Norwich, since 1822.</note> &#8211; One of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">his brothers</ref> hymns was sung there, &amp; I dined at his mothers<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary White, n&#233;e Neville (1755&#8211;1833).</note> where her whole family were assembled, with the father &amp; mother of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Nevilles</ref>
          <del>sweet</del> wife.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Neville White had married Charlotte White, n&#233;e Sewell (1799&#8211;1873) in 1820. Her parents were Joseph Sewell (1772&#8211;1844), a wealthy Norwich solicitor, and Ann Sewell, n&#233;e Cubitt (1780&#8211;1849).</note> Ten years ago when he had no prospect of marriage I volunteered to be godfather to his first son: &amp; very obligingly this son made his entrance a month ago, &amp; is this day to be christened Henry Kirke.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Family histories, including <title>The Homes and Haunts of Henry Kirke White; with some account of the family of White, of Nottingham and Norfolk</title> (London and Nottingham, 1908), p. 260, suggest that Neville White&#8217;s first son, christened Henry Kirke White (d. 1849), was born in 1821, but this information may be inaccurate, as Southey stood as godfather to him in January 1824.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not believe that any act of kindness was ever so largely overpaid, as that has been which I rendered to the Whites.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had edited and arranged the publication of <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White</title> (1807). This had sold extremely well, reaching ten editions by 1823.</note> It has been of far greater consequence to them than I could possibly have dreamt of, &#8211; but their gratitude has more than kept pace with the benefit which they have received. And when I think that to the publication of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henrys</ref> Remains I am indebted for my knowledge of you,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s kindness to Kirke White&#8217;s family had encouraged Caroline Bowles to write to him in 1818, seeking his opinion of her then unpublished <title>Ellen Fitzarthur; a Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (1820). </note> I certainly look upon it as one of the most fortunate events of my life, &amp; perhaps one of the most influential. If as a poet I am to have a second spring (there is still sap enough in the trunk &#8211; &amp; enough life in the root) <del>xxx xxxxx</del> &#8211; to this it must be owing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; But the christening guests are come &#8211; &amp; I must hasten to say two things, &#8211; first that you may introduce a few songs with good effect<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey means here that Bowles could introduce songs into their proposed poem, &#8216;Robin Hood&#8217;.</note> &#8211; &amp; secondly that I have promised to ask you for a devotional poem, &#8211; as an act of charity, to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PettetAlfred">a poor music master</ref> here, now four years a helpless paralytic, for whom poets are willing to write, &amp; composers to set their strains, &#8211; &amp; to whom I have promised something from myself &amp; something from you, &#8211; from whom I might venture to promise.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles contributed &#8216;I weep, but not rebellious tears&#8217;, published in <title>Robin Hood: a Fragment. By the Late Robert Southey, and Caroline Southey. With Other Fragments and Poems By R.S. and C.S.</title> (London, 1847), pp. [227]&#8211;228; and Southey contributed &#8216;Thanksgiving for Victory&#8217; (originally Southey&#8217;s New Year&#8217;s ode for 1816) to Pettet&#8217;s <title>Original Sacred Music</title> (London, n.d., c. 1825&#8211;1827), pp. 67&#8211;70 and 58&#8211;66.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">One thing more, &#8211; do not forget that I wish, &#8211; earnestly wish to pay what tribute I can to Paul Burrards memory.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Paul Henry Durell Burrard (1790&#8211;1809), an Ensign in the 1st Foot Guards, was mortally wounded at the Battle of Corunna (1809). He was Caroline Bowles&#8217;s first cousin. Southey composed &#8216;Lines. To the Memory of a Young Officer, Who was Mortally Wounded in the Battle of Coru&#241;a. By Robert Southey, Esq. Poet Laureate&#8217;, <title>The Literary Souvenir; Or, Cabinet of Poetry and Romance</title> (London, 1826), pp. [341]&#8211;344.</note> Send me such notices of him as you may have heart to give, &amp; I will do my best.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">And now dear friend &#8211; dear Caroline, farewell. Let me have a letter from you in <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q Anne Street</ref> where I hope to arrive on Thursday the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Ediths</ref> love. &#8211; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>