<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3883</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3883Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3883" type="letter">
        <head>3883. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1822-08-14">14 August 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand] Epsom Eighteenth Aug<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. 1822/ Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Nicholas Lightfoot/ Crediton/ Devon/ Free/ JRickman<lb />
               Stamped: EPSOM/ 79<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 110. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-08-14">14 Aug. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Lightfoot</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">It was a great pleasure to us to receive your letter &amp; know that you had reached home safely, &amp; found all well. Now that you have made the journey I trust that you have discovered what an easy thing it is, &amp; that you will feel no disinclination to repeat it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The day after we parted, I breakfasted with <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wordsworth</ref>, &amp; set forward on my return meaning to get into the coach when it should overtake me. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">W.</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
          </ref> walked with me to set me on the way (as the phrase is) &amp; we had got about three miles, when a slight rain came on &amp; sent them back. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W.</ref> had been explaining the evil consequences of letting the gownsmen<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Cambridge undergraduates. Wordsworth persuaded Trinity College, Cambridge, to invest in a quadrangle called &#8216;The New Court&#8217;, opened in 1825, to allow more undergraduates to live in College.</note> lodge in the town, &amp; the measures which he was taking to put an end to so pernicious a practise. I wish you had present, inasmuch as what he said would have given you a very high idea of his good sense &amp; his talents for business. &#8211; By the time I reached the halfway house at Wytheburne<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Wythburn.</note> my clothes were so damp that it would have imprudent to have gone in &amp; waited for the coach. The rain then increased &amp; continued very heavy till I was within four miles of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, when it cleared up, &amp; I entered the town at the same minute as the coach. There I found <ref type="m" target="people.html#SharpRichard">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sharp</ref> &amp; the American &#8216;Randolph of Roanoke&#8217;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Randolph (1773&#8211;1833), Virginia tobacco planter and Representative or Senator almost continuously for his State between 1799 and 1833.</note> who spent the evening with me. Thursday evening Sir John Malcolm<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Malcolm (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), the Scottish soldier, East India Company administrator and historian. He had effectively governed most of central India in 1818&#8211;1822, but had returned home disappointed not to receive further promotion.</note> made his appearance &amp; he &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Duncan,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Duncan (1774&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>), Minister of Ruthwell, Dumfriesshire, who had founded the savings bank movement in 1810.</note> (a Scotch pastor <del>x</del> who is the founder of the Savings-Banks) breakfasted with me the next day. That day was fated to end most frightfully. <ref type="m" target="people.html#KennawayCharlesE">Charles Kennaway</ref>, who had drank tea here, went over to the Island with the girls &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref>. &#8211; I had just finished my supper when Anne<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A maid working for the Southey household.</note> came into the room as pale as death to say there had been a dreadful accident at the Island. a cannon had burst, &#8211; &amp; young M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Henry killed.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Edward Henry (1807&#8211;1833), the younger of Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons. The accident occurred on 2 August 1822 and was widely reported in the newspapers (without naming him): &#8216;A young gentleman, by way of saluting some friends who were taking their departure, fired off a cannon, which unfortunately burst in consequence of being overloaded, and the fragments severely fractured his skull&#8217; (<title>Glasgow Herald</title>, 12 August 1822). The cannon was kept outside Peachy&#8217;s house on Derwent Island and was fired as part of the annual Keswick Regatta.</note> This was the first report, &#8211; the second was that some other person was hurt, &#8211; nor could we ascertain what had actually happened till I &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S</ref> got to the water side, where we found a number of persons collected, waiting in perfect silence to know the extent of the mischief. A boat was coming across, &amp; to our infinite relief the girls (<ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara C.</ref>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>) were in it. Poor things, they had a sad story to tell, &#8211; in spite of their remonstrances Charles Henry would fire the cannon when they were coming away, &#8211; it had burst &amp; fractured his skull, &#8211; &amp; whether he would live or die they knew not. &#8211; Thank God, tho the fracture was a dreadful one (more than thirty pieces of the skull having been taken out &#8211; &amp; the brain itself injured in both lobes) he has been going on well, &amp; every hour strengthens the probability of his entire recovery, twelve<del>n</del> days having now elapsed. &#8211; You may conceive what a shock this has been to us.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> &amp; his son<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802&#8211;1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August&#8211;2 September 1822.</note> did not arrive till Monday, &#8211; had they come on Saturday as was expected they would have found us in the greatest apprehension &amp; distress. Now that all <del>sxxx</del> is going on so much better than we could at first venture to hope, I have been again going over some of the ground which you &amp; I lately traversed with so much satisfaction. Saturday last we walked round the Lake, Monday up <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>, ascending by the line which you descended, &#8211; yesterday to the Vale of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Johns, &#8211; today had the weather permitted we should have attempted Causey Pike. Exercise like this is of great benefit to me; &amp; you have done me a great deal of good by bringing me into good condition.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> came on the same day with the Mays, they on the coach he in it. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FeldborgAndreas">Feldborg the Dane</ref> is also in <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. You may suppose that I have very little time to myself. On Saturday I go again to <ref type="m" target="places.html#RydalMount">Rydale</ref> in order to dine on Sunday at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Boltons (on Windermere)<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Storrs Hall on Windermere, Lake District home of John Bolton (1756&#8211;1837; <title>DNB</title>), a Liverpool merchant and leading supporter of Canning as MP for that city.</note> &amp; remain there on Monday to meet <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Canning</ref>, who comes there to make his farewell visit. My guests meantime will take a three days circuit to Ennerdale &amp; Waswater, &amp; I shall rejoin them on Tuesday: they remain another week, &amp; then I shall be left to pursue my usual course of life at leisure.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">And now my dear Lightfoot let me, before I conclude, thank you for a visit which I shall look back upon with delight as long as we both live. It does not often happen that friends meet after so long a separation, &amp; find in each other so little change. God willing, I shall certainly see you in the winter, or at latest early in the spring. Present my best wishes to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lightfoot<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Lightfoot married Bridget Prideaux (1768&#8211;1856) on 13 July 1801.</note> &amp; my goddaughter,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Frances Jane Lightfoot (1806&#8211;1882), Southey&#8217;s god-daughter.</note> &#8211; Truly glad shall I be to become known to them, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">John</ref> (whom I seem to know already) &amp; your steady Kate, &amp; Bridget, &amp; Nico.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Catherine Anne Lightfoot (1808&#8211;1898); Bridget Mary Lightfoot (1810&#8211;1889); Nicholas Francis Lightfoot (1811&#8211;1881), Vicar of Cadbury 1846&#8211;1855, Rector of Islip 1855&#8211;1881.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All here join in kind remembrances -</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">The proof sheet containing Title page, Dedication &amp; Preface is on my table.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Proofs for Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>