<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3975</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3975Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3975" type="letter">
        <head>3975. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BartonBernard">Bernard Barton</ref>, <date when="1823-03-06">6 March 1823</date>
          </head><p>MS untraced; text is taken from Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965)<lb />
Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 241&#8211;242.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I can at last thank you for your Verses on the death of the miserable <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Barton&#8217;s <title>Verses on the Death of Percy Bysshe Shelley</title> (1822).</note> which did not reach me till yesterday evening, whereby you will perceive that my communication with the booksellers is not very frequent. But this parcel has been a fortnight longer than it should have been, on the way, owing I suppose to the accumulation of packages in the warehouse during the continuance of snow. The panegyrical Elegy<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Chalk Claris (c. 1797&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>) [Arthur Brooke], <title>Elegy on the Death of Percy Bysshe Shelley</title> (1822).</note> which called forth your wiser verses was sent me also by its author, whom I know not, but who probably writes under a <hi rend="ital">nom de guerre</hi>. Whether the sending it was intended as a compliment, or as an insult, is to me a matter of perfect indifference. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelleys</ref> is a flagitious history, and by far the worst tragedy in real life which has ever fallen within my knowledge. As I told him myself in the last communication I had with him, it is truly the Atheist&#8217;s Tragedy.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Shelley, 12 October 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3538, in which Southey invoked Cyril Tourneur (d. 1626; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Atheist&#8217;s Tragedy</title> (1611). The eponymous &#8216;Atheist&#8217; kills himself at the end of the play.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">It is indeed a strange piece of ill-fortune that an act of robbery should have drawn upon you so heavy a burthen of unprofitable and ungrateful employment: and but a poor satisfaction that when this unusual imposition is over the regular task work will appear almost like a holyday.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Barton was a clerk in Messrs Alexander&#8217;s Bank in Woodbridge. The Ipswich branch of the bank sustained a major loss on 11 September 1822 when a parcel of banknotes, to the value of over &#163;30,000, which it had received from their London bankers, was stolen from the mail coach at Colchester. The bank offered a reward of &#163;5,000 for information leading to the recovery of the notes but ended up having to negotiate their return with the thieves.</note> Meantime however your name is making its way, and I think I might venture to predict, that if you were to try a volume of tales in verse, you would find a lucrative adventure.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Peradventure I may see you in the course of spring, as I have the intention of passing a day with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Thomas Clarkson</ref> on the way between Norwich and London.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Barton and Southey did indeed meet at Thomas Clarkson&#8217;s house in 1824.</note> Farewell, and believe me Yours truly</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">When you see <ref type="m" target="people.html#MoorEdwardMajor">Major Moor</ref> have the goodness to present my remembrances to him, and say that I received his friendly letter yesterday, and with it the Ms. Volume.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly letters and documents collected by Sir Augustus Simon Frazer (1776&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), a career soldier, who had seen service in the Peninsular campaign as a highly effective senior commander of horse artillery. He was Moor&#8217;s brother-in-law, and Moor had offered these papers to help with Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>