<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4176Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4176Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4176" type="letter">
        <head>4176. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>], <date when="1824-04-24">24 April 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: April 24 &#8211; 1824 <lb />
               MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have no intention of doing any thing more to the B of the Church,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The second edition of Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824); Murray had already sent this to the press.</note> than what the inclosed paper will enable the printer to perform: &#8211; that is, to correct a slip of the pen &amp; a slip of the press; &amp; to omit a circumstance &#8211; which I learn from some newspaper critic has been disproved in <del>that</del> a volume of Lingards which I have not seen.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">These corrections were for a second edition of <title>The Book of the Church</title>. The &#8216;slip of the pen&#8217; occurred in vol. II, p. 8 of the first edition (2 vols, London, 1824), where Charles V (1500&#8211;1558; Holy Roman Emperor 1519&#8211;1556, King of Spain 1516&#8211;1556) was misidentified as the brother, rather than the nephew, of Catherine of Aragon (1485&#8211;1536; <title>DNB</title>), first wife of Henry VIII (1491&#8211;1547; King of England 1509&#8211;1547; <title>DNB</title>). The &#8216;slip of the press&#8217; occurred in vol. II, p. 341, where Henry IV (1553&#8211;1610; King of France 1589&#8211;1610) was misprinted for Henry III (1551&#8211;1589; King of France 1574&#8211;1589). The error was pointed out in the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 6 February 1824, which contained a letter from &#8216;TRUTH&#8217;, showing that Southey&#8217;s account of the death of Stephen Gardiner (1483&#8211;1555; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Winchester 1531&#8211;1551, 1553&#8211;1555 in vol. II, pp. 209&#8211;210, could not be accurate and was contradicted by John Lingard (1771&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of England, from the First Invasion of the Romans</title>, 5 vols (London, 1819&#8211;1823), V, p. 628. Southey only possessed the first three volumes of the latter, published in 1819, no. 1634 in the sale catalogue of his library. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Having now fairly lost all hope of obtaining the Spanish book which has been sought thro so many channels,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford&#8217;s &#8216;On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez&#8217;, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221&#8211;223. It mentioned Olivarez&#8217;s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title>, published in four volumes at Seville in 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &amp; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877 and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had then written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832), and Herbert Hill had also offered to help. Southey had then sought the assistance of George Canning. Finally, Southey had written to John Mitford, 12 April 1824, Letter 4171.</note> I shall pursue my way without it, &amp; put the second volume to press without delay.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> I shall send you a portion of copy in the course of the ensuing week. Please to send me a book which Kolly has published concerning his attempt to deliver Ferdinand,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Leopold, Baron de Kolli (1757&#8211;1825), <title>Memoirs of Baron de Kolli, Relative to his Secret Mission in 1810, for Liberating Ferdinand VII, King of Spain, from Captivity at Valencay</title> (1823). This recounted de Kolli&#8217;s inept attempt to free Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813&#8211;1833) from captivity in France.</note> &amp; Col Stuarts book about the Highland Regiments,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">David Stewart (1772&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Sketches of the Character, Manners and Present State of the Highlanders of Scotland: with Details of the Military Service of the Highland Regiments</title> (1822).</note> &#8211; in which there will no doubt be many anecdotes relating to this war. You should let me see too the modern books about Spain by Quin, Bramsen, Count Pecchio,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Michael Joseph Quin (1796&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Visit to Spain; Detailing the Transactions which Occurred during a Residence in that Country in the Latter Part of 1822, and the First Four Months of 1823. With an Account of the Removal of the Court from Madrid to Seville; and General Notices of the Manners, Customs, Costume and Music of the Country</title> (1823); John Bramsen (1761&#8211;1832), <title>Remarks on the North of Spain</title> (1823), no. 130 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library; and Giuseppe, Count Pecchio (1785&#8211;1835), <title>Anecdotes of the Spanish and Portuguese Revolutions</title> (1823). Written by travellers to Spain, all three accounts reflected on the revolution in that country in 1820, which had restored the liberal Constitution of 1812.</note> &amp; any others which may have appeared, because tho their object is to treat of the recent revolutions they relate to <hi rend="ital">persons</hi> who figured in my subject, &amp; may in all likelihood afford information which I shall find useful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  You shall have a paper upon Hayleys Life for your next number,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of John Johnson (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263&#8211;311.</note> &#8211; the subject will include a view of <del>the</del> &lt;our&gt; literary history from commencement of his career &#8211; to the end of the last century. Send me his life of Romney.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hayley (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of George Romney, Esq.</title> (1809), no. 1177 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> I have his Essay on Old Maids<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hayley, <title>A Philosophical, Historical, and Moral Essay on Old Maids. By a Friend to the Sisterhood</title> (1785), no. 1294 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; six volumes of his works.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Poems and Plays: by William Hayley, Esq. In Six Volumes</title> (1785), no. 1294 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have now to beg a favour of you. A Dutch Lady,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Katherina Bilderdijk, n&#233;e Schweickhardt (1776&#8211;1830), <title>Rodrigo de Goth, Koning van Spanje</title>, 2 vols (The Hague, 1823&#8211;1824), no. 2701 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, where it was described as &#8216;<hi rend="ital">red morocco, gilt leaves</hi>&#8217;. This was a translation of Southey&#8217;s <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> wife to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BilderdijkWillem">the most distinguished man of letters in Holland</ref> has translated Roderick into Dutch verse, dedicated it to me in a very pleasing &amp; pathetic poem, &amp; sent it to me in as good a dress as could be put upon it by a Leyden bookbinder. I can see that the translation is faithfully done, &amp; I am assured that it is very well done. May I request you to send her in return a copy of the Book of the Church handsomely bound, &#8211; &amp; with it a set of the Illustrations to Roderick,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Westall (1765&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths, by R. Southey. Illustrated with Engravings from the Designs of R. W.</title> (1824), nos 2627&#8211;2628 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> which I will have sent to your house for that purpose. The parcel should be directed to <del>Madam Bilderdyk</del> &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BilderdijkWillem">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Willem Bilderdyk</ref> &amp;c &amp;c Leyden, &#8211; to the care of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> F. Smeer Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Frans Smeer (1766&#8211;1831), a Dutch merchant, based in Rotterdam.</note> Rotterdam, &amp; sent by the steam-packet which goes from London to Rotterdam.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Farewell my dear Sir &amp; believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <lb />
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-04-24">24 Apr. 1824</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>