<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3811Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3811Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3811" type="letter">
        <head>3811. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1822-03-08">8 March 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major-General Peachy/ 18. Albemarle Street/ London.<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 11 MR 11/ 1822<lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">In this age of reformation &amp; improvement, a very needful improvement has been undertaken at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, &#8211; to which I have been desired to solicit your contribution. It is that of making a safe &amp; commodious church-path. <ref type="m" target="people.html#StangerJames">Mr Stanger</ref> has given as much of his field as is necessary for widening the church lane, where it is proposed to form a raised path of a sufficient width, secured from carriages by a curb-stone. The estimate is 27 &#163;. &#8211; there is a hedge to be grubbed, another planted, fenced &amp;c. &amp; if there be any overplus, as it is hoped there will, it goes to improve the path between the church lane &amp; the town. Greenwich Hospital<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Greenwich Hospital owned much of the land around Keswick.</note> contributes railing &amp; two guineas. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stevenson<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Stephensons were a long-established and prominent Keswick family, whose best-known representative had been John Stephenson (1691&#8211;1768), MP for Sudbury 1734&#8211;1741, who made a fortune in India. John Stephenson had no children and by this time his relatives were based in London, mainly engaged in banking. Southey is probably referring here to Edward Stephenson (1759&#8211;1833) of the firm Stephenson, Remington &amp; Co.</note> two guineas. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calvert</ref>, one with the use of carts &amp; horses, &#8211; &amp; there list ended when it was brought to me by <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Mr Edmondson</ref>. The intention is to go from house to house, &amp; collect even the smallest sums that may be offered for a work of general convenience.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for Coltons pamphlett<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Caleb Colton (1777&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Remarks Critical and Moral on the Talents of Lord Byron, and the Tendencies of Don Juan</title> (1819). Colton was a notably eccentric clergyman, writer, wine merchant and gambler, who later lived in the United States and France.</note> which I have received this very day. It is written with great ability, but not always with judgement, &amp; there is a sneer at Lady Byron which would have been improper anywhere, &amp; is here peculiarly out of place.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Remarks Critical and Moral on the Talents of Lord Byron, and the Tendencies of Don Juan</title> (London, 1819), p. 9: &#8216;There are some pairs so ill-sorted, that we ought to be more surprised at their <title>union</title>, than their <title>separation</title>; perhaps, the enigmatical part of this domestic division, might be explained by observing that the <title>mathematics</title>, and what his Lordship would term <title>methodism</title>, were two things not likely to amalgamate the most happily with <title>poetry</title> and with <title>infidelity</title>. The <title>angles</title> of the first might appear to his Lordship to be too pointed and proximate; and the <title>angels</title> of the other too obscure and remote.&#8217; This passage was a reference to the marriage of Byron and Anne Isabella Byron, n&#233;e Milbanke (1792&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>) and to Lady Byron&#8217;s interest in mathematics and religion.</note> &#8211; I heard a good deal of Colton some years ago from <ref type="m" target="people.html#StandertHughChudleigh">Standard</ref>, &amp; the impression then made upon me was he was a man of brilliant talents, but not altogether sane.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a cottage just behind <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> at <ref type="m" target="places.html#RydalMount">Rydal Mount</ref>, where the people had a most providential deliverance two nights ago.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">This incident was reported in the <title>Westmorland Gazette</title>, 9 March 1822. The fire began in the outbuildings of James Fleming (dates unknown), a farmer at Rydal.</note> A person going out from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> about eleven o clock, perceived a strange light there, &amp; gave the alarm just as the flames broke out, the whole family being so fast asleep that there was great difficulty in wakening them. Had he come out five minutes sooner, he would have seen nothing, &#8211; &amp; in ten minutes later it would have been too late to save their lives. The fire began in the stable &amp; burnt down that &amp; the house.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You will have read in the papers of our tremendous flood in which the clergyman of Basenthwaite<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Brown (d. 1822), Perpetual Curate of Bassenthwaite, 1801&#8211;1822, drowned on the night of 2 February 1822 on his way back from the market at Keswick.</note> was taken off his horse, by the turnpike, carried over two hedges &amp; drowned. Nothing equal to it is remembered in these parts. A few days afterwards poor Clarke<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Clark (d. 1822), a nurseryman, had rented some of the land next to Greta Hall. He had been declared bankrupt in 1817. His death was reported in the <title>Westmorland Gazette</title>, 23 February 1822, as occurring on 18 February 1822.</note> dropt down dead, nearly upon the same spot.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am sorry to read of the death of my old school &amp; chamber-fellow James Boswell,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">James Boswell (1778&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>), lawyer, poet and literary scholar. He died on 24 February 1822.</note> &#8211; who was the very image of his father,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">James Boswell (1740&#8211;1795; <title>DNB</title>), diarist and biographer of Samuel Johnson (1709&#8211;1784; <title>DNB</title>). Both Boswells were heavy drinkers.</note> &amp; followed him but too closely in a weakness which has shortened his days. An inoffensive, good-natured, chearful man he was, possessed of good natural parts &amp; much acquired knowledge. He was about three years my junior. When I look round upon the sea of life, for those with whom I began my voyage, I perceive now that they are <hi rend="ital">rari nantes</hi>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A contraction of &#8216;apparent rari nantes in gurgite vasto&#8217;, or &#8216;there in the vast abyss are seen the swimmers few and far between&#8217;, Publius Vergilius Maro (70&#8211;19 BC), <title>Aeneid</title> (29 BC), Book 1, line 118.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Your new road is not yet compleated; neither labour nor materials are spared upon it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">Mrs Peachy</ref> has not seen a little volume of poems entitled the Widows Tale by the Author of Ellen Fitzarthur,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles, <title>Ellen Fitzarthur; a Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (1820) and <title>The Widow&#8217;s Tale and Other Poems</title> (1822).</note> let me recommend it to her: The authoress is a <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Miss Bowles</ref> of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Buckland">Buckland</ref> in the New Forest, near Lymington. Few writers <del>of the</del> possess a finer feeling, or a greater power of expression.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The Ladies join in kind remembrances. Present mine also to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">Mrs Peachy</ref>, &amp; to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Henry,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">James Henry (1803&#8211;1884), the elder of Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons.</note> if he be with you, &amp; believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent4"> Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-03-08">8 March. 1822.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>