<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3868Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3868Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3868" type="letter">
        <head>3868. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-07-12">12 July 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 1x JY 15/ 18x2<lb />
               Endorsements: 12. July 1822./ Lightfoot at Keswick.; 12. July 1822<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 117&#8211;119 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">My old friend Lightfoot</ref> is with me, <del>xx</del> whose library you assisted me in making an inventory of, to whom we wrote a joint letter concerning Snivel &amp; the Bow Begum,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Snivel and the Bow-Begum were dogs owned by Bedford. The joint letter to Lightfoot does not seem to survive, though the same subject was addressed in Southey to Tom Southey, [late October/early November&#8211;]14 December 1793, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 65. The only surviving joint letter by Southey and Bedford to Lightfoot is that of 27&#8211;30 September 1793, <title>Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 59.</note> &#8211; &amp; whom I had not seen since we parted upon leaving Oxford, eight &amp; twenty years ago. The communication between us had never been broken. I had a great regard for him, <del>&amp;</del> talked of him often &amp; oftener thought of him: &amp; as you may suppose, the more I became known &amp; talked of in the world, the larger part I occupied in his thoughts. So at length he mustered up resolution to make a journey hither from Crediton during his midsummer holydays, &#8211; being master of the grammar school there.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Queen Elizabeth&#8217;s Grammar School, Crediton, founded in 1547.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">He declares me to be less altered in appearance &amp; manners than any man whom he ever saw. I should not have known him, &#8211; &amp; yet he has worn better than I have, but he is thinner &amp; altogether less than when he was <del>a</del> young <del>man</del>, &amp; his face has lengthened, partly because he has lost some of his hair. His life has been laborious, uniform, succesful, &amp; singularly happy. After leaving college he became usher at a school in his native county for five years,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Lightfoot was an usher at Kingsbridge Grammar School in Devon 1795&#8211;1800.</note> &#8211; engaged to marry there,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Lightfoot married Bridget Prideaux (1768&#8211;1856) on 13 July 1801.</note> &amp; (a little by virtue of that engagement, his wife being distantly related to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CourtenayThomas">Courtenays</ref> father, then Bp of Exeter,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Reginald Courtney (1741&#8211;1803; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Exeter 1797&#8211;1803.</note> &#8211; but still more by virtue of his excellent character) was elected master of the Grammar School at Crediton,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Lightfoot was appointed Master of Queen Elizabeth&#8217;s Grammar School, Crediton, in March 1800.</note> &#8211; an old foundation but then in a decayed state. He restored the school, married about a year after he had settled there, has now five children,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Prideaux Lightfoot; Frances Jane Lightfoot (1806&#8211;1882); Catherine Anne Lightfoot (1808&#8211;1898); Bridget Mary Lightfoot (1810&#8211;1889); Nicholas Francis Lightfoot (1811&#8211;1881), Vicar of Cadbury 1846&#8211;1855, Rector of Islip 1855&#8211;1881.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">the eldest</ref> a youth of good promise, excellent conduct at Oxford, &amp; has realized enough to make him quite at ease, concerning <del>it</del> a provision for his family.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Although Lightfoot&#8217;s stipend had at first been only &#163;20 p.a., his admission of boarding pupils, and improvements in the schools endowments, gave him a respectable, if not secure, income. In 1818 he received a stipend of &#163;50 as headmaster, plus a house and an allowance for taxes. He was also paid &#163;5 p.a. for each day pupil and charged 30 guineas p.a. for boarding pupils (of whom he had 37 in 1811). In addition, the Governors of the school had presented him to the nearby Rectory of Kennerleigh in 1807, with a stipend of &#163;100 p.a. Nicholas Carlisle, <title>A Concise Description of the Endowed Grammar Schools in England and Wales</title>, 2 vols (London, 1818), I, pp. 254&#8211;265.</note> I have scarcely ever seen a man so thoroughly happy, &amp; thankful for his lot in life. And well may he be so, having never had anxiety enough to break his rest a single night!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> He trembled like an aspen leaf at meeting me. A journey to Cumberland is to him as formidable a thing as it would be for me to set off for Jerusalem, so little has he been used to locomotion. And he <del>has</del> shocked <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> by wishing that the mountains would descend to fill up the lakes &amp; vales <del>xxx</del> because then I should return to the South, &amp; be within reach of him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The only thing short of this which would be likely to remove me from this country, would be if upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> giving up the management of the QR it were to be offered me, &amp; made worth my acceptance. In that case I should probably from prudential reasons think it proper to accept the offer &amp; fix myself within ten or twelve miles of town. But this is not likely &amp; I am not sure that it would be desirable</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am very much better, but have still a hacking cough which has made a lodgement in my chest</p>
        <p rend="indent1">We have been talking over old times, the Installation,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The installation, on 1 July 1793, of William Cavendish-Bentinck, 3rd Duke of Portland (1738&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783, 1807&#8211;1809, as Chancellor of the University of Oxford.</note>
          <hi rend="ital">inter alia</hi>,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;among other things&#8217;.</note> the grease at the gates of the Theatre,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Sheldonian Theatre, Oxford (built 1664&#8211;1669), used for major university ceremonies, including Portland&#8217;s installation in 1793.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppas</ref> appearance when he came out of it his too-solid flesh resolved into a dew,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Hamlet</title>, Act 1, scene 2, lines 129&#8211;130: &#8216;O that this too too <title>solid</title> flesh would melt,/ Thaw, and resolve itself into a dew!&#8217;</note> &#8211; the piece of dried thumb, &#8211; &amp; the Pot of Abomination whose contents we catalogued with such precision.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is referring here to some long-standing jokes from his and Lightfoot&#8217;s student days; see Southey to Nicholas Lightfoot, 22 December 1793, <title>Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 75.</note> I wish you were with us. He talks of departing on Tuesday, but as the rain has confined us for three days to the house, this time must be <del>postponed</del> prolonged. He will take back with him recollections for many an after day, &amp; he will leave me the better for his visit. Indeed he has won the heart of all my family, from <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">my Lady-Mare</ref> down <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">to Cupn</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">What a pleasure <del>there</del> &lt;it&gt; is in declining life to see the friends of our youth, such as we should wish them to be, &#8211; &amp; how infinitely greater will be the pleasure of meeting them in another world, when progression in beatitude will be the only change!</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dear Grosvenor</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-07-12">12 July. 1822</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>