<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4014</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4014Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4014" type="letter">
        <head>4014. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ElliottEbenezer">Ebenezer Elliott</ref>, <date when="1823-05-09">9 May 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: [deletion and readdress in another hand] To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> E Elliott Jun<hi rend="sup">r-</hi>/ <del>Rotherham</del> 61 Burgess Street/ Sheffield<lb />
Seal: [trace] red wax<lb />
MS: Beinecke Library, Osborn MSS File &#8216;S&#8217;, Folder 14119. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-05-09">9 May. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Thank you for your new volume<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Ebenezer Elliott, <title>Love: a Poem, in Three Parts; to which is added The Giaour, a Satirical Poem</title> (1823).</note> which I received the day before yesterday. There came with it copies (as I suppose) &#8211; directed for <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wordsworth</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coleridge</ref>. That for the latter, must wait till an opportunity occurs of sending it to him at Highgate, which is his place of abode. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth&#8217;s</ref> will go tomorrow to his house, but he himself is at present in the Netherlands, or on the way thither.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have not read thro the volume, &#8211; &amp; of what I have read the tribute to your schoolmaster<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Love: a Poem, in Three Parts; to which is added The Giaour, a Satirical Poem</title> (London, 1823), pp. 129&#8211;130. In the &#8216;Notes&#8217; to &#8216;Love: a Poem, in Three Parts&#8217;, Book 2, Elliott paid tribute to Joseph Ramsbottom (c. 1756&#8211;1820), Master of Hollis&#8217;s Charity School, Rotherham 1778&#8211;1820, his teacher and &#8216;the gentlest and most benevolent of living creatures.&#8217;</note> has pleased me most. You write <del>xx</del> sweetly upon grateful subjects &amp; worthy affections. These are worthier themes for poetry than crimes &amp; horrors can be made; &#8211; &amp; as for satire, I am afraid it is more likely to do some injury to him who writes it, than ever to <del>xxx</del> amend the person against whom it is directed. Not that I would proscribe it in the spirit of a Quaker; for it is necessary sometimes to show oneself capable of resentment. Peter Bells ass<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Wordsworth, <title>Peter Bell: a Tale in Verse</title> (1819), in which Peter Bell encounters an ass, which refuses to move, despite the beating he gives the animal.</note> patient as he was, used I have no doubt to fling out his heels sometimes upon just provocation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>Xxxx</del> You have given me that sort of praise which is truly gratifying, because I am conscious that it is just.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">In his &#8216;Address to the Right Honourable Lord Byron&#8217; that preceded &#8216;The Giaour, a Satirical Poem&#8217;, Elliott had criticised Byron for his attacks on the &#8216;Lake Poets&#8217; and argued they had &#8216;pointed out the long-forgotten road to truth and nature&#8217;, which Byron had merely followed (<title>Love: a Poem, in Three Parts; to which is added The Giaour, a Satirical Poem</title> (London, 1823), p. 136).</note> I wish you had touched upon a part of <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">the Giaours</ref> conduct,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Here Southey names Byron by reference to his <title>The Giaour, a Fragment of a Turkish Tale</title> (1813). Byron had married Anne Isabella Milbanke (1792&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>) in 1815, though the couple separated the following year. Byron was supposed to receive &#163;20,000 from the Milbanke family as a marriage settlement but received only &#163;6,200. However, Lady Bryon inherited a substantial fortune on her mother Judith Noel&#8217;s (1751&#8211;1822) death; after that had occurred Byron and his wife shared equally in the income from Lady Byron&#8217;s estates, under the terms of their marriage settlement.</note> which if I have ever occasion to grapple with him again I <del>xxx</del> will certainly bring forward, &#8211; his taking half his wifes fortune, by virtue of those marriage laws, in the <del>xxx</del> open breach of which he lives, &amp; which he avowedly holds in contempt!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">It is long since I have written any poetry. I shall endeavour to finish those poems which were begun many years ago,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825); and Southey&#8217;s unfinished epic, &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;, set in New England. A fragment was published posthumously in <title>Oliver Newman: a New-England Tale (Unfinished): with Other Poetical Remains by the Late Robert Southey</title> (London, 1845), pp. 1&#8211;90. </note> &amp; then leave the field to younger spirits. It has become long since more congenial to my inclinations to be following historical pursuits, In eight or ten weeks my Book of the Church<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> will appear, under which title a view of our ecclesiastical history is comprized As soon as it is compleated I set out for a two months absence in the south &amp; west of England. I wish any propitious circumstances might lead you into these parts before I depart, or after I return, &#8211; for it would give me real pleasure to shake you by the hand.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Farewell &amp; believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">Yrs truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>