<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3824Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3824Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3824" type="letter">
        <head>3824. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">William Wordsworth</ref>, <date when="1822-04-11">11 April [1822]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Wordsworth Trust, WL MS A Southey 9. ALS; 2p.<lb />
               Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London &amp; New York, 1965), II, pp. 234&#8211;235.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear W.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I would fain have let <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C&#8217;s</ref> hopes concerning <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> die gradually, of a natural death, but the position in which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gillman<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">James Gillman (1782&#8211;1839) had taken Coleridge into his house in Highgate 1816; Coleridge continued to live there until his death. Hartley Coleridge had stayed with his father occasionally since his Fellowship at Oriel College, Oxford, was terminated in 1820. Gillman had suggested that Hartley Coleridge should come to live at Greta Hall.</note> has placed me, made this impossible. I therefore put both the letters into her hands.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">My sincere hope is that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">H.</ref> may not accept <ref type="m" target="people.html#Dawes">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dawes</ref> invitation.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Hartley, and his brother Derwent Coleridge, had attended the school at Ambleside run by John Dawes. Dawes had written to Hartley, asking him to visit Ambleside.</note> The scheme of sending him to be under his mothers eye is <del>so</del> preposterous, even if it were possible. What authority can a mother exercise over a man of six &amp; twenty,&#8212;the very disease of whose nature is an impatience of all ordinary observances, &amp; &lt;of&gt;, the restraints which he owes to himself as well as others! &#8211; I cannot understand how <del>xxxx</del>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> can be kept in ignorance of his sons conduct, &#8211; nor indeed how he can be ignorant of it at this time, if it has been such as to render his abode at Highgate impossible, &amp; to eject him from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MontaguBasil">Montagues</ref>: knowing these irregularities, what is there in a fresh instance which is to prove fatal to him if revealed?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gillmans drift is evident, &amp; I am surprized that he should have formed so senseless a scheme. By his own account the possibility of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">H&#8217;s</ref> obtaining testimonials is now postponed sine die:<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;without day&#8217;, i.e. for an indefinite period.</note> I believe indeed for ever. He has no means of living but by his pen; this we all know to be a miserable thing, but he has brought himself to it, &amp; nothing remains but to make the best of it. But to live thus he must be in London, upon the spot, within reach of books &amp; booksellers, editors to set him to work, &amp; printers devils to goad him for copy. The same habits which disqualify him for orders, unfit him also for a tutor. Writing is his only resource; &amp; it is in London that he must follow it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">As to his living under my roof,&#8212;for to this the question comes&#8212;I certainly will not suffer any such disturbance of my peace &amp; comfort as such an arrangement would inevitably bring with it. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C</ref> perfectly understands this, &amp; would have written yesterday to make M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> G understand it, if she had been sufficiently recovered from the shock. &#8211; She wishes G. had not exposed the matter to us, that is natural &amp; therefore excusable</p>
        <p rend="indent1">There has been no letter either from <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">H.</ref> or Jamieson.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Sympson Jameson (1796&#8211;1854), barrister and old school-friend of Hartley Coleridge from Ambleside. Jameson was later Chief Justice of Dominica 1829&#8211;1833 and Attorney-General of Upper Canada 1833&#8211;1837, settling in Canada until his death. Hartley had been living with Jameson in London since June 1821.</note> If you have not heard that they have already packed him off for Westmorland, I think you had better write to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gillman &amp; tell him our thorough disapprobation of the scheme; &amp; remind him, which he seems to have forgotten, that <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C.</ref> has no establishment in which he can be received.&#8212;I have vexations &amp; burdens enough of my own, God knows, &#8212;&amp; of a hopeless kind, to which there will be no end as long as I live.	</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">    RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <date when="1822-04-11"> Thursday morning. Apr. 11.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>