<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4232Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4232Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4232" type="letter">
        <head>4232. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1824-08-14">14 August 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>-/ Florence/ Italy<lb />
               Stamped: ANGLETERRE; CHAMBERY; CORRISP<hi rend="sup">ZA</hi> ESTERA DA GENOA <lb />
               Postmarks: F/ 54/ 24; 2/ SETTEMBRE<lb />
               MS: National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 41. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 437&#8211;439.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
          </address>
          <date when="1824-08-14">14 Aug. 1824.</date>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am so compleatly removed from what is called literary society (which is at this time about the worst society in the world) that not a breath of opinion concerning your book<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title> (1824).</note> has reached me, nor have I seen any thing which has been written concerning it, except <ref type="m" target="people.html#HareJulius ">Julius Hare&#8217;s</ref> paper in the London Magazine.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;On Walter Savage Landor&#8217;s Imaginary Conversations&#8217;, <title>London Magazine</title>, 9 (May 1824), 523&#8211;541.</note> A more striking book never issued from the press in these Kingdoms, nor one more certain of surviving the wreck of its generation; &amp; this not from the adventitious <del>xxx xxxxx</del> importance of the subject, but from the excellence of the workmanship; &#8211; &#8211; for your prose is always, what the most felicitous passages of your poetry are, as excellent in the expression as in the conception.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  My own Colloquies<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> are now so far advanced, that it will soon become my primary object to compleat them. They will contain a connected &amp; extensive view of our existing state of society, <del>&amp;</del> with all its enormous evils, &#8211; &amp; I hope the statement will be startling enough to make some of our political men (I will not call them statesmen) rub their eyes. You will feel in the perusal, as I do, that where there is most difference in our views, it is to be explained by the difference of latitude between Tuscany &amp; Cumberland. I should agree more nearly with you in Florence, &amp; at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> you would find yourself more in sympathy with me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By way of relieving the Dialogues I introduce some of them <del>x</del> with descriptions of the scenery which lies within the circuit of my usual walks; half a dozen views of it, admirably drawn by <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">William Westall</ref>, are now in the engravers hands.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall produced six illustrations: &#8216;Druidical Stones near Keswick&#8217;; &#8216;Derwentwater, Bassenthwaite-water and Skiddaw, from Walla Crag&#8217;; &#8216;Derwentwater from Strandshagg&#8217;; &#8216;Crosthwaite Church and Skiddaw&#8217;; &#8216;Greta Hall, Derwentwater and Newlands&#8217;; and &#8216;Tarn of Blencathra&#8217;.</note> The book will command notice, &amp; provoke hostility. One edition will sell, some of the rising generation will be leavened by it, &amp; in the third &amp; fourth generations its foresight will be proved, &amp; perhaps some of its effects may be seen.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The books you sent me were lucky enough to escape all injury. I have been reading Casaubons letters.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Casaubon (1559&#8211;1614), <title>Epistolae</title> (1656), no. 453 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> If my Book of the Church<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> has reached you (as I trust it has, with its companions) you will see that I ought to have read these letters before: you will perceive also that the view which <del>you</del> they have led you to take of James&#8217;s character,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Dialogue VIII in Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, pp. [93]&#8211;112, where Casaubon converses with James I and VI (1567&#8211;1625; King of Scotland 1567&#8211;1603, King of Great Britain 1603&#8211;1625; <title>DNB</title>). Southey had expressed his views on the King in <title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, pp. 303&#8211;335; especially pp. 328&#8211;330. Southey was generally favourable to James, emphasising his tolerant and moderate views on religious controversies.</note> very much accords with the opinion that I have expressed concerning him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">   My family, thank God, is going on well. The two eldest girls<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha Southey</ref>.</note> are in the south, &amp; greatly do I miss them. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">My little boy</ref> is old enough to have begun upon the Latin grammar; &#8211; &amp; a happier creature does not at this hour exist upon the wide earth. It is in our power to make <del>cxxx</del> children happy while they are children; &#8211; &amp; yet how generally is their happiness curtailed; &amp; as far as nature will per[MS torn]stroyed, by unwise restrictions, &amp; the miserable discipline of our great schools in which the boys are bred up <del>to be x</del> &lt;to&gt; the abuse of power. If <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> lives, &amp; I live to instruct him, he will escape these evils; but how uncertain this must needs be I am fully sensible. Last <del>week</del> &lt;Thursday&gt; I compleated the fiftieth year of my age. <del>Ix xxxxx xxxx fifty xxxx xxxxxxxxxxx</del> My little boy is only in his sixth. I may put him in the way which he should go, &amp; direct him in it when I can accompany him no farther but it is not likely that I should see much of his progress.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here in England we are in an extraordinary state of quiescence, &#8211; not a grievance is afloat; &amp; few persons ask themselves what is to become of the rising generation of educated men who can find no room in the three professions,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Medicine, law and the Church of England.</note> &amp; for whose lives there is no demand nor what are to be consequences of an unlimited &amp; illimitable increase of capital, which even the bubble of foreign loans does not appear to check, nor where the manufacturing system is to end, which breeds Yahoos<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Jonathan Swift (1667&#8211;1745; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Gulliver&#8217;s Travels</title> (1726), Part 4 described a race of beings called the Yahoos who were ignorant, violent and coarse. Here Southey uses the term to refer to workers in the new industrial districts.</note> as fast as they can be bred, &amp; invents machinery to throw them out of employ. One remarkable effect of general education is beginning to show itself. Above fifty weekly miscellanies are published in London at two pence &amp; three pence each, &#8211; &amp; it is much the smaller portion that deal either in irreligion or in discontent<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The most successful and best-known of these publishers was John Limbird (c. 1796&#8211;1883), whose 2<hi rend="ital">d.</hi> weekly miscellany, the <title>Mirror of Literature, Amusement and Instruction</title> (1822&#8211;1847), may well have sold 15,000 copies a week. Limbird had entered publishing as an employee of the radical, Thomas Dolby (1782&#8211;1836), but had turned away from political journalism from 1819 onwards.</note> &#8211; The rest are useful &amp; amusing, &amp; the sale is prodigious. This is a good symptom &#8211; among many evil ones.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  &#8211; I have been getting on with my Tale of Paraguay,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> &amp; when I have once escaped from that most difficult of all stanzas, I shall feel like a racer let loose.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>