<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3895</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3895Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3895" type="letter">
        <head>3895. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1822-09-09">9 September 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Huntington Library, RS 425. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 328&#8211;329 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-09-09">9 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1822.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Such work as that of the Population<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman had organised the decennial census since 1801. He was responsible for the publication of <title>Comparative Statement of Population, etc, Great Britain, 1801, 1811, 1821</title> (1822).</note> in addition to your other labours, is enough to break down any body. The objection to task-work is that it tempts the industrious to work beyond their strength: &amp; in intellectual, over-exertion is worse than in bodily labour.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have spent a very idle summer, <del>&amp; thereby</del> much to the advantage of my health. <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">A fellow collegian</ref> for whom I have a great regard came to pass his Midsummer holy days with me, from Crediton, where he is Master of the Grammar school. I began a course of exercise with him, &amp; persevered in it, much as it cost me for some time, till at length the effect which I looked for was produced; &#8211; &amp; my constitution recovering its tone, I became once more a sound man. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> came to me just after <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoots</ref> departure I walked about an hundred miles more with him, &amp; am now in as good trim for walking as any man of my years need be. This I hope will last till I visit London, which I think of doing as soon as the rigour of the winter shall be over.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">My first volume is compleated.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> I send back by this post two cancels, in each of which insertions to the amount of two pages have been nicely fitted; &amp; with these the printer<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Davison (1766&#8211;1831).</note> will finish his part. The time for publication rests with <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, &amp; I should not think he will delay it till what is called the season, because the demand for such a book cannot depend much upon peoples being in or out of town.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The London &#8216;season&#8217;, when the British elite congregated in the capital, was at its height from Easter to early August.</note> It is dedicated to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref>, briefly, &amp; becomingly.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, p. [iii]: &#8216;It is with peculiar fitness, as well as with pleasure, that I inscribe to your Majesty a History of the most glorious war recorded in the British annals./ When the Regency devolved into your hands, the fortunes of our allies were at their lowest ebb, and neither arts nor efforts were spared for making the spirit of this country sink with them. At that momentous crisis every thing depended, under Providence, upon your single determination; and to that determination Great Britain is beholden for its triumph, and Europe for its deliverance./ To your Majesty, therefore, this faithful History is offered, as a portion of the tribute due to a just, magnanimous, and splendid reign, and as a proof of individual respect and gratitude from/Your Majesty&#8217;s/Most dutiful subject and servant,/ ROBERT SOUTHEY.&#8217;</note> The Buonapartists &amp; the Whigs will be thoroughly exasperated; I have only said enough of the latter to show them what they may expect in the progress of the history, where they shall have full justice.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was invited to meet <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Boltons.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Bolton (1756&#8211;1837; <title>DNB</title>), Liverpool merchant, originally from Ulverston. He was a leading figure in the Tory party in Liverpool and one of Canning&#8217;s chief supporters as the city&#8217;s MP. His home at Storrs Hall was on the east side of Lake Windermere, two miles south of Bowness.</note> It is the opinion of his friends that if he accepts office, the H of Commons will kill him in two or three years.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Canning became Foreign Secretary and Leader of the House of Commons on 13 September 1822. He died five years later.</note> In reality flesh &amp; blood is not equal to such wear &amp; tear as is exacted from an English minister in these times. I told him plainly that the present state of things was a contest between wickedness &amp; weakness, &amp; that there needed no spirit of prophecy to foresee what the event must be. &#8211; To my sore vexation when I returned from this short absence I found that <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Mr Telford</ref> whom I had rather have seen than all the statesmen in Europe had past thro <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. You may suppose how this mortified me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco White</ref> has written an entertaining account of what Spain was before the year 1808 &#8211; under the name of Leucadio Doblado &#8211; which I interpreted as soon as I saw it advertised.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from Spain by Don Leucadio Doblado</title> (1822). &#8216;Leucadio&#8217; was derived from the Greek word for &#8216;white&#8217; and &#8216;Doblado&#8217; is Spanish for &#8216;doubled&#8217;, so the pseudonymous author&#8217;s name could be translated as &#8216;white doubled&#8217;, as in &#8216;Blanco White&#8217;.</note> I mean to review his book &amp; take that opportunity of putting the peninsular revolutions in their proper light.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not review this work.</note> Ferdinand I think can hardly escape with life.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain, 1808, 1813&#8211;1833). The liberal revolution of 1820 had limited his absolute power, though this was restored by a French invasion in 1823.</note> The King of Portugal has a better chance.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John VI (1767&#8211;1826; King of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826). A revolution in 1820 had compelled him to return from Brazil and he finally agreed to a new liberal constitution in October 1822.</note> But I see no end to the miseries of either country, &#8211; except under a strong &amp; vigilant despotism, itself the worst of all evils, anarchy excepted. Who would not rather have lived in the days of Tiberius, or Nero,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Tiberius (42 BC&#8211;AD 37; Roman Emperor AD 14&#8211;37) and Nero (AD 37&#8211;68; Roman Emperor AD 54&#8211;68). Both were notorious for their despotic rule.</note> than in those of Marius &amp; Sylla?<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Gaius Marius (157&#8211;86 BC) and Lucius Cornelius Sulla (138&#8211;78 BC), Roman generals and politicians. Both were central figures in the civil wars that divided the late Roman Republic.</note> &#8211; In Europe the tendency of this time is thro one of these evils to the other.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The volume<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular Wars</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> may come vi&#226; <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmanni</ref>. Tomorrow I shall probably send the commencement of my Tour in the Netherlands.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Journal of a Tour in the Netherlands in the Autumn of 1815</title> (1902).</note> &#8211; I saw lately a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stuart<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> who lives somewhere within reach of the Parallel Roads.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey sent Rickman the fair copy of the journal he kept during their tour of Scotland in August&#8211;September 1819. This had provoked both men to further speculation on the origins of the Parallel Roads of Glen Roy that they had seen on their trip on 20 September 1819, <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (London, 1929), pp. 212&#8211;216. The &#8216;Roads&#8217; are, in fact, lake terraces formed along the shoreline of an ancient ice-dammed lake.</note> He said the local names were in favour of the hunting theory, &amp; promised to send me a list of them, with their significations.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">God bless you &#8211; remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Mrs R.</ref>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>