<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4215</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4215Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4215" type="letter">
        <head>4215. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>], <date when="1824-07-17">17 July&#8211;27
                  August 1824</date>
          </head><p>MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus
                  Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 7p.<lb /> Previously edited or published: Michael Neill
                  Stanton, &#8216;An Edition of the Autobiographical Letters of Robert Southey&#8217; (unpublished PhD, University of Rochester, 1972), pp.
                  182&#8211;192; <lb /> Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850),
                  I, pp. 123&#8211;132 [with variants; Cuthbert Southey&#8217;s text draws on a fair copy of the letter and not on the original version sent to
                  May, which we publish here].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1824-07-17">July 17. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Few boys were ever less qualified for the discipline of a public school, than I was when it was determined to place me
               at Westminster.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey attended Westminster School 1788&#8211;1792.</note> For if my school education
               had been ill conducted, the life which I <del>had</del> led with <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref>
               tended in every respect &lt;still more&gt; to unfit me for the new scenes &#8211; the new world it might almost be called &#8211; on which I was
               about to enter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref> settled at Bristol she brought with her a proud
               contempt for Bristol society. In fact she had scarcely any acquaintances there, &amp; seldom saw any company, except when
                  <del>the</del> some of her Bath friends came to Clifton for the summer, or when the players took up their <del>about</del>
               &lt;abode&gt; in the city, for then Mr Dimond<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Wyatt Dimond (c. 1750&#8211;1812;
                     <title>DNB</title>), actor and manager in Bath 1774&#8211;1801.</note> used to visit her, <del>a good actor, &amp;</del> &lt;He
               was&gt; a most gentlemanly &amp; respectable man, as well as a good actor, great is the delight which I have had in seeing him
               perform, &amp; hardly less was that which I have felt in listening to his conversation. The days when he dined with us were almost our
               only gala days. At such times &#8211; &amp; when she went out, her appearance &amp; manners <del>wh</del> were those of a woman who had been
               bred in the best society &amp; was equal to it: but <del>her way of life was as singular as it was uncomfortable, &amp;</del> if any
               stranger or visitor had caught her in her ordinary apparel she would have been as much confused as Diana when Actaeon came upon her
               bathing place,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek myth, the hunter Actaeon stumbled on the goddess Artemis (known to the
                  Romans as Diana), while she was bathing. She turned him into a deer and he was killed by his own dogs.</note> &#8211; &amp; almost with as
               much reason: for she was always in a bedgown, &amp; in rags. Most people I suspect have a weakness for old shoes: ease &amp; comfort
               &amp; <del>the</del> &lt;one&#8217;s own&gt; fire side are connected with them in fact <del>one</del> we never feel any regard for shoes
               till they attain to the privilege of age<del>x</del> &amp; then they became almost as much a part of the &lt;wearer&gt; as his corns.
               This sort of feeling <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my aunt</ref> extended to old clothes of every kind, the older
               &amp; the raggeder they <del>became</del> &lt;grew), the more unwilling she was to cast them off. But she was scrupulously clean
               &lt;in them&gt; indeed the principle upon which her whole household oeconomy was directed was that of keeping the house clean, &amp;
               taking more precautions against dust, than would have been needful against the plague in an infected city. She laboured under a
               perpetual <hi rend="ital">dustophobia</hi>, &amp; a comical disease it was, but whether I have been most amused or annoyed by it, it
               would be difficult to say. I had however in its consequences an early lesson how fearfully the mind may be enslaved by indulging its
               own peculiarities &amp; whimsies, innocent as they may appear at first.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The discomfort which <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tylers</ref> passion for cleanliness
               produced to herself as well as to her little household was truly curious: to herself indeed it was a perpetual torment, to <del>me
                  &amp;</del> the two servants a perpetual vexation, <del>except when</del> &amp; so it would have been to me if Nature had not blest
               me with an innate hilarity of spirit which nothing but real affliction can overcome. That the better rooms might be kept clean, she
               took possession of the kitchen, sending the servants to one which was underground; &amp; in this little &lt;dark confined&gt; room
               with a stone floor, &amp; a skylight &lt;(for it must not be supposed that it was a best kitchen which was always as it was intended
               to be a comfortable sitting room. This was more like a scullery)&gt; we <del>ate &amp; lived always</del> took our meals, &amp;
               generally lived. The best room was never opened but for company, except now &amp; then on a fine day to be aired, &amp; dusted, if dust
               could be detected there. In the other parlour I was allowed sometimes to read, &amp; she wrote her letters, &#8211; for she had many
               correspondents; &amp; we sate there sometimes in summer, when a fire was not needed, for fire produced ashes, &amp; ashes occasioned
               dust, &amp; dust visible or invisible was the plague of her life. I have seen her order the tea kettle to be emptied &amp; refilled,
               because some one had past across the hearth while it was on the fire, preparing for her breakfast. She had indulged these humours till
               she had formed for herself notions of uncleanness almost as irrational &amp; as inconvenient as those of the Hindoos. She had a cup
               once buried for six week to purify it from the lips of one whom she considered unclean; &#8211; <del>&amp;</del> all who were not her
               favourites were included in that class. A chair in which an unclean person had sate was put out in the garden to be aired; &amp; I
               never saw her more annoyed than when a man who called upon business once sate down in her own chair; how the leather cushion was ever
               &lt;again&gt; to be <del>purified she knew not</del> rendered fit for her use, she knew not. On such occasions her <del>sha</del>
               fine features assumed <del>an expression</del> &lt;a character&gt; either fierce or tragic, her expressions were vehement
                  <del>almost</del> &lt;even&gt; to irreverence, &#8211; &amp; her <del>gestilucat</del> gesticulations those of the deepest distress &#8211;
               hands &amp; eyes uplifted as if she were in hopeless misery, or a paroxysm of mental <del>agony</del> anguish.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As there are none who like to be upon ill terms with themselves, &#8211; most people find out some device &lt;whereby they
               are&gt; <del>for</del> reconciled <del>themselves</del> to their own faults: <del>my</del> &lt;&amp; in this propensity it is that
               much of the irreligion in the world, &amp; much of its false philosophy have originated. My&gt; <del>xxx</del>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Aunt</ref> used frequently to say that all good natured people were fools;
                  <del>&amp;</del> Hers was a violent temper rather an ill one; there was a great deal of kindness in it, <del>but</del> &lt;tho&gt;
               it was under no restraint. She was <del>in fact</del> at once tyrannical &amp; indulgent to her servants, &amp; they usually remained
               in her service a long while partly I believe from fear, &amp; partly from liking; &#8211; from liking, because she sent them often to the
               play, (which is probably to <del>them as</del> &lt;persons in that condition <del>like</del>, as it is&gt; to children the
                  <del>greatest of all</del> most delightful of all amusements) &#8211; &amp; conversed with them much more than <del>was</del> is usual for
               persons in her rank of life. Her habits were so peculiar that the servants became in a certain degree her confidants; she therefore was
               afraid to change them, &amp; they even when they wished to leave her were actually afraid to express the wish, knowing that she would
               regard it as a grievous offence, &amp; dreading the storm of anger which it would produce. Two servants at different times left her for
               the sake of marrying: &amp; tho they had both lived with her many years, she never forgave either <del>of them</del>, nor ever spoke of
               them without some expression of bitterness. I believe no daughter was ever more afraid of disclosing a clandestine marriage to a severe
               parent, than both these women were of making their intention known to their mistress: such was the ascendency that she possessed over
               them. She had reconciled herself to the indulgence of <del>this</del> &lt;her&gt; ungoverned &lt;anger&gt; <del>temper</del>, by
               supposing that <del>it</del> &lt;a bad temper&gt; was naturally connected with a good understanding &amp; a commanding mind:
                  <del>&amp; one of her favourite remarks was that all good natured people were fools.</del>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Besides her servants there were two persons over whom she had acquired the most <del>compleat</del> &lt;absolute&gt;
               controul. <ref type="m" target="people.html#PalmerMiss">Miss Palmer</ref> was the one, a more compleat example could never be found of
               that magic which a strong mind exercises over a weak one. The influence which she <del>exercised</del> &lt;possessed&gt; over <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> was equally unbounded &amp; more continual, but otherwise to be
               explained. It was the ascendency of a determined &amp; violent spirit over a gentle &amp; yielding one. There was a difference of
               twelve years between their ages, &amp; the authority which <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> had first
               exerted as an elder sister, she never relaxed. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">My Mother</ref> was one of those few
               persons &lt;(for a few such there are)&gt; who think too humbly of themselves, &#8211; <del>there are such &amp; they are very few</del>.
               Her only fault was that of yielding <del>to</del> submissively to this imperious sister <del>against</del> to the sacrifice of her own
               inclination &amp; judgement, &amp; sense of what was right. She had <del>been bred up in fear &amp; awe</del> &lt;grown up in awe
               &amp; admiration&gt; of her, as one who moved in a superior rank &amp; &lt;with the advantage of a fine form &amp; beautiful
               person&gt; possessed a superior understanding; withal she loved her with a true sisterly affection which nothing could diminish. But
               never did I know one person so entirely subjected to another, &amp; never have I regretted any thing so deeply as that
                  <del>submission</del> &lt;subjection&gt;, which most certainly in its consequence shortened her life</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> had not been disfigured by the small pox the two
               sisters would have strikingly resembled each other except in complection, my mother being remarkably fair. The expression however of
               the &lt;two&gt; countenances was as <del>dif</del> opposite as the features were alike, &amp; the difference in disposition was not
               less marked. Take her for all in all I do not believe that any human being ever brought into the world &amp; carried <del>out</del>
               thro it a larger portion of original goodness than <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my dear Mother</ref>.
                  <del>She</del> Every body who knew her loved her, for she seemed made to be happy herself &#8211; &amp; to make every one happy within her
               little sphere. Her understanding was as good as her heart, &#8211; it is from her that that I have inherited that alertness of mind &amp;
               quickness of apprehension, without which it would have been impossible for me to have undertaken half of what I have performed. God
               never blessed a human creature with a more chearful disposition, a more generous spirit, a sweeter temper, or a tenderer heart. I
               remember that when first I understood what death was, &amp; began to think <del>it</del> of it, the most fearful thought it induced was
               that of losing <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref>, &#8211; <del>&amp;</del> it seemed to me more than I could
               bear, &amp; I used to hope that I might die before her. Nature is merciful to us. We learn gradually that we are to die, &#8211; &lt;a
               knowledge&gt; which if it came suddenly upon us in riper age would be more than the mind could endure: we are gradually prepared for
                  <del>death</del> &lt;our departure&gt; by seeing the objects of our first &amp; deepest affections go before us; &amp; even if no
               keener afflictions are dispensed to wean us from this world, &amp; <del>place</del> &lt;remove&gt; our tenderest thoughts &amp;
               dearest hopes to another, mere age brings with it a weariness of life till death becomes to the old as natural &amp; desirable as sleep
               to a tired child.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">My fathers</ref> house being within ten minutes walk of Terril Street &#8211; (or rather
                  <hi rend="ital">run</hi>, for I usually galloped along the bye ways) few days past on which I did not look in there. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> never entered the house, because there was an enmity between her &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Thomas Southey</ref>; she had given just occasion to it, &#8211; they hated each other
               cordially now &amp; took no pains to conceal it. My visits at home therefore were short, &#8211; &amp; I was seldom allowed to dine, or pass
               the evening there. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother Tom</ref> was at school. &#8211; <del>but when at home</del>
               &lt;&amp;&gt; the difference of age between us at that time made us &lt;not very&gt; <del>un</del>suitable companions when we were
               together. There was not a single boy of my own age, or near it, in any of the few families &lt;with&gt; whom either <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my mother</ref> or Aunt were acquainted, &amp; my <del>solitary</del> &lt;only&gt; friend
               &amp; companion was &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunts</ref> servant boy, <ref type="m" target="people.html#WeeksShadrach">Shadrach Weeks</ref>, her maids brother. Shad, as we called him was just my own age &amp; had
               been taken into her service soon after she settled in Bristol. He was a good natured, active, handy lad, &amp; became very much
               attached to me, &#8211; as I was to him. At this hour if he be living &amp; were to meet me, <del>be it where it might</del>, I am sure he
               would greet me with a hearty shake by the hand, &#8211; &amp; be it where it might &#8211; I hope I should return the &lt;salutation&gt;. We used
               to work together in the garden, play trap in the fields, make kites &amp; fly them, try our hands at carpentry, &#8211; &amp; &#8211; which was the
               greatest of all indulgences go into the country to bring home primrose, violet &amp; cowslip roots, &amp; sometimes to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Vincents Rocks,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A prominent rock formation on the Avon Gorge near Clifton.</note> &#8211;
               or rather the heights about a mile farther down the river, to search for the Bee &amp; Fly Orchis.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The bee orchid and fly orchid are different plants, but they are closely related and sometimes a natural hybrid
                  occurs between the species.</note>
          <del>which some book has</del> Some book had taught me that these rare flowers were to be found there, &amp; I sought for them year
               after year with such persevering <del>intelligence</del> &lt;industry&gt; for the unworthy purpose of keeping them in pots at home &#8211;
               (where they uniformly pined &amp; died) &#8211; that I am afraid botanists who came after me may have looked for them there in vain. Perhaps
               (see the next page)<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s note, to indicate the insertion that follows, &#8216;Perhaps I have &#8230;
                  comparatively insignificant&#8217;, this can be found on the next page of the manuscript, where it is signalled by a note &#8216;this belongs to
                  preceding page&#8217;. We have restored it to its place in his narrative.</note> &lt;Perhaps I have never had a keener enjoyment of
               natural scenery than when wandering about the rocks &amp; woods on the side of the Avon with Shad &amp; our poor spaniel Phillis.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s pet spaniel and the subject of &#8216;On the Death of a Favourite Old Spaniel&#8217;,
                     <title>Poems</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp. 132&#8211;134.</note> Indeed there are few scenes in the island finer of this kind, &amp;
                  <del>xxx</del> no other where merchant vessels of the largest size may be seen sailing between such rocks &amp; woods, &#8211; the
                  <del>scenery</del> &lt;shores&gt; being upon a scale of sufficient magnitude to supply all that the picturesque requires, &amp;
               not upon <del>such a scale</del> &lt;so large a one&gt; as to make the ships appear comparatively insignificant&gt;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Had it not been for this companion, there would have &lt;been&gt; nothing to counteract the effeminating &amp;
               debilitating tendency of the habits to which <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunts</ref> peculiarities subjected
               me. Pricking playbills had been the pastime which she encouraged as long as I could be prevailed on to pursue it, &#8211; &amp; then she
               encouraged &lt;me&gt; to cut paper into fantastic patterns. But I learnt a better use of my hands in <ref type="m" target="people.html#WeeksShadrach">Shad&#8217;s</ref> company, &amp; we became such proficients in carpentry that before I went to
               Westminster, we <del>commenced a work of</del> set about the enterprize of making &amp; fitting up a theatre for puppets. This was an
               arduous &amp; elaborate work, of which I shall have more to say hereafter, as our design extended with our progress. At this time
               little more had been done than <del>what</del> finishing the body of the theatre, where there were pit boxes &amp; gallery &amp; an
               ornamented cieling, <del>the spectator being to look thro a</del> which when it was put on made the whole look on the outside like a
               box of <del>some</del> unaccountable form. The spectator was to look thro a glass behind the gallery, which we intended to have been a
               magnifier till to our great disappointment we were assured at the Opticians no single magnifier would produce any effect at the
               distance which this was required to act, <del>If</del> The scenery &amp; stage contrivances I shall speak of in <del>a subsequ</del>
               due time, for this was an undertaking which called forth all our ingenuity, &amp; continued for several years to occupy me during the
               holydays.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Before I went to Westminster <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother Henry</ref> had been
               taken into <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tylers</ref> household, &#8211; when he was about four years old. A second
               John who was born two years before him died within the year<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Southey (b. 1782).</note> &#8211; I
               know not of what complaint. In 1787 a daughter was born &amp; christened Margaretta<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaretta
                  Southey (1787&#8211;1788).</note> &#8211; I remember her as well as it is possible to remember an infant, &#8211; that is to say without any fixed
               &amp; discriminating remembrance. She was a beautiful creature &amp; I was old enough to feel the greatest solicitude for her recovery
               when I set <del>out</del> off for London early in the spring of 1788. A thoughtless nursemaid<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> had taken her out one day to the most exposed situation within reach, &#8211; what
               is called the Sea-banks,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The sea banks were west of Bristol, where the Froom joined the Avon,
                  and protected Canons&#8217; Marsh from flooding.</note> &#8211; &amp; kept her there unusually long while a severe east wind was blowing. From
               that hour she droopt &#8211; cough &amp; consumption came on in consequence &#8211; I left her miserably &amp; hopelessly ill, &amp; never saw her
               more. This was the first death that I had ever apprehended &amp; dreaded, &amp; it affected me deeply.</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent0">
          <date when="1824-08-27"> Aug. 27. 1824.</date>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>