<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4253</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4253Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4253" type="letter">
        <head>4253. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-09-22">22 September 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 25 SE 25/ 1824<lb />
               Endorsements: 22. Sept<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1824; 22 Sept<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1824<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">If you &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref> can make holiday for a month, let it be at the beginning of October instead of the latter end, &amp; come here, where mountain air will prove the best restoration for both, &amp; where you will do me good by engaging me in a more determined course of exercise than it is possible to take alone. You know that the mail in returning to London arrives between 9 &amp; 10 &#8211; thus saving the second night: which is an advantage to look to when you turn your faces homeward.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I would not have you say anything to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> farther than to let him know that the article<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of John Johnson (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. It was published in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263&#8211;311. Southey had hoped that it might appear in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (January 1824), published 28 August 1824.</note> has not be sent to me for alteration, &amp; that what he has communicated thro you is all that I have heard concerning it. I have no objection to insert some qualifying sentences, tho if the tenour of the paper be understood as it ought, it will appear less to eulogize Hayley<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hayley (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), the poet and biographer.</note> (which as an author I have nowhere done) than to expose the miserable state of national taste in an age when he could flourish as first poet. The real sin of the article is this Grosvenor, &#8211; that it is written in a humane &amp; gentlemanly spirit altogether at variance with <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> own tone of criticism, &amp; with that <del>of his</del> which he has suffered to characterize &amp; disgrace his Review.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a suspicion that <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> apprehends I may withdraw from the Q. when it changes hands (as it is very likely I may do) &amp; therefore has an eye to saving the expence of the last paper, the place of which he has plenty of merrymen to supply at half price. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">The Megistonos</ref> is quite penny-wise &amp; pound-foolish enough for this. If there is an intentional incivility (&amp; of this there is certainly every appearance at this time) it is because he has played the tradesman with me in the most barefaced manner &amp; knows that I am perfectly well aware of it. <hi rend="ital">N&#8217;importe</hi>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the half-bills, &#8211; &amp; for the Shrewsbury commission.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford had passed on &#163;10 to Edward Southey, Southey&#8217;s youngest brother, who was working in the theatre at Shrewsbury.</note> When you write next pray tell me if you paid the 2 &#163; to the subscription for poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#BloomfieldRobert">Bloomfields</ref> family. Having said that this would be done, I should like to know that my word has been performed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wish very much you could come down &#8211; for the sake of a certain medical practitioner,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Dr Daniel Dove, the central character in Southey&#8217;s <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847).</note> with whom you ought to be better acquainted, &amp; to whom I think you would feel disposed to be of use -</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed>
          <lb />
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-09-22">22 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1824</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>