<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3791Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3791Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3791" type="letter">
        <head>3791. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BrowneSarah">Sarah Browne</ref>, <date when="1822-01-31">31 January 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Sarah Browne/ Ludlow<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               MS: Robert H. Taylor Collection, Princeton University Library. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-01-31">31. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1822.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="people.html#BrowneSarah">My dear Miss Sarah</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am much obliged to you for your letter. There is a satisfaction in knowing the whole on these mournful occasions, &amp; there is a comfort also, &#8211; when the circumstances as in this case, are such as to have mitigated, in all that is possible, &#8211; the severest of all afflictions. &#8211; I am old enough never to enter upon a new year without an aweful sense of the uncertainty of life, &#8211; &amp; a fear of what it may take from me &lt;in its course&gt;. Last year deprived me of my poor fellow traveller <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref>, who was half domesticated with us; &#8211; &amp; of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneWade">your excellent father</ref>, for whom I had a most sincere respect &amp; regard, &amp; whose hospitable house I hoped often to have revisited. These are serious losses. At my age new friends are rarely made, &#8211; &amp; there is hardly life enough before me for them to become old ones.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I had had many fears concerning your brother,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Wade Browne (1796&#8211;1851), only son of Wade Browne and later a country gentleman at Monkton Farleigh in Somerset. He had been travelling in the Near East.</note> &#8211; &amp; indeed it appears that he has gone thro many dangers. His last accident however is not perhaps to be accounted a misfortune, if it has saved him from the risque of a voyage in this tempestuous &amp; most perilous season. His travels have been more interesting than if he had pursued the course which he had purposed. They have led him among stranger people, &amp; thro countries which are much less generally known. I shall be glad to hear that you have had good accounts from him &amp; that his health is reestablished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You see I have been making my appearance of late in the newspapers.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In the &#8216;Appendix&#8217; to &#8216;The Two Foscari&#8217;, <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy. Cain, A Mystery</title> (London, 1821), p. 328, Byron had cautioned: &#8216;I am not ignorant of Mr. Southey&#8217;s calumnies on a different occasion, knowing them to be such, which he scattered abroad on his return from Switzerland against me and others.&#8217; Southey had visited Switzerland in his continental tour of May&#8211;August 1817. The &#8216;calumnies&#8217; Byron believed Southey to have later spread were rumours that Byron and Shelley had engaged in a &#8216;League of Incest&#8217; during their residence in Switzerland in 1816. Southey had responded by writing to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776. His letter was published in the <title>Courier</title> on 11 January 1822.</note> There is some satisfaction in knowing that a letter published thro that channel finds its way to all whom one wishes to see it. I am sure you know my temper well enough to believe that it has not been disturbed on this occasion. In fact I never let my family know the provocation which had been given me, till my letter had been written, sent over to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wordsworth</ref> for his inspection &amp; opinion, &amp; transcribed for transmission to the Courier. I hate controversial writing because it is a waste of time, not because it <del>xx</del> can in any way disquiet me. And in this instance <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> impudent abuse would have past without notice from me, if there had not been a direct charge of slander which required a direct denial, &amp; which gave me an opportunity of again holding up <del>him</del> to public view the abominable tendency &amp; purport of his works. This I have reason to believe has not been without some effect. And I have no wish to pursue the subject farther. Indeed he has now thrown off the mask &amp; made so open an avowal of the vilest principles both moral &amp; religious, that the well-meaning part of the world will <del>be</del> need no &lt;farther&gt; warning against those of his works in which the poison is covertly administered.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am as usual closely employed. The first volume of the Peninsular War<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> will appear in the course of this season. And I have also in the press under the title of the Book of the Church,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> a comprehensive view of the history of religion in England, written with the hope of imbuing young minds with those principles which ought to be their best inheritance &amp; their surest supports. I will take care that a copy shall be sent <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Browne</ref> as soon as it is ready, which however will not be in less than three or four months. Meantime I shall hope to hear that time is doing for you &amp; for her what time alone can do, &amp; that your accounts from Wade are what you would wish. &#8211; We shall meet again I trust. Indeed whenever I may be within a long reach of you, I will not let the opportunity pass by.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">My family, thank God, are well, &amp; desire to be most kindly remembered <del>xxxxxxxx</del> to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Browne</ref>, <del>&amp;</del>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneElizabethdau">your sister</ref> &lt;&amp; yourself&gt;. Forget not to add my love to little Mary,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Browne (1810&#8211;1892), younger sister of Sarah Browne. She later married William Farwell (1806&#8211;1876), Rector of St Martin&#8217;s, Liskeard 1830&#8211;1876.</note> &amp; believe me my dear Miss Sarah</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">Yrs with sincere regard</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>