<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4218</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4218Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4218" type="letter">
        <head>4218. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowringJohn">John Bowring</ref>,<date when="1824-07-20"> 20 July 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Bowring Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 5. Jeffrey&#8217;s Square<lb />
               Stamped: [illegible]<lb />
               Postmark: A. NOON 2/ 23 JY/ 1824<lb />
               Endorsements: Robert Southey/ 20 July 1824; Keswick. 20 July 1824/ Rob Southey/ 23/ 30<title> </title>Aug<lb />
               MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-07-20">20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> July. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>  Dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It was not till yester-evening that I received your volume of Spanish poetry,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Bowring, <title>Ancient Poetry and Romances of Spain</title> (1824), no. 338 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; the obliging note which accompanied it. A most interesting volume it is. Among the pieces which were new to me are those of Gil Vicente,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Bowring translated seven short poems by Gil Vicente (c. 1465&#8211;1536), <title>Ancient Poetry and Romances of Spain</title> (London, 1824), pp. 315&#8211;321.</note> &#8211; there is no <del>volume</del> book in the language which I am so desirous of seeing as the Comedias<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Vicente wrote over forty plays. A posthumous edition of his works, <title>Compila&#231;&#227;o de Toda as Obras de Gil Vicente</title> (1562), appeared in five volumes, with the comedies occupying volume two and the farces volume four.</note> of that writer but I never could hear of any other copy than one which was said to be in the Royal Library at Lisbon &amp; now in danger of being devoured by insects in Brazil.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Portuguese Royal Library followed the Court to Rio de Janeiro in 1810&#8211;1811, to escape the French invasion of Portugal.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  You have succeeded most happily with the Coplas of Manrique.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Bowring translated &#8216;Coplas por la Muerte de su Padre&#8217; by Jorge Manrique (c. 1440&#8211;1479) as &#8216;Ode&#8217;, <title>Ancient Poetry and Romances of Spain</title> (London, 1824), pp. 235&#8211;252.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> attempted them once, &amp; gave up the attempt in despair. I thought the attempt so hopeless, that I did not venture to make a trial when verse flowed more fluently from my pen than it would at present. But you have shown us <hi rend="ital">el impossible veneido</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;the impossible task&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The same feeling which made you suppress your intended introduction<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">In his &#8216;Preface&#8217; to <title>Ancient Poetry and Romances of Spain</title> (London, 1824), pp. [v]&#8211;vi, Bowring had confessed he did not have sufficient knowledge to write his planned &#8216;short history of the popular poetry of Spain&#8217;.</note> would deter me from entering upon the subject in the Q Review. There are too many chasms in my knowledge of it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have recorded your confident hope of Spanish regeneration.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Preface&#8217;, <title>Ancient Poetry and Romances of Spain</title> (London, 1824), p. viii: &#8216;my hopes of Spanish regeneration, have not been shaken by the disasters which have filled some minds with disappointment, and others with despair.&#8217;</note> In our estimate of the Spanish character I believe we are well agreed, &amp; in our wishes for the welfare of the Spaniards, their improvement, &amp; their emancipation from political &amp; ecclesiastical despotism. But the late contest<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Spain had been invaded by France in 1823; the liberal regime was overthrown and royal absolutism restored.</note> was between two parties, both in my judgement, so absolutely bad, that I could not throw away a wish on either side. &#8211; Had I been born a Spaniard, I should probably at this hour have been a thorough-paced <hi rend="ital">Liberal</hi>. I am therefore well aware how much may be pleaded in excuse of their errors: but those errors are not the less fatal in their consequences, because so excusable in their cause: &amp; it is my firm persuasion that liberty in the present state of the world has nothing to fear from its enemies, but every thing from its injudicious friends.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So much evil has been done in Spain, that I can see nothing but evil in long prospective there, &amp; know not even what to hope for. But in Portugal it appears to me that there is a plain &amp; easy course to be pursued, by restoring the old Cortes,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The medieval Portuguese Cortes of three estates had ceased to meet after 1698. A liberal revolution in 1820 created a new constitution in 1822, but royal absolutism was restored in 1823.</note> &amp; administering justice regularly. If this were done &amp; provision made for the liberty of the subject by a Habeas Corpus act,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">In England, the Habeas Corpus Act (1673) guaranteed no imprisonment without trial.</note> it is as much as the Nation is ripe for, &amp; might content all <del>whose</del> who desire the reformation of abuses. The Inquisition<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The Portuguese Inquisition was abolished in 1821 by the liberal regime.</note> might be managed as long as any thing were to be apprehended from the Queens party,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte (1775&#8211;1830), Queen Consort of Portugal and one of the key leaders of the absolutist faction in the Portuguese Court.</note> to whom its suppression would afford a popular pretext, &#8211; &amp; in a few years quietly &amp; safely abolished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Should any chance bring you into these parts I should have much pleasure in talking with you upon subjects concerning which we are, I am well assured, perfectly agreed &#8211; as to the end which is to be aimed at, however much we may differ about the means to be pursued. Even upon those, time will bring us nearer, whichever may be wrong.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Believe me Dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">  yrs with sincere good will</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">  Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>