<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3809</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3809Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3809" type="letter">
        <head>3809. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-03-01">1 March 1822.</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 4 MR 4/ 1822<lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.121. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I meant to have written to you concerning <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> when the effect of the medicine had been observed. The first trial is not yet over: &#8211; but I was vexed to learn that after the fourth dose, the lids fell as before. It was perhaps occasioned by a stronger light than usual. &#8211; It did not occur to me to tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref>, in corroboration of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Farres<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Richard Farre (1775&#8211;1862; <title>DNB</title>), distinguished physician at the London Dispensary for Curing Diseases of the Eye and Ear (1806&#8211;1856) and author of works on diseases of the eye.</note> opinion, that she has always been subject to bleeding at the nose, rather in greater quantity than is usual with children; &amp; that for some months past there has been no discharge of this kind. Her eyes are large &amp; globular, &#8211; much the largest of all my children; &amp; her general health much the best, &#8211; that is the least liable to head ache, or derangements of any kind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The pictures must be packed by the framer &amp; sent by wagon.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Portraits of the Southey family made by Edward Nash. Southey had sent them to London for framing by William Haines (1778&#8211;1848, <title>DNB</title>), painter and engraver, whose studio was at 3 Boyle Street, Savile Row.</note> I conclude that you have obtained the miniature from Bowyer.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The artist and publisher Robert Bowyer (1758&#8211;1834) was working on a painting, &#8216;View of the Interior of the House of Lords, during the important investigation of 1820&#8217;, and wished to include Southey in the crowd in the Strangers Gallery in the House of Lords. Southey had loaned him a miniature painted by Edward Nash in 1820 (it is now in the National Portrait Gallery); see Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 4 May 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3681.</note> &#8211; If you have received a book for me (probably in pamphlett size) from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Holmes&#8217;s in Manchester Street,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Holmes, later Hunter (1751&#8211;1827), a wealthy East India merchant of Beoley Hall, Worcestershire, had his London home in Manchester Street, Marylebone. He was the father of Southey&#8217;s correspondent Ann Attersoll. She had presumably arranged that her father should convey a book to Southey on her behalf, since she lived in France.</note> consign it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murraylemagnes</ref> care, for his next parcel, which will probably be sent off when the Review comes out.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 26 (January 1822) was published on 30 March 1822.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am sorry that you are among the sufferers by this financial operation.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The resumption of the link between bullion and the currency in 1819&#8211;1821 had caused a general deflation in prices.</note> I am of that class of <del>pers</del> travellers in this world whom the poet describes as singing in sight of the robber.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Decimus Iunius Iuvenal (late 1st century AD &#8211; early 2nd century AD), <title>Satires</title>, Book 4, Satire 10, line 21: &#8216;The empty-handed traveller will cheerfully sing when confronted by a robber.&#8217;</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">We are not in the best condition just now. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> has a feverish attack upon him, &amp; I have a recurrence of an ugly flatulent affection of the lower intestines which plagued me some weeks ago. I sent rhubarb<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Rhubarb was commonly used as a laxative.</note> upon a mission there last night, &amp; rhubarb performed its part, &#8211; but I fear has not performed a cure, for I still feel a distention &amp; hear sounds which a highlander might mistake for the music of his native land. &#8211; I want a shaking up &amp; shall go to <ref type="m" target="places.html#RydalMount">Rydal</ref> shortly for that purpose, &#8211; early next week if <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> be recovered. If I could afford it I would take a long journey every year, but travelling is doubly expensive to me, as incurring loss <del>at the same</del> &amp; cost at the same time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Some unknown person sent me the New Times with a letter from an equally unknown hand about the Editor of Wat Tyler.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been sent copies of two newspapers which contained anonymous letters about the unauthorised publication of Southey&#8217;s early radical play, <title>Wat Tyler</title>, in 1817. The first letter appeared in <title>The Times</title>, 25 January 1822, and was signed &#8216;THE EDITOR OF WAT TYLER&#8217; and dated 23 January 1822. It claimed to be from one of the people instrumental in arranging for the publication of Southey&#8217;s play in 1817; see Daniel E. White, &#8216;The Case of the Nocturnal Amanuenses: New Evidence in the <title>Wat Tyler</title> Affair&#8217;, <title>Modern Philology</title>, 118/2 (2020), 277&#8211;303. The second letter appeared in the <title>New Times</title>, 12 February 1822, unsigned and dated 6 February 1822. It contained a detailed defence of Southey and, in particular, the change in his political opinions from early radicalism to his own, later, idiosyncratic brand of conservatism.</note> &#8211; Of course I did not for a moment think of noticing the subject, &amp; thereby letting a scoundrel that he could put me to the trouble of <del>writing x xx</del> replying to him</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  They are I believe about to print some of my poems in France, &#8211; &amp; to translate more of them.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Ann Holmes, 6 February 1822, Letter 3795.</note> I believe there is a third translation of Roderic.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The two translations were: Antoine Andr&#233; Brugi&#232;re, Baron de Sorsum, <title>Roderick, le Dernier des Goths</title> (1820), no. 2697 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library; and Pierre Hippolite Amillet de Sagrie (1785&#8211;1830), <title>Roderic, Dernier Roi de Goths</title> (1821), no. 2700 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Am&#233;d&#233;e Pichot (1795&#8211;1877), French novelist, historian and prolific translator, began a translation of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), but abandoned the project once the two other versions in French appeared.</note> But if I have any favour in that country, it will not be of long continuance, inasmuch as the Buonapartists will find my Hist. of the War<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832), which was relentlessly hostile to the invasion of Spain ordered in 1808 by Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815).</note> rather unpalatable &#8211; 536 pages are printed. I am now working upon some very interesting papers of <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew Dalrymples</ref> &#8211; which have given me more insight into the affairs of Andalusia than all my other documents. And I have got much useful information in correspondence from <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">Bart. Frere</ref>, from himself, &amp; from Gen. Whittingham<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant General Sir Samuel Ford Whittingham (1772&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>), British soldier who served with Spanish forces in the Peninsular War 1808&#8211;1813.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has had the nurse in his house this month, &amp; the <ref type="m" target="people.html#RumneyJohn">Doctor</ref> (both from Brough) more than a fortnight.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey already had seven children. An eighth, Sophia Jane Southey (1822&#8211;1859), was born on 2 March 1822.</note> His hooping cough has reached <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> but I hope we may escape it.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Love to all &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-03-01">1 March. 1822.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1">Go to the <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Exchequer</ref> for whatever I owe you on the Frame &#8211; or any other score</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>