<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">TO IMMAGINATION (1800)</title>
        <title type="main">Collected Poems of Robert Bloomfield</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author><name>Bloomfield, Robert</name></author>
        <editor>Tim Fulford</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor,</resp>
          <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor,</resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado, Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only
            in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
            republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic Circles.
            Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
            <address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine><addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine><addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine></address></p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list></p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
            Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">editions.2019.bloomfield_poems.11ToImmagination</idno>
        <idno type="resource">bloomfield_poems</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">TO IMMAGINATION (1800)</title>
            <author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Bloomfield</surname></persName></author>
            <ptr target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_poems/editions.2019.bloomfield_poems.11ToImmagination.html"/>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Collected Poems of Robert Bloomfield</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2019-04-28">April 28, 2019</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
<tagsDecl>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent1">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent2">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent3">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent4">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent5">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent6">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent7">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent8">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent9">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent10">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="center">text-align: center;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="left">text-align: left;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="right">text-align: right;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="small">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="large">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="largest">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="smallest">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="titlem">font-style: italic;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="titlej">font-style: italic;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="figure">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="sup">vertical-align: super;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="sub">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>       </tagsDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
            http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2019-04-15" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list>
          <item>Initial transforms to HTML</item>
        </list></change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="poetry">
        <head rend="noCount" rendition="#center">TO IMMAGINATION (1800)</head>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">Editorial Introduction</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Bloomfield composed ‘To Immagination’ in May 1800 on the evidence of the surviving manuscript and of his correspondence. He
          was in the first flush of success as a published poet and was revisiting the village in which he had spent his boyhood and in which he had
          set <title>The Farmer’s Boy</title>—<ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/places.html#Honington">Honington</ref>. ‘To Immagination’ was, in this context,
          something of an oblique tribute to the poetic imagination that had conjured up a Suffolk country boyhood from the distance of London’s
          rookeries and garrets. It was his first major composition after the appearance of <title>The Farmer’s Boy</title>, an ambitious piece that
          was a considerable departure in style and subject-matter—an ode in the poetic territory marked out by poets renowned for their sublimity,
          such as Mark Akenside, Edward Young, William Collins and Erasmus Darwin, whose Popean couplets and machinery it echoed. </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Problems began when Bloomfield showed the manuscript to his patron <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#LofftCapel">Capel Lofft</ref>. Lofft did not want to prevent him reaching for a so-called higher genre—the ode. As a Foxite radical, a Whig of advanced liberal
          views, Lofft regarded it as part of his duty to represent the interests of the labouring classes. He wanted to show that the common people,
          if properly encouraged, could produce as sophisticated forms of poetic expression as their social superiors. The issue was the nature of
          this encouragement: Lofft wanted both to edit Bloomfield’s verse to fit his own notions of taste and to gain the credit for having
          shepherded the prodigy into print (see Introductions to <title>The Farmer’s Boy </title>and to <title>Rural Tales</title>). Now, Lofft added
          to the needy grandstanding in which he had indulged in <title>The Farmer’s Boy</title> a well-meaning but coercive rewriting of Bloomfield’s
          new manuscript. The resultant tensions are evident in Bloomfield’s letters, the first reference coming in early 1801, when Bloomfield wrote
          to his brother <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> to say that ‘Mr. L —is deafening me with solicitations to
          print “Imagination,” which I had rejected; he has set it to rights, and certainly made it Better by adding here and there a connective line
          as he calls them; he has written out the whole piece for me, and says I shall do an injury to him, to the public, to poetry, and to myself,
          if I do not publish it, there is a sufficient volume without it and I have not yet determined.’ (<ref
            target="https://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/letterEEd.25.48.html">Letter 48</ref>). By the end of the year, Bloomfield
          had decided not to print the poem in his forthcoming collection <title>Rural Tales </title>and, in the wake of the increasingly bitter
          dispute with Lofft triggered by the publisher wishing to omit Lofft’s embarrassing prefatory remarks in the new edition of <title>The
            Farmer’s Boy</title>, was restoring his manuscripts to their pristine state. He sent George a manuscript of ‘To Immagination’, noting ‘I
          have copied it, and copied what Mr L would have added and withdrawn. I think you will not wonder at my rejecting it’ (30 November 1801, <ref
            target="https://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/letterEEd.25.69.html">Letter 69</ref>) </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Bloomfield’s sensitivity over his ‘Immagination’ manuscript was clearly greater than over <title>The Farmer’s Boy</title>
          which, after all, he had initially been content to publish with Lofft’s revisions. This stemmed not just from accumulated resentment over
          Lofft’s behaviour but also from the fact that the new poem was a departure from the Georgic into a loftier, more gentlemanly, voice.
          Bloomfield was aware that his social claim upon that voice was slight and was acutely sensitive to the interfering of his patron who,
          precisely because this poem was written in a gentlemanly voice, felt himself better qualified to modify it. Bloomfield had not the authority
          over this poetic voice to insist on his own words, whereas he had (albeit at a price) over his poems that dealt with rural labour and
          village tales. The outcome was that, after Lofft’s revisions, well-meaning though they were, Bloomfield felt alienated from his own language
          of the imagination. It fell dead in his hands and became a poem he could neither publish nor polish, written in a style he would never again
          attempt. He vented his feelings in a letter of April 1804 to <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#BrayleyEdward">Edward Brayley</ref>: ‘Three
          years past I had written a long address “to Imagination,” in what I calld Blank Verse, but my friend Mr Lofft thinking it deficient, was for
          adding and explaining, and in effect perverting my meaning till I finish’d the contest by refusing to print the piece, and by ultimately
          destroying it’ (13 April 1804, <ref target="https://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/letterEEd.25.120.html">Letter
          120</ref>).</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Fortunately, Bloomfield did not destroy all the manuscripts of the poem. The manuscript, which is kept in the British
          Library (Add. MS 30809), and which we publish here, is decidedly Augustan in manner, while suggesting a relationship between nature and the
          poet’s creativity that is akin to <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth’s</ref>. In contrast to ‘Tintern Abbey’,
          imagination, stimulated by the view of nature, is personified but not self-consciously related to the poet. Instead, the personified faculty
          takes a topographic flight, a departure indeed for Bloomfield, formerly bard of a single Suffolk village, and a token of his desire to
          escape the labourer-poet tag (since labourers’ views were held to be limited to the local range within which their experience was
          confined). It is as if he deliberately set out to elaborate upon Dr Johnson’s maxim that the poet should ‘Let Observation with extensive
          view / Survey mankind from China to Peru’<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Vanity of Human Wishes</title>, lines
            1–2.</note>—since in rhyming couplets and eighteenth-century diction he takes a shifting but apparently omniscient view of nature and
          humanity in South America (principally) and Africa. It is a less egotistical response to nature than Wordsworth’s, but nevertheless derives
          from it a comparable emotional and moral pressure. Bloomfield, learning from Pope’s <title>Windsor Forest </title>and Darwin’s
            <title>Botanic Garden</title>, disengages the poetic imagination from the personality of the poet and from his own limited viewpoint,
          allowing him vicariously a greater scope of comment. The voice allows the narrator to seem to rise above his own personal interest and
          moralise: this is not the egotistical sublime but a new version of the eighteenth-century poetic persona of narratorial independence of
          self. As such, it puts the Wordsworthian—the Romantic—imagination in a wider cultural context showing that imagination could be addressed
          via a renewal of an older Augustan discourse. In this, Bloomfield learned from Akenside, Young, Darwin and Joel Barlow, whose 1787
            <title>Vision of Columbus </title>surveys the American continent from the skies as Bloomfield does in ‘To Immagination’. Bloomfield’s poem
          contains verbal echoes of all these poets and it is intriguing to think that he may have derived his narrative device and main topic—the
          aerial flight over the Atlantic and South America—from one of the earliest American poets. </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Pliable enough to allow heartfelt sympathy with exploited labourers (another sign of the respect for the realities of hard
          bodily labour that is present in many of Bloomfield’s poems) as well as generalising moral commentary about slavery, ‘To Immagination’
          reveals, despite Bloomfield’s fragile confidence in it, that it was possible to fuse Romantic-era aesthetics with Augustan style. It helps
          us see why Wordsworth’s autobiographical verse looked singular and perverse to critics as different as Jeffrey and Byron. The visionary
          revelation of inwardness was not the only discourse created, and seen to be created, by the Romantic-era imagination.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">As a poem that modifies eighteenth-century poetic language from a labouring-class perspective, ‘To Immagination’ has much to
          show us about that language’s continued potential as a sensitive medium for the expression of moral and emotional truth. It also reveals
          some of the limitations of that language: Bloomfield’s is certainly not a romantic-era poem on imagination that succeeds where others fail
          in displaying its own imbrication in social and political forces. Bloomfield does not—and he’s like <ref type="m"
            target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#ClareJohn">Clare</ref> in this—offer a communitarian model of imagination arising from a world of shared labour to
          counter the individual transcendentalism of Wordsworthian Romanticism. His imagination is disembodied—from himself and from others—a moral
          discourse that is divorced from the speaker’s position and from the context from which it arises. This might be judged, though Bloomfield
          never explicitly acknowledged as much, a sign of the alienation of the poet from a socially-produced poetic voice that he could call his own
          or call the voice of his class. Instead, he produced a simulacrum of poetic discourses previously produced by Augustan gentlemen for whom
          adopting an omniscient objectified voice was an unproblematic sign of cultural power—Young’s <title>Night Thoughts</title>, Akenside’s
            <title>Pleasures of the Imagination</title>, Darwin’s <title>Botanic Garden. </title>It is not surprising, then that ‘To Immagination’ has
          hesitancies and failings which are symptoms of the author’s unease with the position of authority in which his narratorial position places
          him. The fact that Bloomfield left it unpublished, meanwhile, is telling evidence of the crisis in poet-patron relationships caused by
          class-difference as it operated in poetic language. Equally, the fact that it languished in manuscript for so long suggests the continuing
          class bias and social exclusivity that attended the critical adoption of the Romantic imagination as a criterion of worth.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
