<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
              <title level="a">3859. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 26 June 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
                <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
                
                <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp> Editor</resp>
                    <name />
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2024-04-08</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address>
                    </p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="edition">3859Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
                <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                      <title level="a" type="main">3859. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 26 June 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
                        <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3859Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m" />
                        <title level="s" />
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags" />
                    <term subtype="tags" />
                    <term subtype="tags" />
                    <term subtype="tags" />
                    <term subtype="tags" />
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <name />
                <date />
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3859" type="letter">
        <head>3859. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-06-26">26 June 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 29 JU 29/ 1822<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> will be much obliged to you if you will purchase for her, &amp; to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> if he will take charge of, two articles which it will neither incommode you to buy, nor him to put in his trunk.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">First a drawing book of coloured paper, &#8211; that sort of tint which is given by tobacco water:<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A preparation made by boiling tobacco in water; it was a popular insecticide.</note> the size about 9 &#189; inches long 6 &#189; wide. Secondly a bottle of a certain preparation of lamp black<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Carbon black, made from the incomplete burning of products such as coal tar. It was widely used as a black pigment.</note> or ivory black (I know not which) used for painting screens &amp; such things &amp; sold at Fielders N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 2 Greek Street, Soho.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Fielder (c. 1793&#8211;1854), maker of picture and looking glass frames.</note> She has excellent use of her fingers. If <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">poor Nash</ref> had been living, it would have delighted him to see the extraordinary progress she has made.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have had a letter of thanks from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref>. One has the painful feeling of not knowing how much is to be believed of what he says, &amp; how much to be allowed for theatrical effect. What is the real state of his health?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I am nearly recovered, thank God, after an attack of an ugly nature. I have always apprehended that the violent catarrh which for the last twenty years has regularly seized me with the first warm weather would at last effect a lodgement in my chest, &amp; this year for the first time it has given serious indication of such a tendency. After trying squills<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A preparation known as squills, made from the squill, or sea onion, and used as an expectorant.</note> in vain, &amp; ipecacuanha lozenges,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Ipecacuanha, extracted from a South American plant, was used as an emetic and purgative.</note> I have nearly removed it by paregoric, taking at the same time calomel &amp; dandelion to counteract the effect which the smallest possible quantity of laudanum produces upon my liver.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Paregoric was a traditional pain relieving medicine, containing opium dissolved in alcohol, known as laudanum. Since this operated as a cough suppressant it would have given Southey relief from his hay fever. However, it also had a number of side-effects, including constipation, for which Southey took the purgative calomel and the laxative dandelion.</note> To day for the first time I have thought myself sufficiently free from any feverish symptom to venture upon wine.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Miss Wilbrahams marriage<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Laetitia Wilbraham (1799&#8211;1874), Tom Southey&#8217;s lodger. She married Joseph Harrison Fryer (1777&#8211;1855) of Whitley House, Northumberland. Fryer was a surveyor, geologist and mining engineer who spent part of each year at Keswick. At this time he was renting Ormathwaite, a large house about a mile and a quarter from Keswick.</note> took place last week. Her brother<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Randle Wilbraham (1801&#8211;1887). Notably, Miss Wilbraham was not given away by her father, Randle Wilbraham (1773&#8211;1861), landowner, of Rode Hall, Cheshire.</note> came to give her away, &amp; returned immediately. The history of the courtship, with the talk, &amp; correspondence, &amp; broils that it has occasioned, would make a volume, in which neither <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> nor <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheySarah">his wife</ref> would appear to any advantage, &#8211; both having acted very intemperately, &amp; very foolishly. He has the vice of tetchiness in a very great degree, &amp; his wife in a greater, if that be possible. For me, I always bear in mind one of the first maxims which I teach my children. &#8211; The least that is said. Is the soonest mended.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I look shortly to hear from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> saying when we may expect to see him, &#8211; about Monday week I think.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802&#8211;1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August&#8211;2 September 1822.</note> Your visit I suppose will be in September, when London is emptiest. Tell me how you all are, for it seems a long while since I have heard of you.</p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
           RS.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-06-26">26 June. 1822</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>