<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3890. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 31 August 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3890Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3890. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 31 August 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3890Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3890" type="letter">
        <head>3890. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1822-08-31">31 August 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: 10 o&#8217;Clock/ SP 3/ 1822 FN<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 221. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 325&#8211;327.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-08-31">31 Aug. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I am now after a succession of visitors left awhile to myself, &#8211; a good deal the better for the course of exercise into which I have been led, &amp; somewhat the worse for the large subtraction these made from time which would otherwise have been bestowed upon my ways &amp; means. By the time this evil is remedied, the good I suspect will be undone, &#8211; good however it is as long as it lasts. &#8211; My farthest stretch from home has been to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Boltons, on Windermere,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Storrs Hall on Windermere, Lake District home of John Bolton (1756&#8211;1837; <title>DNB</title>), Liverpool merchant and leading supporter of Canning as MP for that city.</note> whither I went to meet <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref>, &amp; where I found <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> also. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> has since been here, &#8211; &amp; upon looking over these Sp. &amp; P. books pronounced them a better collection than any which he had seen, except his own, &#8211; much better than Murdochs.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Murdoch (1758&#8211;1846), Scottish merchant and senior partner in the firm of Newton, Gordon and Murdoch, specialising in importing fortified wine from Madeira.</note> If the channel which you are now trying should prove a good one, there are several books which I shall be desirous of obtaining, &#8211; among these the Agiologio Lusitano of Cardoso,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Jorge Cardoso (1606&#8211;1669) and Antonio Caetano de Sousa (1674&#8211;1759), <title>Agiologio Lusitano dos Sanctos, e Varoens Illustres em Virtude do Reino de Portugal e suas Conquistas </title>(1652&#8211;1774).</note> &#8211; the Sermoens do P. Antonio das Chagas,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio da Fonseca Soares (1631&#8211;1682), a soldier who became a Franciscan friar under the name Antonio das Chagas. Southey later acquired a seven-volume edition of his <title>Obras</title> (1763), no. 3257 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; &amp; the Obras de S. Teresa,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;Works&#8217; of St Teresa of Avila (1515&#8211;1582), which had appeared in numerous editions since the early seventeenth century. Robert Gooch had recently sent Southey a life of St Teresa; see Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 14 July 1822, Letter 3869.</note> &#8211; of which Mal-lavado<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Ill-washed&#8217;; clearly a pun at the expense of a bookseller known to Southey and Hill in Portugal.</note> used to have copies in abundance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Among the many reasons which make me regret that you would never be persuaded to travel thus far, one is that I should so have liked to show you the progress which is made in the history of Portugal.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;; this work was never completed.</note> It is in more forwardness than any work that I ever yet committed to the Press, &amp; as soon as the Pen. War is finished,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> to the printer it will go. I have a continuous narrative from the C. Henrique down to the accession of Sebastian.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">From the time of the foundation of Portugal by Henry (1066&#8211;1112; Count of Portugal 1096&#8211;1112) to that of Sebastian (1554&#8211;1578; King of Portugal 1557&#8211;1578).</note> A great deal is to be added in transcribing it from materials good part of which are ready. The Cardinals reign<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry (1512&#8211;1580; King of Portugal 1578&#8211;1580). He was a Cardinal and succeeded his great-nephew, Sebastian, on that king&#8217;s early death. Henry was the last member of the House of Aviz.</note> &amp; the subsequent events till Philip obtained possession of the Kingdom<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">After Henry&#8217;s death, the succession to the throne was disputed, but it was eventually gained by his nearest legitimate heir, Philip II (1527&#8211;1598; King of Spain 1556&#8211;1598). This signalled the end of Portugal&#8217;s independence until a successful rebellion in 1640.</note> are written &amp; large collections made for the <del>xxxxx</del> following period, &#8211; you would be well pleased to see the order in which all this is, &#8211; &amp; the battle array of my shelves, where so many of your old acquaintance are stationed in good company.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> enjoyed his visit greatly.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802&#8211;1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August&#8211;2 September 1822.</note> &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">Dr Bell</ref> is here, &#8211; he rode off this morning with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref>, &amp; is just returned after a circuit of one &amp; twenty miles with her, &#8211; part of it the wildest road in this country. He went as usual without a servant, they had to lead their horses themselves, &amp; he opens the gate with all the alacrity of a boy. So youthful an old man I never before saw.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have not heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> concerning the Yankee books<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">These books were a present from George Ticknor.</note> which I desired him to enquire about. Randolph of Roanoak<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">John Randolph (1773&#8211;1833), a Virginia tobacco planter and Representative or Senator almost continuously for his State between 1799 and 1833.</note> has been here. But I had the vexation of missing <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Telford</ref>, who arrived with Sir Henry Parnell<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Henry Parnell, 4th Baronet (1776&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>), later 1st Baron Congleton. Parnell was an Irish landowner and Whig politician; MP for Queen&#8217;s County 1806&#8211;1832 and Dundee 1833&#8211;1841. He was later Secretary at War 1831&#8211;1832, Paymaster of the Forces 1835&#8211;1836 and Paymaster-General 1836&#8211;1841. His main interest was financial reform, but he was also a close collaborator of Telford&#8217;s and the author of <title>A Treatise on Roads, wherein the Principles on which Roads should be made are explained by the Plans, Specifications and Contracts made use of by Thomas Telford, Esq.</title> (1833).</note> while I was at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Boltons. This was a great mortification inasmuch I owe <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Telford</ref> every kind of friendly attention, &amp; like him heartily.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">There is only one proof more of the first vol. to reach me, containing some additions which I have grafted in their proper place by cancelling two leaves: the new matter is very curious, &amp; was drawn from <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew Dalrymples</ref> papers.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The Battle of Bail&#233;n, 16&#8211;19 July1808, was the first great success of Spanish forces in the Peninsular War. Southey dealt with the matter in his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 382&#8211;386. At pp. 389&#8211;390, Southey inserted some material concerning Dalrymple&#8217;s role in the attempts of Spanish commanders to change the terms of surrender of the French army.</note> Whether <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> will delay the publication till the winter I cannot tell. I <del>shall</del> have made a memorandum concerning M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Withers copy<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Harris Bigg-Wither (1781&#8211;1833), a Hampshire landowner and brother-in-law of Herbert Hill.</note> &amp; it will be duly sent you. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> may take the presentation copy to Court if he thinks proper; &amp; I should think it &lt;be&gt; worth <del>it</del> &lt;<del>xxx</del>&gt; his while to show himself upon the occasion. I wait only for some promised papers from <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">B. Frere</ref> to begin with the second volume, &#8211; that is, with the printing of it, &#8211; a large portion of the volume will be transferred from the Ed. An: Register<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Much of the text for Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) was drawn from his earlier writings in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> (1808&#8211;1811).</note> without much alteration.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When you are prowling at the booksellers, &#8211; or looking over their catalogues, lay hold of Nalson&#8217;s Collection<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">John Nalson (1637&#8211;1686; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Impartial Collection of the Great Affairs of State, from the Beginning of the Scotch Rebellion in the Year MDCXXXIX to the Murther of King Charles</title> (1682&#8211;1683), no. 1924 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> from the beginning of the Rebellion if you see it, as I think you may, at a low price. There are two volumes, small folio. It is a Collection made by Charles 2<hi rend="sup">ds</hi>
          <note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles II (1630&#8211;1685; King of Great Britain 1660&#8211;1685; <title>DNB</title>).</note> command, to counteract the <del>xx</del> impression which Rushworth<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">John Rushworth (1612&#8211;1690; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Historical Collections of Private Passages of State</title> (1659&#8211;1721).</note> by his insidious omissions intended to produce &amp; has in fact produced. Nalsons is much better as far as it goes. I have been working upon a copy which I borrowed from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lowther</ref>. the book is probably now at a low price, but in all likelihood it will be very considerably raised by what I shall one day say of it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">A Baltimore review<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> of the Life of Wesley<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of Wesley, and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> has just been sent me, wherein it is affirmed that beyond all doubt I constructed it upon the plan of &#8211; Homers Iliad. And this is said seriously. <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoodenoughEdmund">Goodenough</ref> it is said will be made Dean of Ch. Ch. whenever they can promote the present Dean<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Henry Hall (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Dean of Christ Church, Oxford 1809&#8211;1824, Dean of Durham 1824&#8211;1827. Goodenough did not succeed Hall at Christ Church.</note> &#8211; who can only thus be got rid off: &#8211; so that in his case promotion is to be the reward of misconduct. I wish Westminster were in the hands of a man who would look into the mischievous system pursued in College<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">At Westminster School, 40 boys were selected to become King&#8217;s Scholars and lived thereafter in their own accommodation in College. They had considerable advantages, including the automatic right to proceed to a Closed Scholarship at either Trinity College, Cambridge, or Christ Church, Oxford. Selection was through a grueling oral examination called &#8216;The Challenge&#8217;, but there was little in the way of further examination. Edward Hill was about to try to become a King&#8217;s Scholar.</note> &#8211; where the boys thro the slavery which they endure at first &amp; the tyranny which they exercise afterwards rather lose ground than gain it. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">Dr Wordsworth</ref> told me he was equally surprized at the examination of the juniors (those just elected) &amp; of the seniors, &#8211; the former appearing to such advantage, the latter so much below what they ought to have been. I explained to him the cause. A good Master might easily remedy it. &#8211; Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the boys &#8211;</p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
           RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>