<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3899. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 30 September 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3899Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3899. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 30 September 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3899Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3899" type="letter">
        <head>3899. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-09-30">30 September 1822</date>
          </head><p>Endorsement: 30 Sept<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1822./ Horsemangander<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 2p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-09-30">30 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I found your letter to day with its inclosure, on our return from <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Sirius</ref>, being my third ascent this season. If tomorrow be favourable (which the barometer seems to indicate it will not) we are to breakfast with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> &amp; ascend Causey Pike, &#8211; &amp; on Wednesday <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Sirius</ref> takes his departure for London to our sorrow. I shall then be left to myself, &amp; to my needful occupations, which have been very long interrupted. &#8211; Great bodily exercise is incompatible with much mental exertion, &amp; I am so circumstanced as to stand in need of both. I must compromise the matter thro the winter as well as I can</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Have you seen a series of Costumes etched by Lewis as Illustrations of <ref type="m" target="people.html#DibdinThomasFrognall">Dibdins</ref> Tour.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1818, the painter George Robert Lewis (1782&#8211;1871, <title>DNB</title>) had accompanied Thomas Frognall Dibdin on a continental journey. This was documented in Dibdin&#8217;s, <title>Bibliographical, Antiquarian and Picturesque Tour in France and Germany</title> (1821), no. 830 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. On the same journey Lewis made drawings which were etched and published as a series of <title>Groups illustrating the Physiognomy, Manners, and Character of the People of France and Germany</title>, issued in parts and completed in 1823, no. 1718 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. The intention was that these could be inserted as plates into Dibdin&#8217;s <title>Tour</title>. Plate 25 was titled &#8216;Peasants of the Environs of Paris&#8217;.</note> If you have not, look for them &amp; in the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> print, you will find as perfect a likeness as ever was produced of &#8211; John Cockbaine.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cockbaine (1786&#8211;1873), Keswick draper and tailor.</note> Lewis avers it to be a faithful portrait, observing at the same time that few artists could have resisted the temptation of taking it.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">George Robert Lewis, <title>Groups illustrating the Physiognomy, Manners, and Character of the People of France and Germany</title> (London, 1823), p. 7: &#8216;there are few indeed, who, once having seen the original, could have resisted the temptation to preserve his representation unaltered.&#8217;</note> It appears therefore that Nature did not break the mould in which the Perfect Taylor was made. She was so pleased with it, that she made two <del>pers</del> who could only be paralleled by each other, &#8211; &amp; gave one to England another to France.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Alas Johnny is growing old &amp; is no longer what he was in his prime. As a Taylor he must always remain unequalled, &#8211; the fair ideal of that character: but in ugliness he is rivalled by Wells Fisher the nephew &amp; successor of poor old John Fisher:<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Fisher (dates unknown) was the Keswick barber who also rented a room to visitors to the Lakes. Wells Fisher (dates unknown), his nephew, was described as a &#8216;jeweller, dealer and chapman&#8217; when he went bankrupt in 1829.</note> a curious personage in his way, to whom you must be introduced.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>I have</del> Will you tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> or <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> that I have not had the last number of the QR,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (April 1822), published 4 July 1822.</note> &#8211; so that it may come with the forthcoming one<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (July 1822), published 23 October 1822.</note> in the next parcel. I shall write to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">G.</ref> with the next portion of MSS.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a further section of Southey&#8217;s review of Henri Gr&#233;goire (1750&#8211;1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu&#8217;a l&#8217;Epoque Actuelle, sont N&#233;es, se sont Modifi&#233;es, se sont &#201;teintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), published 15 February 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Meantime tell him that I have not given up James 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> but have been preparing for him.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write an article on the reign of James VI and I (1567&#8211;1625; King of Great Britain 1603&#8211;1625; <title>DNB</title>) for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Sirius</ref> will tell you of our goings on, &#8211; of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">your godson</ref>, &#8211; of our Saddleback expedition &amp; the descent of that mountain by <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs Coleridge</ref> &amp; how <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref> horsemanganders <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs Coleridge</ref>. I wish you were here to see it. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Your godson</ref> has determined upon being an Archbishop, &amp; I have instructed him that when he has attained the object of his ambitions, he may play at drafts, backgammon, &amp; chess but that he must never play the fool. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cupn</ref> who knows that his father means to play the fool as long as he lives, does not relish the prohibition, but <del>x</del> is somewhat reconciled to it by hearing that he may play the fool with his <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cupns</ref> if he has any. &#8211; He sees that my bells are going all day long.</p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
           RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>