<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3923. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 25 November 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3923Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3923. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 25 November 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3923Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3923" type="letter">
        <head>3923. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-11-25">25 November 1822</date>
          </head><p>MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.126. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 347&#8211;349.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-11-25">25. Nov. 1822.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not recollect whether I have given you joy of your son<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Herbert Southey, Jnr (1822&#8211;1829) was born on 6 November 1822.</note> or not; &#8211; for without talking extravagantly or madly upon the subject, where there is a fair prospect that a child will be fairly set forward in the world, its birth is a subject for congratulation. Besides it is a joyful change in a house when all is &#8220;as well as can be expected.&#8221;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The letter for <ref type="m" target="people.html#KnightonSirWilliam">Sir William</ref> comes herewith.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to William Knighton, 25 November 1822, Letter 3922. This asked Knighton to present a copy of the first volume of the <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) to George IV, to whom it was dedicated.</note> Will you tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> where a copy can be directed to Haygarth,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Haygarth (1784&#8211;1825), a poet and travel writer, son of the physician John Haygarth (1740&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>). Haygarth was a friend of Henry Herbert Southey and had provided Southey with a letter describing the campaign in northern Portugal in 1809; see Southey to Herbert Hill, 31 January 1816, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Letter 2705.</note> to whom one is due for some materials which he communicated.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">If <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref> would make me a present of the publications of the Record Committee<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Commissioners on the Public Records of the Kingdom had been periodically appointed since 1800. They had supported plans to publish series such as <title>Statutes of the Realm</title> (1810&#8211;1825).</note> they would be well bestowed. <del>&amp;</del> I want too many costly books for my historical pursuits, &amp; these are among them. Wherever original documents are within my reach I go to them; &amp; it is surprizing how much I find there which has been overlooked. My gleanings are often worth more than the harvest of those who have been before me. Something of this you will see in the B of the Church,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> at which I have been chiefly employed since your departure.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You must know &lt;more&gt; concerning the QR.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Gifford, the editor of the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, was ill and there was much speculation over who would succeed him; John Taylor Coleridge did so briefly.</note> at this time than I do. A note from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> some fortnight ago let me know that he was well disposed toward <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref>, &amp; waited till he could talk with <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> upon the subject. &#8211; &amp; I have heard nothing since from any quarter. If he understood his own interest, there could not be a moments hesitation. What with <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> indifference in all matters of taste &#8211; (where if he had any leaning it was to the wrong side) with his admission of mischievous articles, such as those relating to America, &amp; of the sermons of the Dean of Westminster<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Ireland (1761&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>), Dean of Westminster 1816&#8211;1842. He was a close friend of William Gifford and had been a regular contributor to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> (to whom I ascribe the <hi rend="ital">discourse</hi> on <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> in the last number)<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of Byron&#8217;s <title>Marino Faliero, Doge of Venice. An Historical Tragedy, in Five Acts. With Notes. The Prophecy of Dante, a Poem</title> (1821) and <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy, Cain, A Mystery</title> (1821), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (July 1822), 476&#8211;524, published 23 October 1822, was by Reginald Heber, not John Ireland. It was not the swingeing condemnation that Southey would have liked.</note> &amp; what with the disgraceful temper in which some of his own papers were written, <del>&amp; som</del> the Review might easily decline as rapidly as it had risen.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">There is a passage from my tender epistle quoted in the last number.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Palgrave&#8217;s review of the first volume of Lewis Cottingham (1787&#8211;1847), <title>Plans, Elevations, Sections, Details and Views of the Magnificent Chapel of King Henry VII at Westminster Abbey Church, with a History of its Foundation &amp;c</title> (1822&#8211;1829), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (July 1822), 308&#8211;336 (esp. 310&#8211;311), published 23 October 1822, quoting Southey&#8217;s <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M. P.</title> (London, 1817), pp. 37&#8211;41. Southey suggests that this passage had originated in one censored by Gifford from Southey&#8217;s article, &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 225&#8211;278, published 11 February 1817.</note> It is curious that that very passage should have been originally written for the review, &amp; struck out of it by <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">the Editor</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will tell you another anecdote. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> has lately edited Sir Charles Hanbury Williams&#8217;s poems.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Works of the Right Hon. Sir Chas Hanbury Williams</title> (1822). Charles Hanbury Williams (1708&#8211;1759; <title>DNB</title>) was a diplomat and writer. Southey had declined to edit his poems as Williams was &#8216;not quite so decent as he should be&#8217;; see Robert Southey to Charles Danvers, 23 March 1802, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 664.</note> They were put into my hands for that purpose in 1802; &#8211; &amp; I refused to have any part in bringing them out because of their profligacy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Your precepts have been observed as regularly as a series of dreadfully tempestuous weather would let me; &#8211; at some expence of time, but with less effort, as it becomes a habit. I was over the Dod<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">A small fell north west of Keswick.</note> some ten days ago with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref>. The boat is now laid upon the island, not having been used since your departure, &#8211; for there literally has not been one day pleasant enough for going on the water.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I should be very glad to hear of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridges</ref> accession, which if <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> continues to be incapacitated, cannot be deferred much longer. &#8211; To day I have a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> &#8211; dated Falmouth, &#8211; - it contains a promise of strong beer, &#8211; for which you know I have a weakness. Never was man more mistaken in his prognosis than <ref type="m" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">Chauncy Townsends</ref> father<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Hare Townsend (1765&#8211;1827), a wealthy landowner and radical. For his misapprehension of Southey&#8217;s habits, see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 4 November 1818, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Letter 3204.</note> when he supposed me to be a water drinker.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a proper taste for all pleasant liquors, in their place &amp; season, &#8211; from bottled twopenny<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Twopenny&#8217; was a pale ale, originally costing 2<title>d</title>. per pint.</note> in the heat of summer, up to the purest whiskey &#8220;unexcised by Kings.&#8221;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Hawkins Browne (1705&#8211;1760; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Pipe of Tobacco: in Imitation of Six Several Authors</title> (London, 1736), p. 20: &#8216;Imitation V&#8217;, line 20.</note> &#8211; But Rhenish wine<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Sweet white wine from the Rhineland.</note> is best, &amp; so Pindar<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Pindar (c. 522&#8211;c. 443 BC), <title>Olympian</title> 1, line 1, &#8216;Water is best&#8217;.</note> would have said if he had ever tasted it.</p>
        <p>
          Our love to all &#8211; God bless you<lb/>
           RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>