<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3931. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 13 December 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3931Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3931. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 13 December 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3931Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3931" type="letter">
        <head>3931. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-12-13">13 December 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer./ Westminster<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 16 DE 16/ 1822<lb />
               Endorsement: 13. Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <del>1823</del>. 1822/ Copies of Penins. War<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-12-13">13 Dec. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Thank you for the half notes, &amp; for your story of the price of a Black Captain,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Grosvenor Bedford&#8217;s letter to Southey of 11 December 1822 had contained halves of banknotes to the value of &#163;40. Bedford told Southey that this was the amount that Quashy Boland (dates unknown), a black man who served as a Captain in the British Army during the American Revolutionary wars of 1775&#8211;1783, had been sold for by a commissary. Bedford had become friendly with Boland, who regularly visited the Exchequer, where Bedford worked, to pick up instalments of the pension of &#163;27 p.a. that Boland had been awarded in 1783. Boland was last recorded as being in receipt of his pension in 1813 and may have died around that time.</note> &#8211; which is a good story. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> I believe, would have been glad to have <del>xxxx</del> sold &lt;some&gt; of his officers cheaper &amp; would have thought himself well rid of them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I ordered the copy for G. Hawker,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Major-General Samuel Hawker (1763&#8211;1838), who had served in the Peninsular War between 1808 and 1811 as commander of the 14th Light Dragoons. His sketches were used in <title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey&#8217;s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &amp;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823). These could be inserted into the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> somewhat with prospective view to some statements promised, &#8211; (I think) in one of your letters, relating to Soults flight.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicolas Jean-de-Dieu Soult (1769&#8211;1851), Marshal of the French Army. He was in command of the French forces in northern Portugal in 1809 when they were defeated and forced to withdraw to Galicia. Hawker had taken part in many of the key actions in this conflict.</note> It has been a rule with me to present copies in quarters where materials have been supplied to me; &#8211; this I have done with other books where the expence fell in proportion on myself, &#8211; in this case it will fall upon the work; &#8211; &amp; my bargain having been made ten years ago is so improvident a one,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray offered Southey one thousand guineas for his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, in two volumes (rather than the three it eventually comprised), Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 23 July 1813, <title>Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2284.</note> that I have no reason to be scrupulous in laying the charge of a few copies on the proprietors. &#8211; With regard to this, the destination cannot be changed, if it comes, as I conclude it will, with the Generals name written therein. &#8211; You shall introduce me to the brother,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Hawker (c. 1773&#8211;1833), Rector of Woodchester 1809&#8211;1833.</note> &amp; I will find an opportunity of sending him some other book.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">My own copies arrived yesterday.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Copies of the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> One of my own works when it first reaches me is as agreable to me as a new plaything to a child, &#8211; &amp; I am not yet tired of looking at it. It has prevented me from sending the Ode<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Scotland, an Ode, Written after the King&#8217;s Visit to that Country. By Robert Southey, Esq. Poet Laureat&#8217;, <title>The Bijou: Or Annual of Literature and the Arts</title> (London, 1828), pp. 81&#8211;88. This was Southey&#8217;s New Year&#8217;s ode for 1823 in fulfilment of his obligations as Poet Laureate.</note> by this post, the said Ode being finished, &amp; half transcribed. I have now to put together pieces of it for the <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShieldWilliam">Musdoc</ref>, &#8211; &amp; tomorrow I shall dispatch it to your highness. When it has lain by for a few weeks, &amp; received such alterations here &amp; there as I shall then see how to make, it bids fair to please me tolerably well. The subject is <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the Kings</ref> visit to Scotland:<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">George IV paid a state visit to Scotland 15&#8211;29 August 1822.</note> &#8211; or rather it starts with that, &#8211; a sort of parallel to the last years Ode.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Ireland&#8217;, <title>Sir Thomas More: or. Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title>, 2 vols (London, 1829), I, pp. [295]&#8211;302. The poem was Southey&#8217;s new year&#8217;s ode for 1822, as Poet Laureate and was inspired by George IV&#8217;s state visit to Ireland 12 August&#8211;3 September 1821.</note> It has cost me a weeks work, which I should not grudge, if it had not taken me from the B of the Church,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> now in good progress.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">We are going on well, thank God. It would amuse you to hear how gravely <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">his Very Reverence, the Rural Dean</ref> talks of his primacy in <hi rend="ital">rus</hi>,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;in the country&#8217;; part of an in-joke about the supposed clerical ambitions of Southey&#8217;s infant son.</note> &#8211; &amp; how exceedingly pleased he is with his destination.</p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
          RS.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">You would render <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my eldest daughter</ref> a good service, if &#8211; when you pass a shop where such things are sold, &#8211; you would purchase for her some ultramarine<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">A deep blue pigment used in painting.</note> &amp; send it in a frank</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> I cannot guess what there was in the tenour of my last, which you do not like.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>