<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3935. Robert Southey to [Sara Coleridge] [fragment], [c. mid-December 1822]</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3935Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3935. Robert Southey to [Sara Coleridge] [fragment], [c. mid-December 1822]</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3935Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3935" type="letter">
        <head>3935. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref>] [fragment], <date when="1822-12">[c. mid-December 1822]</date>
          </head><p>MS: British Library, Add MS 47891. ALS; 1p.<lb />
               Unpublished.<lb />
               Dating note: This dates from Sara Coleridge and her daughter&#8217;s visit to the south of England, 1822&#8211;1823. They had left Keswick by 8 November; see Robert Southey to Nicholas Lightfoot, 8&#8211;12 November 1822 (Letter 3915). They spent about a month staying with Elizabeth Evans near Derby. This letter probably dates from mid-December 1822, when they were in transit between Derby and the Clarksons&#8217; home, Playford Hall, Suffolk; see Southey to John May, 5 December 1822 (Letter 3927). On their way to the latter, they paid a brief visit to Cambridge, where Derwent Coleridge was a student.<lb />
               Note on MS: This fragmentary letter (or at least the surviving version of it) was possibly not sent to Sara Coleridge but instead dispatched at an unknown date to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, a connoisseur of Mrs Coleridge&#8217;s linguistic practice, as an example of her lingo grande. This is suggested by the fact that the manuscript survives as part of a short run of letters to Bedford and &#8211; unusually &#8211; opens (top of fol. 1r) with an address to him: &#8216;And so-oh-oh/ Dar Miscumber Bedfordiddlededford/ I sub&lt;cum&gt;scribe myself &#8211; your sincumcere friendiddledend/ Robcumbert Southeydiddledouthey/ Student of the Lingo Grande, Graduate in Butlerology, Professor of/ the Science of Noncumsensediddledence, of sneezing, &amp; of vocal music &#8211;/ P.L. &amp; LLD.&#8217; This nearly duplicates the closing salutation of Southey to Bedford, 24 December 1822 (Letter 3940), perhaps indicating that this fragment was sent to Bedford shortly after this date.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Venerable</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Odiddledowloo, why is it that neither you nor <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">that poor lassitudinarian thing</ref> will write to the &lt;Umaining&gt; porkaboarobumbels of this family? <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Scampalum</ref>
          <del>xxxxxxxx</del> looks every day for a letter, &amp; every day it gives her a pange to be disappointed. We thought you would not stay more than a jiffump among the Chappets &lt;at Cambridge&gt; giddytonians as they are, &amp; shall think you can hardly be indiscrukt enough to be dumdawdling, among them, for you are not as improvidentipur. Yet had you reached Playford,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Playford Hall, home of Thomas Clarkson.</note> we think you would shartainly have written. This we have conclucted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I write in your own lingo-grande, <del>because</del> &lt;because then&gt; if you should happen to leave <del>the</del> your &lt;portfolio&gt; <del>xxxx</del> about &amp; any improprieter or indelicardium should be roken &amp; dabdobbering among your papers, the signifumpification of this will not be undercamestood, at least not in a momper.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Scampalum</ref> will have told you most of what has happened, since you &amp;
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">the lassitudinarian</ref> left your two holes at the table here. 
          The journey we hope will have given both your constitutions a jerk. You must stulch when the weather is not going to ramp &amp;
          tear so as to make slatching disagreeavobus, &#8211; &amp; when the rampasity of the day prevents any other exercise then I advise you to be horsemangandered,
          which is better than stroming or meandering up &amp; down the room <del>I practice what I preach</del> It will never do for you to be a slouwdowdlecum, a slowdonothinger. 
          For you to keep in health the nocksen must vork as well as the towsalowset the foottells-tottels &amp; legrums as well as in <del>chaprat</del> under futoarum</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Dont cody me now for this good advice &#8211; nor detest me, nor play the very dunder, forshammenum if you do.
          Dont tear goarum (why should poor gravum suffer such toru?) &#8211; dont go tarradiddle.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>