<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3937. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 20 December 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3937Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3937. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 20 December 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3937Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3937" type="letter">
        <head>3937. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-12-20">20 December 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 23 DE 23/ 1822<lb />
               Endorsements: 20. Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1822./ King&#8217;s Let on the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Vol of Hist<hi rend="sup">y</hi> of the War.; 20. Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1822<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 129&#8211;132 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have no written form of admission to the office of Laureate, &amp; very well remember being surprized at the thoroughly unceremonious manner of my induction. At the day &amp; hour appointed (a very memorable one, <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the Prince Regent</ref> going to Parl. just after the news of the Battle of Leipsic had been made public -)<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The Prince Regent opened Parliament on 4 November 1813. The same day, news of the Battle of Leipzig (16&#8211;19 October 1813), in which the French army was decisively defeated by a coalition comprised of Russian, Prussian, Austrian and Swedish forces, was published in an extraordinary edition of the <title>London Gazette</title>.</note> I went to a little low dark room in the purlieus of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> James&#8217;s, where a fat old Gentleman Usher<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Hale Young Wortham (1747&#8211;1820), First Gentleman Usher and Daily Waiter on His Majesty.</note> in full buckle administered an oath to me, in presence of a solitary clerk, &#8211; &amp; that was all, payment of fees excepted, which was not made at the time. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, I recollect, was amused at the description which I sent him of this ceremony,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Walter Scott, 5 November 1813, <title>Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2323.</note> &amp; said it was a judgement upon me for inserting among the Notes to the Cid a reflection of Sir John Finetts upon &#8220;the superstition of a Gentleman-Usher.&#8221;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Scott to Robert Southey, 13 November 1813, John Lockhart, <title>Memoirs of the Life of Sir Walter Scott</title>, 3 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), II, p. 46: &#8216;You see what it is to laugh at the superstitions of a gentleman-usher, as I think you do somewhere.&#8217; Scott was referring to Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid, from the Spanish</title> (London, 1808), p. 427, quoting Sir John Finett (1571&#8211;1641; <title>DNB</title>) in James Howell (c. 1594&#8211;1666; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Finetti Philoxenis: Some Choice Observations of Sir John Finett, Knight and Master of the Ceremonies to the Two Last King, Touching the Reception and Precedence, the Treatment and Audience, the Punctilios and Contests of Forren Ambassadors in England</title> (London, 1656), p. 35; no. 1035 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; Whether any entry was made, &amp; whether I signed my name, I cannot call to mind, it being nine years ago. Gazetted however I was, &amp; P.L. I have been from that time. But <del>what</del> how can this concern you?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You know the proverb that he who is not handsome at 20, wise at 40 &amp; rich at 50, will never be rich, wise, or handsome. Quoad<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;with respect to&#8217;.</note> my handsomeness &#8211; handsome is as handsome does, &#8211; &amp; whatever I may have <del>done</del> &lt;been&gt;, they have made a pretty figure of me in magazines. There is a portrait <del>of me</del> in a German edition of my smaller poems<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Works of Robert Southey</title> (1820); no. 2696 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This was a cheap, two-volume edition of Southey&#8217;s shorter poems, published by August Schumann (1773&#8211;1826), of Zwickau, Saxony. The engraving of Southey was by Christian Gottfried Zschoch (1775&#8211;1833).</note> which it will be a treat for you to see, &#8211; you will never again complain of your ugly likeness below stairs. Concerning the second part of the adage, &#8211; certain it is that about the age of forty, my views upon all important subjects were matured, &amp; settled, so that I am not conscious of their having undergone any change since, except in <del>such</del> slight modifications upon inferior points. But for the last part of the story, rich at fifty I certainly shall not be, nor in the way to be so.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">When I deliberated &#8211; if deliberating it can be called &#8211; about the QR &#8211; the single motive on one side was the desire of having an adequate &amp; sure income, &#8211; which I have never had since I discontinued the Ed. An. Register &#8211; <del>when</del> because it ceased to pay me for my work.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was considering whether he would accept the editorship of the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, if it was offered to him (it was not) when William Gifford retired. Between 1810&#8211;1813 Southey had been paid &#163;400 p.a. for writing the historical section of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> My establishment requires 600 &#163; a year, exclusive of other calls. The average produce of my account with <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> is about 200 &#163; what I derive from the Exchequer you know,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s pension and his salary as Poet Laureate were both subject to income tax, reducing them to a combined net income of about &#163;234 p.a.</note> the rest must come from the grey goose quill: &amp; the proceeds of a new book have hitherto pretty generally been anticipated, they may float me for a second year perhaps &#8211; Roderick<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> did for three years &#8211; with the help of the Pilgrimage,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> &#8211; then the tide ebbs, &amp; so I go on. At present it is neap tide<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The tide when there is least difference between low and high tide, i.e. Southey&#8217;s earnings from the volumes he published with Longman were moderate but not disastrous.</note> in <ref type="m" target="places.html#PaternosterRow">the Row</ref>. My Tale of Paraguay<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> when I can finish it, will about make it high water.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is all very well, while I am well: &#8211; but if any of the countless ills which flesh is heir to should affect my health, eyesight, &#8211; or faculties, I should instantly be thrown into a state in which my income would only amount to about half my expenditure. Concerning death I have no anxieties &#8211; with a life insurance for 4000 &#163; (which by this time is worth not less than 5) &#8211; &amp; with my books, copy-rights &amp; papers &#8211; there would be full 10,000 &#163; for my family possibly (with good management on the part of my Executors &#8211; &amp; good fortune in putting together <del>xx</del> my Reliquiae) &#8211; a good deal more. On that score I am easy: &#8211; &amp; not uneasy upon any other. But I have said all this to explain why it was that I could even ask myself the question whether it would become me to take the QR. into my own hands. I am quite satisfied that it would not: but that it behoves me to go on, as I have always hitherto done, hopefully contentedly, &amp; thankfully, &#8211; taking no farther care for the morrow, than that of endeavoring always to be able to say &#8211; sufficient for the day hath been the work thereof</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have made <del>as</del> &lt;a&gt; valiant <del>xx</del> resolution that the produce of this History<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> shall not be touched for current expences, &#8211; looking to it always as the work wherewith I was to begin to make myself independent. The B. of the Church<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> I must eat. But I will not eat these peninsular quartos. The Whigs may nibble at them if they please.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> advertisement at the beginning of the QR. explains what the B.C. is.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray&#8217;s advertisement comprised part of the introduction to <title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, pp. 1&#8211;2, in which Southey promised &#8216;a brief but comprehensive record&#8217; of the Church of England.</note> I could find no other title which would not have been objectionable, &#8211; a Church History it is not, because it skims only the cream of the events, &#8211; a sketch it is not, because the details are full where fullness is required, &amp; in other parts [MS missing] philosophical view is substituted where the narrative would have been less impressive. The present title has the advantage of making people ask what it means, &#8211; which is an advantage at starting; &#8211; when the book is once known the meaning [MS missing] the title signifies as little as the etymology of your Christian name or mine. It merely designates <del>that</del> the book. But my main reason for choosing it, was an intention <del>then</del> (not yet wholly laid aside) of bringing out a parallel work to be called the Book of the Constitution.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">This was not written.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just received an official communication from <ref type="m" target="people.html#KnightonSirWilliam">Sir Wm Knighton</ref> which tho it be marked <hi rend="ital">Private</hi>, there can be no unfitness in my communicating to you. It is in these words, &#8216;I am commanded by <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the K.</ref> to convey to you the estimation in which <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">H.M.</ref> holds your distinguished talents, &amp; the usefulness &amp; importance of your literary labours. &#8211; I am farther commanded to add that <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">H.M.</ref> receives with great satisfaction the first vol. of your valuable work on the late Peninsular War.&#8221; &#8211; this is the letter, &#8211; &amp; at the head of it is written &#8211; entirely approved &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">GR.</ref> &#8211; Is not this very gracious? &#8211; &amp; how many persons are there whom such a communication would make quite happy. For <del>xxyx plxxx xxx</del> myself I am sorry there are so few persons connected with me who can be gratified by it, &amp; wish <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my good Aunt Mary</ref> had been here to have enjoyed it. I may deposit <del>xx</del> it with my letters affiliatory from the Cymmrodorion<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been elected a member of the Honourable Society of Cymmrodorion in 1821.</note> &amp;c &#8211; &amp; my letter of thanks from the Ty,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">A letter of thanks from the Admiralty, which Southey often referred to as &#8216;Admiral Ty&#8217;; see Southey to Tom Southey, 23&#8211;24 June 1808, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Three</title>, Letter 1472. Southey had sent the Admiralty an account of his experiments in throwing bottles containing letters into the sea and trying to record where they washed up. He received &#8216;the thanks of the [Admiralty] Lords for the communication&#8217;; see Southey to Herbert Hill, 3 August 1810, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 1798.</note> &#8211; which <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">the Master of the Rolls</ref> remembers, &#8211; &amp; I might write upon the packet that contains them <hi rend="ital">Vanitas Vanitatum, omnia Vanitas</hi>.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Quotation from the Latin version of <title>Ecclesiastes</title> 1: 2: &#8216;Vanity of vanities, all is vanity&#8217;.</note> &#8211; Not that I would be understood as affecting in the slightest degree to undervalue what I am continually labouring to deserve.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I <hi rend="ital">must</hi> finish the B.C. before I can leave home, &amp; <hi rend="ital">must</hi> moreover write an article for the QR, to cover the expences of my absence, &amp; carry on the war at home. My journies tax me doubly, in as much as they increase my ways for the whole time of absence, &amp; suspend the <del>larger part</del> &lt;main&gt; source of my means. March is the time to which I look on, &#8211; it may perhaps be April.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not leave Keswick until 3 November 1823; <title>The Book of the Church</title> was still unfinished.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">You must quarrel with nothing in Welsh but the orthography, &#8211; the word which offends your eye is 
          euphonious enough for an Ionian-Greek. it is pronounced Cumrodorion. Do you know that the Welsh has a greater proportion of vowels than any other language &#8211;
          ancient or modern?<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">The widely accepted view (in English) had been that Welsh abounded with consonants. &#8216;Meirion&#8217; 
            [William Owen Pugh] had argued that, on the contrary, Welsh had a very high percentage of vowels to consonants, Meirion to the Editor of the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>,
            1 January 1799, <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 7 (January 1799), 5&#8211;6.</note> &#8211; God bless you RS.</p>
        <p>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-12-20">20 Dec. 1822.</date>
          </dateline>
        </p>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">Pray convey my thanks to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Evans<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">James Evans (dates unknown), Secretary of the Honourable Society of Cymmrodorion until 1824.</note> for the Welsh transactions.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Transactions of the Cymmrodorion, or Metropolitan Cambrian Institution</title> (1822), no. 2829 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> I may spare myself the trouble of writing on this occasion as the book came with no written memoranda. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">His Rt Honour</ref> was about to send me <del>xx</del> a copy. I shall expect the cambro Briton from him,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>The Cambro-Briton</title> (1819&#8211;1822), a journal on Welsh history, no. 527 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; 
            shall set about an ode to the praise &amp; glory of the Ancient Britons<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write this ode.</note> &#8211; 
            when I have looked it over. What is better I may very likely put together a good paper for the QR.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Pray &#8230; 
              QR.&#8217; &#8211; Southey&#8217;s postscript was written at the top of fol. 1r of his letter. He did not write anything on the ancient Britons for the
              <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>