<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3941. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 29 December 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3941Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3941. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 29 December 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3941Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3941" type="letter">
        <head>3941. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-12-29">29 December 1822</date>
          </head><p>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-12-29">29 Dec. 1822.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I have made search &amp; can find no such paper as you think you recollect. I believe there never was <del>such</del> one: &amp; am confirmed in this belief by what I find in a letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> written the morning after my installation<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Edith Southey, 5 November 1813, <title>Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2324.</note> &#8211; to wit, &#8211; &#8220;a good old Gentleman Usher by name Wortham, or Worthan,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Hale Young Wortham (1747&#8211;1820), First Gentleman Usher and Daily Waiter on His Majesty.</note> a worthy sort of a fat old man in a wig &amp; a bag, &amp; a snuff-coloured full dress with cut steel buttons &amp; a sword administered an oath, in which I swore to reveal all treasons which might come to my knowledge, &amp; to obey the Lord Chamberlain upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the Kings</ref> service, &amp; in his stead the vice chamberlain.&#8221;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Charles Seymour-Conway (1777&#8211;1842; DNB), who, as heir to the Marquessate of Hertford, held the courtesy title of Lord Yarmouth. He was a close friend of the Prince Regent, who appointed him to the post of Vice-Chamberlain in 1812. The Lord Chamberlain was his father, the Marquess of Hertford.</note> &#8211; Hence I infer that I had seen the said Gentleman Usher write his name at the office. But if any paper had been given me, it would have been deposited either with the letter from which this extract is taken, or with my appointments to the Spanish Academy &amp;c.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been made a Member of the Royal Spanish Academy in 1814.</note> &#8211; I am therefore as certain as I well can be that that no such is in existence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Miss Walker<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Anne Walker (1781&#8211;1854) of Gilgarran House, sister and heir of William Walker (d. 1819). In 1825 she married Captain James Robertson, of the Royal Navy (d. 1858), who took the name Robertson-Walker.</note> reports flatteringly of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">the rural Deans</ref> hair. His very Reverence has not inherited my curls. His hair has only a slight turn after it has been wetted, &#8211; but there is nothing episcopal in its appearance even then. He is however in all respects a worthy godson, &amp; makes a very favourable impression upon all who are acquainted with him: I wish you could hear some of our conversations concerning the primacy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have had a very civil letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew Dalrymple</ref>, &#8211; in which he disclaims all share in the censure at p. 583.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, p. 583, in which Southey had condemned British officers for socialising with their French counterparts after the Convention of Cintra (1808). Given the war crimes that the French had perpetrated in Portugal, this was to Southey &#8216;a moral fault, as well as a political error.&#8217;</note> I am glad of this disclaimer, as it shows that the justice of the censure is felt. There is no person whom, judging from his official correspondence, I am led to respect more highly that Sir Hew. One of the few facts which I deemed it expedient to withhold from this generation is one which would have shewn how entirely &amp; scandalously he was left to act without instructions in the first communications with the Spaniards. Lord Castlereagh<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Stewart, Viscount Castelreagh (1769&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>), Secretary of State for War and the Colonies 1807&#8211;1809, Foreign Secretary and Leader of the House of Commons 1812&#8211;1822.</note> only acknowledged two of his dispatches out of 37, &#8211; 34 of which related to the affairs of Spain, the most important subject at that time, which could be brought before his department.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A Major Tomkinson<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">William Tomkinson (1790&#8211;1872) joined the 16th Light Dragoons as a cornet in 1808 and served in Spain 1809&#8211;1813. He was a Captain at Waterloo (1815). His diary was later published as <title>The Diary of a Cavalry Officer in the Peninsular and Waterloo Campaign, 1809&#8211;1815</title> (1894).</note> of the Light Dragoons, who served with <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">the Duke</ref> from 1809 to the end of the war, &amp; was in every action with him (except Talavera)<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The Battle of Talavera, 27&#8211;28 July 1809, in which Anglo-Spanish forces compelled the French army to withdraw. Tomkinson had been seriously wounded at the Battle of the Douro on 11 May 1809 and so missed Talavera.</note> has written (upon reading my first volume) to offer me the use of his journal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I send you an epistle, which if I had foreseen its length, should have been made into two. It will amuse you if you are in the humour for it.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey to [Grosvenor Charles Bedford], 24 December 1822, Letter 3940.</note>
        </p>
        <p>
          A merry Christmas to you, &amp; a happy new year &#8211;<lb/>
          God bless you<lb/>
          RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>