<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3976. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 7 March 1823</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3976Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3976. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 7 March 1823</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3976Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3976" type="letter">
        <head>3976. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1823-03-07">7 March 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey<lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Postmarks: E/ 10 MR 10/ 1823; [partial] 10 / MR/ 18; [partial] NOO<lb />
Seal: red wax; design illegible <lb />
MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 228. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 242&#8211;243.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Your Gazetas are a lucky purchase for me. My series <hi rend="ital">de Gobierno</hi> is compleat from the beginning of 1810. I have in all 21 volumes, including a good many provincial Gazettes.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey eventually acquired a collection of 24 volumes of Spanish <title>Gazetas</title>, 1808&#8211;1813, no. 3472 in the sale catalogue of his library. These included <title>Gazetas</title> &#8216;de Gobierno&#8217; (&#8216;of the Government&#8217;) and from the Juntas of Seville and Valencia.</note> But I have not a single Spanish newspaper for 1808, &amp; only a broken set for 1809, consisting of such as were sent over to my poor correspondent <ref type="m" target="people.html#AbellaManuel">Abella</ref> when he was attached to the embassy here. After his return he supplied <del>xx</del> me very punctually: &amp; thro his means the Junta of Aragon had promised me a compleat series of theirs (which was the best conducted of the whole) &#8211; but Ferdinand returned<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813&#8211;1833). He restored royal absolutism in 1814.</note> &amp; there was an end of the Junta, &amp; of my resources in that quarter</p>
        <p rend="indent1">In 1809, there is a gap in my collection from Apr. 24 &#8211; to July 20, &#8211; besides many smaller chasms. Nothing therefore can be better timed than your supply. And at my leisure I shall be most glad to improve the first volume,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of <title>Southey&#8217;s History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &#8211; throughout which I felt the want of such materials grievously.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have Valentyn<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Fran&#231;ois Valentijn (1666&#8211;1727), <title>Oud en Niew Oost-Indien</title> (1724&#8211;1726), no. 2892 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; a set which <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> spared me. &#163;3 was its price, &amp; it wanted a leaf, &amp; one or two prints. I believe its price at Brussels is about 80 francs: fine books are surprizingly cheap there. So much so, that if I lived in the south, I should pay my Verbeyst<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-Baptiste Ver Beyst (1770&#8211;1849), the Brussels bookseller, whom Southey had visited in 1815 and 1817.</note> a visit every two or three years, for the purpose of overhauling his stores.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> tells me the sale has answered his best expectations, what the extent of those expectations may have been, of course, he has not told me, but they are not likely to have been moderate ones. I may reasonably hope that it will prepare a sale <del>from my</del> for my history of Portugal,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;. This work was never finished.</note> as the general opinion in its favour seems to be much more than I myself, <del>xxx xxx</del>, who never court opinion, had looked for.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The election at Westminster is easily comprehended: &amp; is altogether distinct from the ordinary business of the school.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hill was about to take &#8216;The Challenge&#8217; at Westminster School. If successful, he would become a King&#8217;s Scholar. This had considerable advantages, including the right to proceed to a Closed Scholarship at either Trinity College, Cambridge, or Christ Church, Oxford.</note> The examination is wholly between the boys themselves, the master sitting as judge. It begins with the two lowest candidates, the <del>xxx</del> lower of these sets the other an epigram in the Anthology, out of a certain number appointed for that challenge, &amp; asks him as many questions upon any two words of that epigram as his Help<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Each boy taking &#8216;The Challenge&#8217; was entitled to be assisted by an existing King&#8217;s Scholar, who was known as his &#8216;Help&#8217;.</note> can cram him with. As soon as he has corrected him thrice he takes his place, &amp; is in his turn tasked in the same manner, he whose store of questions is first exhausted, retires the loser, &amp; then the next boy in the ascending list comes out to be in like manner challenged by the winner. In the Latin challenge<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;The Challenge&#8217; included Greek, as well as Latin, grammar.</note> only three questions are asked by each: this therefore is in comparison a mere trifle. The examination is so long &amp; so strict, that tho the preparation is altogether <del>x</del> an affair of cramming, the boys are excellently grounded by going thro it;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A challenge between two boys could last the best part of a day; the whole period of the examination lasted six to eight weeks.</note> but I am sorry to say the system of the College<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">There were forty King&#8217;s Scholars in all. They lived in a separate building called &#8216;College&#8217;, wore distinctive clothing and were taught together.</note> is such, that at the examination when they are to be elected off to Oxford &amp; Cambridge, the seniors are found as much below what they ought to be, as the newly elected juniors are above the usual standard of their age. So <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wordsworth</ref> told me last year, &amp; I explained to him that the cause lay in the system of tyranny which <del>px</del> is suffered there. The truth is that the economy of the College requires a total change. And if any friend of mine should ever be Dean of Westminster,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Westminster Abbey and Westminster School were part of the same foundation and their buildings were next to each other. The Dean of the Abbey played an important role in the life of the School.</note> I will endeavor to convince him of it</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am sorry to hear of your colds &#8211; &amp; hope <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillAlfred">Alfreds</ref> may not turn out to be the whooping cough. &#8211; I am always better pleased to be at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>, than in the noise &amp; dirt &amp; smoke of London, &amp; in the wearying round of excitement which I am there involved in. &#8211; Thus far we have got thro this long winter well. Yesterday was a delicious day, &#8211; &amp; now the ground is again covered with snow! &#8211; Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref>
        </p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
          RS.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-03-07">7 March. 1823.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>