<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3984. Robert Southey to Edward Hawke Locker, 21 March 1823</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3984Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3984. Robert Southey to Edward Hawke Locker, 21 March 1823</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3984Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3984" type="letter">
        <head>3984. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LockerEdwardHawke">Edward Hawke Locker</ref>, <date when="1823-03-21">21 March 1823</date>
          </head><p>MS: Huntington Library, LR 325. ALS; 5p.<lb />
Previously published: W. A. Speck, &#8216;Robert Southey&#8217;s Letters to Edward Hawke Locker&#8217;, <title>Huntington Library Quarterly</title>, 62.1&#8211;2 (1999), 159&#8211;161 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-03-21">21 March. 1823.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I am glad to hear of the proposed edition of the Plain Englishman.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Locker&#8217;s journal <title>The Plain Englishman</title> (1820&#8211;1823) had folded, but he was planning a miscellany of its best contents, <title>The Englishman&#8217;s Library: Comprising a Series of Historical, Biographical and National Information</title> (1824).</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My daughter</ref> is now transcribing for it the pieces which will accompany this letter.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s New Year&#8217;s odes for January 1820 and January 1821, &#8216;The Warning Voice: Ode I and Ode II&#8217; appeared in <title>The Englishman&#8217;s Library: Comprising a Series of Historical, Biographical and National Information</title> (London, 1824), pp. 381&#8211;389.</note> Should they require more room than it is convenient to afford them, lay them aside without scruple, &amp; I will send you something shorter. They are two of my annual Odes, written at the close of the years in which they are respectively dated. My successor may perhaps find the benefit of my withholding these pieces from the newspapers at the<del>x</del> time they are written. On my part they have been regularly prepared, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShieldWilliam">my musical colleague</ref> has as regularly composed them (that is such portions of them as have been thought suitable) &#8211; but since I held the office the performance has never been called for, &amp; there is good hope therefore that it may fall into disuse, &#8211; being a custom more honoured in the breach than in the observance.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">As Poet Laureate, Southey was required to write an annual New Year&#8217;s ode; but the performance of musical settings of these odes at Court had been suspended since 1810.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Thank you for the American Sermons.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Jonathan Boucher (1738&#8211;1804; <title>DNB</title>) was an Anglican clergyman and close friend of George Washington (1732&#8211;1799; President of the United States 1789&#8211;1797), who left America in 1775 because he opposed the American Revolution. His <title>A View of the Causes and Consequences of the American Revolution</title> (1797) comprised annotated versions of thirteen sermons that Boucher preached in America 1763&#8211;1775. Locker had married, in 1815, <ref type="m" target="people.html#LockerEleanor">Eleanor Locker</ref>, daughter of Jonathan Boucher.</note> That I have read them you will perceive by an incidental reference in the next number of the Q.R. if it contains my paper upon the rise &amp; progress of Infidelity:<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Henri Gr&#233;goire, &#8216;Histoire de la Th&#233;ophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu&#8217;&#224; son Extinction&#8217;, part of Gr&#233;goire&#8217;s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu&#8217;a l&#8217;Epoque Actuelle, sont N&#233;es, se sont Modifi&#233;es, se sont &#201;teintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55&#8211;171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493&#8211;536 (519), published 8 July 1823. </note> &#8211; &amp; that they will be of great advantage to me will be seen as soon as I can prepare a paper upon the condition &amp; prospects of the United States, for which Dwights Travels<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752&#8211;1817), <title>Travels in New-England and New-York</title> (1821&#8211;1822), no. 881 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey reviewed Dwight&#8217;s book in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (October 1823), 1&#8211;40, published 17 April 1824.</note> afford good materials &amp; opportunity. The discourses are as able as I have expected to find them; they confirm the opinions which I had formed upon the subject, &amp; have added largely to the information upon which those opinions were founded.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> has not written to me since his recovery, &#8211; but I learn from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> that he means to die in harness. The last number<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), published 15 February 1823.</note> was a great deal better than its predecessor, which was disgraced by that wretched half-apology for <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref>, &#8211; &amp; a defence of Shakespeare &amp; Revealed Religion against him!!<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray was the publisher of both Byron and the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. The review of Byron&#8217;s <title>Marino Faliero, Doge of Venice. An Historical Tragedy, in Five Acts. With Notes. The Prophecy of Dante, a Poem</title> (1821) and <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy, Cain, A Mystery</title> (1821) by Reginald Heber, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (July 1822), 476&#8211;524, published 23 October 1822, was not the swingeing condemnation that Southey would have liked. Heber&#8217;s article (pp. 479&#8211;487) defended English drama (not just Shakespeare) against Byron&#8217;s strictures; and Heber defended orthodox Christianity against the arguments put forward by the characters in Byron&#8217;s <title>Cain</title>, especially on the issue of the compatibility of a supreme deity with the existence of evil (pp. 514&#8211;524).</note> Neither <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> nor <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> are aware how strong a feeling of disapprobation toward their journal has been excited by this, &amp; other sins, both of omission &amp; commission with which it is justly to be charged. There is a strong disposition to start a rival journal,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The proposal came from Joseph Mawman (1759&#8211;1827), a bookseller and author from York, who became a well-known London publisher. His firm was based in the City of London, rather than the West End, like Murray. The proposal for a rival journal to the <title>Quarterly Review</title> did not materialise.</note> &#8211; &amp; <del>offers</del> &lt;overtures&gt; which few men in my circumstances would have rejected were held out to me to take the management, upon terms much more liberal than it had ever been my fortune to meet with, in all my numerous transactions with the booksellers. But tho the love of money is the last sin which besets us, it will never be my besetting sin. The great historical works which I have in hand, or in preparation, &amp; for which I have been preparing since the year 1800,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Primarily Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never completed.</note> will be sufficient to occupy the remainder of my life, even should it be extended to old age; &amp; I will not <del>sacrifice</del> allot more time, than is absolutely necessary, for employments of temporary interest, &amp; for the sake of immediate emolument. &#8211; I had rather see the QR. reformed, than rivalled; it possesses greater influence than a competitor could obtain till after many years. What is published there is sure to be read by the very persons whom it is most desirable to influence upon great public questions. Of all men whom I know <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> would make the best editor, for principles, talents &amp; strength of character. Into his hands I think it must devolve.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I shall take the affairs of Spain for my next paper, if the subject is not pre occupied, &amp; Leucadio Doblado (<ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco White</ref>) for my text.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Blanco White&#8217;s <title>Letters from Spain by Don Leucadio Doblado</title> (1822). Southey did not write on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> Are you acquainted with him, &amp; his history? He is a man for whom I have the highest respect, &#8211; for tho suffering under a bad constitution &amp; valetudinarian habits, he has done his part well; &amp; had his countrymen listed to his warning voice, Spain might at this day have been a free &amp; prosperous country. The only circumstance which makes me apprehend even a possibility of our being drawn into the war, is the appearance &amp; speech of <ref type="m" target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Littleton</ref> at the dinner to the Ambassadors.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">A public dinner was held at the City of London Tavern on 7 March 1823 to support the Spanish liberal regime, which was threatened by imminent invasion by France to restore royal absolutism. The guests of honour were Juan Jabat Aztal (1772&#8211;1825), the Spanish Ambassador 1822&#8211;1823, Jo&#227;o Francisco de Oliveira (dates unknown), the Portuguese charg&#233; d&#8217;affaires 1821&#8211;1822, and Lorenzo Fernandez de Villavicencio y Canas, 3rd Duke of San Lorenzo and Valhermoso (1778&#8211;1859), formerly Spanish Ambassador to France. Littleton was one of a number of eminent speakers and proposed a toast to &#8216;Civil and Religious Liberty all over the World&#8217;. Littleton was a supporter of Canning, but might be expected to know <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Wellington&#8217;s</ref> thoughts on Spain as he was married to Wellington&#8217;s niece, Marquess Wellesley&#8217;s daughter, Hyacinthe Mary (d. 1849).</note> He, as <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M. Wellesleys</ref> son in law, must know what the feelings of that family are, &amp; is likely to act in conformity to them. I was therefore surprized &amp; grieved at what he said. The interference of France would be right, if it could be efficacious. But how is the Government which it may establish, to be supported? Where are its revenues to be found? And what is to prevent the Radicals from filling the whole country with banditti, &#8211; a course of life to which the destruction of all trade, &amp; the total want of protection, must drive all &lt;able-bodied men,&gt; who chuse neither to beg nor starve. &#8211; It is a deplorable state of things. The minds of men are in such a state there, that they are equally impatient of a bad government, &amp; incapable of a good one. As for Ferdinand &amp; the Cortes,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813&#8211;1833) had been forced by an army revolt in 1820 to restore the Constitution of 1812 with its elected Cortes.</note>
          <del>I think xxxible of both know tho</del> what may happen to them may excite horror, &lt;but&gt; it will hardly raise compassion; &#8211; but that the Spaniards should be re-barbarized, &amp; degraded, would indeed be an evil for Europe &amp; for the World. And yet the tendency of events is to render the country one wide scene of anarchy, overrun by troops as barbarous as any of the wild Arabs, or mountaineers of Asia.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">What you say of Negro emancipation coincides entirely with my feelings upon that subject. The present D of Northumberland made a motion to that effect, some sixteen or seventeen years ago;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Hugh Percy, 3rd Duke of Northumberland (1785&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>), had proposed a motion in the House of Commons on 16 March 1807 for leave to bring in a Bill to gradually abolish slavery, by stipulating that all children born of slaves after a certain date should be declared free; but the motion was &#8216;counted out&#8217; as the Commons was not quorate.</note> it was not supported, &amp; scarcely noticed; &#8211; I however sent the following lines to one of the newspapers at the time, &#8211; &amp; if you think them worth reprinting, they are at the Plain Englishmans service.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">This poem was first published as &#8216;Sonnet to Lord Percy, on his late motion for the gradual abolition of slavery in the West Indies&#8217; in the <title>Courier</title>, 22 April 1807. It was reprinted in <title>The Englishman&#8217;s Library: Comprising a Series of Historical, Biographical and National Information</title> (London, 1824), p. 380.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="center">Sonnet &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="center">to Lord Percy, on his motion for the gradual</p>
        <p rend="center">abolition of Slavery in the British West Indian Islands</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Percy, &#8220;of virtuous father virtuous son,&#8221;<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;Sonnet XX&#8217; (&#8216;Lawrence of virtuous Father virtuous Son,&#8217;), line 1, from <title>Poems, &amp;c. upon Several Occasions</title> (London, 1673).</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent3">(Thou too, like him, the friend of the forlorn)</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Well hast thou done, &amp; rightly didst advance</l>
          <l rend="indent3">From bondage to redeem a race unborn,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Abandond else to their inheritance</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Of vice &amp; misery: &#8211; rightly hast thou done,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And England turns an eye of hope on thee</l>
          <l rend="indent3">For this fair promise of thine opening morn.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">In the good path which thou hast chosen, proceed!</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Be ever thus the friend of Liberty,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And Earth &amp; Heaven will give thee both thy meed.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Yea greener laurels will be thine in store</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Than thy heroic fathers won of yore</l>
          <l rend="indent3">In Tiviotdale, &amp; on the banks of Tweed.</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">the allusion to his father was made, because I happened to know that the late D of Northumberland<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Hugh Percy, 2nd Duke of Northumberland (1742&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>).</note> was munificent in his secret charities.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am sorry to hear that <ref type="m" target="people.html#LockerEleanor">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Locker</ref> is indisposed, &amp; hope that I may find her well recovered in the month of May. &#8211; Thank you for your Views,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Locker had offered to contribute some of his drawings as sources for Westall&#8217;s <title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey&#8217;s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &amp;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823).</note> &#8211; which I shall have great interest in seeing, &#8211; they had better be sent to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brothers</ref>
          <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">15 Q Anne Street</ref>. &#8211; When these Odes, &amp; the Algiers<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was unaware that his New Year&#8217;s ode for January 1817, &#8216;Ode on the Battle of Algiers&#8217;, had already appeared in <title>The Plain Englishman</title>, 3 (1823), pp. 427&#8211;428.</note> are <del>xx</del> set up, I should like to see the proof, &#8211; in the hope of improving them. Trifles catch the eye in types which sometimes escape observation in the manuscript.</p>
        <p>
          Believe me<lb/>
          	Yours very truly<lb/>
          Robert Southey.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>