<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4006. Robert Southey to John Murray, 23 April 1823</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4006Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4006. Robert Southey to John Murray, 23 April 1823</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4006Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4006" type="letter">
        <head>4006. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1823-04-23">23 April 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London <lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Postmark: E/ 26 AP 26/ 1823<lb />
Endorsement: April 23/ 23/ R. Southey Esqre<lb />
MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 3p.<lb />
Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-04-23">23 Apr. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">This Book of the Church<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> has grown under my hands, tho I have introduced nothing that is extraneous, have past rapidly over that what is least interesting, &amp; not touched upon any thing which is not in some point of view material to the structure &amp; object of the work. Will it not be better to divide it into two volumes, somewhat short of 400 pages each,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Book of the Church</title> (1824) was published in two volumes, running to 394 and 528 pages, respectively.</note> than to produce on of inconvenient bulk, &#8211; or in any way <del>th</del> injure the composition by curtailing it toward the conclusion? For I have yet to handle the parts which are of deepest interest, &#8211; Q Marys reign, &amp; the overthrow of the Church by the Puritans,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, pp. 141&#8211;251, 347&#8211;467, dealing with the reign of Mary I (1516&#8211;1558; Queen of England 1553&#8211;1558; <title>DNB</title>), and the replacement of Anglicanism as the State Church during the period of the Civil War of 1642&#8211;1651 and the Republic 1649&#8211;1660.</note> &#8211; the latter a most important part of our <del>relig</del> history which has never yet been presented in a clear &amp; connected manner.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">If you think it will be better to divide it, the first volume may end with the tenth chapter.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of the <title>Book of the Church</title> (1824) ended with Chapter 11.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Unawares I have been led to produce a work of more importance than either you or I intended. Yet from the interest which I have felt, &amp; the pains which I have taken in writing it, I believe that <del>ultimately</del> it will be to the advantage of us both.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">That I may not be deficient any where for want of full information, let me trouble you for Strypes <title>Annals</title> (not his <title>Memorials</title>)<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey wished for a copy of John Strype (1643&#8211;1737; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Annals of the Reformation and Establishment of Religion</title> (1709). Oxford University Press published a new edition in 1824, no. 2753 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. He did not want Strype&#8217;s <title>Ecclesiastical Memorials, Relating Chiefly to Religion, and the Reformation of it, and the Emergencies of the Church of England under King Henry VIII, King Edward VI, and Queen Mary the First</title> (1721).</note> &#8211; I shall then have the whole of his historical works. &#8211; Thank you for sending the Oxford edition of his Cranmer, <del>which</del> &lt;it&gt; contains an important document, not in the folio.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Strype (1643&#8211;1737; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memorials of the Most Reverend Father in God Thomas Cranmer, Sometime Lord Archbishop of Canterbury: Wherein the History of the Church, and the Reformation of it during the Primacy of the said Archbishop are Greatly Illustrated; and Many Singular Matters Relating Thereunto, now first Published</title> (1694). This was reprinted by Oxford University Press in 1812 and was no. 2754 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
	Thank you also for Franklins Journey.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Franklin (1786&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Narrative of a Journey to the Shores of the Polar Sea in the Years 1819, 1820, 1821, and 1822</title> (1823), no. 1128 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> The prints are very beautiful, &amp; excellently characteristic<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The book contained 31 engravings by Edward Francis Finden (1791&#8211;1857; <title>DNB</title>), based on drawings by members of Franklin&#8217;s company.</note> The narrative very interesting &amp; most creditable to the author &amp; his companions. It would be a delightful book altogether, were not for its dismal conclusion, &amp; the loss of poor Lt Hood,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant Robert Hood (1797&#8211;1821), naval officer, explorer, painter and surveyor, and member of Franklin&#8217;s expedition. He was murdered on 20 October 1821 by a travelling companion following a quarrel. Despite the expedition&#8217;s discoveries in northern Canada, 11 members died from exposure or starvation.</note> who seems to have been a man of wonder talents &amp; accomplishments of every kind.</p>
        <p>
          Believe my my dear Sir<lb/>
          Yours very truly<lb/>
          Robert Southey
        </p>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">I am in the full tide of composition, &amp; shall not leave home till the book is compleated. You shall have more copy when I return the proofs &#8211; by the next post.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>