<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4104. Robert Southey to Nicholas Lightfoot, 22 December 1823</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4104Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4104. Robert Southey to Nicholas Lightfoot, 22 December 1823</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4104Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4104" type="letter">
        <head>4104. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1823-12-22">22 December 1823 </date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Nicholas Lightfoot/ Crediton/ Devonshire<lb />
Postmarks: E E/ D 22/ 1823; [partial] DE 22/ 1823; T.P./ Tooting<lb />
Endorsement: Dec-23<lb />
Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 110. ALS; 2p.<lb />
Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1823-12-22">22 Dec. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Lightfoot</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I can write to you concerning my movements now with as much certainty as any <del>things </del>&lt;arrangement&gt; dependent upon such frail things as health &amp; life will admit. My place is taken for Friday Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 2 in a coach, which will deposit me the next <del>x</del> day about noon, near Sir John Kennaways<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Kennaway, 1st Baronet (1758&#8211;1836), made a fortune in the East India Company and became a landowner in Devonshire. Southey knew him through his son, Charles Edward Kennaway, who had visited Southey in the Lake District in 1819&#8211;1820. The Kennaway home, Escot House, is close to Ottery St Mary.</note> door. I am to pass that day with his family, the next with Col. Coleridge,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">James Coleridge (1759&#8211;1836), the eldest brother of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and father of John Taylor Coleridge and Henry Nelson Coleridge.</note> Monday &amp; Tuesday with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Marryat<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Marriott (1780&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman, poet and friend of Walter Scott. He was Curate of St James, Exeter, St Lawrence, Exeter, and St John, Broadclyst. The patron of the latter church was Sir Thomas Acland, who was also a friend of Marriott.</note> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir Thomas Acland</ref>, (they will determine their respective days) Wednesday I get to Exeter as early as I can to make my calls there on M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Keenan,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Frances Keenan (d. 1838), an artist and widow of the Irish portrait painter, John Keenan (d. 1819). Southey had first met her in Exeter in 1799.</note> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">the widow</ref> of my excellent friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneWade">Wade Browne</ref> of Ludlow, &amp; then proceed to Crediton, taking chaise if no other ready means of conveyance should offer. Thursday, Friday, Saturday &amp; Sunday I propose to stay with you; &#8211; I know your friendship will think the time short, &#8211; &amp; I feel it to be so, &#8211; but you will perceive that it is four times as much as I allow to any other person in the West, &amp; when you know that I left home on the third of November, &amp; cannot reach it again before the middle of February, &#8211; I am sure you will not press me to lengthen an absence which is necessarily so much too long. Monday the 12. I must get to Taunton.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Your last letter &#8211; like all your letters &#8211; is full of warm-hearted kindness. Very gladly would I bring <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref> to your hospitable home, if it suited the disposal which has been made of her time, &amp; if she was equal (which she is not) to bear the continued fatigue &amp; excitement of my hurried movements. She has too little of the strength of a mountaineer, &amp; too much of that home sickness which mountaineers feel more than any other people. &#8211; I may tell <hi rend="ital">you</hi>, that her easy &amp; natural manners are thought good proofs of what may be effected by domestic education, &amp; that those persons who were disposed to regard her with friendly feelings for my sake, like her now for her own.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">At present she is with our fellow travellers from the North, in Gloucester Place.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">100 Gloucester Place was the home of Lady Susanna Malet, n&#233;e Wales (1779&#8211;1868), the widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), maternal uncle of the Charter sisters <ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Louisa Charter</ref>, and Elizabeth Charter (1782&#8211;1860), friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>). They were the sisters of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, first wife of William Peachy, and Peachy had lent the Charter sisters his home on Derwent Island in 1823. They had travelled south with Southey in November. Their other companion was one of Sir Charles Malet&#8217;s three children in India with Amber Kaur (b. 1772): Eliza (b. 1791); Henry Charles (1793&#8211;1844); and Louisa (b. 1795). They accompanied Malet to Britain in 1798 and were brought up with his children by Susanna Malet. Eliza Malet married, in 1812, Robert Ekins (1785&#8211;1874), Vicar of Godalming 1810&#8211;1833, Rector of Folke, Dorset 1833&#8211;1843, Perpetual Curate of North Wootton 1843&#8211;1854. Southey is probably referring here to Louisa Malet.</note> I write from <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>, where I am closely employed in finishing a paper for the QR.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752&#8211;1817), <title>Travels in New-England and New-York</title> (1821&#8211;1822), no. 881 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (October 1823), 1&#8211;40, published 17 April 1824.</note> Tomorrow I expect to finish it. I have still to put the last hand to the B of the Church.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> Wednesday will do so much it, that two or three mornings more will bring me to the end desired. I return to town on Thursday to my Xmas dinner, &amp; remain there in <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q. Anne Street</ref> till my departure from the West</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I cannot obtain a frank for this letter because there is no franking it from hence to London. My best wishes to all your fireside. It will be a great disappointment to me not to see <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">John</ref>, &#8211; for I have no chance of visiting Oxford.</p>
        <p>
          God bless you my dear old friend!<lb/>
          Yrs affectionately<lb/>
          Robert Southey.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>