<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4151. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 7 March 1824</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4151Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4151. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 7 March 1824</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4151Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4151" type="letter">
        <head>4151. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-03-07">7 March 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>./ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 10 MR 10/ 1824<lb />
               Endorsements: 7 March 1824; 7 March 1824<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 263&#8211;264.<lb />
               Note on MS: This letter is written on a sheet of paper printed at the head with the following: TO BE/ PUBLISHED/ BY/ SUBSCRIPTION, IN THREE VOLS. OCTAVO,/ PRICE, &#163;2. S2./ (The money to be paid on delivery,)/ A CHRONOLOGICAL HISTORY OF THE/ WEST INDIES,/ BY CAPTAIN THOMAS SOUTHEY, COMMANDER/ ROYAL NAVY. [Tom Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827) was finally published by Longmans.]</p>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  If you can render any assistance in furthering this subscription, I need not say that <del>xx</del> it will be rendering me a service. <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> will print 750 copies provided we can procure 200 subscribers to begin with. That we shall be able to do this I am by no means confident; but it must not fall to the ground for want of exertion on my part.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  The plan was of my suggestion. The subject cannot be treated in any other way so well, for it includes the whole of the islands, &amp; therefore has neither national or territorial unity. At proper intervals I shall assist him with general views, &#8211; &amp; throughout with such materials &amp; remarks as my multifarious pursuits have brought within my reach. &#8211; It will be a very respectable book, bringing together a great deal of matter from scattered sources, &amp; filling up a portion of history which disgraceful as it is in every point of view to every nation whom it concerns, ought nevertheless to be known</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Can you put me in the way of getting a daily paper without paying the full price for one? I have just lost the Courier<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Courier</title> (1792&#8211;1842) was a pro-government daily London evening paper. Stuart bought it in 1796. However, he had taken little active part in the <title>Courier</title> since 1811 and had finally sold his share in its ownership.</note> &#8211; for which I have been obliged to <ref type="m" target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> ever since I have resided in this place. In the years 98 &amp; 99 I was his Poet Laureate &amp; wrote verses at a guinea a week for the Morning Post.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Morning Post</title> (1772&#8211;1937), a London daily paper. When Southey wrote for the <title>Morning Post</title> it was an opposition paper. Stuart was its owner 1795&#8211;1803.</note> That pay was then a great object to me; &amp; I must say of him that of all persons with whom I have ever been connected in the way of <hi rend="ital">trade</hi> he <del>has been the</del> is the one whom I have served least, &amp; who has shewn himself most sensible of the service. But he has now parted with his last share in the Courier &amp; consequently I no longer receive it. I could very well be content with my weekly Westmorland Gazette,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Westmorland Gazette</title> is a weekly newspaper, based in Kendal, founded in 1818. At this time it was pro-government.</note> but it is not proper that I should so content myself. It is quite necessary that I should <del>be</del> not be ignorant of what is going on at home &amp; abroad &#8211; but if you can help me to get a morning paper at half price, &#8211; it will answer as well as an evening one at the first cost.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">The Bp of London</ref> has written to express his &#8220;high satisfaction&#8221; with which he has read my Book.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> And I have had a message to the same effect from the Bp. of Durham.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Shute Barrington (1734&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Durham 1791&#8211;1826.</note>
        </p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
            RS.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> blows the horn better than I do.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A kind of bugle that Southey had bought as a joke, as his sister-in-law Sara Coleridge had a horror of loud noises.</note> But practise makes perfect, &#8211; &amp; I am aiming at perfection</p>
          <lb />
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-03-07"> 7 March. 1824.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>