<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4178. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 27 April 1824</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4178Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4178. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 27 April 1824</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4178Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4178" type="letter">
        <head>4178. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-04-27">27 April 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer,/ Westminster<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 30 AP 30/ 1824<lb />
               Endorsements: 27 April 1824./ Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> May.<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 173&#8211;175 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-04-27">27 Apr. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter was as welcome as this days rain when the thirsty ground was gaping for it. Indeed I should have been uneasy at your silence, &amp; apprehended that some untoward cause must have occasioned it, if I had not heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> that you had supplied her Exchequer. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I should indeed have enjoyed the sight of <ref type="m" target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> in the condition which you describe &amp; the subsequent process of transformation.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford had written to Southey on 16 April 1824, describing how Duppa had arrived at his house caked in mud after being splashed by a passing coach. Bedford had provided Duppa with an ill-assorted selection of his own and his brother, Henry Bedford&#8217;s, clothes. This allowed Duppa to attend a nearby dinner party.</note> How well I can call to mind his appearance on his return from the Theatre one &amp; thirty years ago!<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Duppa had visited Southey in Oxford to attend the installation of William Cavendish-Bentinck, 3rd Duke of Portland (1738&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>; Prime Minister 1783, 1807&#8211;1809) as Chancellor of the University of Oxford, on 1 July 1793. The ceremony had been held in the Sheldonian Theatre (built 1664&#8211;1669).</note> Little did I think that day that the next time I was to enter that Theatre would be in a red <del>dress</del> gown to be bedoctored &amp; called every thing <del>xxx</del> that ends in <hi rend="ital">issimus</hi>.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was awarded an honorary Doctorate of Civil Law at the University of Oxford on 14 June 1820. The ceremony was again in the Sheldonian Theatre.</note> And yet of the two days, the former was one of the most chearful in my life, &amp; the latter if not the most melancholy, I think the very loneliest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> writes to me that he has put the Book of the Church<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> to press for a second edition. I make no alterations, except to correct two slips of the pen &amp; the press &#8211; when the Emperor Charles 5 is called Q. Catharines brother instead of her nephew<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, p. 8, where Charles V (1500&#8211;1558; Holy Roman Emperor 1519&#8211;1556, King of Spain 1516&#8211;1556) was misidentified as the brother, rather than the nephew, of Catherine of Aragon (1485&#8211;1536; <title>DNB</title>), first wife of Henry VIII (1491&#8211;1547; King of England 1509&#8211;1547; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; Henry IV printed for III.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, p. 341, where Henry IV (1553&#8211;1610; King of France 1589&#8211;1610) was misprinted for Henry III (1551&#8211;1589; King of France 1574&#8211;1589).</note> &#8211; &amp; to omit an anecdote about Gardiners death which <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> tells me has been disproved by Lingard.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 6 February 1824, contained a letter from &#8216;TRUTH&#8217;, provoked by the first edition of Southey&#8217;s <title>Book of the Church</title> (1824). It pointed out that Southey&#8217;s account of the death of Stephen Gardiner (1483&#8211;1555; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Winchester 1531&#8211;1551, 1553&#8211;1555, in <title>Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, pp. 209&#8211;210, could not be accurate and was contradicted by John Lingard (1771&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of England, from the First Invasion of the Romans</title>, 5 vols (London, 1819&#8211;1823), V, p. 628. Southey only possessed the first three volumes of the latter, published in 1819, no. 1634 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> I do not know what number <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> printed. But if there should appear a probability of its obtaining a regular sale, in that case I shall be disposed to think seriously of composing a similar view of our civil history, &amp; calling it the Book of the State,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write this work.</note> with the view of showing how the course of political events has influenced the condition of society, &amp; tracing the growth &amp; effect of our institutions, the gradual <del>decay of</del> disappearances of some evils &amp; the rise of others. Meantime however I have enough upon my hands &#8211; &amp; still more in my head.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Hudson Gurney<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Hudson Gurney (1775&#8211;1864; <title>DNB</title>), an antiquarian and poet from a prominent Quaker family in Norwich. Gurney was a Whig MP for Shaftesbury 1812&#8211;1813, and Newtown, Isle of Wight 1816&#8211;1832.</note> said to me he wished <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref> would lay his commands on me to write the history of his Fathers reign.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of Great Britain 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>). Southey did not write a history of his reign.</note> I wish he would &#8211; provided he would make my pension a clear 500 &#163; a year,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. &#163;500 after tax. Southey&#8217;s pension, paid since 1807, was only &#163;200 per annum, which was reduced to about &#163;144 per annum after tax. </note> to support me while I was writing it. And then I think I could <del>xx</del> treat the subject with some credit to myself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> can tell you nothing more about <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brothers</ref> intended book<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey, <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827).</note> than that he will venture upon printing 750 copies provided 200 subscribers can be obtained. The form of the work is that of President Henault&#8217;s Abr. Chronologique <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles-Jean-Fran&#231;ois H&#233;nault (1685&#8211;1770), <title>Abr&#233;g&#233; Chronologique de l&#8217;Histoire d&#8217;Espagne et de Portugal, divis&#233; en huit p&#233;riodes, avec des remarques particulieres &#224; la fin de chaque p&#233;riode sur le g&#233;nie, les moeurs, les usages, le commerce, les finances de ces monarchies; ensemble la notice des Princes contemporains, &amp; un pr&#233;cis historique sur les savans &amp; illustres</title> (1765), no. 2714 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. He was President of the Chamber of Enquiries of the Parlement of Paris 1710&#8211;1731.</note>&#8211; which is the only form adapted to that particular subject &#8211; the sole thread being that of chronology. The plan includes the whole of the West India Islands.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> returns to town the end of this week. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> I believe is at this time at <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  How is <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>? I know nothing of him, of the Review, &#8211; nor of any thing in town &#8211; or any body. Half a dozen from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> about the new edition<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The second edition of Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> being all I have heard from him since my return.</p>
        <p>
           God bless you. I have scrawled this in the twilight &amp; made &lt;it&gt; I fear even more unintelligible than usual<lb/>
           RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>