<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4224. Robert Southey to Edith May Southey, [late July 1824]</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4224Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4224. Robert Southey to Edith May Southey, [late July 1824]</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4224Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4224" type="letter">
        <head>4224. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-07">[late July 1824] </date>
          </head><p>MS: Mitchell Library, Glasgow, Special Collections. ALS; 11p.<lb />
               Previously published: <title>The Doctor</title>, 7 vols (London, 1834&#8211;1847), VII, pp. 598&#8211;615.<lb />
               Dating note: Dated from content. The letter was written while Edith May Southey was absent from Keswick and shortly after Mrs Keenan&#8217;s arrival there on 28 July 1824. Mrs Keenan&#8217;s drawing of &#8216;Apollo&#8217; and &#8216;Venus&#8217; were in existence by 23 November 1824, when Southey mentioned them to Edith May Southey (Letter 4283).</p>
        <p rend="center">
          <hi rend="ital">EI&#931; &#932;&#927;&#933;&#931; &#913;&#916;&#929;&#921;&#913;&#925;&#932;&#913;&#931;</hi>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;On the statues&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8009; &#956;&#8050;&#957; &#948;&#953;&#940;&#946;&#959;&#955;&#959;&#962; &#7952;&#957;&#941;&#960;&#957;&#949;&#957;&#963;&#941; &#964;&#953;&#963;&#953;
            &#960;&#945;&#961;&#945;&#957;&#948;&#956;&#959;&#953;&#962; <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey appears to have mistakenly written &#8216;&#960;&#945;&#961;&#945;&#957;&#948;&#956;&#959;&#953;&#962;&#8217;, meaning &#8216;unmarried&#8217;. This is corrected to &#8216;&#960;&#945;&#961;&#945;&#957;&#972;&#956;&#959;&#953;&#962;&#8217;, meaning &#8216;lawless&#8217; or &#8216;illegal&#8217;, in the printed version in <title>The Doctor</title>. </note> &#7936;&#957;&#952;&#961;&#974;&#960;&#959;&#953;&#962;, &#954;&#945;&#8054; &#949;&#7984;&#962;
            &#964;&#959;&#8058;&#962; &#964;&#8182;&#957; &#946;&#945;&#963;&#953;&#955;&#941;&#969;&#957; &#8021;&#946;&#961;&#953;&#963;&#945;&#957; &#7936;&#957;&#948;&#961;&#953;&#940;&#957;&#964;&#945;&#962;.</p>
        <p rend="indent7">Chrysost. Hom. Ad Popul. </p>
        <p rend="indent8"> Antiochen. xv.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">St John Chrysostom (c.347&#8211;407), <title>Homiliae XXI de Statuis ad Populum Antiochenum Habitae</title> (387) Homily 15: &#8216;The Devil inspired certain lawless individuals and they mistreated the statues of the emperors.&#8217;</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent0"> My dear daughter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Having lately been led to compose an inscription for one of our Garden statues,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Actually two scarecrows in the garden of Greta Hall; the &#8216;inscription&#8217; is at the end of the letter.</note>
          <del>it has occurred to me that</del> an authentic account of two such extraordinary works of art <del>ought to be applied to</del> has appeared to me so desirable that I even wonder at myself for having so long delayed to write one. It is the more incumbent on me to do this, because neither of the artists have thought proper to inscribe their names upon these masterpieces <del>xx their skills</del>, &#8211; either from that modesty which often accompanies the highest genius, or from a dignified consciousness that it was unnecessary to set any mark upon them, the works themselves sufficiently declaring from what hands they came.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I undertake this becoming task with the more pleasure because our friend M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Keenan<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Frances Keenan (d. 1838), an artist and the widow of the Irish portrait painter John Keenan (d. 1819). Southey had first met her in Exeter in 1799. Her visit to Keswick began on 28 July 1824.</note> has kindly offered <del>her assistance</del>, to illustrate the intended account by drawings of both  statues, &#8211; having as you may well suppose been struck with admiration by them. The promise of this cooperation induces me not to confine myself to a mere description, but to relate on what occasion they were made, &amp; faithfully to record the very remarkable circumstances which have occurred in consequence, <del>of this</del> circumstances I will venture to say, as well attested &amp; as well worthy of preservation as any of those related in the History of the Portugueze Images of Nossa Senhora, in ten volumes quarto,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Agostinho de Santa Maria (1642&#8211;1728), <title>Santuario Mariano e Historia des Imagens Milagrosas de Nossa Senhora e das Milagrosamente Apparacidas</title> (1707&#8211;1723), no. 3222 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; a book of real value, &amp; which <del>xx</del>, you know, I regard as one of the <del>curiosities</del> most curious in my collection. If in the progress of this design I should sometimes appear to wander in digression, you will not impute it to any habitual love of circumlocution; &amp; the speculative notions which I may have occasion to propose, you will receive as mere speculations &amp; judge of them accordingly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Many many years &lt;ago&gt; I remember to have seen these popular &amp; rustic rhymes in print.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">God made a great man to plough &amp; to sow,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">God made a little man to drive away the crow.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">These lines are part of a popular rhyme that existed in various forms in different parts of England. John Lawrence (1753&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Philosophical Treatise on Horses, and on the Moral Duties of Man towards the Brute Creation</title> (London, 1796), p. 292, attributed a version very close to the one Southey uses to a sermon of Adoniram Byfield (1602&#8211;1660; <title>DNB</title>), a Puritan clergyman.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent0"> they were composed perhaps to make some little man contented with that office, &amp; certain it is that in all ages &amp; all countries it has been an object of as much consequence to preserve the seed from birds when sown, as to sow it. No doubt Adam himself when he was driven to cultivate the ground<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">When Adam, the first man, was expelled from the Garden of Eden he was compelled to work to support himself; see <title>Genesis</title> 3: 19.</note> felt this, &amp; we who are his lineal descendants (tho I am sorry to say we have &lt;not&gt; inherited <del>xxxx</del> &lt;a rood&gt; of his <del>property</del> &lt;estates&gt;) have felt it also, in our small but not unimportant concern, the Garden. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref>, the Lady of that Garden used to complain grievously of the depredations committed there, especially <del>x</del> upon her pease. Fowls &amp; Ducks were condemned either to imprisonment for life, or to the immediate larder for their offences of this kind; but the magpies (my proteg&#233;es) &amp; the sparrows, &amp; the blackbirds &amp; the thrushes bade defiance to the coop &amp; the cook. She tried to fright them away by feathers fastened upon a string &#8211; but birds were no more to be frightened by feathers than to be caught by chaff. She drest up two mopsticks; not to be forgotten, because when two youths sent their straw hats upon leaving <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, the girls consigned <del>them</del> &lt;the hats&gt; to these mopsticks <del>which they named</del> &lt;&amp; named the <del>xxxxx</del> figures thus attired&gt; in due honour of the youths, <ref type="m" target="people.html#NoelLeland">Leland Noel</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#KennawayCharlesE">Charles Kennaway</ref>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">This incident probably occurred in October 1820, when both Charles Kennaway and Leland Noel were in the Lake District.</note> These mopsticks however were well drest enough to invite thieves from the town, &#8211; &amp; too well to frighten the birds. Something more effectual was wanted, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L.</ref> bespoke a man of Joseph Glover.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <hi rend="sup"> </hi>Joseph Glover (dates unknown) was the Keswick carpenter employed by the Southey family; see John Wood Warter, ed. <title>Common-Place Book</title>, 4 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, p. 534.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Such is the imperfection of language that write as carefully &amp; warily as we can it is impossible to use words which will not frequently admit of a double construction, upon this <del>xxxxx</del> indeed it is that the Lawyers have founded the science of the Law, which said science <del>xxxxxx</del> &lt;they <del>xxx</del> display&gt; in extracting &lt;any meaning&gt; from &lt;any&gt; words &lt;&amp; generally that&gt; meaning that shall <del>entirely frustrate</del> &lt;be most opposite to&gt; the intention for which they were used. When I say that your <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Aunt L.</ref> bespoke a man of Joseph Glover I do not mean that she <del>emp</del> commissioned him to engage a labourer: nor that she required him &lt;actually&gt;to make a man like Frankenstein,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Godwin Shelley (1797&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</title> (1818). </note> &#8211; tho it must be admitted that such a man as Frankenstein made, would be the best of all scare crows provided he were broken in so as to be perfectly manageable. <del>This</del> &lt;To have made a man indeed&gt; would have been more than even Paracelsus would have undertaken to perform; for according to the receipt which that illustrious Bombast ab Hohenheim has delivered to posterity, an homunculus cannot be produced in a hot bed in less than forty weeks &amp; forty days;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Paracelsus&#8217; was the name by which the Swiss polymath, Philippus Aureolus Theophrastus Bombastus von Hohenheim (1493&#8211;1541), preferred to be known. Southey had referred to this &#8216;receipt&#8217; before in <title>Omniana or Horae Otiosiores</title>, 2 vols (London, 1812), I, p. 92. His source was Paracelsus&#8217;s <title>Opera Omnia Medico-Chemico-Chirurgica</title>, 3 vols (Geneva, 1658), II, p. 72; no. 2166 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note>
          <del>x xxxx</del> &amp; this would not have been in time to save the pease; not to mention that one of his homunculi had it been ready could not have served the purpose, for by his account, when it was produced, it was smaller even than Mark Thumb.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Mark Thumb was possibly a variant of Tom Thumb, a character in English folklore, who was no bigger than his father&#8217;s thumb. </note> Such an order would have been more unreasonable than any of those which Juno imposed upon Hercules;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Juno was the Roman equivalent of the Greek goddess Hera. Hera drove the hero Hercules mad, leading him to murder his family and to undertake his &#8216;Twelve Labours&#8217; as a penance.</note> whereas the task imposed by <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref> was nothing more than Glover thought himself capable of executing, for he understood the <del>words</del> &lt;direction&gt; plainly &amp; simply in their direct &lt;its proper&gt; sense, as a carpenter ought to understand <del>them</del> it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">An ordinary Carpenter might have hesitated at undertaking it, or bungled in the execution. But Glover is not an ordinary Carpenter. He says of himself that he should have been a capital singer, only the pity is, that he has no voice. Whether he had ever <del>the same</del> a similar persuasion of his own &lt;essential but unproducible&gt; talents for sculpture or painting I know not; &#8211; but if ever genius &amp; originality were triumphantly displayed in the first effort of an untaught artist, it was on this occasion. Perhaps I am wrong in calling him untaught; &#8211; for there is a supernatural or divine teaching; &#8211; &amp; it will appear presently that if there be any truth in heathen philosophy, <del>xx</del> or in that of the Roman Catholicks (which is very much the same in many respects) some such assistance may be suspected in this case. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> With or without such assistance, but certainly <hi rend="ital">con amore</hi>,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;for love&#8217;.</note> &amp; with the aid of his own genius, if of no other, Glover went to work: <del>&amp; in a short time</del> &lt;ere long&gt; shouts of admiration were heard one evening in the kitchen, so loud &amp; of such long continuance that enquiry was made from the parlour into the cause, &amp; the reply was that <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovells</ref> man was brought home. Out we went, father <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">mother</ref> &amp; daughters<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha Southey</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate Southey</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note> (yourself among them, &#8211; for you cannot have forgotten that memorable hour) <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">My Lady</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">the Venerabilis</ref> &#8211; and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref> herself, as the person more immediately concerned. Seldom as it happens that any artist can embody with perfect success the conceptions of another, in this instance the <del>xxx</del> difficult &amp; delicate task had been perfectly accomplished. But I must describe the Man, &#8211; calling him by that name at present, the <del>character</del> &lt;power, &#230;on or intelligence&gt; which had incorporated itself with that ligneous resemblance of humanity not having at that time been suspected.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Yet methinks more properly might he have been called youth than man, the form &amp; stature being juvenile. The limbs &amp; body were slender, <del>yet</del> &lt;tho&gt; not so as to convey any appearance of feebleness, it was rather that degree of slenderness which in elegant &amp; refined society is deemed <del>xxxxxxx</del> essential to grace. The countenance at once denoted strength &amp; health &amp; hilarity, &amp; the incomparable Carpenter had given it an expression of threatful &amp; alert determination suited to the station for which he was designed &amp; the weapon which he bore. The shape of the face was rather round than oval, resembling methinks the broad harvest moon, the eyes were of the deepest black, <del>xx</del> the eye brows black also; &amp; there was a blackness about the nose &amp; lips, such as might be imagined in the face of Hercules, while he was in the act of lifting &amp; strangling the yet unsubdued &amp; struggling Ant&#230;us.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek mythology, Antaeus was a giant, who challenged passers-by to a wrestling match, in which he was invincible as long as he remained in contact with the ground. The hero, Hercules, defeated him, as one of his &#8216;Twelve Labours&#8217;, by holding Antaeus off the ground and crushing him.</note> On his head was a little hat, low in the crown &amp; narrow in the brim. His dress was a sleeved jacket without skirts, &#8211; our ancestors would have called it a gipion,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had used this obsolete medieval word before in his <title>Roderick, The Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 25, line 147.</note>
          <hi rend="ital">jubon</hi> it would be <del>called</del> &lt;rendered&gt; if ever this description were <del>rendered</del> &lt;translated&gt; into Spanish, <hi rend="ital">gib&#227;o</hi> in Portugueze, <hi rend="ital">jupon</hi> or <hi rend="ital">gippon</hi> in old French. It was fastened from the neck downward with eight white buttons, two &amp; two, &amp; between them was a broad white stripe, the colour of the gipion being brown: whether the &lt;stripe&gt; was to represent <del>xx</del> silver lace, or a white facing like that of the naval uniform, is doubtful &amp; <del>xxxxx</del> of little consequence. The lower part of his dress represented innominables &amp; hose in one, of the same colour as the gipion. And he carried a fowling piece in his hand.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Great was the satisfaction which we all expressed at beholding so admirable a man; great were the applauses which we bestowed upon the workman with one consent; &amp; great was the complacency with which Glover himself regarded the work of his own hands. He thought, he said, this would please us. Please us indeed it did, &amp; so well did it answer that after short trial &lt;<ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref>&gt; thinking that a second image would render the whole Garden secure, &amp; moreover that it was not good for her Man to be alone, directed Glover to make a Woman also. The woman accordingly was made. Flesh of his flesh &amp; bone of his bone,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Adam, speaking of Eve in <title>Genesis</title> 2: 23: &#8216;This <hi rend="ital">is</hi> now bone of my bones And flesh of my flesh; She shall be called Woman, Because she was taken out of Man.&#8217;</note> she could not be, the Man himself not being made of <del>flesh &amp; bone</del> &lt;such materials&gt;; but she was &lt;wood of his wood &amp;&gt; plank of his plank, &#8211; which was coming as nearly as possible to it, made of the same <del>materials</del> &lt;tree&gt; &amp; fashioned by the same hand. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Woman was in all respects a goodly mate for the man, except that she seemed to be a few years older; she was rather below the mean stature, in that respect resembling the Venus de Medicis;<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">The Venus de&#8217; Medici, a Greek statue, by an unknown sculptor of the 1st century BC, of the goddess Aphrodite, in the Uffizi Palace, Florence. It is only five feet tall.</note> slender waisted yet not looking as if she were tight-laced, nor so thin as to denote ill health. Her dress was a gown of homely brown, up to the neck. The artist had employed his <del>dark</del> &lt;brightest&gt; colours upon her face, even the eyes &amp; nose partook of that brilliant tint which is sometimes called the roseate hue of health or exercise, sometimes the purple light of love. The whites of her eyes were large. She also was represented in a hat, but higher in the crown &amp; broader in the rim than the mans, &amp; where his brim was turned up, hers had a downward inclination giving a feminine character to that part of her dress.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> She was placed in the garden; greatly as we admired both pieces of workmanship, we considered them merely as what they seemed to be; <del>xx</del> they went by the names of <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovells</ref> Man &amp; Woman; &amp; even when you departed for the south they were still known only by that vague &amp; most unworthy designation. Some startling circumstances after awhile excited a more particular attention to them. Several of the family declared they had been frightened by them; &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> one evening came in saying that <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Aunt Lovells</ref> Woman had <hi rend="ital">given her</hi> a jump. Even this did not awaken any suspicion of their supernatural powers as it ought to have done, till on a winters night, one of the maids hearing a knock at the back door opened it, &amp; started back when she saw that it was the Woman with a letter in her hand! This is as certain as that Nosso Senhor dos Passos knocked at the door of S. Roques convent in Lisbon &amp; was not taken in, &#8211; to the infinite regret of the Monks when they learnt that he had gone afterwards to the Gra&#231;a Convent &amp; been admitted there. It is as certain &lt;as&gt; that I have seen men women &amp; children of all ranks kissing the foot of the said Image in the Church, &amp; half Lisbon following his procession in the streets.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey related this tradition in <title>Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp. 390&#8211;391; he had seen the image being carried through the streets of Lisbon in the Lent processions of 1796. The statue represented &#8216;Our Lord of the Steps&#8217;, or Christ carrying his cross to Calvary. Its ownership was disputed between the Gra&#231;a Convent, headquarters of the Order of St Augustine, and the Church of St Roch, headquarters of the Lisbon Holy House of Mercy.</note> It is as certain as all the miracles in the <del>Acta</del> Fasti, the Metamorphoses, &amp; the Acta Sanctorum.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">The Fasti were yearly records in Ancient Rome that included everything connected to the gods and religious practices; Publius Ovidius Naso (43 BC&#8211;AD 17/18), <title>Metamorphoses</title> (AD 8) is a long narrative poem including many myths; and the massive, 53-volume compendium of hagiographies, entitled <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (1643&#8211;1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Many remarkable things were now called to mind <del>xx</del> both of the Man &amp; Woman; &#8211; how on one occasion they had made Miss Christians<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Christian (1759&#8211;1831) was one of the Southeys&#8217; neighbours in Keswick; her maid&#8217;s name is unknown.</note> maid miscarry of &#8211; half a message; &amp; &lt;how&gt; at another time when Isaac<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac (dates unknown) was presumably a servant in the Calvert household.</note> was bringing a basket from <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Calverts</ref> he was frightened into his wits by them. But on Sunday evening last the most extraordinary display of <del>their</del> wonderful power &lt;occurred&gt; <del>both xxxx</del>: for in the evening the Woman, instead of being in her place among the pease, appeared standing erect on the top of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fishers<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">The Forge Field lay next to Greta Hall, on the banks of the River Greta. It is not clear who &#8216;Mr Fisher&#8217; was; he might have been John Fisher (dates unknown), a butcher in Keswick.</note> haymow in the forge field, &amp; there on the following morning she was seen by all Keswick, who are witnesses of the fact.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You may well suppose that I now began to examine into the mystery, &amp; manifold were the mysteries which I discovered, &amp; many the analogies in their formation of which the maker could never by possibility have heard, &amp; many the points of divine philosophy &amp; theurgic science which they illustrated. In the first place two Swedenborgian correspondencies<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">In the cosmology of Emmanuel Swedenborg (1688&#8211;1772), all items in the natural world &#8216;correspond&#8217; to items in the spiritual world, reflecting the intimate relationship between the two levels of existence.</note> flashed upon me in the material whereof they were constructed. They were intended to guard the Garden. There is a proverb which says set a thief to catch a thief, &amp; therefore it is that they were <hi rend="ital">fir</hi> statues. Take it in English &amp; the correspondence is equally striking; they were made of <hi rend="ital">deal</hi>, because they were to do a <hi rend="ital">deal</hi> of good. &lt;The dark aspect of the male figure also was explained; for being stationed there contra <hi rend="ital">fures</hi>,<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;against thieves&#8217;.</note> it was proper that he should have a furious countenance.&gt;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Secondly there is something wonderful in their formation: &#8211; they are <del>xx xthxx statues xxx fixtures</del>, bifronted, not merely bifaced like Janus,<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Roman god of beginnings, time, doorways and endings; he was always depicted with two faces.</note> but bifronted from top to toe. <del>xxx</del> &lt;Let&gt; the thief be as cunning as he may he cannot get behind them. &#8211; They have no backs, &amp; were they disposed to be indolent &amp; sit at their posts it would be impossible. They <del>may xxxxx</del> &lt;can appear as&gt; if at the kitchen door, <del>they may breakfast</del> or on the hay mow, they <del>may</del> &lt;can&gt; give the children &amp; even the grown <del>xxxxxx</del> persons of the family a jump, but to sit is beyond their power however miraculous it may be: for impossibilities cannot be effected even by miracle, &amp; as it is impossible to see without eyes, or to walk without legs, &#8211; or for a ship to <del>xxx</del> float without a bottom, so is it for a person in the same predicament as such a ship &#8211; to sit.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Yet farther mysteries; both hands of these marvellous statues are right hands &amp; both are left hands, they are at once ambidexter &amp; ambisinister. It was said by Dryden of old Jacob Tonson that he had two left legs:<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacob Tonson (1655/1656&#8211;1736; <title>DNB</title>) was a bookseller and publisher. John Dryden (1631&#8211;1700; <title>DNB</title>) described him as &#8216;With leering Looks, Bull-fac&#8217;d, and Freckled Fair,/ With two left Legs, and Judas-colour&#8217;d Hair,/ With Frowzy Pores, that taint the ambient Air&#8217; in some lines, that were later published in <title>Faction Display&#8217;d</title> (London, 1704), p. 15.</note> but these marvellous statues have two left legs &amp; two right legs each, &amp; yet but <del>two legs apiece</del> four legs between them, that is to say but two apiece. In the whole course of my reading I have found no account of any <del>thing like</del> &lt;statues so wonderful as&gt; these. For though the Roman Janus was bifronted, &amp; my old acquaintance Yamen<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">Yama, the Hindu god of death and justice, who featured in Southey&#8217;s <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> had in like manner a double face, &amp; many of <del>xxxx</del> &lt;the&gt; Hindoo &amp; other oriental Deities have their necks set round with heads, &amp; their elbows with arms, yet it is certain that all these Gods have backs, &amp; sides to them also. In this point no similitude can be found for <del>them</del> &lt;our Images&gt;. They <del>xxxx</del> &lt;may be&gt; likened &lt;to&gt; the sea as being bottomless, &#8211; but as being without a back &amp; in the mystery of having both hands &amp; legs <del>equally</del> &lt;at once&gt; right &amp; left, <del>xxxx</del> they are unequalled; none but themselves can be their parallel. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Now my daughter I appeal to you &amp; to all other reasonable persons, &#8211; I put the question to your own plain sense, &#8211; is it anyways likely that Statues so wonderful, so inexpressibly mysterious in their properties should be the mere work of a <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> carpenter<del>?</del>, &lt;tho&gt; aided as he was by <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovells</ref> directions? Is <del>xx</del> it not certain that neither <del>her</del> he, nor <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L</ref>, had the slightest glimpse, the remotest thought of any such properties, &#8211; she when she designed, he when he executed the marvellous productions? Is it possible that they should? Would it not be preposterous to <del>xxxx</del> suppose it? </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This supposition therefore being proved to be absurd, which in mathematics is equal to a demonstration that the contrary must be true, it remains <del>xx</del> to enquire into the real origin of their stupendous qualities. Both the &lt;ancient&gt; Heathens &amp; the Romanists <del>believe</del> &lt;teach&gt; that certain Images of the Gods or of the Saints have been made without the aid of human hands, &amp; that they have appeared no one knew whence or how. The Greeks called such images Diopeteis, as having fallen from the sky, &amp; I could enumerate were it needful sundry Catholic Images which are at this day venerated as being either of angelic workmanship or celestial origin. We cannot however have recourse to this solution in the present case; for Glover is so veracious a man that if he had found these figures in his workshop without knowing how they came there, &#8211; or if he had seen them grow into shape while he was looking on, &#8211; he would certainly not have concealed a fact so extraordinary. All <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> &lt;would have known it. It must have become as notorious as Prince Hohenloe&#8217;s<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander Leopold Hohenlohe-Waldenberg-Schillingsfurst (1794&#8211;1875), an Austrian priest who claimed, from 1821 onwards, to effect miraculous cures through prayer. The publication of <title>Prince Hohenlohe&#8217;s Prayer Book</title> (1824) led to some controversy and a flurry of pamphlets and essays.</note> miracles.&gt;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There remains then another hypothesis, which is also common to the ancient Pagans &amp; the Romanists; &#8211; that some superior powers finding a congruity in the Images have been pleased to communicate to them a portion of their influence, &amp; even of their presence, &amp; so if I may be allowed the word, have actually become <hi rend="ital">inligneate</hi> in them. Were my old acquaintance Thomas Taylor<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Taylor (1758&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), a translator of numerous Greek texts and admirer of Greek philosophy. Southey had met him on several occasions; see, for example, Southey to Joseph Cottle [fragment], [c. 8 May 1797], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 216; Southey to Edith Southey, 15 May 1799, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 409; and Southey to John King, 15&#8211;16 April 1802, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 669b.</note> here, who entirely believes this, he would at once determine which of his Heathen Deities have thus manifested their existence. Who indeed that looks at the Youth but must be reminded of Apollo?<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">Apollo was one of the leading ancient Greek deities. One of his aspects was Phoebus, the god of the sun. Apollo had also served Admetus of Pherae as a mortal for a year, as a punishment for killing the serpent at Delphi.</note> Said I that his face resembled in its rotundity the Moon? the Sun would have been the fitter similitude, &#8211; the sun shorn of its beams: &#8211; Phoebus, &#8211; such as he appeared when in the service of Admetus. And for his <del>fellow</del> female companion, her beauty &amp; the admiration which it excites in all beholders, identify her with no no less certainty for Venus.<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors">Roman goddess of love and equivalent of Aphrodite.</note> We have named them therefore the Apollo de Lovell, &amp; the Venus de Glover; in <del>honour</del> justice to both artists; &amp; in farther honour of them &amp; of the Images themselves have composed the following inscription:</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">No works of Phidias<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors">Phidias (c. 480&#8211;c. 430 BC) was a renowned Greek sculptor.</note> we; but <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mrs Lovell</ref>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent4">Designd, &amp; we were made by Joseph Glover.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Apollo, I, &amp; yonder Venus stands, </l>
          <l rend="indent4">Behold her, &amp; you cannot chuse but love her.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">If antient sculptors could behold us here</l>
          <l rend="indent4">How would they pine with envy &amp; abhorrence!</l>
          <l rend="indent3">
            <del>For I xx</del>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent3">
            <del>For xxx had I surpass the Belvedere</del>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent3">For &lt;even as&gt; I surpass their <del>boasted</del> Belvedere<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors">The Apollo Belvedere, a Roman copy made in the 2nd century AD, of a lost Greek statue of Apollo in the Vatican Palace.</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent3">
            <del>And she as much</del> &lt;so much doth she&gt; excell<del>x</del> the pride of Florence<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors">The Venus de&#8217; Medici.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>
           RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>