<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4240. Robert Southey to [John May], 29 August&#8211;17 October 1824</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4240Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4240. Robert Southey to [John May], 29 August&#8211;17 October 1824</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4240Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4240" type="letter">
        <head>4240. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>], <date when="1824-08-17">29 August&#8211;17 October 1824</date>
          </head><p>MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 8p.<lb />
               Previously edited or published: Michael Neill Stanton, &#8216;An Edition of the Autobiographical Letters of Robert Southey&#8217; (unpublished PhD, University of Rochester, 1972), pp. 194&#8211;206; <lb />
               Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 133&#8211;143 [with variants; Cuthbert Southey&#8217;s text draws on a fair copy of the letter and not on the original version sent to May, which we publish here].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1824-08-29"> Aug. 29. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The business of placing me at Westminster afforded <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref> an excuse for going to London. <ref type="m" target="people.html#PalmerMiss">Miss Palmer</ref> was easily persuaded to accompany her &amp; to jobb a carriage for the season, &amp; we set off in February 1788. I had never been a mile from Bath in that direction before, &#8211; &amp; when my childish thoughts ever wandered into the terra incognita which I was one day to explore, this had been the road to it, &#8211; simply because all the other outlets from that city were familiar to me. We slept at Marlborough one night, at Reading the second &amp; on the third day reached Salt Hill.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A village in Buckinghamshire, and site of the annual &#8216;Montem&#8217; custom observed by Eton scholars 1561&#8211;1847.</note>
          <del>The three boys</del> Tom<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Palmer (b. 1775/1776) attended Eton and was admitted to Trinity College, Cambridge, in 1793, moving to Trinity Hall in 1795. He joined Lincoln&#8217;s Inn in 1794. His date of death is not recorded. Southey asserted that he committed suicide; see Southey to John May, 7 April&#8211;1 September 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3665.</note> &amp; Charles Palmer<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Palmer (1777&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), educated at Eton and Oriel College, Oxford. He later served in the Army, rising to the rank of Major-General, and was MP for Bath 1808&#8211;1826, 1830&#8211;1837.</note> were summoned from Eton to meet their <ref type="m" target="people.html#PalmerMiss">Aunt</ref> there, &amp; we remained a day for the <del>sake</del> purpose of seeing Windsor, &#8211; which I have never seen since. Lodgings had been taken at a small house in Pall Mall, &#8211; for no less fashionable situation would content <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref>, &#8211; &amp; she had a reckless<del>ness of expense</del> &lt;prodigality&gt; at fits &amp; starts, the effects of which could not be counteracted by the parsimony of her usual habits. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Palmer<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Palmer (1742&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), a theatre proprietor and postal reformer; MP for Bath 1801&#8211;1808. He devised a postal system that used fast and secure mail coaches. Palmer was Comptroller-General of the Mails 1786&#8211;1789 and Surveyor and Comptroller-General of the Mails 1789&#8211;1793. He was forced from office after a series of quarrels with other civil servants and members of the government. John Palmer was the father of Thomas and Charles Palmer.</note> was at that time Comptroller of the Post Office, holding the situation which he had so well deserved, &amp; from which he was not long afterwards most injuriously displaced. We visited him, &amp; the Newberrys<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Newbery (1743&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), a publisher of children&#8217;s books, and his wife, Mary Newbery, n&#233;e Raikes (1748&#8211;1829).</note> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#DolignonElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Dolignon</ref>, &amp; went often to the theatres, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref> appeared to be as happy as if she were not incurring expenses which she had no means of discharging. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">My father</ref> had given her thirty pounds &lt;for the journey; a sum&gt; <del>as</del> amply sufficient for taking me to school &amp; leaving me there, &amp; moreover as much as he could afford, &#8211; but she had resolved upon passing the season in town, as careless of the consequences as if she had been blind to them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> About six weeks elapsed before I was deposited at my place of destination. In the interval I had passed a few days with the Newberrys at Addiscombe, &amp; with the Miss Delamares<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Sisters of Elizabeth Dolignon: Mary Delamere (1740&#8211;1820); and a sister whose dates and first name are unknown.</note> at Cheshunt, &#8211; at the latter place I was happy, &#8211; for they were excellent women to whom my heart opened, &amp; I had the full enjoyment of the country there without any drawback. London I very much disliked, &#8211; I was of course too young to take any pleasure in the society to which I was introduced as an <del>app</del> inconvenient appendage to <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref>, &#8211; nor did I feel half the interest at the theatres, splendid as they were which I had been wont to take at Bath &amp; Bristol, where every actors face was familiar to me, &amp; every movement of the countenance could be seen. I wished for <ref type="m" target="people.html#WeeksShadrach">Shad</ref> &amp; the carpentry, &amp; poor Phillis,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s pet spaniel and the subject of &#8216;On the Death of a Favourite Old Spaniel&#8217;, <title>Poems</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp. 132&#8211;134.</note> &amp; our rambles among the woods &amp; rocks. At length upon the first of April (of all ominous days that could be chosen)<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s name was actually entered on the register of Westminster School on 2 April 1788.</note> &#8211; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Palmer took me in his carriage to Deans Yard, introduced me to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Smith<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Smith (c. 1731&#8211;1808), Headmaster of Westminster School 1764&#8211;1788, Prebendary of Westminster Abbey 1787&#8211;1808.</note>
          <del>who</del> entered my name with him, &amp; by his recommendation placed me at the boarding house they called Otly&#8217;s but kept by M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Farrer<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Most boys at Westminster School lodged in boarding houses near the School. This house was on the terrace of Great Dean&#8217;s Yard and was run by Elizabeth Farren (dates unknown), but had previously been connected to someone called Otly and retained this name.</note> &amp; left me their with Samuel Hayes<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Hayes (1749&#8211;1795) was educated at Westminster School and Trinity College, Cambridge (BA 1771, MA 1774). An usher at Westminster School 1770&#8211;1788, he was ordained in 1772 and married Mrs Farren as his second wife on 1 May 1788.</note> the Usher of the house &amp; of the fifth form for my tutor.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Botch Hayes as he was called for the manner in which he mended his pupils verses <del>was as somebody said of old Nahum Tate a good natured, free, fuddling companion</del>
          <note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had related this description of Nahum Tate (1652&#8211;1715; <title>DNB</title>), Poet Laureate 1692&#8211;1715, in <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807) I, p. 173, and again in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 29 (April 1823), 165&#8211;214 (208), published 27 or 28 September 1823. The source he gave was William Oldys (1696&#8211;1761; <title>DNB</title>), but it is not possible to locate this phrase in Oldys&#8217; work; however, Oldys did refer to William Elderton (d. c. 1592; <title>DNB</title>) as &#8216;a facetious fuddling companion&#8217;.</note> kept a smaller boarding house next door, but at this time a treaty of union between the two houses was going on, &#8211; which &lt;like&gt; the union of <del>other larger communities</del> &lt;Castile &amp; Aragon&gt;<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The marriage of Ferdinand II (1452&#8211;1516; King of Aragon 1479&#8211;1516) and Isabella I (1451&#8211;1504; Queen of Castile 1474&#8211;1504) in 1469 united the two countries and created the basis of modern Spain.</note> &#8211; was to be brought about by marriage between the respective heads of the <del>states separate</del> &lt;several&gt; states. This marriage took place during the ensuing Whitsun-holydays; &amp; the small flock was then removed to our boarding house, which then took the name of Hayes&#8217;s, but retained it only a few months. For Hayes in disgust at not being appointed Under Master withdrew from the school, &#8211; his wife of course followed his fortunes, &amp; was succeeded by M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Clough<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Mrs Clough (d. 1798).</note> who migrated thither with a few boarders from Abingdon Street. But as Botch Hayes is a person who must make his appearance in the Athenae Cantabrigienses<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Anthony Wood (1632&#8211;1695; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Athenae Oxonienses</title> (1692), a collection of biographies of distinguished figures with University of Oxford connections, had not inspired a Cambridge equivalent. Thomas Hughes did not undertake this work.</note> (if my <del>friend</del> good natured friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesThomas">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughes</ref> carries into effect his intention of compiling such a work) I will say something of him here.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">He was a man who having some skill &amp; much facility in versifying, walked for many years over the Seatonian <del>course</del> race ground at Cambridge, &amp; enjoyed the produce of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Seatons Kislingbury estate without a competitor.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The Seatonian Prize has been awarded annually by the University of Cambridge since 1750 for the best poem in English on a sacred subject. It is open to any MA of the university. The prize was endowed by Thomas Seaton (1684&#8211;1741; <title>DNB</title>), who left his estate at Kislingbury, Northamptonshire, to the university. Hayes won the prize in 1775&#8211;1778 and 1783&#8211;1785.</note> He was moreover what Oldys describes Nahum Tate to have been &#8220;a free, good-natured, fuddling companion, &#8211; to all which qualities his countenance bore witness. With better conduct &amp; better fortunes, Hayes &lt;would have&gt; had learning &amp; talents enough to have deserved &amp; obtained promotion. His want of conduct might in some degree be imputed to ill fortune, &#8211; for his first marriage had <del>pl</del> been an &lt;unhappy if not&gt; imprudent one, &amp; his wife<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> had served him as Michael Angelo did Moses in marble.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">The sculpture of the Old Testament prophet Moses by Michelangelo (1475&#8211;1564) in the Church of San Pietro in Vincoli in Rome (1513&#8211;1515) depicts the prophet with horns on his head, following the description in <title>Exodus</title> 34: 29&#8211;30. This was also used to describe a man whose wife had been unfaithful.</note> When I went to Westminster it was fresh in remembrance that <ref type="m" target="people.html#DoddJamesWilliam">Dodd the Usher</ref> &amp; Porson<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Porson (1759&#8211;1808; <title>DNB</title>), the classical scholar.</note> both intrigued with her, &amp; had <del>once</del> encountered in her bed chamber, when a quarrel took place, &amp; Porson twisted Dodds nose in such a manner, that for many days he could not appear in school. &lt;(By the way this was the first mention I ever heard of Porson.)&gt; Poor Hayes went to the bottle for comfort, his wife did the same, but she drank deeper, &amp; killed herself by so doing &#8211; &amp; Hayes did not wait long after shedding his horns before he married M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Farrer. &#8211; His failings were so notorious, &amp; the boys took such liberties with him (sticking his wig full of paper darts in school -) that it would have been a most unfit thing to have appointed him Under Master when <ref type="m" target="people.html#VincentWilliam">Vincent</ref> succeeded D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Smith. Perhaps he would not have taken offence at being overlooked if a person thoroughly qualified had been chosen, but he could not bear to have an inferior usher (<ref type="m" target="people.html#WingfieldJohn">Wingfield</ref>) who was a person of no talents whatever put over his head, &amp; therefore to the great injury of his worldly affairs &#8211; which could <del>not</del> &lt;ill&gt; bear such a sacrifice, he left the school altogether. &#8211; Hayes &lt;it&gt; was <del>the person</del> who <del>published</del> &lt;edited&gt; those sermons which D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Johnson is supposed to have written for his friend D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Taylor.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Sermons on Different Subjects, Left for Publication by John Taylor</title> (1788&#8211;1789). John Taylor (1711&#8211;1788; <title>DNB</title>) was a clergyman and schoolfriend of Samuel Johnson (1709&#8211;1784; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I was placed in the under fourth, &#8211; a year lower than I might have been if I had learnt to make Latin verses, &#8211; &amp; yet more that a year too high for being properly trained to make them. The manner of introducing a boy into the ways of the school was by placing him for a week or ten days under the direction of one in his own form, who is called his Substance &#8211; the new comer being the Shadow; the Shadow neither taking nor losing place by his own deserts, but following the Substances. A diligent boy is of course chosen for this service, &amp; Smedley<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Smedley (1750&#8211;1825) was educated at Westminster School and Trinity College, Cambridge, BA 1773, MA 1776. He was usher at Westminster School 1774&#8211;1820, and also held a variety of clerical appointments, ending as Rector of North Bovey and Powderham 1816&#8211;1825.</note> the Usher of the fourth to my great joy picked out &lt;<ref type="m" target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">George Strachey</ref>&gt; the very individual on whom <del>I should have fixed</del> my physiognomical eyes &lt;would have rested&gt;, if I might have made a choice throughout the whole school. <ref type="m" target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> &amp; I were friends at first sight, &#8211; but he boarded at home, &amp; it is in the boarding house more than in school that a friend is wanted, &amp; there God knows, I had for some time a solitary heart.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The present Lord Amhurst<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">William Amherst, 1st Earl Amherst (1773&#8211;1857; <title>DNB</title>), succeeded his great-uncle as 2nd Lord Amherst in 1797. He was educated at Westminster and Christ Church, Oxford, and was Governor-General of India 1823&#8211;1828.</note> was head of the house, a mild, inoffensive boy, who interfered with no one, &amp; having a room to himself, lived very much to himself in it, liked &amp; respected by every body. I was in the room with one boy a little younger than myself only worth remembering as being slow &amp; obtuse at what he ought to have learnt, &amp; sharp &amp; mannish in every thing else,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> &#8211; &amp; with Sparrow,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Sparrow (1773&#8211;1805), from a Suffolk landowning family, was admitted to Westminster School in 1785. He succeeded to the estates of his uncle, Sir Robert Bernard, 5th Baronet (c. 1739&#8211;1789), in January 1789 and this may have hastened his early departure from the school. He married Olivia (c. 1778&#8211;1863), daughter of the Irish peer Arthur Acheson, 1st Earl of Gosford (c. 1745&#8211;1807), on 14 March 1797. A religious woman, Lady Olivia was also interested in the education and welfare of the poor. In the 1830s she established schools and encouraged mission work on her estates.</note> afterwards the husband of that sweet creature Lady Olivia. Never was woman of a dove-like nature more unsuitably mated for Sparrow when either in anger or in drink was perfectly frantic. His face was as fine as a countenance could be which expressed so ungovernable &amp; dangerous a temper, &#8211; the finest red &amp; white, dark eyes &amp; brows, &amp; black curling hair; &#8211; but the expression was rather that of a savage than of a civilized being, &amp; no savage could be more violent. He had seasons of good nature, &amp; at the worst was rather to be dreaded than disliked, &#8211; for he was plainly not master of himself. But I had cause to dread him, for he once attempted to hold me by the leg out at the window &#8211; <del>of</del> it was the first floor &#8211; &amp; over a stone area. Had I not <del>struck back</del> struggled in time, &amp; clung to the frame with both hands, my life would probably have been lost. He used <del>at night</del> to pour water into my ear, when I was a bed &amp; asleep, &amp; in many ways exercised such a capricious tyranny &#8211; merely by right of the strongest, for he had no right to fag me, &#8211; that at last I desired M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hayes to remove me into another room. Thither he followed me, &lt;&amp;&gt; at a very late hour one night, <del>in a wild</del> &lt;came in&gt; wrapt in a sheet &amp; thinking to frighten me by personating a ghost, in which character he <del>came &amp; rolled upon my head bed</del>. &lt;threw himself upon the bed &amp; rolled upon me&gt;. Not knowing who it was, but certain that it was flesh &amp; blood, I seized him by the throat, &amp; we made noise enough to occasion an enquiry which ended in requiring Sparrows word that he would molest me no more. <del>&amp;</del> He kept that word faithfully, &amp; left school a few months afterwards, when he was about 17 or 18 &amp; apparently full grown, &#8211; a singularly fine &amp; striking youth &#8211; indeed one of those figures which you always remember vividly. I heard nothing of him till the Irish rebellion, he served in the army there, &amp; there was a story which got into the papers of his meeting a man upon the road &amp; putting him to death without judge or jury upon suspicion of his being a rebel. It was no doubt an act of madness, <del>but in those times every thing</del> was past over. I know not if any proceedings took place &lt;(indeed in those dreadful times every thing was past over) &#8211; but&gt; <del>&amp; indeed</del> he died soon afterwards happily for himself &amp; all who were connected with him.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Sparrow, by then a Lieutenant-Colonel in the Essex Fencibles, was appointed High Sheriff of Armagh on 22 February 1797, as some of the Bernard estates he had inherited included Tandragee Castle in Armagh. In August of the same year, while on patrol, Sparrow stopped Captain William Lucas (1760&#8211;1797) of the Monaghan militia. Lucas refused to accompany Sparrow as his prisoner, and after Sparrow&#8217;s troops refused to shoot, Sparrow attacked Lucas with his sabre, mortally wounding him. Sparrow was tried and convicted at the Armagh Assizes but received a pardon. He died of yellow fever in 1805 on the way home from Barbados.</note> &#8211; Some ten years ago as I was returning from <ref type="m" target="places.html#CrosthwaiteChurch">Keswick Church</ref> after the evening service, Lord Calthorpe<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">George Gough-Calthorpe, 3rd Baron Calthorpe (1787&#8211;1851). </note> accosted me, introduced me to a Lady whose name owing to his low voice I did not catch, &amp; engaged me to dine with him at the Inn;<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Either the Royal Oak hotel or the Queen&#8217;s Head hotel in Keswick.</note> an invitation which perhaps I accepted the more willingly, because there was something in the Ladys countenance &amp; manners particularly pleasing. I was seated next her at table, &amp; opposite was her son<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Acheson Bernard St John Sparrow (c. 1800&#8211;1818).</note> a youth of seventeen, who had just left Harrow &amp; had now a tutor with him.<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> The warmth &amp; unreservedness of her animated manner &lt;had&gt; made me more interested than I commonly am with the conversation of a stranger when I discovered that she was Lady Olivia, Sparrows widow, &amp; that the <del>boy</del> youth was his only son. Thus to fall in with a son of the age at which you had last seen his father, &#8211; is one of those incidents in life that bring home to us the lapse of time with most effect.<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 22&#8211;[23] October 1814, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2492; and Southey to James Montgomery, 29 May 1815, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2607.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> returned to Bristol before the Whitsun holydays, &#8211; for which time to spare the expence of a journey so soon after my entrance at school, I was invited by the good Miss Delameres to Cheshunt. I past <del>my time</del> &lt;three weeks&gt; there very happily, having the use of an excellent microscope, &amp; frequently taking my book into the green house, for the sake of its temperature &amp; the odour of its flowers. During part of the time there were two other guests in the house. The one was a nice good humoured warm hearted girl in the very flower of youth, who was engaged to a <del>Hugenot or</del> French or Swiss <del>Protestant</del> Clergyman Mercier<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis Mercier (d. 1811), Minister of the French London Church in Threadneedle Street 1784&#8211;1811.</note> by name: her own was La Chaumette.<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Susanna de la Chaumette (1769&#8211;1797), daughter of Louis de la Chaumette (1735&#8211;1803), Minister of the French London Church in Threadneedle Street 1761&#8211;1766. She married Louis Mercier in April 1789. Like the Delameres and Dolignons, the de la Chaumettes were of Huguenot descent.</note> She was of Swiss extraction, &amp; having past the preceding year among her relations in the Pays de Vaud, had brought home something like a <hi rend="ital">maladie du pays</hi> if that phrase may be applied to a longing for any country which is not our own &#177;<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">&#177; [Southey&#8217;s mark to indicate an insertion, noted in the left-hand margin: &#8216;it was however &#8230; for Spitalfields&#8217;. We have restored it to its place in his narrative.]</note> &lt; it was however a very natural affection for one who was compelled to exchange Lausanne for Spitalfields&gt;. I used to abuse Switzerland as a land of bears &amp; wolves, &amp; ice &amp; snow for the sake of <del>seex</del> seeing the animation with which she defended &amp; praised it. She married not long afterwards to her hearts content &#8211; &amp; to the very great regret of all who knew her, died in first child bed. Poor Betsy La Chaumette, I thought of her in Switzerland, &amp; when I was at Echichens with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Audrey,<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey first visited Echichens from 1&#8211;3 June 1817. He stayed with John Awdry (1766&#8211;1844), a solicitor in Reybridge and the husband of Jane, n&#233;e Bigg-Wither (1770&#8211;1845), sister of Herbert Hill&#8217;s wife, Catherine. </note> met with a person<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors">While staying at the Awdrys&#8217; on 1 June, Southey met a Protestant Pastor &#8216;by name Conob&#233; (or so it sounded)&#8217; who &#8216;had been in England, &amp; speaks English well&#8217;. They had talked about &#8216;poor&#8217; Betsy de la Chaumette and her family.</note> who knew her &amp; remembered her visit to that country.&lt;see + 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> page&gt;<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey adds a note in the left-hand margin that reads &#8216;see + 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> page&#8217; to indicate that additional material can be found on the third manuscript page of the letter. We have restored it to its place in his narrative: &#8216;I have heard her mother &#8230; with which she accompanied the relation!&#8217;.</note>&lt;I have heard her mother<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne Susanne Louise de la Chaumette, n&#233;e Mieville (1740&#8211;1795).</note> relate an anecdote of herself, which is well worthy of preservation because of another personage to whom it relates also. She was a most lively, good-humoured entertaining woman, &amp; her conversation was the more amusing because it was in broken English, intermingled plentifully with French interjections, in person strong featured, large &amp; plain even to ugliness, if a countenance can be ugly which is always brightened with chearfulness &amp; good nature. There was a M. Giffardiere who held some appointment about the Queen, (I think he used to read French to her) <del>which</del> &amp; was one of those persons with whom the Royal Family were familiar.<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles de Guiffardiere (called Giffardiere) (1740&#8211;1810), Prebendary of Salisbury Cathedral 1792&#8211;1810, Rector of Newington 1794&#8211;1810, Rector of Great Berkhampstead, 1798&#8211;1810. He was a reader of French for Queen Charlotte (1744&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>) and also taught history to her daughters. </note> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> La Chaumette <del>went to</del> was on a visit <del>at his house</del> &lt;to him&gt; at Windsor, &amp; it was insisted upon by the Giffardieres that she must have one of the Lunardi bonnets, &lt;(immortalized by Burns)&gt;<note n="39" place="foot" resp="editors">The lunardi bonnet, balloon-shaped headgear made fashionable by the aerial exploits of Vincenzo Lunardi (1759&#8211;1806), was mentioned in &#8216;To a Louse: on Seeing One On a Lady&#8217;s Bonnet at Church&#8217; (1786), line 35, by Robert Burns (1759&#8211;1796; <title>DNB</title>).</note> which were then in fashion (it being the first age of balloons); this she resisted most <hi rend="ital">womanfully</hi>, pleading her time of life &amp; ugliness with characteristic volubility &amp; liveliness, but to no purpose; her eloquence was overruled, &amp; as nobody could appear without such a bonnet, such a bonnet she had. All this went to the Palace, for Kings &amp; Queens are sometimes as much pleased at being acquainted with private affairs, as their subjects are in conversing upon public ones &#8211; <del>xx</del> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> La Chaumettes conversation was worth reporting &lt;even to a King,&gt; &amp; she was so original a person that the King<note n="40" place="foot" resp="editors">George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of Great Britain 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> knew her very well by character, &amp; was determined to see her. Accordingly he stopt his horse one day before Giffardieres <del>window</del> &lt;apartments&gt;, &amp; after talking a while with him, asked if M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> La Chaumette was within, &amp; desired she might be called to the window. She came in all the agitation &lt;or <hi rend="ital">fluster</hi>,&gt; that such a summons was likely to excite. The King spoke to her with his <del>characteristic</del> &lt;wonted&gt; good-nature, asked her a few questions, hoped she liked Windsor, &amp; concluded by saying he was glad to hear she had consented at last to have a Lunardi bonnet. &#8211; Trifling as this is, it is a sort of trifling in which none but a kind-hearted <del>man</del> &lt;King&gt; would have indulged, &amp; I believe no one ever heard the story without liking <del>the King</del> &lt;George 3&gt; the better for it. How well do I remember the looks &lt;&amp; tones&gt; &amp; gestures of <hi rend="ital">mon Dieus</hi> with which she accompanied the relation!&gt; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> James Beresford<note n="41" place="foot" resp="editors">James Beresford (1764&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>), a writer and clergyman, Fellow of Merton College, Oxford 1787&#8211;1812, Rector of Kibworth 1812&#8211;1840. He was the author of <title>The Aeneid of Virgil</title> (1794) but found fame with <title>The Miseries of Human Life</title> (1806).</note> was the other guest, &#8211; an unsuccessful translator of Virgil, &#8211; but the very successful author of the Miseries of Human Life. || &lt;|| see p.4&gt;<note n="42" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey adds a note in the left-hand margin that reads &#8216;|| see p.4&#8217; to indicate that additional material can be found on the fourth manuscript page of the letter. We have restored it to its place in his narrative: &#8216;He was then a young man &#8230; cost poor Beresford a flogging&#8217;.</note> &lt; He was then a young man &#8211; <del>if I remember rightly</del> &lt;either&gt; just in orders, &#8211; or on the point of being ordained.<note n="43" place="foot" resp="editors">Beresford had attended Charterhouse School 1773&#8211;1780 and Merton College, Oxford, where he graduated as BA, 1786. He was ordained as a deacon on 9 November 1788 and a priest on 25 April 1789, serving as Rector of Hawridge, Buckinghamshire 1789&#8211;1792, before resigning his living.</note> This story was then remembered of him at the Charter House, that he was equally remarkable <del>remarkabl</del> for his noisiness &amp; his love of music, &#8211; &amp; having one day skipt school to attend a concert, xxx there was such an unusual quietness in consequence of his absence that the master, &lt;looked round &amp; said&gt; &#8211; Where is Beresford? I am sure he cannot be <del>here</del> &lt;in school&gt;, &#8211; &amp; the detection thus brought about cost poor Beresford a flogging.&gt; Him too I never saw after that visit, &amp; with all his pleasantness &amp; good nature he left upon me an unpleasant impression from a trifling circumstance which I remember as indicative of my own moral temper at that time. Our holydays exercise was to compose a certain number of Latin verses from any part of Thompsons Spring.<note n="44" place="foot" resp="editors">James Thomson (1700&#8211;1748; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Seasons</title> (1728&#8211;1730).</note> I did my task doggedly, in such a manner that it was impossible any exercise could have been more unlike a good one, or <del>at</del> &lt;yet&gt; the <del>same time</del> &lt;very best could not&gt; have more effectually proved the diligence with which it had been made. There was neither a decent line, nor a false quantity in the whole. The Ladies made me show it to Beresford, &amp; he instead of saying in &#8216;good natured sincerity &#8211; &#8220;&#8216;you have never been taught to make verses but it is plain that you have taken great pains <del>x</del> in making these, &#8211; &amp; therefore I am sure the Usher will give you credit for what you have done,&#8221; &#8211; returned them to me <del>with the absurd</del> saying Sir &#8211; I see you&#8217;ll be another Virgil one of these days. &#8211; I knew that this was neither deserved as praise nor as mockery: &amp; I felt then as I have continued to do that <del>undeserved</del> &lt;unmerited&gt; censure <del>provides</del> &lt;brings with it&gt; its own <del>balm</del> &lt;antidote&gt; in the sense of injustice which it provokes, but that nothing is too mortifying as <del>the</del> praise &lt;to&gt; which you are conscious &lt;that&gt; you have <del>not deserved</del> no claim.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Smedley <del>was then Usher of the</del> spoke to me sensibly &amp; kindly about this <del>verse</del> &lt;exercise&gt; &amp; put me in training as far as could then be done. He had no reason to complain of my want of good will &#8211; for before the next holydays I <del>composed</del> &lt;wrote&gt; a poem about fifty long &amp; short verses upon the death of Fair Rosamond<note n="45" place="foot" resp="editors">Rosamund Clifford (b. before 1140?, d. 1175/6; <title>DNB</title>), mistress of Henry II (1133&#8211;1189; King of England 1154&#8211;1189; <title>DNB</title>). The schoolboy Latin poem does not survive, but in March 1793, while a student at Oxford, Southey visited Rosamund&#8217;s reputed burial place at Godstow. This formed the subject for Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Rosamund to Henry. Written after Taking the Veil&#8217;, <title>Poems</title> (Bath, 1795), pp. 85&#8211;95; and an inscription &#8216;For a Tablet at Godstow Nunnery&#8217;, published in the second edition of his <title>Poems</title> (Bristol, 1797), p. 131. </note> which I put into his hands. The &lt;composition&gt; was bad enough I dare say in many respects, but it <del>bore</del>&lt;gave&gt; proofs of good progress, &lt;they were verses to the ear as well as to the fingers&gt; &amp; I remember them sufficiently to know that the attempt was that of a poet. It is <del>more</del> worth remembering as being the only Latin <del>verses</del> &lt;poem&gt; that I ever composed voluntarily. But there my ambition ended when I was so far upon a footing with the rest of the remove that I could make verses decent enough to pass muster, I was satisfied. <del>knowing</del> It was in English &amp; not in <del>Latin</del> heathen Latin that &#8211; </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">the sacred Sisters for their own</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Baptized me in the springs of Helicon.<note n="46" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s adapts his <title>The Lay of the Laureate</title> (1816), &#8216;Proem&#8217;, lines 17&#8211;18. In Greek mythology, the Hippocrene spring on Mount Helicon was sacred to the nine Muses and the source of poetic inspiration.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent0"> &amp; I also knew &#8211; tho I did not know Lope de Vega had said it, that </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Todo paxaro en su nido</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Natural canto mantiene,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">En que ser perfeto viene;</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Porque en el canto aprendido</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Mil imperfeciones tiene<note n="47" place="foot" resp="editors">Lope Felix de Vega Carpio (1562&#8211;1635), <title>Isidro. Poema Castellano</title> (1599), Canto 1, lines 31&#8211;35. This stanza was quoted and translated into English by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (October, 1817), 35&#8211;36, as: &#8216;Every bird that free as day/ Sports his native woods among/ Warbles well its native song:/ Is it taught another lay?/ Then it falters and goes wrong.&#8217;</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1">
          <date when="1824-10-17">Oct. 17. 1824</date>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>