<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4247. Robert Southey to John Rickman, 12 September 1824</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4247Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4247. Robert Southey to John Rickman, 12 September 1824</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4247Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4247" type="letter">
        <head>4247. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1824-09-12">12 September 1824</date>
          </head><p>Endorsement: 12 Sept<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &#8211; &#8211; 24<lb />
               MS: Huntington Library, RS 452. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 439&#8211;440 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-09-12">12 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My Dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  Thank you for your letter, &#8211; &amp; for the Chidham statistics,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Chidham is a parish in Sussex; it contained the family home of Susannah Rickman, and Rickman had written to Southey from there on 8 September 1824.</note> which by the method &amp; the <hi rend="ital">multum in parvo</hi>
          <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;much in little&#8217;.</note> I should have known to be yours. The letter travels back for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha&#8217;s</ref> profit. The fault which you notice consists I believe a good deal manner, &amp; arises not from any deficiency in the sense of kindness, as from timidity &amp; a sense of awkwardness in expressing it. I think so from what I know of her nature, as well as because she expresses in her letters a very warm sense of the kindness she is experiencing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">So you have a built a house,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman was building a country house near Portsmouth.</note> the thing of all things which I have for many years desired to do, &#8211; but then mine <del>x</del> must have been in a situation to my hearts content, with a clear stream running thro the grounds, near enough, &amp; secure enough in its privacy for the women to bathe there. &#8211; May you live to enjoy your new domicile as long as life is desirable: &#8211; &amp; may you have many Sessions as little pugnacious &amp; therefore as little prolonged as the last.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The parliamentary session of 1824 only lasted from 3 February to 25 June, making it three weeks shorter than its predecessor in 1823.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am well pleased that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> has had so good an opportunity of seeing the details of agricultural life; &#8211; here she had no means of observing them. She has grown up with a love of the country, &amp; it is well <del>of</del> if a love of rural occupations &amp; a country life should be added to it. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Her mother</ref> has trained her in habits of wise frugality, &amp; she has good domestic qualities, which let her lot be what it may, cannot but be useful. We miss her &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">her sister</ref>, as you may suppose. And yet I think <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Berthas</ref> absence has <del>been</del> had good effect upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref>, who has certainly made great progress in her lessons since she has not had <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> to rely on.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You have heard that I am engaged in an incredible number of works. The booksellers are to blame for sometimes announcing as an intention what has been mentioned as a project for consideration, &#8211; but the truth is twofold, to wit 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> that I have (&amp; am aware of having) a propensity for planning works &#8220;of great pith &amp; moment&#8221;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Hamlet</title>, Act 3, scene 1, line 87.</note> which leads me to dream of more than can ever by possibility be fulfilled, &#8211; &amp; 2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi> that in pursuing any one of my determined engagements, I am continually meeting with something applicable to other schemes, not yet in course of execution, &amp; in this way while rearing one edifice, I collect materials for others. It is not with me as it would be if I had nothing to consider but how to employ my time either most worthily or most agreably to my own desires. While I have some thing before me to be pursued for its own sake, I must of necessity have something in hand for the Ways &amp; Means of the year, &#8211; something on the present sale of which I can rely. If I have many irons in the fire, one reason therefore is <del>because</del> &lt;that&gt; there is a large pot to boil. Now I have <del>rea</del> grounds for believing that the part of my time which must be devoted to this essential object could in no way be so profitably employed as in sketching our civil history, with a view of showing the growth &amp; progress of our institutions, &amp; treating those portions fairly &amp; fearlessly, <del>upon</del> &lt;concerning&gt; which the greatest prejudices prevail.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write this work.</note> Three 8vos would suffice for this, down to the death of Anne;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne (1665&#8211;1714; Queen of Great Britain 1701&#8211;1714; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; then I should think of following it up with the Age of George 3<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of Great Britain 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; introduced by a brief view of the two intermediate reigns.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The objection is what you point out, the wide course of reading wherein I should be tempted to discurse. Of that however I should not have much apprehension, if I were provided with the books</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At present I am <del>x</del> getting on well with my second volume,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &amp; with certain minora,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;minor works&#8217;.</note> &#8211; the Dialogues being one.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.s</ref> note arrived to day, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> is much obliged by her kind solicitude. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> will have received two communications before this packet arrives. In case of any future suspension, let her be <hi rend="ital">angry</hi> rather than <hi rend="ital">fearful</hi>, in the certainty that ill news always travels fast.</p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
           RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>