<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4298. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, [19 December 1824]</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4298Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4298. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, [19 December 1824]</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4298Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4298" type="letter">
        <head>4298. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1824-12-19">[19 December 1824]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer.<lb />
               Endorsements: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 23 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1824; &#163;30 to E.S.; Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 23 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1824; Notes sent/ 13762. &#163;20 &#8211; 17 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1824/ 19563 10 13 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1824<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Unpublished.<lb />
               Dating note: Dating from content: Southey&#8217;s observation that he will write to Sharon Turner &#8216;this night&#8217;. Southey to John Taylor Coleridge, 21 December 1824 (Letter 4300) indicates that Southey had written to Turner two days earlier, i.e. 19 December 1824.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It never can be worth while to take any notice of so foul &amp; atrocious an attack as this which you have sent me.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 17 December 1824, published a letter headed &#8216;Southey versus Lord Byron&#8217;. Although this contained a sustained attack on Southey, he eventually decided not to take legal action.</note> &#8211; The single truth in <del>thxx</del> &lt;it&gt; is that in my letters from Portugal a disbelief of the eternity of hell-torments is declared, &#8211; which disbelief I am ready to repeat whenever it is needful.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The fifth point in the <title>Morning Chronicle</title> letter was: &#8216;Has Mr. Southey, or has he not, in one of his publications, declared his disbelief of the leading doctrine of the Scriptures &#8211; namely, Eternal Punishment in a Future State. Has he not even called it there damnable and impious; and has he not, in his other publications, represented it to be a Divine Truth, and necessary to justify God&#8217;s moral government of the world?&#8217; Southey believed this to refer to his <title>Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp. 525&#8211;532, where he discussed &#8216;the diabolical belief of eternal punishment&#8217; (p. 525).</note> Other charges are founded upon Espriella,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England: Translated from the Spanish by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella</title> (1807). The seventh point in the <title>Morning Chronicle</title> letter was: &#8216;Has Mr. Southey, or has he not, published a work without his name, in which he holds up the Roman Catholic Church as the one true Church of Christ, the Reformation in England as no Reformation at all, but the destruction of her best institutions, both moral, civil, and religious, and in which he represents her Reformers as a pack of rascals altogether? And has he not published another work since with his name, [<title>The Book of the Church</title>, 1824] in which he has extolled the Church of England, represented the Church of Rome as the whore of Babylon, the reformation of the light of the world, and the reformers of the glory of it?&#8217;</note> as if in personating a true Spaniard I had been stating my own opinion of the Catholic faith! the &lt;first,&gt; last,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The first point in the <title>Morning Chronicle</title> letter was: &#8216;Was Mr. Southey, or was he not, during the French Revolution, a member of a republican revolutionary society? And did he, or did he not, at that time openly avow himself to be a republican and a revolutionist?&#8217; Southey had not, in fact, been a member of a &#8216;revolutionary society&#8217;, but he had certainly been a republican. The eighth and final point was: &#8216;Has Mr. Southey, or has he not, in one of his publications, raked up and collected together (note upon note, and line upon line) the most salacious, prurient, and filthy witticisms upon the most awful and sacred subjects, upon the Vessel of Incarnation chosen for the redemption of mankind, upon the Salutation of the Angel, upon the formation of our Holy Redeemer in the uterus, and upon the practicability of clergymen baptizing children in the vagina of their mothers&#8217; wombs before they were brought into the world?&#8217;</note> &amp; that about O Meara <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The third point in the <title>Morning Chronicle</title> letter was: &#8216;Has Mr. Southey, or has he not, in one of his publications, stigmatised the character of Mr. Barry O&#8217;Meara, for being expelled from the army (though it was only for fighting a duel, a thing very natural in a fighting man), and was he, or was he not, himself long before expelled from Balliol College, in Oxford, and if so, for what was he expelled; and when Ministers sent for Mr. Southey to Oxford for a LL.D. did Balliol or did any other College in Oxford enroll him as a Member of it?&#8217; Barry Edward O&#8217;Meara (1786&#8211;1836) attended Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815) as his doctor on St Helena 1815&#8211;1818 and published <title>Napoleon in Exile, or a Voice from St Helena</title> (1822). When he encountered Napoleon, O&#8217;Meara held an appointment in the Navy. He had previously been Assistant-Surgeon to the 62nd Regiment in the Army but had been dismissed in 1807 for acting as the second in a duel. O&#8217;Meara&#8217;s conduct had been attacked in the review of his book in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), 219&#8211;264 (220), published 15 February 1823. The review was by Croker, but, as it was anonymous, it could easily be misattributed to Southey, a well-known writer for the <title>Quarterly</title> and critic of Napoleon. Southey had not been expelled from Balliol, but left voluntarily in 1794; he had, though, been expelled from Westminster School in 1792.</note>&lt;&amp; the expulsion from College&gt; are lies <hi rend="ital">in toto</hi>, without the slightest foundation or <del>resemblance</del> shadow of truth. &#8211; The whole is too bad to be noticed. And perhaps you do not know that the Editor of the M Chronicle<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Black (1783&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>), editor of the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 1817&#8211;1843.</note> is a thorough-paced scoundrel, &#8211; or you would not talk of the respectability of that paper.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My letter<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 8 December 1824, Letter 4289, published 13 December 1824.</note> has annoyed these villains, as much as the former one<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776, published 11 January 1822.</note> enraged <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref>: Let them spit their venom till they blacken their own lips with it. The only answer that could be given to such an assailant would be to spit in his face, call him liar, &amp; knock him down.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  The only question is whether it would not be fitting to prosecute the M. Chronicle upon the last charge. Upon this I will take advice For that the passage is libellous there can surely be no doubt, at least there would be none, if law were <del>any thing</del> not the rascally craft it is.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Will you &#8211; who are my high treasurer &amp; sole resource in time of need, &#8211; send thirty pounds to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref>.</p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
            RS.
        </p>
        <postscript>
          <lb />
          <p rend="indent1">I write this night to <del>Turner[Sharon]</del>, &amp; shall be guided by his advice, caring very little what that determination may be, for such enemies can do me no injury &amp; give me no molestation.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>