<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4303. Robert Southey to John Taylor Coleridge, 24 December 1824</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4303Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4303. Robert Southey to John Taylor Coleridge, 24 December 1824</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4303Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4303" type="letter">
        <head>4303. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1824-12-24">24 December 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ J.T. Coleridge Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 2. Pump Court/ Temple.<lb />
               Postmark: 7. NIGHT.7/ 27. DE/ 1824; Bge St West<lb />
               Endorsement: 1824 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>/ R Southey Keswick<lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47553. ALS; 6p.<lb />
               Previously published: W. Braekman, &#8216;Letters by Robert Southey to Sir John Taylor Coleridge&#8217;, <title>Studia Germanica Gandensia</title>, 6 (1964), 139&#8211;141.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.<date when="1824-12-24"> 24. Dec. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  I am heartily glad that the QR. is in your hands,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Taylor Coleridge was editor of the <title>Quarterly Review</title> 1824&#8211;1825.</note> &#8211; for many reasons public &amp; private. That it will injure your professional interests I do not think, &amp; I am quite sure that in rescuing a part of your time from professional pursuits, it will promote your better interests, &amp; enable you to exercise a wider &amp; much more beneficial influence! That Journal will now become what it ought to be. I am not so hasty as to suppose a thorough reform can be immediately effected: but we shall at least make peace with America, without delay, &amp; have no more such papers as those upon Keats &amp; Maturin.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Two notoriously hostile reviews by John Wilson Croker: of John Keats (1795&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Endymion: a Poetic Romance</title> (1818), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 204&#8211;208, published 26 September 1818; and of Charles Maturin (1782&#8211;1824), <title>Melmoth, the Wanderer. By the Author of Bertram</title> (1820), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 24 (January 1821), 303&#8211;311, published 6 April 1821.</note> You will be able to avoid gross offences at first, &#8211; &amp; gradually to bring it in all its departments to something like consistency, &amp; to your own standard.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now let me say something about contributors. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> will be a very competent one: but one upon whom you never can depend for punctuality. You will do well therefore never to reckon upon a paper from him, till you receive it, &amp; taking him with that caution, it will be as serviceable to the Review to employ him, as it will for him to be so employed. There is another person of whom just the same may be said, &amp; whom <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> wished to engage many years ago &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#DeQuinceyThomas">De Quincey</ref>. There is no man who can so well supply some papers upon German literature, in any of its branches, a subject <del>upon</del> &lt;in&gt; which the QR. has hitherto been wholly deficient. It is with him precisely as with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref>; he is very able &#8211; &amp; not to be depended on.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must get <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother</ref> to bring you acquainted with <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorHenrySir">Henry Taylor</ref>, &#8211; for his sake. It will do him good, &amp; he is worth all that can be done for him. That paper upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landors</ref> Conversations<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A review of Landor&#8217;s <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title> (1824), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (January 1824), 508&#8211;519, published 28 August 1824, by Henry Taylor (though amended by William Gifford).</note> is his &#8211; I have not seen it (for <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> forgot to send me the last number,) &#8211; but I know from himself that it was originally written in a very reprehensible spirit, &amp; made ten times worse by <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>, &#8211; who struck out all the qualifying &amp; redeeming parts &#8211; <hi rend="ital">more suo</hi>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;in his own manner&#8217;.</note> &#8211; But you will form a better opinion of <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorHenrySir">Henry Taylor</ref> if you will look at some memoirs of Charles Featherstonehaugh in <del>one of</del> the London Magazine for one of the last spring months.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Taylor, &#8216;Memoir and Remains of Charles Foster Featherstonehaugh&#8217;, <title>London Magazine</title>, 9 (February 1824), 133&#8211;139.</note> You will see there not only how he writes &#8211; but some thing very like his own history.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I must tell you more of him. At present he is in the Colonial Office, &#8211; &amp; in a fair way, from his talents, of becoming one day a very considerable person. In fact whoever may be the mouth piece for that office, what is in that mouth will come from his head. &#8211; He is a fine, generous, noble, creature. But he wants religion: &#8211; more by his misfortune than his fault; for he was not trained up in the way that he should go.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Taylor had largely been educated at home by his father, an enthusiast for the principles of William Godwin (1756&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorGeorge">His father</ref> (a most extraordinary man for acquirements, talents, &amp; strength of character) is the second of three brothers: The elder of whom, William Taylor was a Northumberland Laird, born to a good property, &#8211; I think the estate was let for 1200 a year.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">George Taylor was actually the third and youngest of three brothers. His two elder brothers were: William Taylor (1761&#8211;1826) and Thomas Forster Taylor (b. 1769). Both attended Trinity College, Cambridge. William Taylor inherited the small estate of Swinhoe-Broomford in Northumberland.</note> This head of the family was ruined by the French Revolution, &#8211; in a manner most honourable to himself, &#8211; &amp; which you will know how to appreciate, tho it is hardly to be expected that any man who did not live in those stirring times, can tell what the elevation of mind was which they produced. He thought the law of primogeniture unjust, &amp; therefore &#8211; without dividing the estate, gave his brothers their equal share of <del>the</del> its worth, &#8211; &amp; thus embarrassed himself for life &#8211; without benefitting them.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Taylor, <title>Autobiography of Henry Taylor</title>, 2 vols (London, 1885), I, p. 5, relates the estate&#8217;s difficulties were caused by a prolonged lawsuit over a property in Kent.</note> The younger brother squandered his portion, &#8211; &amp; with it his character, &#8211; so that he has disappeared from society.&lt;<ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorGeorge">George</ref>&gt; The second (<ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorHenrySir">Henry T&#8217;s</ref> father) was afflicted with a complaint in the eyes, just at the time when he ought to have gone to college; &#8211; &amp; during those years his education was finished (I will venture to say <hi rend="ital">better</hi> than it would then have been done at college) by William, &#8211; who read to him, while he sate in darkness. These two brothers farmed together in the county of Durham, &amp; were well known as some of the most scientific farmers in England. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorGeorge">George</ref> married &amp; was early left a widower with three sons.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">George Taylor married Eleanor Ashworth (1766&#8211;1802), the daughter of a Durham ironmonger, in 1797. They had three sons: George Taylor (c. 1798&#8211;1817); William Taylor (c. 1799&#8211;1817); and Henry Taylor.</note> He educated them himself, &#8211; &amp; I will venture to say that no family could produce three brothers of greater promise. The two elder grew up &amp; were both in a public office,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">George Taylor was an Assistant in the Office for Auditing the Public Accounts, but William Taylor was studying medicine. It was Henry Taylor who held the other minor government post, with the Storekeeper-General.</note> when the one was seized with typhus, &#8211; the other caught it in nursing him, &#8211; &amp; the father arrived in London &#8211; to find the one dead, &#8211; &amp; witness the death of the other.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The blow could not have fallen upon a man who would have felt it more, &#8211; or borne it better. For whatever has been said of Roman or Stoic virtue is to be found in <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorGeorge">G. Taylor</ref>. In the course of my experience (which has not been a very limited one, even tho I have long lived in retirement) &#8211; I have only known one other person who was so compleatly </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Lord of his own resolves, of his own heart absolute master: &#8211; <note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1822), Canto 6, line 20.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  &amp; that was <ref type="m" target="people.html#SewardEdmund">my early friend Edmund Seward</ref>, to whom I owe more than to any other human being.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">His boys were bred up in the highest principles of honour &amp; integrity &#8211; but for religion they were left at large; &#8211; the disease of the family was a dislike to existing establishments. I suppose if the &lt;<ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorGeorge">father</ref>&gt; had called himself any thing it would have been an Unitarian. Time &amp; affliction have wrought a great change in him. He married again about three or four years ago,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">George Taylor married, for a second time in 1818, Jane Mills (1770&#8211;1853), daughter of Henry Mills (1737&#8211;1807), a minor landowner in County Durham, wine merchant and partner in the Durham bankers, Mills, Hopper &amp; Co.</note> &#8211; the attachment had been of long standing, &#8211; but the marriage was delayed till he &lt;should&gt; have fulfilled his duty to his children: &#8211; nor did it take place till after the loss of the two eldest. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">My brother</ref> will tell you more of him, &#8211; &amp; what I have said will induce you to regard <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorHenrySir">his son</ref> with some interest. But the young man is a most promising person, with the heart &amp; mind of a poet.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  If you would like an article (&amp; it would be very useful at this time) upon the quiet, real &#8211; substantial reforms which are going on in the North of Germany, <ref type="m" target="people.html#RobinsonHenryCrabb">Henry Robinson</ref> can supply you with one. I think you know him: but if you do not, he may be applied to thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref>, &#8211; or thro me.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Despite Southey&#8217;s helpful advice, none of Hartley Coleridge, Thomas de Quincey, Henry Taylor or Henry Crabb Robinson contributed to the <title>Quarterly Review</title> during John Taylor Coleridge&#8217;s brief editorship.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A word or two now concerning my own contributions. I have begun Bayard for your first number;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Sara Coleridge&#8217;s translation, <title>The Right Joyous and Pleasant History of the Feats, Gests, and Prowesses of the Chevalier Bayard, the Good Knight without Fear and without Reproach</title> (1825). Unsurprisingly, Southey gave this a glowing recommendation in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (October 1825), 355&#8211;397.</note> &amp; am planning (as I mentioned in my last) a paper on the Church-Societies.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 32 (June 1825), 1&#8211;42. This was (ostensibly) a review of <title>An Abstract of the Annual Reports and Correspondence of the Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, from the Commencement of its Connexion with the East India Missions, A. D. 1709, to the Present Day</title> (1814); and of the Church Missionary Society&#8217;s <title>Missionary Register</title> (1813&#8211;1824), no. 1962 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. The latter organisation was founded in 1799 by evangelical Anglicans.</note> You shall have an article regularly for every number for some time to come, &amp; if you desire, a shorter paper also upon any book of travels,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Marianne Baillie (1788&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Lisbon in the Years 1821, 1822 and 1823</title> (1824), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 378&#8211;390, published 11 March 1825.</note> &#8211; it is but to say so. And it will be well to make a good shew of strength at your commencement. Tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to send me the new edition of Baxters Works, that I may write a life of him for you.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The Puritan clergyman, Richard Baxter (1615&#8211;1691; <title>DNB</title>). It is not clear which edition of his works Southey is referring to: he may have heard of the forthcoming <title>The Practical Works of the Rev. Richard Baxter with a Life of the Author and a Critical Examination of his Writings</title> (1830), edited by William Orme (1787&#8211;1830; <title>DNB</title>). Southey did not write on the subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> This I shall enjoy doing. I have his own Life &amp; times,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Baxter, <title>Narrative of His Life and Times</title> (1696), no. 239 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; &amp; I have also as most useful auxiliaries Ormes rascally life of Owen (upon whom (i.e. Orme) the lash shall be well laid.)<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">William Orme (1787&#8211;1830; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life, Writings, and Religious Connections of John Owen D. D.</title> (1820), no. 2062 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This was a biography of the Nonconformist theologian, John Owen (1616&#8211;1683; <title>DNB</title>).</note> Jacksons life of Goodwin,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Jackson (1783&#8211;1873; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of Thomas Goodwin, A. M.</title> (1822), no. 1490 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This was a biography of the Nonconformist preacher, John Goodwin (1594&#8211;1655; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; that rich repository of ill arranged materials Nichols&#8217;s Arminianism &amp; Calvinism compared.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">James Nichols (1785&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Calvinism and Arminianism Compared in their Principles and Tendency</title> (1824), no. 2032 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> I have also cart loads of Quakerism, so that I want only Baxters own works</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Another subject that I can undertake is the present state of Portugal.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> at this time, beyond his comments in his review of Marianne Baillie (1788&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Lisbon in the Years 1821, 1822 and 1823</title> (1824), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 378&#8211;390, published 11 March 1825.</note>
        </p>
        <p>
           And now God bless you &#8211;<lb/>
            yrs affectionately<lb/>
           RS.
        </p>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">I am desired to say that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> thanks you for your letter, &#8211; &amp; that <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C. </ref> will communicate your message to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref>.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">An invitation to Hartley Coleridge to write for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; I had nearly forgotten to say that I shall thankfully receive your Blackstone<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">John Taylor Coleridge had just edited the sixth edition of Sir William Blackstone (1723&#8211;1780; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Commentaries on the Laws of England</title> (1825), no. 305 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>