<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Robert Southey and Millenarianism: </title>
                <title type="subordinate">Documents Concerning the Prophetic Movements of the Romantic
                    Era</title>
                <editor>
                    <name>Tim Fulford</name>
                </editor>
                <editor role="editor">Tim Fulford</editor>
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor,</resp>
                    <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor,</resp>
                    <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Laura Mandell</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="nines">rce6000</idno>
                <idno type="edition">Espriella</idno>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                    Maryland</publisher>
                <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                <date when="2011-11-01">June 1, 2012</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                        or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                        purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                        use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                        are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                        with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                        permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                        requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                        notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
                        forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
                    </p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                        conditions: <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                        them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                        have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                        Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                        continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                        generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                        a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                        use.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title level="a" type="main">From Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez
                            Espriella</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Robert</forename>
                                <surname>Southey</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m" type="main">Robert Southey and Millenarianism: </title>
                        <title level="m" type="subordinate">Documents Concerning the Prophetic Movements of the Romantic
                            Era</title>
                        <editor>
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Tim</forename>
                                <surname>Fulford</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                                Maryland</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                            <date when="2011-11-01">November 1, 2011</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>APEX used utf-8 codes for quotation marks, hyphens, and all special characters; except in the introduction, "hi rend="ital" has been used for titles.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                    10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smcap" scheme="css">font-variant:small-caps;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                    xml:id="genre">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                        http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                        on 2009-02-26</bibl>
                    <category xml:id="g1">
                        <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g2">
                        <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g3">
                        <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g4">
                        <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g5">
                        <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g7">
                        <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g6">
                        <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g8">
                        <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g9">
                        <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g10">
                        <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g11">
                        <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g12">
                        <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g13">
                        <catDesc>History</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g14">
                        <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g15">
                        <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g16">
                        <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g17">
                        <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g18">
                        <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g19">
                        <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g20">
                        <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g21">
                        <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g22">
                        <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g23">
                        <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g24">
                        <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g25">
                        <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g26">
                        <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g27">
                        <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g28">
                        <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g29">
                        <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g30">
                        <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g31">
                        <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g32">
                        <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g33">
                        <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g34">
                        <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g4"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
                <date>2012-25-04</date>
                <list>
                    <item>change to RC TEI Headers</item>
                    <item>runs transforms to html</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="extract">                
                <head>From Robert Southey, <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez
                Espriella</title> (London, 1807)</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head> </head>
                <p>I had prepared for you an account of a pseudo-prophet who excited much attention
                    in London here at the beginning of the last war, when, almost by accident, I was
                    made acquainted with some singular circumstances which are in some manner
                    connected with him, and which therefore should previously be told. These
                    circumstances are as authentic as they are extraordinary, and supply a curious
                    fact for the history of the French Revolution.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">We were talking one evening of the Abbé Barruel’s proofs of a
                    conspiracy against the governments, religion and morality of Christendom. <note
                        n="1" place="foot" resp="editor">Abbé Augustin Barruel (1741-1820), a French
                        Jesuit who had fled France after the revolution and was living in Britain,
                        was in 1797 the author of <title>Mémoires pour server à l’Histoire du
                            Jacobinisme</title>, translated as <title>Memoirs Illustrating the
                            History of Jacobinism</title>. In this highly popular conspiracy theory,
                        he attributed the revolution to a series of societies holding mystical
                        beliefs and observing secret rituals—the <hi rend="ital">Illuminati</hi>—and
                        dedicated to destroying the Catholic Church and the states that supported
                        it.</note> A friend of J.’s said, there was about as much truth in it as in
                    one of Madame Scudery’s romances;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editor">The
                        novels of Madelaine de Scudéry (1607-1701) featured unlikely plots, in which
                        the heroines suffered multiple abductions at the hands of Oriental
                        despots.</note> the characters introduced were real persons, to whom false
                    motives and manners were imputed; a little of what was ascribed to them had
                    really occurred, but the whole plot, colouring and costume of the book were
                    fictitious. It was a work, said he, written to serve the purposes of a party,
                    with the same spirit and the same intent as those which in old times led to such
                    absurd and monstrous calumnies against the Jews; and had its intent succeeded,
                    there would have been a political St. Bartholomew’s day in England. True it was
                    that a society had existed whose object was to change or to influence the
                    governments of Europe; it was well organized and widely extended, but
                    enthusiasm, not infidelity, was the means which they employed.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">In proof of this he stated the sum of what I shall relate more at
                    length from the book to which he referred as his authority, and which I obtained
                    from him the next morning. Its title is this,—<title level="m">A revealed Knowledge of
                        some Things that will speedily be fulfilled in the World, communicated to a
                        Number of Christians brought together at Avignon, by the Power of the Spirit
                        of God from all Nations; now published by his Divine Command, for the Good
                        of all Men, by John Wright his Servant, and one of the Brethren. London,
                        printed in Year of Christ</title> 1794. It is one of those innumerable
                    pamphlets which, being published by inferior booksellers, and circulating among
                    sectarians and fanatics, never rise into the hands of those who are called the
                    public, and escape the notice of all the literary journals. They who peruse them
                    do it with a zeal which may truly be called consuming; they are worn out like a
                    schoolboy grammar; the form in which they are sent abroad, without covers to
                    protect them, hastens their destruction, and in a few years they disappear for
                    ever.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#WrightJohn">John Wright</ref>, the author
                    of this narrative, was a working carpenter of Leeds in Yorkshire; a man of
                    strong devotional feelings, who seems, like the first Quakers, to have hungered
                    and thirsted after religious truth in a land where there was none to impart it.
                    Some travelling Swedenborgian preachers having heated his imagination, he was
                    desirous of removing to London to find out the New Jerusalem Church.<note n="3"
                        place="foot" resp="editor">The Swedish mystical author Emmanuel Swedenborg
                        (1688-1772), who claimed, after a spiritual awakening in 1758, to be able to
                        visit heaven and hell and communicate with spirits, died in London. There, a
                        number of Protestant dissenters and Anglican clergymen proved receptive to
                        his books and in May 1787 the Swedenborgian New Jerusalem Church was
                        established and began to send missionaries across the country; by April
                        1789, when the first General Conference was held in Eastcheap attended by
                        Bryan’s fellow engraver William Blake, several churches had been
                        established.</note> It was no easy thing for a labouring man with a large
                    family to remove to such a distance: however, by working over hours he saved
                    money enough to effect it. The New Jerusalem Church did not satisfy him; every
                    thing was too definite and formal, too bodily and gross for a mind of his
                    complexion. But it so happened that at this place of worship he entered into
                    talk with a converted Jew,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editor">A converted Jew
                        named Samuel. See John Wright, <title level="m">A Revealed Knowledge of Some Things
                            That Will Speedily be Fulfilled in the World</title> (London, 1794), p.
                        4.</note> who, when he learnt his state of mind, and that he expected the
                    restoration of the Jews would shortly be accomplished, said to him, I will tell
                    you of a man who is just like yourself;—his name is <ref
                        target="people.html#BryanWilliam">William Bryan</ref>, and he lives in such
                    a place.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Bryan was a journeyman copperplate-printer. J.’s friend saw him
                    once at the house of one of the Brotherists; <note n="5" place="foot"
                        resp="editor">Southey himself met Bryan, probably in Bath at the house of
                        one of Brothers’ supporters—either Samuel Whitchurch, ironmonger, or James
                        Crease, picture framer and restorer, to whose pamphlets hailing Brothers as
                        a prophet he alluded in a letter of 9 May 1795 (<title>Romantic
                            Circles</title>, <title level="m">Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title>,
                        gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer, <ref
                            target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_One/HTML/letterEEd.26.126.html"
                            >Vol. I, Letter 126</ref>). Whitchurch, a poet as well as an ironmonger,
                        paid tribute to Southey’s poem <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title> (1795) in <title level="a">Lines on the
                        Crucifixion</title> in his collection <title level="m">Hispaniola</title> (Bath, 1804).</note> he says that
                    before he saw him he had heard of his resemblance to the pictures of our Lord,
                    but that it was so striking as truly to astonish him. These features, his full
                    clear and gentle eye, the beauty of his complexion, which would have been
                    remarkable even in a girl, and the voice, in which words flowed from him with
                    such unaffected and natural eloquence as to remind the hearer of the old
                    metaphorical description of oratory, united to produce such an effect upon his
                    believers as you may conceive, considering that they were credulous, and he
                    himself undoubtedly sincere. Wright had now found a man after his own heart.
                    They were both Quietists, whom for want of a guide their own good feelings led
                    astray, and their experiences, he says, operated with each other, as face
                    answers face in a glass.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Bryan told him of a society of prophets at Avignon,<note n="6"
                        place="foot" resp="editor">The history of the Avignon Society remains
                        disputed by scholars: most now agree that it was established in 1786 by Don
                        Antoine Joseph Pernety (1716-96) a former Benedictine monk influenced both
                        by Freemasonry and by Swedenborg, whose writings he translated into French
                        while working as the librarian to Frederick the Great, King of Prussia, in
                        Berlin. In 1763-64 Pernety had been part of the scientific voyage into the
                        South Atlantic commanded by Louis Antoine de Bougainville. On his return he
                        published <title>Journal historique d’un voyage fait aux îles Malouines en
                            1763 et 1764 pour les reconnoître et y former un établissement et de
                            deux voyages au détroit de Magellan avec une relation sur les
                            Patagons</title> (1769). Pernety’s Avingon scheme was aided by Count
                        Thaddeus Leszczy Grabianka (1740-1807), another Swedenborgian whom he met in
                        Berlin. Following a visit to English Swedenborgians, Grabianka joined
                        Pernety in founding the Société des Illuminés d’Avignon, a group whose
                        spiritual practices took elements from freemasonry, alchemy, mesmerism,
                        Catholic mysticism and Swedenborgianism. The Society was dispersed in the
                        early 1790s during the upheavals of the Revolution.</note> assembled there
                    from all parts of the world. This was in the autumn of 1788. In the January of
                    the ensuing year Wright mistook strong inclination for inspiration, and thought
                    the Spirit directed him to join them. The same spirit very naturally sent him to
                    communicate this to Bryan, whom he found possessed with the same impression.
                    Neither of them had money to leave with their families, or to support themselves
                    upon the journey, and neither of them understood a word of French. Both were
                    determined to go—Bryan that night, Wright the following morning—such being their
                    implicit obedience to the impulse within them, that the one would not wait, nor
                    the other hasten. Before his departure Bryan called upon a friend, who said to
                    him, ‘William, I have had it in my mind to ask if thou wert not sometimes in
                    want of money.’ He acknowledged that it was this want which now brought him
                    there; and the friend gave him four guineas. If this same friend was the person
                    who first told him of the society at Avignon, as may reasonably be suspected,
                    the whole collusion will be clear. One guinea he left with his wife, who was at
                    that time in child-bed, gave half a guinea to Wright to carry him to Dover, and
                    set off.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Bryan’s wife, not being in a state of belief, was greatly offended
                    with Wright, thinking that if it had not been for him her husband would not have
                    left her. His own wife was in a happier temper of mind, and encouraged him to
                    go. She had a son by a former husband who was some little support to her, and
                    who acquiesced in the necessity of this journey. He seems indeed to have
                    communicated something of his own fervour to all about him. A young man with
                    whom he was intimate bought him several things for his journey, and gave him a
                    guinea; this same person befriended his family during his absence. At three in
                    the morning he rose to depart: his son-in-law prepared breakfast, and they made
                    the watchman who had called him partake of it, for it was severely cold. ‘I
                    then’, says Wright, ‘turned to my children, who were all fast asleep, and kissed
                    them, and interceded with the great and merciful God, relating to him their
                    situation, in which, for his sake, they were going to be left without any
                    outward dependence;—and at that time some of them were lying on a bed of
                    shavings that I used to bring from my shop; at the same time imploring him that
                    he would be pleased to bless them, and if one friend failed, another might be
                    raised up, as I did not know whether I ever should see them any more; for
                    although our first journey was to Avignon, we did not know it would end
                    there’.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">He then went to Bryan’s wife, whom his own was nursing in
                    child-bed. The poor woman’s resentment had now given way, the quiet
                    self-devotion of her husband and his friend had almost persuaded her to believe
                    also; she burst into tears when she saw him, and saluted him, as he says, in the
                    fear and love of God, in which she bade him remember her to her husband. Wright
                    then went to the coach. Soon after they left London it began to rain and snow,
                    and he was on the outside. He was of a sickly habit, always liable to take cold,
                    and had at this time a bad cough. A doubt came upon him that if the Lord had
                    sent him he would certainly have caused it to be fine weather. Besides this, he
                    began to fear that Bryan would already have crost the channel, in which case
                    when he got to Dover he should have no money to pay his passage. Was it not
                    better therefore to turn back? But the testimony of God’s power in his heart, he
                    says, was greater than all these thoughts.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">The wind had been contrary, and detained Bryan. They crossed over
                    to Calais, took some food at an inn there, and got their money changed, inquired
                    the names of bread, wine, and sleeping, in the language of the country, and
                    which way they were to go, and then set off on their journey. They travelled on
                    foot to Paris. Wright’s feet were sorely blistered; but there was no stopping,
                    for his mind was bound in the spirit to travel on. They carried their burthen by
                    turns when both were able, but it generally fell upon Bryan as the stronger man.
                    Change of climate, however, aided probably by the faith which was in him,
                    removed Wright’s cough. Their funds just lasted to Paris; here Bryan had an
                    acquaintance, to whose house they went. This man had received a letter to say
                    who were coming, and that they were bad men, Wright in particular, whom it
                    advised him to send back. As you may suppose he was soon fully satisfied with
                    them—he entertained them three days, and then dismissed them, giving them five
                    louis d’or to bear them on. The whole journal of their way is interesting: it
                    relates instances of that subsiding of overwrought feelings which bodily
                    exhaustion produces, and which enthusiasts call desertion; of natural thoughts
                    and fears recurring, remembrances of home, and depression which sometimes
                    occasioned self-suspicion and half repentance:—with these symptoms the Church is
                    well acquainted, as common to the deluded, and to those who are in truth under
                    the influence of divine inspiration, and they prove the sincerity of this
                    narrative.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">At length they came in sight of Avignon. They washed some linen in
                    the river, sat down under the bushes till it was dry, then put it on; and,
                    having thus made their appearance as decent as they could, proceeded to the
                    house of the prophets, to which as it appears they had brought with them a
                    sufficient direction. The door was opened by one of the brethren and by a person
                    who could speak English, and who had arrived there a day or two before from
                    another part of the world. After they had washed and shaved, they were taken
                    across the street to another house and shown into a large room, where there was
                    a table spread nearly the whole length; they were told that table was provided
                    by the Lord, and when they wanted any thing to eat or to drink they were to go
                    there, and they would find a servant ready to wait upon them. The brethren also
                    provided them with cloth and whatever else they needed, and with money to give
                    to the poor, saying they had orders from the Lord to do so. In a short time
                    their Paris friend arrived, and was admitted a member of the society before
                    them, that he might be their interpreter. I wish the form of initiation had been
                    given. They met every evening to commemorate the death of our Lord by eating
                    bread and drinking wine. Very often, says Wright, when we have been sitting
                    together, the furniture in the room has been shaken as though it were all coming
                    to pieces; and upon inquiring what was the cause, we were told that it announced
                    the presence of angels; when these were not heard the brethren were always
                    afraid that something was amiss, and so inquired at the Word of the Lord.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">You will easily suppose that they had orders to keep to society
                    secret till the appointed time. I much wish that the book had stated how their
                    answers from the Lord were received, but on this it is silent. The drift and
                    character of the society are, however, sufficiently manifested by the Extracts
                    which Wright has published from their Journals, and of which I here subjoin
                    enough to satisfy you:
                <quote>‘You will soon see the pride of the Mahometan in the field:
                    several sovereigns will unite to lay it low. It is then that the great light
                    will appear. These perfidious enemies of the name of God will keep themselves
                    for a time in their obstinacy, and in the mean time will grow up he who shall
                    destroy them. Before the end of this year they will begin to show their
                    fierceness, and you will hear of extraordinary things and memorable feats. You
                    will hear that the world is filled with trouble and dissension; father, son,
                    relations, friends, all will be in motion; and it is in this year (1789) that
                    all will have its beginning.</quote>
                <quote>‘Remember that the face of the world will be changed, and you
                    shall see it restored to its first state. The thrones shall be overturned, the
                    earth shall be furrowed and change its aspect. They who shall be alive at that
                    time will envy the fate of the dead.</quote>
                <quote>The world will very soon be filled with trouble. Every where
                    people will experience misfortunes. I announce it to you before-hand. The
                    shepherd will forsake his flock; the sheep will be dispersed. He will oppress
                    another land, and the nations will rise up in arms.</quote>
                <quote>‘You will learn very soon that a part of the world is in
                    confusion; that the chiefs of nations are armed one against another. The earth
                    will be overflowed with blood. You will hear of the death of several sovereigns;
                    they give themselves up to luxury, they live in pleasures, but at last one of
                    them will fall and make an unhappy end.</quote>
                <quote>‘All the events of this century have been foreseen, and no century
                    has been distinguished by so many prodigies, but the ensuing will be filled with
                    much greater still.</quote>
                <quote>‘The fire is kindled, the moment is come, the Mahometan is going
                    to fall. Asia and Africa are staggering; fear pursues them, and they have a
                    glimpse of the fate that awaits them.</quote>
                <quote>‘The cross of Jesus Christ shall be set up and triumph in those
                    vast countries where it has been so long despised. Then Palestine will become
                    again the most fortunate country on the earth; it shall be the centre of the
                    faith of which it was the cradle, and from thence faith will spread itself all
                    over the earth. All the people will embrace it. The world will become again what
                    it was in the beginning. The enlightened Jews will embrace the Catholic faith.
                    All people will acknowledge God, the only true God. They will be guided by one
                    only Pastor, and governed by one sole Master.</quote>
                <quote>‘The second Zion has contributed the most to misguide the spirits
                    of men. She has introduced new Gentiles still more monstrous than those who have
                    reigned upon the earth. She only wants the statues of the Gods to resemble the
                    ancient times. Yea, they have been replaced by these carnal divinities to which
                    they render a sacrilegious adoration, and lavish an incense to them which they
                    refuse to God.</quote>
                <quote>‘The end of this century will be a series of calamities of the
                    people. Very few men are struck with the rapid decline of the present age. All
                    the nations will be enlightened to see their dangerous errors. They will
                    acknowledge how much they have been deceived by the masters who have instructed
                    them, and they will be desolated at the thoughts of having lost so precious a
                    treasure for having believed such rascals. But at the marked time how many
                    errors will they not abjure, when our children every where, in the name of God,
                    shall make their impious and monstrous errors disappear!—And thou, Crescent, who
                    so much at this day applaudest thyself, the lustre with which thou shinest is
                    soon to be eclipsed;—thy unjust conquests have long enough spun out the time of
                    thy empire, and thy power from one pole to another is far enough extended. Thou
                    dost not suspect that thy ruin is so near, and thou dost not know him who is
                    growing up to operate it.</quote>
                <quote>‘Here is the time in which God will break the laws made by the
                    children of the earth. Here is the time wherein he will reprove the science of
                    men, and here is the time of his justice. This is the time that we must believe
                    all those who announce the new reign of the Lord, for his spirit is with
                    them.</quote>
                <quote>‘The ages have not now long to linger for the accomplishment of
                    the promises of the Eternal.—The Eternal calls the times which walk in the
                    shadows and days of darkness, without light and without strength, to come and
                    change the face of the world, and commence his new reign. This is the time of
                    the new Heavens and the new Earth.</quote>
                <quote>‘The Eternal has spoken, I shall simplify all things for the
                    happiness of my elect. The moment is at hand when the confusion of languages
                    shall no more be an obstacle to the knowledge of the truth.</quote>
                <quote>When the impious and his superb eagle in his fury will dare to
                    declare war against the God of Heaven, every thing will give way immediately to
                    his pride. He will dare to make victims for himself among the saints whom Heaven
                    has chosen; he will dare to profane their asylums, to appropriate to himself the
                    gifts of the Eternal by the blackest of crimes, and by his success strengthening
                    his pride he will believe himself master of the world. Then—then—Heaven will
                    stop him: a feeble child will subdue his valour, and his fall will testify that
                    in the sight of the Eternal there is no other power but the power of his
                    arm.</quote>
                <quote>‘Already the measure is filled; already the times are
                    accomplished, and the reign of the Word is at hand. Terror will precede to
                    enlighten the blind who go astray, to humble the obstinate high-minded men, and
                    to punish the impious.’</quote>
                These are no common prophecies. Honest fanaticism has had no share
                    in manufacturing them. Vague as the language necessarily is, there is an end and
                    aim in it not to be mistaken; and it is almost startling to observe how much of
                    what was designed has taken place, and how much may still be applied to these
                    immediate times.</p>
                <p>Among these communications ‘For the Benefit and Instruction of all
                    Mankind’, are others which are addressed to Wright and Bryan, and to those who,
                    like them, were the unsuspecting tools of the society. I copy them with their
                    cyphers and forms.</p>
                    <quote>
                <ab rend="center">
                    <hi rend="ital">Question</hi>
                </ab>
                <ab rend="center">February 9, 1789.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">H. W. We supplicate thee to give us thy orders about the two
                    Englishmen B. and W. who arrived here on Thursday the 19th instant.</ab>
                <ab rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Answer</hi>.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">O thou who walkest before them to show them the way, Son of the
                    Voice, tell them that very soon the instruction will grow in their souls; they
                    will believe it and love it. Then, Son of the Voice, I shall let thee know what
                    Heaven ordains about their fate.</ab>
                <ab rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Question</hi>.</ab>
                <ab rend="center">March 18, 1789. By 2. I. 9.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">H. W. Let me know the moment in which B. and W. should be
                    consecrated.</ab>
                <ab rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Answer</hi>.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">Son of the Voice, fidelity and happiness will in the first
                    instance be the fruit of their union, the second will fill them with love and
                    zeal. The moment hastens that is to call them near to us and to you.</ab>
                        </quote>
                <p rend="noCount">Some things seem to have been inserted in their journal in
                    condescension to the weaker brethren, who required to be amused. Such as the
                    following instances:—</p>
                    <quote>
                <ab rend="indent1">‘In the month of June, 1789, we received a letter from the Union
                    at Rome, which informed us that the weather was as cold there as it is in
                    England in the month of January, and the Archangel Raphael asked the brethren
                    and sisters if the cold made them uneasy, and said, Have a little patience, and
                    the weather will be warm enough.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">‘The 17th of June, 1789, we received a letter from the Union at
                    Rome, in which they informed us of a sister, the daughter of a Turk, whom
                    Brother Brimmore baptized at Silesia, in the dominions of the king of Prussia,
                    between ten and fifteen years ago; after having lived some time in the enjoyment
                    of the Christian faith, she was suddenly taken by her father, and carried to
                    Alexandria in Egypt, which is in the dominions of the Turk, where she lived with
                    her father in much sorrow and trouble. After her father was dead she was ordered
                    by the Archangel Raphael to dress herself in a soldier’s dress, and fly into a
                    Christian country; which she did, and got aboard a Spanish ship, and from this
                    date has been between two and three months at sea.’</ab>
                    </quote>
                <p rend="noCount">But though the society occasionally accommodated itself to the
                    capacity of the weaker brethren, its oracles were more frequently delivered to
                    correct troublesome credulity, or repress more troublesome doubts.</p>
                    <quote>
                <ab rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Question</hi>.</ab>
                <ab rend="center">April 12, 1789.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">H. W. The three knocks which I. 4. 7. heard in the night, was it
                    any thing supernatural?</ab>
                <ab rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Answer</hi>.</ab>
                <ab rend="center">To 2. I. 9.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">Ask no more questions, if thou hast none to make of more
                    importance.</ab>
                <ab rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Question</hi>.</ab>
                <ab rend="center">April 14, 1789.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">H. W. If it please thee, I. 4. 7. would be glad to know if the
                    offering which he made on the mountain was acceptable to the Lord his God.</ab>
                <ab rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Answer</hi>.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">If Wisdom hath called thee, if Wisdom hath been thy guide, my son
                    why dost thou stop? Leave to thy God the care of thy conduct; forget—forget
                    thyself in approaching to him, and his light will enlighten thy soul, and thy
                    spirit shall no more make the law. Believe—believe, my son, that docility is the
                    way which leadeth to knowledge; that with love; and simplicity thou shalt have
                    nothing to fear from the snares of Hell, and that Heaven cannot lead thee
                    astray, for it is Heaven which hath marked to thee thy route.</ab>
                <ab rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Question</hi>.</ab>
                <ab rend="center">July 8, 1789.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">H. W. I. 4. 7. prays to know if it is the will of Heaven that he
                    should cause his wife to come with Duché<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editor">According to J. F. C. Harrison, <title>The Second Coming: Popular
                            Millenarianism, 1780-1850</title> (Piscataway, NJ, 1979), p. 243,
                        probably Thomas Spence Duché (1763-90), an artist who visited the Avignon
                        society, and son of the preacher, former American revolutionary and
                        Swedenborgian Jacob Duché (1737-98). Duché’s Swedeborgian meeting had been
                        visited by Grabianka in 1785-86.</note> to be consecrated.</ab>
                <ab rend="center">
                    <hi rend="ital">Answer.</hi>
                </ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">Heaven sees thy motive, my son, and approves thy zeal: but in
                    order that it may take place ************* do not think of it; thy hope is
                    vain.</ab>
                <ab rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Question</hi>.</ab>
                <ab rend="center">April 16, 1789.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">I. 2. 3. prays the H. W. to let him know if the Eternal has
                    accepted of his incense.</ab>
                <ab rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Answer</hi>.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">Raphael is the spirit which thy heart followed, my son, when thou
                    camest into these countries to seek for science and rest: but the spirit which
                    confuses thy idea is not the spirit of Raphael. Mistrust, son that art called,
                    the father of lies. Submit thy spirit to my voice. Believe—believe, my son, and
                    thy God forgives thee, and then thy incense is accepted, and thy return will
                    cover thee with glory.</ab>
                <ab rend="center">August 11, 1789.</ab>
                <ab rend="center">for the B. 12 April, 1756. Of I. 2. 3.</ab>
                <ab>C. 24 March.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">April 1.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">If the ardour which animates thee gives at last to thy heart over
                    thy spirit the victory and the empire; if thy desire renounces to discover,
                    before the time, the secret of the mysteries which simple reason is not able to
                    conceive, nothing can, my son, convey an obstacle to that happiness which awaits
                    thee.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">Walk without fear, and chase from thy soul the deceiving spirit
                    who wants to lead thee astray. Believe—believe, my son, every thing that I
                    reveal to our elect in the name of the Eternal, and the Eternal will make thee
                    the forerunning instrument of his glory in the places where his clemency wants
                    to pardon those of thy nation whom the enemy seduces by his prestiges.</ab>
                <ab rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Question</hi>.</ab>
                <ab rend="center">August 21, 1789.</ab>
                <ab rend="center">I. 4. 7. prays the H. W. to inform him if it is the will of Heaven
                for him also to return with I. 2. 3.*</ab> 
                        <ab>* [I. 4. 7. and I. 2. 3 seem to mean the two Englishmen. H. W. is
                    evidently Holy Word.]</ab>
                    
                <ab rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Answer</hi>.</ab>
                <ab rend="indent1">Yes. Son called, thou canst yet hearken to what I have to say unto
                    thee. Thy fate is in thy hands. It will be great if thou makest haste to offer
                    to thy God who chooseth thee the vain efforts of a useless knowledge, when it is
                    only necessary to obey. Forget—forget thy knowledge: it fatigues thy spirits, it
                    hurts thy heart, and retards from thy soul the influence of Heaven. Renounce, in
                    fine, to search into the sublime mysteries of thy God. Believe—believe, and the
                    Eternal will bless thy return, and thy simplicity will confound the knowledge,
                    the pride, and the prepossession of the senseless man, who believeth in his own
                    wisdom much more than in the wisdom of his God.</ab></quote>
                <p>The subject is so curious that I think you will be pleased to see
                    the character of this mysterious society further exemplified by a few of the
                    sentences, moral maxims, and spiritual instructions, which they delivered as
                    from Heaven. The first is sufficiently remarkable:
                    <quote>
                <list><item>‘Woe to him who dares to cover a lie with the sacred name of the
                    Eternal!</item>
                <item>‘One ray of light is not the entire light.</item>
                <item>‘A wise man is silent when he ought to be so.</item>
                <item>‘It is to the simple of heart that the Eternal will grant the
                    wisdom of the Spirit.</item>
                <item>‘The night was before the day, the day is before the night. </item>
                <item>‘When God commands, he who consulteth does not obey. </item>
                <item>‘He who walketh alone easily goes astray.</item>
                <item>‘To doubt, Is that believing? and to tremble, Is that to hope?</item>
                <item>‘He who thinks himself wise lies to himself, deceives himself,
                    goeth astray, and knoweth nothing.</item>
                <item>‘Shall man tremble when God supports him?</item>
                <item>‘The repentance of the wise is in his works, that of the fool in his tear; ‘The
                    child of man thinks of man, the child of God thinks of God; he must forget every
                    thing else.</item>
                <item>‘Fear leads our spirit astray; by laying a weight upon our days it
                    overturns wisdom, it intimidates nature, and the painful seeds of uneasiness and
                    anguish take part in our hearts.</item>
                <item>‘Heaven explains itself sufficiently when it inspires.</item>
                <item>‘Wilt thou never hear my word with the ears of thy soul, and will
                    thou never overturn the idol of mistrust that is in thy heart?</item>
                <item>‘The Lord has placed the key of his treasure under the cup of
                    bitterness.</item>
                <item>‘The ark of God conveys death to those who make use of false keys. </item>
                <item>‘Who is that man, saith the Lord, that will not abandon his heart
                    to me when I have promised to guide it?</item>
                <item>‘I am One, and all that is in me is One.</item>
                <item>‘Remember, and remember well, that the Word is but One for who
                    desires to comprehend; and there would be no more mysteries for man but for the
                    vanity of his heart and the folly of his understanding.</item>
                <item>‘Is it in the tumult of the world that the voice of the Most High
                    can enter into the heart?</item>
                <item>‘Do not attach any importance to your opinions: Of what avail to
                    your fate are your very weak ideas?</item>
                <item>‘Forget all, O our friends, except Heaven and yourselves, to obey
                only what Heaven prescribes to you.’</item></list>
                        </quote></p>
                <p>This narrative, and these extracts, require no comment. They prove incontestably
                    the existence of a society of political Jesuits; they prove also, that however
                    little may have been the religion of these men themselves, they were convinced
                    how indispensably necessary it was for mankind; and that, instead of plotting to
                    break up the system of social order by destroying faith and morals, faith was
                    the engine which they employed to prepare society for some imaginary
                    amelioration, forgetting that nothing which is founded upon delusion can be
                    permanent.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">The two Englishmen remained at Avignon six months, and were then
                    informed by the Spirit that they might return. The Brethren supplied them with
                    money, so that they went back with more comfort than they came, and had a
                    handsome sum left when they landed in England, where they both returned to their
                    former employments, expecting the accomplishment of the mighty changes which had
                    been foretold. The Revolution brake out.—They who had raised the storm could not
                    direct it: they became its victims—and knavery reaped what fanaticism had sown,
                    as they who lag in the assault enter the breach over the bodies of the brave who
                    have won the passage for them. What became of the Avignon society Heaven knows.
                    The honest dupes whom they had sent abroad, fully prepared to welcome any
                    novelty as the commencement of the Millennium, were left to their own direction.
                    A king of the Hebrews appeared in England, and Wright and Bryan were, as you may
                    suppose, among the first to acknowledge him. They imagined that the appointed
                    time was come, and published these secrets of the society which they had been
                    ordered to keep concealed. Of the King of the Hebrews in my next.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head rend="center">LETTER LXIX.<lb/>
                <hi rend="ital">Account of Richard Brothers</hi>.</head>
                <p>MY FORMER letters must have shown you that these English, whom we are accustomed
                    to consider as an unbelieving people, are in reality miserably prone to
                    superstition; yet you will perhaps be surprised at the new instance which I am
                    about to relate.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">There started up in London about the beginning of the late war, a
                    new pseudo-prophet, whose name was <ref target="people.html#BrothersRichard">Richard Brothers</ref>, And who called himself King of the Hebrews, and
                    Nephew of God. He taught that all existing souls had been created at the same
                    time with Adam, and his system was, that they had all lived with him in
                    Paradise, and all fallen with him in consequence of their joint transgression;
                    for all things which they saw and knew were in God, and indeed were God, and
                    they desired to know something besides God, in which desire they were indulged,
                    fatally for themselves, for the only thing which is not God is Evil. Evil was
                    thus introduced, and they for their punishment cast into hell, that is to say,
                    upon this present earth; and in this hell they have remained from that time till
                    now, transmigrating from one human body to another. But the term of their
                    punishment is now drawing towards its close: the consummation of all things is
                    at hand, and every one will then recover the recollection of all the scenes and
                    changes through which he has passed. This knowledge has already been vouchsafed
                    in part to Brothers himself, and it is thus that he explained the extraordinary
                    relationship to the Almighty which he laid claim to, asserting that in the days
                    of our Lord he was the son of James the brother of Christ. You know the
                    heretics, in their hatred to virginity and to Mary the most pure, maintain that
                    when Christ’s brethren are mentioned in the Gospels, the word is to be
                    understood in its literal and carnal sense; consequently he was then the Nephew
                    of the second Person in the Trinity.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Human fancy, it has been said, cannot imagine a monster whose
                    constituent parts are not all already in existence; it is nearly as impossible
                    for a new heresy to be now devised, so prolific has human error been. This
                    metempsychosis not only bears a general resemblance to that doctrine as held by
                    the Orientals and by Pythagoras, <note n="8" place="foot" resp="editor"
                        >Brothers’ supporter, the Orientalist Nathaniel Brassey Halhed (1751-1830),
                        noticed similarities between Brothers’ doctrine of transmigration and the
                        Hindu Trimourtee, or ‘triad of Energies’, Shiva, Vishnu, and Brahma. See
                        Halhed, <title>Testimony of the Authenticity of the Prophecies of R.
                            Brothers and of his Mission to Recall the Jews</title>, 2nd edn (London,
                        1795), p. 10. A fragment by Xenophanes suggests that the Greek philosopher
                        Pythagoras (c. 570-c. 495 BC) believed in the transmigration of the soul
                        into different bodies.</note> but has been held in this peculiar heretical
                    form by the old heretic Barules, and by the Flagellants of the fourteenth and
                    fifteenth centuries.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editor">The Barules believed
                        that the Son of God had only a phantom body and that souls were created
                        before the world and all existed at the same time. The Flagellants, a
                        fourteenth century middle-European sect, believed that human souls
                        transmigrated into animals.</note></p>
                <p rend="indent1">Brothers had been a lieutenant in the navy, and was known to be
                    insane; but when a madman calls himself inspired, from that moment the disorder
                    becomes infectious. The society at Avignon had unintentionally trained up
                    apostles for this man. Wright and Bryan had now for some years been looking for
                    the kingdom of Christ, and teaching all within the circle of their influence to
                    expect the same promised day. Of what had been announced to them much had been
                    too truly accomplished. The world was indeed filled with troubles and
                    dissension, the fire was kindled, the thrones of Europe were shaken, and one of
                    its kings had been brought to an unhappy end, according to the prediction. The
                    laws made by the children of the earth were broken, the reign of terror was
                    begun, and the times disastrous to the full measure of their prophecies. They
                    had been instructed to look for a miraculous deliverer and Lord of the earth,
                    and here was one who laid claim to the character. There were however some
                    difficulties. At Avignon they had been informed that he who was to be the Leader
                    of the Faithful, and to overthrow the kingdom of the world, was at that time
                    twelve years old, and living at Rome; even his name had been revealed. Neither
                    in this, nor in age, nor country did Brothers answer the prophecy. One of these
                        men<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editor">Bryan, as he himself recorded in
                        his <title>A Testimony of the Spirit of Truth concerning Richard Brothers
                            ... in an address to the people of Israel, &amp;c., to the gentiles
                            called Christians, and all other gentiles. With some account of the
                            manner of the Lord’s gracious dealing with his servant W. Bryan</title>
                        (London, 1795). Bryan also told Southey personally of his plan. See
                        Southey’s <ref target="../HTML/Prophets.html">letter of 7 July 1807 to John
                            May</ref>
                    </note> therefore decided in his own mind that he was an impostor; he went to
                    see him, with a full belief that whether he was so or not would be revealed to
                    him during the interview, and he took a knife with him, with which, if his
                    suspicions had been confirmed, he was resolved to deliver him such a message
                    from the Lord as Ehud carried to the king of Eglon.<note n="11" place="foot"
                        resp="editor">In the Book of Judges 3: 12-28 the Israelite Ehud, on the
                        pretext of taking the annual tribute to the Moabite King Eglon, stabbed him
                        in the stomach with a short sword.</note> Luckily for both parties,
                    Brothers, who little knew the dangerous trial he was undergoing, supported his
                    part so well that the desperate fanatic was converted.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">The new King of the Hebrews had not perhaps a single Jew among his
                    believers. These people, who have in old times suffered well nigh as severely
                    for their credulity in false Messiahs as for their rejection of the true one,
                    are less disposed to lend ear to such delusions now than in any former time, and
                    here than in any other country. Here they have no amelioration of their
                    condition to wish for; the free exercise of their religion is permitted, what
                    they gain they enjoy in security, and are protected by the state without the
                    trouble of self-defence. The flesh pots of England are not less delicious than
                    those of Egypt, and a land flowing with milk and honey not so attractive for the
                    sons of the Synagogue as one which abounds with old clothes for the lower order,
                    and loans and contracts for their wealthier brethren. The land of promise offers
                    nothing so tempting to them as scrip and omnium.<note n="12" place="foot"
                        resp="editor">Terms for marketable purchases of instalments of stock and
                        government securities.</note> The King of the Hebrews therefore was not
                    acknowledged by any of his own people; his scheme of pre-existence helped him
                    out of this difficulty. He could tell if any person had been a Jew in any former
                    stage of being, and even of what tribe; that of Judah, as the most favoured, he
                    bestowed liberally upon his believers, and those whom he hoped to convert. He
                    informed Mr. Pitt<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editor">William Pitt the
                        Younger (1759-1806), Prime Minister 1783-1801.</note> by letter that he was
                    a Jew, some of the royal family were in like manner declared to be Jews, and
                    J.’s friend received from Bryan the same flattering assurance.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Besides the prophets from Avignon, Brothers succeeded in making
                    two other useful and extraordinary disciples. The one, an engraver of first-rate
                    skill in his art, who published a masterly portrait of him, with these words
                    underneath, Fully <hi rend="ital">believing this to be the man whom God hath
                        appointed, I engrave his likeness</hi>.<note n="14" place="foot"
                        resp="editor">William Sharp the engraver (1747-1824), already interested in
                        Mesmerism and Swedenborgianism, became a follower of Brothers and, in 1795,
                        engraved Brothers’ image above the title ‘Richard Brothers Prince of the
                        Hebrews’. After Brothers’ confinement, Sharp became a follower, and
                        subsequently one of the elders, of Southcott. He published <title>An Answer
                            to the World, for putting in print a book in 1804, called, Copies and parts of Copies of Letters and Communications, written from Joanna Southcott</title> (London, 1806).</note> This was to be seen
                    in all the print-shops. Mr. Halhed was the other of these converts, a member of
                    the house of commons, and one of the profoundest oriental scholars then
                        living.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editor">The Orientalist scholar and
                        M.P. Nathaniel Brassey Halhed (1751-1830) astonished the educated classes by
                        declaring himself a believer in the prophetic mission of Brothers. See
                        Halhed, <title>Testimony of the Authenticity of the Prophecies of R.
                            Brothers and of his Mission to Recall the Jews</title>, 2nd edn (London,
                        1795).</note> This gentleman was in the early part of his life an
                    unbeliever, and had attempted to invalidate the truths of holy writ by arguments
                    deduced from Indian chronology. The study of Indian mythology brought him back
                    to Christianity, and by a strange perversion of intellect the Trimourtee of the
                        Hindoos<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editor">Halhed noticed similarities
                        between Brothers’ doctrine of transmigration and the Hindu Trimourtee, or
                        ‘triad of Energies’, Shiva, Vishnu, and Brahma. See Halhed,
                            <title>Testimony</title>, p. 10.</note> convinced him of the doctrine of
                    the Trinity; and as he recovered his faith he lost his wits. To the astonishment
                    of the world he published a pamphlet avowing his belief that Richard Brothers
                    was the Lion of the Tribe of Judah,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editor"
                        >Halhed, <title>Testimony of the Authenticity of the Prophecies of R.
                            Brothers and of his Mission to Recall the Jews</title>, 2nd edn (London,
                        1795). See the prophecy of a coming apocalypse in Revelation 5: 5, ‘Weep
                        not: behold, the Lion of the tribe of Judah, the Root of David, hath
                        prevailed to open the book, and to loose the seven seals thereof’.</note>
                    and that in him the prophecies were speedily to be fulfilled.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Brothers wrote letters to the king and to all the members of both
                    houses of parliament, calling upon them to give ear to the word of God, and
                    prepare for the speedy establishment of his kingdom upon earth. He announced to
                    his believers his intention of speedily setting out for Jerusalem to take
                    possession of his metropolis, and invited them to accompany him. Some of these
                    poor people actually shut up their shops, forsook their business and their
                    families, and travelled from distant parts of the country to London to join him,
                    and depart with him whenever he gave the word. Before he went, he said, he would
                    prove the truth of his mission by a public miracle, he would throw down his
                    stick in the Strand at noon day, and it should become a serpent; and he affirmed
                    that he had already made the experiment and successfully performed it in
                    private. A manifest falsehood this, but not a wilful one; in like manner he said
                    that he had seen the Devil walking leisurely up Tottenham-Court-road;—the man
                    was evidently in such a state of mind that his waking dreams were mistaken for
                    realities. He threatened London with an earthquake because of its unbelief, and
                    at length named the day when the city should be destroyed. Many persons left
                    town to avoid his threatened calamity; the day passed by, he claimed the merit
                    of having prevailed in prayer and obtained a respite, and fixed another.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">The business was becoming serious. All the madmen and enthusiasts
                    in England, a land wherein there is never any lack of them, made a common cause
                    with this King of the Hebrews. Pamphlets in his favour swarmed from the press;
                    the prophecy of some old heretic was raked up, which fixed the downfall of the
                    church as destined now to be accomplished; and the number of the Beast was
                    explained by Ludovicus XVI. One madman printed his dreams, another his
                    day-visions; one had seen an angel come out of the sun with a drawn sword in his
                    hand, another had seen fiery dragons in the air, and hosts of angels in battle
                    array; these signs and tokens were represented in rude engravings, and the lower
                    classes of people, to whose capacity and whose hungry superstition they were
                    addressed, began to believe that the seven seals were about to be opened, and
                    all the wonders in the Apocalypse would be displayed. Government at last thought
                    fit to interfere, and committed Brothers to the national hospital for
                        madmen.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editor">Brothers was arrested on 4
                        March 1795 and examined by the Privy Council. On 27 March, he was declared
                        insane and confined as a criminal lunatic. From 4 May, he was held in Fisher
                        House, Islington, a private asylum.</note> Mr. Halhed made a speech in
                    parliament upon this occasion, the most extraordinary perhaps that ever was
                    delivered to a legislative assembly.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editor"
                        >Halhed published the text of his Commons speech as <title>Mr. Halhed’s
                            Speech in the House of Commons (March 31st 1795; being a motion for the
                            printing and distributing of Mr. Brother’s Prophecys, etc. for the use
                            of the Members;) his Reply to Dr. Horne’s Sound Argument and Common
                            Sense; with cursory observations on the Age of Credulity, and his
                            Calculation on the Millennium</title> (London, 1795).</note> It was a
                    calm and logical remonstrance against the illegality and unreasonableness of
                    their proceedings. They had imprisoned this person as a madman, he said, because
                    he announced himself as a prophet; but it was incumbent upon them to have fairly
                    examined his pretensions, and ascertained their truth or falsehood, before they
                    had proceeded against him in this manner. Brothers had appealed to the Holy
                    Scriptures, the divine authority of which that house acknowledged; he appealed
                    also to certain of his own predictions as contained in the letters which he had
                    addressed to the king and his ministers;—let them be produced, and the question
                    solemnly investigated as its importance deserved. According to the rules of the
                    house of commons, no motion can be debated or put to the vote, unless it be
                    seconded; Mr. Halhed found no one to second him, and his proposal was thus
                    silently negatived.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Thus easily and effectually was this wild heresy crushed. Brothers
                    continued to threaten earthquakes, fix days for them, and prorogue them after
                    the day was past; but his influence was at an end. The people had lost sight of
                    him; and being no longer agitated by signs and tokens, dreams and denunciations,
                    they forgot him. A few of his steadier adherents persisted in their belief, and
                    comforted him and themselves by reminding him of Daniel in the lions’ den, and
                    of Jeremiah in the dungeon. He was lucky enough to find out better consolation
                    for himself. There was a female lunatic in the same hospital, whom he discovered
                    to be the destined Queen of the Hebrews; and as such announced her to the world.
                    At present he and this chosen partner of the throne of David are in daily
                    expectation of a miraculous deliverance, after which they are to proceed to
                    Jerusalem to be crowned, and commence their reign. Plans and elevations of their
                    palace and of the new Temple have been made for them, and are now being engraved
                    for the public;<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editor">Engravings of this kind
                        featured in Brothers’<title> A Description of Jerusalem: its houses and
                            streets ... with the Garden of Eden in the centre as laid down in the
                            last chapters of Ezekiel. Also the first chapter of Genesis
                            verified</title> (London, 1801). Further engravings appeared in the work
                        printed for Brothers’ supporter John Finleyson: <title>The New Covenant
                            between God and His People; or, the Hebrew constitution and charter;
                            with the statutes and ordinances, the laws and regulations, and commands
                            and covenants</title> (London, 1830).</note> and in these dreams they
                    will probably continue as long as they live. Upon madmen of this stamp,
                    experience has as little effect as hellebore. Their thoughts of the future are
                    so delightful as they forget the past, and are well nigh insensible to the
                    present just as all other objects near or distant appear darkened to him who has
                    been looking at the sun. Their hope has neither fear nor doubt to allay it, and
                    its intensity gives them a joy which could scarcely be exceeded by its
                    accomplishment.</p>
            </div>
                <div type="section">
                <head rend="center">LETTER LXX.<lb/>
                Account of Joanna Southcott.</head>
                <p>IN THE early part of the thirteenth century there appeared an English virgin in
                    Italy, beautiful and eloquent, who affirmed that the Holy Ghost was incarnate in
                    her for the redemption of women, and she baptized women in the name of the
                    Father, and of the Son, and of herself. Her body was carried to Milan and burnt
                    there. An arch-heretic of the same sex and country is now establishing a sect in
                    England, founded upon a not dissimilar and equally portentous blasphemy. The
                    name of this woman is Joanna Southcott; she neither boasts of the charms of her
                    forerunner, nor needs them. Instead of having an eye which can fascinate, and a
                    tongue which can persuade to error by glossing it with sweet discourse, she is
                    old, vulgar, and illiterate. In all the innumerable volumes which she has sent
                    into the world, there are not three connected sentences in sequence, and the
                    language alike violates common sense and common syntax. Yet she has her
                    followers among the educated classes, and even among the beneficed clergy.<note
                        n="21" place="foot" resp="editor">In 1802 the Reverends Thomas P. Foley, of
                        Old Swinford, Worcestershire, Thomas Webster of St. George’s the Borough,
                        London, and Stanhope Bruce, of Inglesham, Gloucestershire, having
                        interviewed Southcott, declared their belief in her prophetic mission. In
                        1805 Foley published <title>The Answer of the Rev. Thomas P. Foley, to the
                            World, Who Hath Blamed His Faith in Believing It Was a Command from the
                            Lord to Put in Print Such Parable, As He Printed Last Year at
                            Stourbridge, under the Ttitle ‘What Manner of Communications are
                            These?’</title> (Oldswinford, 1805).</note> ‘If Adam,’ she says, ‘had
                    refused listening to a foolish ignorant woman at first, then man might refuse
                    listening to a foolish ignorant woman at last:’—and the argument is admitted by
                    her adherents. When we read in romance of enchanted fountains, they are
                    described as flowing with such clear and sparkling waters as tempt the traveller
                    to thirst; here, there may be a magic in the draught, but he who can taste of so
                    foul a stream must previously have lost his senses. The filth and the
                    abominations of demoniacal witchcraft are emblematical of such delusions; not
                    the golden goblet and bewitching allurements of Circe and Armida.<note n="22"
                        place="foot" resp="editor">The Saracen sorceress who enthralled the
                        Christian hero in Tarquato Tasso’s poem <title>Gerusalemme Liberata</title>
                        (1580).</note></p>
                <p rend="indent1">The patient and resolute obedience with which I have collected for
                    you some account of this woman and her system, from a pile of pamphlets half a
                    yard high, will, I hope, be imputed to me as a merit. Had the heretics of old
                    been half as voluminous, and half as dull, St. Epiphanius would never have
                    persevered through his task.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editor">Saint
                        Epiphanius (ca. 310/320-403), Bishop of Salamis, compiled a huge compendium
                        of heresies.</note></p>
                <p rend="indent1">She was born in Devonshire about the middle of the last century,
                    and seems to have passed forty years of her life in honest industry, sometimes
                    as a servant, at others working at the upholsterers’ business, without any other
                    symptom of a disordered intellect than that she was zealously attached to the
                    Methodists. These people were equally well qualified to teach her the arts of
                    imposture, or to drive her mad; or to produce in her a happy mixture of
                    craziness and knavery, ingredients which in such cases are usually found in
                    combination. She mentions in her books a preacher who frequented her master’s
                    house, and, according to her account, lived in habits of adultery with the wife,
                    trying at the same time to debauch the daughter, while the husband vainly
                    attempted to seduce Joanna herself. This preacher used to terrify all who heard
                    him in prayer, and make them shriek out convulsively. He said that he had
                    sometimes, at a meeting, made the whole congregation lie stiff upon the floor
                    till he had got the evil spirits out of them; that there never was a man so
                    highly favoured of God as himself; that he would not thank God to make him any
                    thing, unless he made him greater than any man upon earth, and gave him power
                    above all men; and he boasted, upon hearing the death of one who had censured
                    him, that he had fasted and prayed three days and three nights, beseeching God
                    to take vengeance upon that man and send him to eternity. Where such impious
                    bedlamites as this are allowed to walk abroad, it is not to be wondered at that
                    madness should become epidemic.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Joanna Southcott lived in a house which this man frequented, and
                    where, notwithstanding his infamous life, his pretensions to supernatural gifts
                    were acknowledged, and he was accustomed to preach and pray. The servants all
                    stood in fear of him. She says, he had no power over her, but she used to think
                    the room was full of spirits when he was in prayer; and he was so haunted that
                    he never could sleep in a room by himself, for he said his wife came every night
                    to trouble him: she was perplexed about him, fully believing that he wrought
                    miracles, and wondering by what spirit he wrought them. After she became a
                    prophetess herself, she discovered that this Sanderson was the false prophet in
                    the Revelation, who is to be taken with the Beast, and cast alive with him into
                    a lake of burning brimstone.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Four persons have written to Joanna upon the subject of her
                    pretended mission, each calling himself Christ! One Mr. Leach, a Methodist
                    preacher, told her to go to the Lord in <hi rend="ital">his name</hi>, and tell
                    the Lord that <hi rend="ital">he said</hi> her writings were inspired by the
                    Devil. These circumstances show how commonly delusion, blasphemy, and madness
                    are to be found in this country, and may lessen our wonder at the phrensy of
                    Joanna and her followers. Her own career began humbly, with prophecies
                    concerning the weather, such as the popular English almanacks contain, and
                    threats concerning the fate of Europe and the successes of the French, which
                    were at that time the speculations of every newspaper, and of every ale-house
                    politician. Some of these guesses having chanced to be right, the women of the
                    family in which she then worked at the upholstering business, began to lend ear
                    to her, and she ventured to submit her papers to the judgement of one Mr.
                    Pomeroy, the clergyman whose church she attended in Exeter. He listened to her
                    with timid curiosity, rather wanting courage than credulity to become her
                    disciple; received from her certain sealed prophecies which were at some future
                    time to be opened, when, as it would be seen that they had been accomplished,
                    they would prove the truth of her inspiration; and sanctioned, or seemed to
                    sanction, her design of publishing her call to the world. But in this
                    publication his own name appeared, and that in such a manner as plainly to
                    imply, that if he had not encouraged her to print, he had not endeavoured to
                    prevent her from so doing. His eyes were immediately opened to his own
                    imprudence, whatever they may have been to the nature of his call, and he
                    obtained her consent to insert an advertisement in the newspaper with her
                    signature, stating that he had said it was the work of the Devil. But here the
                    parties are at issue: as the advertisement was worded, it signifies that Mr.
                    Pomeroy always said her calling was from the Devil; on the other hand, Joanna
                    and her witnesses protest that what she had signed was merely an acknowledgment
                    that Mr. Pomeroy had said, after her book was printed, the Devil had instigated
                    her to print his name in it. This would not be worthy of mention, if it were not
                    for the very extraordinary situation into which this gentleman has brought
                    himself. Wishing to be clear of the connection in which he had so unluckily
                    engaged, he burnt the sealed papers which had been intrusted to his care. From
                    that time all the Joannians, who are now no inconsiderable number, regard him as
                    the arch-apostate. He is the Jehoiakim who burnt Jeremiah’s roll of
                        prophecies,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editor">Jeremiah 36: 1-32.
                        Jehoiakim (c. 635-597 BC), King of Judah, had the manuscript of one of
                        Jeremiah’s prophecies burned, as it criticised his rule.</note> he is their
                    Judas Iscariot, a second Lucifer, son of the Morning. They call upon him to
                    produce these prophecies, which she boldly asserts, and they implicitly believe,
                    have all been fulfilled, and therefore would convince the world of the truth of
                    her mission. In vain does Mr. Pomeroy answer that he has burnt these unhappy
                    papers:—in an unhappy hour for himself did he burn them! Day after day long
                    letters are dispatched to him, sometimes from Joanna herself, sometimes from her
                    brother, sometimes from one of her four-and-twenty elders, filled with
                    exhortation, invective, texts of scripture, and denunciations of the Law in this
                    world and the Devil in the next; and these letters the prophetess prints, for
                    this very sufficient reason—that all her believers purchase them. Mr. Pomeroy
                    sometimes treats them with contempt, at other times he appeals to their
                    compassion, and beseeches them, if they have any bowels of Christian charity, to
                    have compassion on him and let him rest, and no longer add to the inconceivable
                    and irreparable injuries which they have already occasioned him. If he is
                    silent, no matter, on they go, printing copies of all which they write, and when
                    he is worried into replying, his answers also serve to swell Joanna’s books. In
                    this manner is this poor man, because he has recovered his senses, persecuted by
                    a crazy prophetess, and her four-and-twenty crazy elders, who seem determined
                    not to desist, till, one way or other, they have made him as ripe for Bedlam as
                    they are themselves.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">The books which she sends into the world are written partly in
                    prose, partly in rhyme, all the verse and the greater part of the prose being
                    delivered in the character of the Almighty! It is not possible to convey any
                    adequate idea of this unparalleled and unimaginable nonsense by any other means
                    than literal transcript. Her hand-writing was illegibly bad, so that at last she
                    found it convenient to receive orders to throw away the pen and deliver her
                    oracles orally; and the words flow from her faster than her scribes can write
                    them down. This may be well believed, for they are mere words and nothing else:
                    a rhapsody of texts, vulgar dreams and vulgar interpretations, vulgar types and
                    vulgar applications;—the vilest string of words in the vilest doggerel verse,
                    which has no other connection than what the vilest rhymes have suggested, she
                    vents, and her followers receive, as the dictates of immediate inspiration. A
                    herd, however, was ready to devour this garbage as the bread of life. Credulity
                    and Vanity are foul feeders.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">The clergy in her own neighbourhood were invited by her, by
                    private letters, to examine her claims, but they treated her invitation with
                    contempt: the bishop also did not choose to interfere;—of what avail, indeed,
                    would it have been to have examined her, when they had no power to silence her
                    blasphemies! She found believers at a distance. Seven men came from different
                    parts of the country to examine—that is—to believe in her; these were her seven
                    stars; and when at another time seven more arrived upon the same wise errand,
                    she observed, in allusion to one of those vulgar sayings from which all her
                    allusions are drawn, that her seven stars were come to fourteen. Among these
                    early believers were three clergymen, one of them a man of fashion, fortune, and
                    noble family. It is not unlikely that the woman at first suspected the state of
                    her own intellects: her letters appear to indicate this; they express a humble
                    submission to wiser judgments than her own; and could she have breathed the
                    first thoughts of delusion into the ear of some pious confessor, it is more than
                    probable that she would have soon acknowledged her error at his feet, and the
                    phrensy which has now infected thousands would have been cut off on its first
                    appearance. But when she found that persons into whose society nothing else
                    could ever have elevated her, listened to her with reverence, believed all her
                    ravings, and supplied her with means and money to spread them abroad, it is not
                    to be wondered at if she went on more boldly;—the gainfulness of the trade soon
                    silencing all doubts of the truth of her inspiration.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Some of her foremost adherents were veterans in credulity: they
                    had been initiated in the mysteries of animal magnetism, had received spiritual
                    circumcision from Brothers, and were thus doubly qualified for the part they
                    were to act in this new drama of delusion. To accommodate them, Joanna confirmed
                    the authenticity of this last fanatic’s mission, and acknowledged him as King of
                    the Hebrews,—but she dropt his whole mythology. Her heresy in its main part is
                    not new. The opinion that redemption extended to men only and not to women, had
                    been held by a Norman in the sixteenth century, as well as by the fair English
                    heretic already mentioned. This man, in a book called <title>Virgo
                        Veneta</title>, maintained that a female Redeemer was necessary for the
                    daughters of Eve, and announced an old woman of Venice of his acquaintance as
                    the Saviour of her sex.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editor">Southey refers to
                        William Postellus, whose identification of Mother Johanna of Venice as the
                        female redeemer led to his dismissal by the Jesuits and persecution by the
                        Inquisition. Fleeing Italy for France, he published several heterodox works
                        under the protection of Charles IX, and died in a monastery there in
                        1581.</note> Bordonius, a century ago, broached even a worse heresy. In a
                    work upon miracles, printed at Parma, he taught that women did not participate
                    in the atonement, because they were of a different species from man, and were
                    incapable of eternal life.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editor">The Franciscan
                        friar Francesco Bordoni da Parma (1594-1671), author of numerous works of
                        theology, ecclesiastical history and law. Bordoni argued for women’s
                        spiritual inferiority to men in <title level="m">Opus posthumum, de recenti primò in
                            lucem proditur, quod consistit in duas appendices ad Manuale consultorum
                            in causis Sancti Officii contrà haereticam pravitatem occurrentibus ...
                            in prima diffusè ostenditur quasi omnem excogitabilem blasphemiam ... In
                            secunda verò explicantur essentia, qualitates, ac diversitatum genus
                            omnium sortilegiorum...Ad cujus calcem subsequitur nova reimpressio
                            Tractatus de legatis ejusdem auctoris denuò revisus, ac ... correctus
                            ... industria</title> (Parma, 1703).</note> Joanna and her followers are
                    too ignorant to be acquainted with these her prototypes in blasphemy, and the
                    whole merit of originality in her system must be allowed her, as indeed she has
                    exceeded her forerunners in the audacity of her pretensions. She boldly asserts
                    that she is the Woman in the Revelation, who has the Moon under her feet, and on
                    her head a crown of twelve stars; the twelve stars being her twelve Apostles,
                    who with the second dozen of believers make up her four-and-twenty Elders. In
                    her visitation it was told her, that the angels rejoiced at her birth, because
                    she was born to deliver both men and angels from the insults of the Devil. Let
                    it be lawful for me to repeat these blasphemies, holding them up to merited
                    abhorrence. The scheme of redemption, she says, is completed in her, and without
                    her would be imperfect; by woman came the fall of man, by woman must come his
                    redemption; woman plucked the evil fruit, and woman must pluck the good fruit;
                    if the Tree of Knowledge was violated by Eve, the Tree of Life is reserved for
                    Joanna. Eve was a bone from Adam, she is a bone from Christ the second Adam. She
                    is the Bride, the promised seed who is to bruise the Serpent’s head; she it is
                    who claims the promise made at the creation, that woman should be the helpmate
                    of man, and by her the Creator fulfils that promise, and acquits himself of the
                    charge of having given to man the woman in vain. The evening star was placed in
                    the firmament to be her type. While she arrogates so much to herself, she is
                    proportionately liberal to her followers; they have been appointed to the
                    four-and-twenty elderships: and to one of them, when he died, a higher character
                    was more blasphemously attributed: she assured his relations that he was gone to
                    plead the promises before the Lord; that to him was to be given the key of the
                    bottomless pit, and that the time was at hand when he should be seen descending
                    in the air,—for they knew not the meaning of our Saviour’s words when he said,
                    ‘Ye shall see the Son of Man coming in the clouds, in power and great
                        glory!’<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editor">From Matthew 26:
                    24.</note></p>
                <p rend="indent1">The immediate object of her call is to destroy the Devil: of this
                    the Devil was aware, and that it might not be said he had had foul play, a
                    regular dispute of seven days was agreed on between him and Joanna, in which she
                    was to be alone, and he to bring with him as many of the Powers of Darkness as
                    he pleased: but he was not to appear visibly; for, as he did not choose to make
                    his appearance on a former occasion when some of her elders went to give him the
                    meeting, but had disappointed them, he was not to be permitted to manifest
                    himself bodily now. The conditions were, that if she held out with argument
                    against him for seven days, the Woman should be freed and he fall; but if she
                    yielded, Satan’s kingdom was to stand, and a second fall of the human race would
                    be the consequence. Accordingly, she went alone into a solitary house for this
                    conference. Joanna was her own secretary upon this occasion, and the
                    process-verbal of the conference has been printed, as literally taken down; for
                    she was ordered to set down all his blasphemies, and show to the world what the
                    language of Hell is. It is by no means a polite language;—indeed the proficiency
                    which Satan displays in the vulgar tongue is surprising.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Of all Joanna’s books this is the most curious.<note n="28"
                        place="foot" resp="editor">
                        <title>A Dispute between the Woman and the Powers of Darkness</title>
                        (London, 1802).</note> Satan brought a friend with him, and they made up a
                    story for themselves which has some ingenuity. ‘It is written,’ said they, ‘Be
                    still, and know that I am God;’<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editor"><title>A
                            Dispute</title>, p. 6.</note> this still worship did not suit Satan; he
                    was a lively cheerful spirit, full of mirth and gaiety, which the Lord could not
                    bear, and therefore cast him out of Heaven. This, according to Apollyon’s<note
                        n="30" place="foot" resp="editor">In Revelation 9:11 Apollyon is the
                        destroyer, ‘the angel of the bottomless pit’.</note> account of Heaven,
                    could have been no great evil. ‘Thou knowest,’ he says, ‘it is written of God,
                    he is a consuming fire, and who can dwell in everlasting burnings? Our backs are
                    not brass nor our sinews iron, to dwell with God in Heaven.’<note n="31"
                        place="foot" resp="editor"><title>A Dispute</title>, p. 48.</note> The
                    Heaven therefore which men mistakenly desire, is in its nature the very Hell of
                    which they are so much afraid; and it is sufficient proof of the truth of all
                    this, that the Devil invites them to make themselves happy and lead a gay life,
                    agreeably to his own cheerful disposition, whereas religion enjoins self-denial,
                    penitence, and all things which are contrary to our natural inclinations. Satan
                    accounted to Joanna for her inspiration by this solution: An evil spirit had
                    loved her from her youth up, he found there was no other access to her heart
                    than by means of religion; and, being himself able to foresee future events,
                    imparted this knowledge to her in the character of a good spirit. This spirit,
                    he said, was one which she had been well acquainted with; it was that of one Mr.
                    Follart, who had told her if she would not have him for a husband he should die
                    for her sake, and accordingly he had died. But this deception had now been
                    carried so far that Satan was angry, and threatened, unless she broke her seals
                    and destroyed her writings, he would tear her in pieces. The conference
                    terminated like most theological disputes. Both parties grew warm. Apollyon
                    interfered, and endeavoured to accommodate matters, but without effect, and
                    Joanna talked Satan out of all patience. She gave him, as he truly complained,
                    ten words for one, and allowed him no time to speak. All men,he said, were tired
                    of her tongue already, and now she had tired the Devil. This was not
                    unreasonable; but he proceeded to abuse the whole sex, which would have been
                    ungracious in any one, and in him was ungrateful. He said no man could tame a
                    woman’s tongue—the sands of an hour-glass did not run faster—it was better to
                    dispute with a thousand men than one woman. After this dispute she fasted forty
                    days; but this fast, which is regarded by her believers as so miraculous, was
                    merely a Catholic Lent, in which she abstained from fish as well as flesh.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">The Moon which is under her feet in the Revelation,<note n="32"
                        place="foot" resp="editor">Revelation 12: 1.</note> typifies the Devil: for
                    the moon, it seems, having power to give light by night but not by day, is
                    Satan’s kingdom, and his dwelling-place; he, I conclude, being the very person
                    commonly called the Man in the Moon, a conjecture of my own, which, you must
                    allow, is strongly confirmed by his horns. Once, when the Lord made her the same
                    promise as Herod had done to Herodias, she requested that Satan might be cut off
                    from the face of the earth as John the Baptist had been. This petition she was
                    instructed to write, and seal it with three seals, and carry it to the altar
                    when she received the sacrament! and a promise was returned that it should be
                    granted. Her dreams are usually of the Devil. Once she saw him like a pig with
                    his mouth tied, at another time skinned his face with her nails after a fierce
                    battle; once she bit off his fingers, and thought the blood sweet,—and once she
                    dreamt she had fairly killed him. But neither has the promise of his destruction
                    been as yet fulfilled, nor the dream accomplished.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">This phrensy would have been speedily cured in our country; bread
                    and water, a solitary cell, and a little wholesome discipline are specifics in
                    such cases. Mark the difference in England. No bishop interferes; she therefore
                    boldly asserts that she has the full consent of the bishops to declare that her
                    call is from God, because, having been called upon to disprove it, they keep
                    silent. She who was used to earn her daily bread by daily labour, is now taken
                    into the houses of her wealthy believers, regarded as the most blessed among
                    women, carried from one part of England to another, and treated every where with
                    reverence little less than idolatry. Meantime dictating books as fast her
                    scribes can write them down, she publishes them as fast as they are written, and
                    the Joannians buy them as fast as they are published. Nor is this her only
                    trade. The seals in the Revelation furnished her with a happy hint. She calls
                    upon all persons ‘to sign their names for Christ’s glorious and peaceable
                    kingdom to be established and to come upon earth, and his will to be done on
                    earth as it is done in heaven, and for Satan’s kingdom to be destroyed, which is
                    the prayer and desire of Joanna Southcott’. They who sign this are to be sealed.
                    Now if this temporal sealing, which is mentioned by St. John in the Revelation,
                    had been understood before this time, men would have begun sealing themselves
                    without the visitation of the Spirit; and if she had not understood it and
                    explained it now, it would have been more fatal for herself and for all mankind
                    than the fall of Eve was. The mystery of sealing is this: whosoever signs his
                    name receives a sealed letter containing these words: <hi rend="ital">The Sealed
                        of the Lord, the Elect, Precious, Man’s Redemption, to inherit the Tree of
                        Life, to be made Heirs of God, and Joint-heirs with Jesus Christ.</hi>
                    Signed <hi rend="ital">Joanna Southcott.</hi> I know not what the price of this
                    initiation is; but she boasts of having sealed above eight thousand persons, so
                    that the trade is a thriving one.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">And these things are believed in England! in England, where
                    Catholic Christians are so heartily despised for superstition; in England, where
                    the people think themselves so highly enlightened,—in this country of reason and
                    philosophy and free inquiry! It is curious to observe how this age in which we
                    live is denominated by every writer just as its temper accords with his own
                    views: with the infidel, it is the Age of Reason; with the Churchman, the Age of
                    Infidelity; with the Chemist, the Age of Philosophy; with Rulers, the Age of
                    Anarchy; with the People, the Age of Oppression, every one beholding the
                    prospect through a coloured glass, and giving it sunshine or shade, frost or
                    verdure, according to his own fancy, none looking round him and seeing it fairly
                    as it is. Yet surely if we consider the ignorance of the great majority of the
                    English, the want of anchorage for their faith, the want of able directors for
                    their souls, the rapidity with which novelties of any kind are circulated
                    throughout the country, the eagerness with which the credulous listen to every
                    new blasphemy, the contemptuous indifference of the clergy to any blasphemy
                    provided it does not immediately threaten themselves, the unlimited toleration
                    shown to Jews, Gentiles, and Heretics of every description, above all if we
                    remember that every person has the power of comparing these delusive books with
                    the Bible, of which they are instructed to consider themselves competent
                    expounders,—we must acknowledge that there never was any age or any country so
                    favourable to the success of imposture and the growth of superstition, as this
                    very age and this very England.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">I have to add concerning Joanna, that she prophesies how she and
                    her believers are to be tried in the ensuing year, and that this awful trial
                    will be only second to that of our blessed Lord at Pilate’s bar! What new juggle
                    is in preparation I pretend not to divine. Thus much is certain, that her
                    believers are proof against conviction, and you will agree with me in thinking
                    no further trial necessary to prove that she and her abettors ought either to be
                    punished as impostors, or silenced as lunatics.*</p>
                    <p rend="noCount">*[Southey’s note:] The Translator has been curious enough to
                    inquire the event of this trial, which may be related in few words. None but her
                    believers assembled; they provided an attorney to give their proceedings some of
                    the ceremonials of legality, examined witnesses to prove the good character of
                    the prophetess, signed a profession of belief in her,—and afterwards published
                    an account of all this folly under the title of <title level="m">The Trial of Joanna Southcott</title>.
                    Joanna had predicted that at this trial she was to be cast into a trance; not
                    thinking this convenient when the time appointed came, she had a revelation to
                    say, that if any of her judges required it, the Lord would still entrance her,
                    but that it would certainly be her death: and thus throwing herself upon the
                    mercy of her own accomplices, it will easily be guessed that none among them
                    insisted upon the proof. One of the company inquired whether Satan knew he was
                    cast by this trial; as, in that case, it was to be presumed he would rage
                    against her and her friends with the utmost of his fury. This gentleman would
                    have been a good subject for a night-mare.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">D. Manuel might well say that nothing but literal transcript could
                    convey an idea of this woman’s vulgarity and nonsense; witness the passages
                    which he has selected,      
<quote>                    
                    <lg type="verse">
                        <l rendition="#indent2">So, learned men, no more contend, </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent3">Till you have seen all clear, </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">The Woman clothed with the Sun </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent3">A wonder to you here.</l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">So, in amaze, you all may gaze, </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent3">As Adam did at first,</l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">To see the bone to him unknown, </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent3">The woman there was placed. </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">The woe you see, she brought on he, </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent3">And the first woe for man;— </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">But how shall Satan now get free, </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent3">She casts her woe on man.—</l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">Though ’twas not she, I must tell ye, </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent3">Did cast the woe on man;</l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">The serpent was condemned by she, </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent3">And there her woe must come.<note n="33" place="foot"
                            resp="editor"><title>A Dispute</title>, p. 66.</note></l>                        
                </lg></quote>
                It is speaking within compass to say, that she has sent into the world above
                    twenty thousand of such verses as these, as the dictates of the Spirit!</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> What follows is in the words of one of her chosen disciples; ‘On
                    Monday morning Joanna received a letter from Exeter, which informed her she
                    would have Mr. Jones’s answer about Mr. Pomeroy in the evening; and her fears
                    for him flung her into a violent agitation; every nerve in her shook, and she
                    fell sick as though she would have fainted away. She could not keep in her bed,
                    but laid herself on the floor in agonies, and said she knew not whether to pity
                    or condemn him; but at last got up in a rage against the Devil, and said her
                    revenge would be sweet to see the Devil chained down, and she should like, with
                    a sharp sword, to cut him in pieces. She then got into bed, exclaiming against
                    the clergy, and asked for a glass of wine; but she brought it up immediately.
                    Soon after the bason was set upon the bed, she took it up and dashed it
                    violently across the room, and broke it to pieces. After that she had some lamb
                    brought up for her dinner; she tried to swallow a mouthful but could not, but
                    spit it into another bason, and said she could neither swallow the wine nor the
                    lamb, but found the fury of the Lord break in upon her, and she dashed the
                    second bason on the floor. She then said she felt herself happier and easier
                    since she had broken both the basons; for so would the Lord, in his anger, break
                    the clergy.’</p>
                <p rend="indent1">This is from a book with the following curious title:
                    <quote>MR. JOSEPH SOUTHCOTT, THE BROTHER OF
                JOANNA SOUTHCOTT, WILL NOW COME FORWARD AS DINAH’S BRETHREN DID, THAT THEY SHALL NOT DEAL WITH HIS SISTER AS THEY WOULD WITH A HARLOT, FOR SO THEY ARE NOW DEALING WITH HER. AND HE WILL PROVE TO THE WORLD WHERE THE ADULTERY IS COMMITTED, BY MEN WHO ARE UNCIRCUMCISED IN HEART AND LIFE: AND NOW HE WILL EXPEND ALL THAT HE HAS IN THE WORLD, IF REQUIRED, IN THE HONEST DEFENCE OF HER CHARACTER, TILL HE HAS SLAIN THE UNCIRCUMCISED PHILISTINES, AND ENTIRELY FREED HIS SISTER FROM THE REPROACHES OF THEIR ADULTERY.<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editor">(London, 1804), pp. 30-31.</note></quote></p>
                <p>A few flowers of infernal eloquence should be added from The Dispute with the
                    Powers of Darkness. Satan says to her, ‘Thou infamous B---ch! thou hast been
                    flattering God that he may stand thy friend. Such low cunning art I despise.Thou
                    wheening devil! stop thy d-mn d eternal tongue; thou runnest on so fast all the
                    Devils in Hell cannot keep up with thee.—God hath done something to chuse a b-ch
                    of a woman that will down-argue the Devil, and scarce give him room to
                        speak.’<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editor">
                        <title>A Dispute</title>, p. 32.</note>—It may truly be said, in Joanna’s
                    own words, <hi rend="ital">‘If the woman is not ashamed of herself the Devil
                        cannot shame her</hi>’.<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editor"><title>A
                            Dispute</title>, p. 34.</note></p>
                <p rend="indent1">If the language of Joanna herself is grovelling in the very mud
                    and mire of baseness and vulgarity, one of her elders has soared into the
                    sublime of frenzy. The passage is long, but deserves insertion, as, perhaps,
                    there does not exist elsewhere so complete a specimen of a prophet rampant. The
                    gentleman begins in some plain prose reflections upon the Fall, and goes on
                    addressing the Devil, till he has worked himself up, and begins thus to rave in
                    rhythm.
                    <quote>‘—Then where’s thy ground on earth? receive thy doom, the pit,
                    there twist in flames, and there thy like deceive!—Then Cain receive thy doom
                    from Abel’s blood. Then where is Pharoah and his host? Judge then, need Moses
                    fear! Where is the Lion fallen! and the pit has oped its mouth,—the covering’s
                    dropt; the Lamb has nought to fear—then roar no more to shake the earth and sea.
                    Where now’s the eagle and vultur’d host—thy wings are pluck’d on earth, she
                    stands defenceless, the fatal net beneath.—The Dove now has protection; she
                    ranges earth and sea, and soars aloft unhurt, unfeared, to carry peace to
                    all.—The Ark is opened now, she brings the olive branch,—the floods are past,
                    where’s now the giant race?—Who pressed on Lot? ’Twas thee the proud oppressor!
                    Where art thou now?—Where is thy pride and city? Knowest thou the words, come
                    out! come out! let Sodom feel its doom. Where now is Lot? At Zoar safe! Where is
                    his wife? Is she not salt all?—The writing’s on the wall.—Thou lewdly revellest
                    with the bowls of God.—Thy kingdoms past away—Now see my Daniel rise—Who cast
                    him in his den?—’Twas thee—Thou rolledst the stone, thou sealedst his doom—the
                    roaring Lion thee! Then let the stone return, the seal be broke, and go thou in
                    his stead. Where is the image gold and Bel? Where is proud Babel’s builder?
                    Confusion is thy name: confusion is thy doom! Let Bel asunder burst! the pitch,
                    and tar, and walls of wood expose thy make, deceit, and craft,—and pass in
                    flames away. The God of Daniel stands—Daniel rise up! Six days are past—the
                    seventh now is here—seven times refined and purified in innocency come.—The
                    emerald, unhurt in fire, displays great Judah’s son.—Let Urim’s light and
                    Thummim shine in bright perfection’s day. The twelve men stand upon the
                    plate—the fourth denotes great Judah’s son, who is the rightful heir. The stones
                    denote all Jacob’s sons, their light and quality—they shine as stars in Jesus’
                    crown upon the Woman’s head.—The Sun unveil’d shall now arise—The Moon from
                    scarlet shall emerge—The stars from darkness now appear to light the midnight
                    hour—Then where art thou, O Satan! Where are thy heads, and horns, and dragon’s
                    tail, which slew and hurt the living stars! Where are thy rays of fire—thy
                    watery floods—behold they are past away—The woman’s fears of thee are o’er—the
                    wilderness receives her child, whose iron rod now feel. The pit has oped its
                    mouth—thou art now cast, shut up and sealed—the saints now judge the earth. The
                    Omnipotent is here in power and spirit in the word—The sword, white horse, and
                    King of Kings has drawn the flailing sword! Rejoice, ye saints, rejoice! The
                    Beast and Dragon, mountain, tree, no more shall hurt, devour, becloud, the
                    Saint, the gold and vine. The gold and gems appear—The mighty earthquake now
                    displays the hidden son of God. The rod and smitten rock gush forth, and smite
                    and slay, and make alive, now saves and now destroys. The cloud and glory,
                    Jonah’s sign, display the virtues of the word, the light and darkness shews. The
                    Gospel brings the light, and life, and death—and death as men obey or mock. The
                    six denotes the suffering time to show the Son of Man—The sign within the
                    Sun—The fowls now feast on thee! Then where’s thy former reign? Beneath the rod
                    of Moses see thy fall from Heaven’s height. Son of the Morning, Lucifer, no more
                    oppress—be thou a fallen star! Great Gog and Agag, where are ye? The walls of
                    Jericho art thou; fall flat! Joshua’s ram’s horns, the seven and twelve, pass
                    Jordan’s stream.—Where is the Lion, Bear, Goliath huge, but in the center thee.
                    David appears, a stripling youth, now tears and slays, and slings the stone, and
                    smites thy dragon’s head. Now see great David’s reign—The temple’s stones,
                    unhewed by man in those days, unite, the King of Peace amidst the seven in oil
                    unite, and in a stone with seven eyes appears, The stately fabric now is laid,
                    founded and topped with gems of every hue. The ark of Moses now is built—The
                    words, the laws, the sceptre, all unite, and Aaron’s budded rod—He now is
                    chosen; eat the bread, prepare the sacrifice. John eats the book, which sweet
                    and bitter is—He prophecies; the temple metes, and stands before the Lamb. The
                    temple measures, and anoints, and Moses’ tabernacle. The witnesses, Matthew and
                    John, as olive trees appear.—The broken stones of Moses now uplift, renewed in
                    books arise from death.—The Lord’s anointed reigns—The rods, or laws, of Ephraim
                    ten, unite is one and hold by Judah’s skirt—The Son of Man o’er Israel
                    reigns—The dry bones now arise—Here ends thy earthly reign—The bond of union now
                    is come—The marriage ring appears—The Bride is come—The Bridegroom now receives
                    the marriage seal—The Law and Gospel now unite—The Moon and Sun appear—Caleb and
                    Joshua pass the stream in triumph to restore. Where now thou Canaanite art thou?
                    Where all thy maddened crew?               
                    <lg type="verse">                    
                    <l rendition="#indent2">‘Hittites, be gone! no more appear to hurt or to annoy; </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">Now Israel’s sons in peace succeed, and Canaan’s land enjoy. </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">Behold from Edom I appear with garments dipt in blood;</l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">My sons are freed and saved, and wash’d amidst the purple
                        flood. </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">The law, of moon, imperfect was to save—</l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">But now the star points dead men to the grave.</l>                        
                    </lg>
                    
                ‘Mercy benign appears—The Gospel Sun embraces all—The Spirit and the Bride
                    invite, and offer wine and milk—but not to mockers here. Infinity of love and
                    grace! Gentiles and Jews unite, no more from love to part. Six days are
                    past—Peter, and James, and John, behold my glory in my word.                    
                <lg type="verse">                    
                    <l rendition="#indent2">‘The Law and Prophets now are seen with Jesus’ word to shine, </l>
                    <l rendition="#indent2">But what hast thou, thou serpent here, to do with love
                        benign?</l>
                </lg>
                   
                    
                ‘Tremble and flee, ’tis done. The seals are burst—the vials pour and end thy
                    destiny.</quote>
                ‘These are a small part of the thoughts of the judgments of God
                    pronounced on Satan,’ concludes the writer, who is a gentleman of vast
                    respectability.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">One of her books has the title printed on the last page, because
                    it was ordered that the book should contain neither more nor less than
                    forty-eight pages. Another has a seal in the middle of it bearing the letters J.
                    C.—the J., it is said, being meant for Jesus and Joanna!!</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
