<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Robert Southey and Millenarianism: </title>
                <title type="subordinate">Documents Concerning the Prophetic Movements of the Romantic
                    Era</title>
                <editor>
                    <name>Tim Fulford</name>
                </editor>
                <editor role="editor">Tim Fulford</editor>
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor,</resp>
                    <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor,</resp>
                    <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Laura Mandell</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="nines">rce6004</idno>
                <idno type="edition">intro</idno>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                    Maryland</publisher>
                <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                <date when="2011-11-01">June 1, 2012</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                        or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                        purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                        use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                        are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                        with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                        permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                        requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                        notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
                        forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
                    </p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                        conditions: <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                        them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                        have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                        Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                        continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                        generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                        a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                        use.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title level="a" type="main">Introduction</title>
                     
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m" type="main">Robert Southey and Millenarianism: </title>
                        <title level="m" type="subordinate">Documents Concerning the Prophetic Movements of the Romantic
                            Era</title>
                        <editor>
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Tim</forename>
                                <surname>Fulford</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                                Maryland</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                            <date when="2011-11-01">November 1, 2011</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>APEX used utf-8 codes for quotation marks, hyphens, and all special characters; except in the introduction, "hi rend="ital" has been used for titles.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                    10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smcap" scheme="css">font-variant:small-caps;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                    xml:id="genre">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                        http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                        on 2009-02-26</bibl>
                    <category xml:id="g1">
                        <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g2">
                        <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g3">
                        <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g4">
                        <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g5">
                        <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g7">
                        <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g6">
                        <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g8">
                        <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g9">
                        <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g10">
                        <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g11">
                        <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g12">
                        <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g13">
                        <catDesc>History</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g14">
                        <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g15">
                        <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g16">
                        <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g17">
                        <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g18">
                        <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g19">
                        <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g20">
                        <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g21">
                        <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g22">
                        <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g23">
                        <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g24">
                        <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g25">
                        <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g26">
                        <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g27">
                        <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g28">
                        <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g29">
                        <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g30">
                        <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g31">
                        <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g32">
                        <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g33">
                        <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g34">
                        <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g4"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
                <date>2012-25-04</date>
                <list>
                    <item>change to RC TEI Headers</item>
                    <item>runs transforms to html</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="paratext">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <ab>
                    <hi rend="bold">A Brief History of Prophetic Movements 1788-1832</hi>
                </ab>
                <p>The commentaries on millenarian enthusiasm<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editor"
                        >I adopt the term <hi rend="ital">millenarianism</hi> to describe the belief
                        that Christ’s second coming and/or an apocalypse would precede the coming of
                        a millennium; <hi rend="ital">millennialism</hi> is used to denote the
                        belief in a gradually approaching millennium without preceding
                        apocalypse.</note> reproduced in this edition date from two significant
                    periods in the career of a onetime religious and political radical, who was so
                    fascinated by prophecy that he portrayed it in poem after poem. Robert Southey
                    was a friend of prophets and their followers when in 1796 he published the epic
                        <title>Joan of Arc</title>, in which the central focus is on the
                    power of Joan’s prophetic conviction to inspire both herself and others. He
                    followed it with the Arabian epic <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801),
                    in which the hero is named as one of the Taliban—Muslim fanatics believing
                    themselves to be called by God to stamp out corruption and heresy, even at the
                    cost of their own lives. His next epic <title>Madoc</title> (1805), featured a
                    Native American prophet, Neolin, who enthralled his tribe, persuading them he
                    could propitiate the gods and foresee future events. And <title>The Curse of
                        Kehama</title> (1810) demanded that readers, if they were to follow its plot
                    with interest, must suspend their disbelief in Hindu ‘superstitions’.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Given Southey’s abiding interest in the nature and culture of
                    prophetic belief, it is not surprising that he should have provided some of the
                    first detailed accounts of the prophetic movements of his time. The first, from
                        <ref target="../HTML/Espriella.html">his mock-travelogue <title>Letters from
                            England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella</title></ref> was written
                    between 1805-07, when Southey, settled in Keswick and remote from the radical
                    acquaintances of his 1790s’ years in Bristol, was revising his political and
                    religious views in the wake of Napoleonic aggression in Iberia. The second, <ref
                        target="../HTML/Holmes.html">a piece from the <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title> of 1809</ref>, shows him gathering information about
                    religious sects in America and their relationship to millenarianism in Britain.
                    The third, an <ref target="../HTML/Wesley.html">extract from his 1820
                            <title>Life of Wesley</title></ref>, appeared when he, faced by the
                    revival of radical agitation in the years of the Peterloo Massacre and the trial
                    of Queen Caroline, made it his business to detect threats to the established
                    church and state and to diagnose their underlying causes. Here, he cites
                    examples of popular enthusiasm to demonstrate that even Wesley, though often
                    cautious about such manifestations, sometimes gave them credit. Yet he is still
                    an admirer of Wesley, both for having the charisma to awaken people’s spiritual
                    consciences and for directing the movement he began disinterestedly, rather than
                    for self-glorification or political influence (the operative contrast being with
                    Lord George Gordon). The fourth is <ref target="../HTML/Gregoire.html">an
                        article from the <title>Quarterly Review</title> of 1822</ref>, surveying
                    popular prophetic movements in the past and present in great detail. This piece
                    constitutes one of the most comprehensive studies of millenarian
                    enthusiasm to be published in the Romantic era. In all these commentaries, it is
                    apparent that Southey viewed religious enthusiasm as a quintessential part of
                    the spirit of the age, a social phenomenon with political ramifications, capable
                    of fomenting revolutionary fervour.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">How perceptive was he? To what extent, looking back from the
                    twenty-first century, does Southey’s diagnosis ring true? And how do the details
                    that he put into print for the first time—details, for example, of the Avignon
                    prophets <ref target="people.html#BryanWilliam">William Bryan</ref> and <ref
                        target="people.html#WrightJohn">John Wright</ref>, of <ref
                        target="people.html#BrothersRichard">Richard Brothers</ref> and of <ref
                        target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcott</ref>—resonate in the
                    wider context of prophetic writing in the period? To answer these questions it
                    is necessary to survey the history of prophecy and of the culture in which it
                    was received.</p>
                <ab rend="center">**************</ab>
                <p>In 1780 most Britons, whether they were Anglicans or dissenters, accepted the
                    conventional Christian teaching that the millennium was a distant event. They
                    believed in the gradual passage of the present, sinful, world into the reign of
                    Christ at some unknown time in the future. After a thousand years of Christ’s
                    kingdom on earth, judgment and apocalypse would occur. By the 1790s, things had
                    changed: after the unprecedented upheaval of the French Revolution many
                    abandoned the conventional view and expected the millennium to arrive in their
                    own lifetime, preceded by apocalyptic destruction. This expectation was shared
                    by poets and political leaders as well as sectarians and self-styled prophets.
                    It was reflected in the verse of self-taught writers such as Joanna Southcott
                    and William Blake and in the prose of university-educated scholars such as G. S.
                    Faber and S. T. Coleridge. Social reformers, clerical conservatives and
                    religious revolutionaries all preached versions of the ancient belief, set down
                    in the books of Daniel and Revelation, that the world would be convulsed by
                    apocalyptic destruction only to be renewed in a millennium of peace and plenty.
                    In the words of historian W. H. Oliver, millenarianism was ‘distributed over
                    English society as a whole, and was felt by every group, from landed proprietors
                    to out-of-work factory hands’.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editor">W. H.
                        Oliver, <title>Prophets and Millennialists: The Uses of Biblical Prophecy in
                            England from the 1790s to the 1840s</title> (Auckland and Oxford, 1978),
                        pp. 15-16.</note></p>
                <p rend="indent1">The prophetic movements of the French Revolutionary period have
                    been studied by numerous historians, in the wake of the groundbreaking
                    assessment of millenarian and radical politics in E. P Thompson’s <title>The
                        Making of the English Working Class</title> (1963). Thompson’s discussion of
                    the impact on nineteenth-century society of Richard Brothers and Joanna
                    Southcott ensured that popular millenarianism would no longer be dismissed as
                    the fantasy of crackpots. Subsequently, more detailed work by Clarke Garrett and
                    J. F. C. Harrison revealed the sheer extent to which millenarianism—and the
                    interconnected practices of mesmerism, mysticism and popular medicine—shaped
                    British radicalism in the aftermath of the French Revolution.<note n="3"
                        place="foot" resp="editor">Clarke Garrett, <title>Respectable Folly:
                            Millenarians and the French Revolution in France and England</title>
                        (Baltimore, Md. and London, 1975) and J. F C. Harrison, <title>The Second
                            Coming: Popular Millenarianism 1780-1850</title> (New Brunswick, N. J.,
                        1979).</note> Millenarianism was not an addition to radical politics but one
                    of the principal discourses in which that politics was formulated, and not only
                    for the urban labouring class but also, as Garrett and Oliver reveal, for
                    ‘respectable’ middle-class dissenters such as Joseph Priestley and Richard
                    Price. Indeed, it was Price who, in a 1789 sermon to the London Revolution
                    Society, imagined that events in France would bring about an era in which the
                    nations ‘would beat (as Isaiah prophesies) their swords into ploughshares, and
                    their spears into pruning hooks’.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editor">Quoted
                        in Morton D. Paley, <title>Apocalypse and Millennium in English Romantic
                            Poetry</title> (Oxford, 1999), p. 41.</note> Priestley went further
                    still, abandoning his earlier belief in a gradual progress to a distant
                    millennium and announcing that the violence of the French Revolution was
                    fulfilling Daniel’s prophecies that a fifth monarchy, ruled by the Son of Man,
                    would supersede all others.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editor">Joseph
                        Priestley, <title>The Present State of Europe Compared with Ancient
                            Prophecies</title> (1794, facs. rpt. Oxford, 1989).</note></p>
                <p rend="indent1">The flavour of this radical conflation of contemporary world
                    events and biblical texts is revealed in the diary of Thomas Holcroft. On 20
                    February 1799, after Napoleon’s defeat in Egypt, Holcroft called on William
                    Sharp, the engraver and radical campaigner, and
                <quote>paid him for his print of <title>The Sortie of Gibraltar;</title> which he
                    said ... was the last on such a subject, meaning the destruction of war, that
                    would ever be published.. . . The wisdom of the Creator had occasioned all our
                    miseries: but the tongue of wisdom was now subdued, meaning Egypt, which was not
                    only a slip of land resembling a tongue, but the place in which the learning of
                    the world originated. Thus, by the help of a pun and a metaphor, he had double
                    proof... Syria, Palestine, and all these countries are soon to be
                    revolutionized; and those who do not take up arms against their fellow men, are
                    to meet at the Grand Millennium.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editor">Quoted
                        in Erdman, <title>Prophet Against Empire,</title> 3rd edn. (Princeton, NJ.,
                        1977), p. 343. William Sharp the engraver (1747-1824), already interested in
                        Mesmerism and Swedenborgianism, became a follower of Brothers and, in 1795,
                        engraved Brothers’ image above the title ‘Richard Brothers Prince of the
                        Hebrews’. After Brothers’ confinement, Sharp became a follower, and
                        subsequently one of the elders, of Southcott. He published <title>An Answer
                            to the World, for putting in print a book in 1804, called, Copies and
                            parts of Copies of Letters and Communications, written from Joanna
                            Southcott</title> (London, 1806).</note></quote>
                Horrified at this kind of optimistic interpretation of revolutionary violence,
                    Edmund Burke depicted Price, Priestley, and their fellow millenarians as
                    dangerous subversives, comparing them with the regicide sectarians of Britain’s
                    revolution of the 1640s. From then on, millenarianism, real and accused, became
                    a crucial factor in the vituperative war of words that polarized British
                    politics and precipitated the imprisonment of many opponents of the
                    government.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Millenarianism became a feature of the urban, artisan culture that
                    produced the political societies that the government feared would bring about
                    revolution. William Sharp was a not untypical example: a member of the London
                    Corresponding Society, he associated with other millenarians and sectarians,
                    including <ref target="people.html#BryanWilliam">William Bryan</ref>. Like many
                    dissenting Londoners, he already had a history of millenarian faith. Followers
                    of Emmanuel Swedenborg (including, for a short time, William Blake) believed
                    that the millennium had already arrived. Faced with dissension in their New
                    Jerusalem church, however, many transferred their allegiance to the most famous
                    and extraordinary millenarian prophet to emerge in the 1790s—<ref
                        target="people.html#BrothersRichard">Richard Brothers</ref>. Brothers, as
                    Morton D. Paley has shown, had begun prophesying in 1792.<note n="7"
                        place="foot" resp="editor">Morton D. Paley, ‘William Blake, The Prince of
                        the Hebrews, and The Woman Clothed with the Sun’, in <title>William Blake:
                            Essays in Honour of Sir Geoffrey Keynes,</title> ed. Morton D. Paley and
                        Michael Phillips (Oxford, 1973), pp. 260-93 (p. 261). On Brothers, see also
                        E. P Thompson, <title>The Making of the English Working Class,</title> rev.
                        edn. (Harmondsworth, 1968).</note> Then, he had declared that Britain’s war
                    with revolutionary France presaged the ‘fall of Monarchy in Europe’.<note n="8"
                        place="foot" resp="editor">Richard Brothers, <title>A Revealed Knowledge of
                            the Prophecies and the Times</title> (London, 1794), pp. 11, 19.</note>
                    By 1795 he was announcing that God had commanded him to bear witness that George
                    III would deliver up his crown to him. London was Babylon; the British monarchy
                    was the Beast of the Book of Revelation: both would be destroyed by an
                    apocalyptic earthquake with only those who followed Brothers to Jerusalem
                    escaping to found a new millennium there. Brothers announced himself to be the
                    prince of the Israelites, sent by God to lead the Hebrews back to the promised
                    land.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Brothers scheduled the earthquake for 4 June. Unfortunately for
                    him, he was not by that time on his way to the Holy Land, but confined, by order
                    of the Lord Chancellor, in a private madhouse. Alarmed by Brothers’ statements,
                    the ministry had had him arrested, on 4 March, on the charge of ‘wickedly
                    writing, publishing, and printing various fantastical prophecies, with intent to
                    cause dissension and other disturbances within the realm’.<note n="9"
                        place="foot" resp="editor"><title>The Times</title>, 6 March 1795, quoted
                        in Paley, ‘William Blake, The Prince of the Hebrews’, p. 261.</note>
                    According to the <title>Times</title>, the arrest was justified, for Brothers
                    had ‘become the tool of a faction, employed to seduce the people, and to spread
                    fears and alarms’.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editor"><title>The
                            Times</title>, 5 March 1795.</note> Visited by known radicals,<note
                        n="11" place="foot" resp="editor">As James K. Hopkins reminds us, many of
                        the reformers most feared by the ministry were, even before Brothers’
                        appearance, millenarians. Several, including William Sharp, became followers
                        of Brothers. See A <title>Woman To Deliver Her People: Joanna Southcott and
                            English Millenarianism in an Era of Revolution</title> (Austin, Tex.,
                        1982), pp. 152-53.</note> Brothers, in the ministry’s eyes, threatened to
                    bring about revolution and regicide by harnessing religious fervour to
                    democratic politics—and this at a time of millenarian preaching by reformers
                    such as Coleridge, who viewed the French Revolution as the beginning of the Last
                    Days, heralding apocalypse. James Gillray illustrated the government’s fear with
                    a caricature in which Brothers appears as an agent of revolutionary France,
                    against a backdrop of a burning London.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editor"
                        >James Gillray ‘The Prophet of the Hebrews, The Prince of Peace, conducting
                        the Jews to the Promis’d-Land’, 5 March 1795.</note></p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Brothers seemed dangerous to the government because the
                    millenarian ideology of reformers such as Price and Priestley, taken into the
                    working classes by charismatic figures such as Brothers, resembled the radical
                    Protestantism of the seventeenth century. Then, groups such as the Muggletonians
                    had supported the overthrow of the monarchy in the name of millenarian religion.
                    Now, dissenters were consciously reviving their ideas and those of men such as
                    the regicide John Milton, who, in his political tracts, <title>Of
                        Reformation</title> and <title>Areopagitica,</title> had identified the
                    English republic of the 1640s with the prophesied second coming of Christ, the
                    ‘shortly-expected king’. This heady brew of prophecy and politics had issued in
                    the execution of Charles I. Now, Pitt and his ministers, after George III was
                    attacked in his carriage on the way to open Parliament, were desperate to
                    prevent a repeat. They had Coleridge, admirer of Priestley and Milton and writer
                    of millenarian poetry that condemned Britain’s rulers, spied upon. And as a
                    warning to millenarian radicals, they had Gilbert Wakefield, a retiring
                    classical scholar influenced by Milton’s writings, thrown in prison. Wakefield
                    had been typical of many dissenters in adopting the tones of a seer, as this
                    example of his work from 1796 reveals: ‘I see that deluge of mighty waters
                    gradually subside into their wonted channel: I see them flow with a majestic
                    tranquility to the ocean, and all the traces of their former ravages obliterated
                    by one extensive and expanding Paradise of verdure, fertility, and beauty’.<note
                        n="13" place="foot" resp="editor">Gilbert Wakefield,<title> A Reply to the
                            Letter of Edmund Burke, Esq., to a Noble Lord</title> (London, 1796), p.
                        31.</note> Wakefield’s flood is the deluge of the French Revolution. He
                    welcomes it because it promises, in the pattern of millenarian religious
                    dissent, a paradise of beauty after its awful destructiveness. Wakefield’s
                    imprisonment told other millenarian writers that a gentlemanly education and a
                    retiring scholarly life would not save them from prosecution. Prophetic texts,
                    as well as agitation on the streets, could put one’s liberty in danger. By 1798
                    Brothers languished in a madhouse, Wakefield rotted in jail, Priestley fretted
                    in America. Government repression seemed to have stamped out religious
                    radicalism.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Millenarianism proved a hardier plant than the ministry expected,
                    although it persisted in different forms, some simply less visible, others less
                    immediately worrying. A less visible form was Mesmerism, a practice based on the
                    belief that humans could learn to channel, for the benefit of others, the
                    universal ether of which the world was created. To orthodox scientists and
                    priests, Mesmerism and millenarianism went together. They were an infectious new
                    plague: the Edinburgh chemist John Robison, for instance, feared the ‘almost
                    irresistible’ influence of an association dedicated to ‘rooting out all the
                    religious establishments, and overturning the existing governments of Europe’.
                    The members of this association were, he diagnosed,
                    ‘Magicians-Magnetisers-Exorcists, &amp;c’.<note n="14" place="foot"
                        resp="editor">J. Robison, <title>Proofs of a Conspiracy Against All the
                            Religions and Governments of Europe</title> (Dublin, 1798), pp. 11,
                        6.</note> And for former radical W. H. Reid, millenarian medicine threatened
                    London itself: a set of ‘Infidel mystics’, ‘made up of Alchymists, Astrologers,
                    Calculators, Mystics, Magnetizers, Prophets, and Projectors’, had embraced the
                    politics of France and were spreading democracy among the ‘lower orders’.<note
                        n="15" place="foot" resp="editor">W. H. Reid, <title>The Rise and
                            Dissolution of the Infidel Societies in this Metropolis</title> (London,
                        1800), pp. 91, iii.</note> Mesmerism and millenarianism appealed to the
                    ‘lower orders’ because they gave power to men who were otherwise
                    powerless—excluded by poverty and/or faith from voting or holding office: men
                    like the engraver <ref target="people.html#BryanWilliam">William Bryan</ref>,
                    who after visiting the secret Society of Avignon became a healer and magnetist
                    in Bristol. The painter Phillipe De Loutherborg also thought himself to be
                    empowered to manipulate divine grace for medicinal purposes. He became a faith
                    healer as well as a kabbalistic hermeneutist and apocalyptic artist.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> If faith healing was a displaced form of millenarianism (an
                    attempt to realize the prophet’s role at the level of the body), then so was the
                    political philosophy of William Godwin, himself a lapsed dissenting minister.
                    Godwin’s <title>Essay Concerning Political Justice</title> (1793) was ostensibly
                    atheist. Yet, although he rejected the Christianity he had once taught, Godwin
                    retained in his secular vision of historical progress the pattern of
                    millennialist belief. As men became more rational and desires withered,
                    government would also die away because men would act for what they reasoned to
                    be right—the greater good of all. Even sexual desires would be replaced by a
                    recognition of what was reasonable. Godwin attacked marriage as ‘the worst of
                    all laws’ and ‘the worst of all properties’,<note n="16" place="foot"
                        resp="editor"><title>An Enquiry Concerning Political Justice</title>, vol.
                        III of <title>Political and Philosophical Writings of William
                        Godwin</title>, ed. Mark Philp (London, 1993), p. 453.</note> and envisaged
                    a slow, natural progression to a rational, communal society, to an anarchistic
                    millennium in which people would live without private property or government, in
                    equality and peace. He offered, that is to say, a secularized and politicized
                    version of the Christian belief in a slow transition of this world to the
                    millennial one, without apocalyptic destruction intervening. Because of this
                    long timescale, and because Godwin thought the transition was inevitable,
                    requiring no immediate political action to bring it about, the government did
                    not prosecute him. And his vogue was in any case brief. Nevertheless, Godwin was
                    a continuing influence on Coleridge and Wordsworth, who retained the imprint of
                    his ideas even though they came to reject his exclusive emphasis on rationalism.
                    And Godwin inspired Percy Shelley, helping to shape some of the greatest
                    millenarian poetry of the age in <title>Prometheus Unbound</title>.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Godwin’s philosophical millennialism may have appealed to poets,
                    but it revolted conservative politicians and Christian philosophers. In 1798 the
                    Revd. Thomas Malthus challenged it in a seminal work whose continuing cultural
                    power often obscures the fact that it was the mirror image of the millennialist
                    system it was designed to refute. Malthus charged Godwin with naive prophesying
                    and set out to answer him in statistical and empiricist terms. But Malthus also
                    adopted prophetic tones: he adapted the language of the Bible and of Milton to
                    depict humanity facing a perpetual apocalypse without a millennium to follow
                    it:
                <quote>The power of population is so superior to the power in the earth to produce
                    subsistence for man, that premature death must in some shape or other visit the
                    human race. The vices of mankind are active and able ministers of depopulation.
                    They are the precursors in the great army of destruction; and often finish the
                    dreadful work themselves. But should they fail in this war of extermination,
                    sickly seasons, epidemics, pestilence, and plague advance in terrific array, and
                    sweep off their thousands and ten thousands. Should success be still incomplete,
                    gigantic inevitable famine stalks in the rear, and with one mighty blow levels
                    the population with the food of the world.<note n="17" place="foot"
                        resp="editor">I quote from the 1798 edition in <title>The Works of Thomas
                            Robert Malthus,</title> 8 vols (London, 1986), I: <title>An Essay on the
                            Principle of Population</title> (1798), ed. E. A. Wrigley and David
                        Souden, pp. 51-52.</note></quote>
                Malthus’s arguments achieved great and lasting power. He had spoken to Britons’
                    fears about increasing population and poverty among the labouring classes and
                    had voiced their anxieties about national immorality and possible defeat in the
                    war with France. Much of the public subscribed to Malthus’s apocalyptic vision
                    of a nation deserving war, plague, famine and pestilence, as Revelation
                    suggested, if it did not mend its ways. So convincing was Malthus’s combination
                    of statistical ‘proof’ and prophetic rhetoric that the government introduced
                    measures designed to discourage the poor from having large families. For many
                    churchmen too, Malthus had proved the habits of rural labourers to be not only
                    immoral but a threat to national prosperity. Malthus’s apocalyptic scenario
                    encouraged Evangelical clerics to reform the poor, while his analysis prompted
                    secular economists to apply statistics to the study of society.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">
                    <ref target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcott</ref> had plenty of
                    experience of rural poverty and the social tensions it provoked. A former
                    servant in rustic Devon, she had little education or wealth. But she had
                    self-belief, and a gift for prediction that appealed to people (especially
                    women) of her background all over rural England. So when she arrived in London
                    in 1802, she was already a self-proclaimed prophet with an established
                        following.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editor">On Southcott, see James
                        K. Hopkins, <title>A Woman to Deliver Her People: Joanna Southcott and
                            English Millenarianism in an Era of Revolution</title> (Austin, TX,
                        1982).</note> She rapidly attracted many of Brothers’ followers, including
                    William Sharp, who tried to make William Blake a Southcottian too.<note n="19"
                        place="foot" resp="editor">As Paley shows (‘William Blake, The Prince of
                        the Hebrews’, p. 281).</note> Although Brothers himself disowned her,
                    Southcott continued to win support, hinting that she was the woman mentioned in
                    Genesis 3:15 whose ‘seed’ would bruise the head of the serpent. She offered
                    visions of the New Jerusalem in which her followers would live after the ‘woman
                    clothed with the sun’ had given birth to ‘a man child, who was to rule all
                        nations’.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editor">Revelation 12: 1, 5. See
                        Joanna Southcott, <title>Song of Moses and the Lamb</title> (London, 1804)
                        and <title>A Continuation of Prophecies</title> (Exeter, 1802).</note> This
                    event, according to the Book of Revelation, would precipitate the apocalyptic
                    battle in which Satan would be cast down.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Southcott gained a remarkable hold on the popular imagination—as
                    many as 100,000 may, by 1808, have accepted the seals of salvation she issued.
                    And the hold was long-lived, for even after she died, in 1814, having announced
                    she was pregnant with the child who would rule in the coming millennium, many of
                    her followers continued to look for the Shiloh she had borne. At least two men
                    tried to fill the role: testament to the continuing need throughout the Romantic
                    period to believe in a divine intervention that would transform living
                    conditions and bring about peace, security and wealth on this earth. To a nation
                    facing economic depression and unprecedented social change, the appeal of
                    Southcott is understandable.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Southcott steered deliberately clear of the political radicalism
                    with which Brothers had been associated. Her writing was avowedly loyal to the
                    government and in this it was similar to the millenarian prophecies of a number
                    of well-educated, higher-class, exegetes of scripture. The appeal of
                    millenarianism was not confined to urban artisan radicals and to the labouring
                    poor by any means. Bishops and dons also felt the need to interpret the European
                    war that followed the French Revolution as the fulfilment of Old Testament
                    predictions. They differed, however, from Priestley, Price and Brothers on the
                    question of whether Britain was to be singled out by God as one of the sinful
                    monarchies deserving destruction or whether it would be the nation chosen to
                    restore the Jews to the New Jerusalem. Samuel Horsley was a successful
                    churchman—a bishop and a fellow of the Royal Society—when, responding to the
                    French Revolution, he turned to prophesying. Horsley regarded the ‘French
                    Democracy, from its infancy to the present moment’, as ‘a conspicuous and
                    principal branch at least of the western Antichrist’.<note n="21" place="foot"
                        resp="editor"><title>Critical Disquisitions on the Eighteenth Chapter of
                            Isaiah</title> (1799), quoted in Oliver, <title>Prophets and
                            Millennialists</title>, p. 52.</note> The rise of the Antichrist would,
                    as predicted in Daniel, accompany ‘a dissolution of the whole fabric of the
                    external world’ and then the second coming.<note n="22" place="foot"
                        resp="editor">‘Letters to the Author of Antichrist in the French
                        Convention’, quoted in Oliver, <title>Prophets and Millennialists</title>,
                        p. 53.</note> Napoleon’s appearance was a stage in the rising of the
                    Antichrist too: it was Britain’s prophetic destiny to resist him.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> G. S. Faber, fellow of Lincoln College Oxford and then prebend of
                    Salisbury Cathedral, agreed. Like Horsley, a successful pillar of the
                    established church, Faber was no radical. He too saw the progress of the French
                    Revolution as evidence that the triumph of the Antichrist was at hand, preceding
                    apocalypse and the return of the Jews to the New Jerusalem. The battle of
                    Trafalgar, Faber thought, might be evidence that Britain was the great ‘maritime
                    power’, the messenger nation of Isaiah 18, which would alone be saved like ‘a
                    column in the midst of surrounding ruins [w]hile mighty empires totter to their
                    base, and while Antichrist advances with rapid strides to his predicted
                    sovereignty over the inslaved kings’.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editor">G.
                        S. Faber, quoted in Oliver, <title>Prophets and Millennialists</title>, p.
                        61.</note> James Hatley Frere was still more specific in his identification
                    of Napoleon as the Beast of Revelation who would reign in Rome and Palestine as
                    a false Messiah. In their many books, Horsley, Faber and Frere ranged their
                    millenarianism against the political radicalism that coloured the prophetic
                    interpretations of contemporary history made by men such as Price, Priestley,
                    and, at least in the 1790s, Coleridge too. Britain, they implied, was far from
                    being one of the sinful monarchies to be cast down, as the Bible predicted.
                    Instead, it might be the nation chosen by God to lead people to the New
                    Jerusalem.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Faber and Frere were interpreters, men whose prophetic activities
                    were confined to writing. But by the 1820s one of their students had turned to
                    action. Millenarian prophecy often went hand-in-hand with new and ‘alternative’
                    practices in which the body was viewed as the source of spiritual power. This
                    was the case in the church of the Revd. Edward Irving, a Scots preacher and
                    protégé of Coleridge, whose apocalyptic sermons won him fame in 1820s London.
                    Irving credited Coleridge with helping him to see the ‘error under which the
                    whole of the Church is lying, that the present world is to be converted unto the
                    Lord, and so slide by a natural inclination into the Church—the present reign of
                    Satan hastening, of its own accord, into the millennial reign of Christ’.<note
                        n="24" place="foot" resp="editor">Quoted in Oliver, <title>Prophets and
                            Millennialists</title>, p. 106.</note> Influenced by Coleridge’s views,
                    Irving came to believe in the necessity of an apocalypse to convulse the sinful
                    world into a millennial one. But he became a far more literal and dogmatic
                    interpreter of scripture than Coleridge ever was. The French Revolution, he
                    believed, had precipitated the pouring out of the six vials of wrath upon the
                    Beast. Now, after thirty years, the seventh was about to be poured. Destruction
                    and renewal was at hand; the dead would live again on earth with the returned
                    Christ.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> These views, announced in stirring sermons, made Irving a
                    fashionable sensation and drew to his Regent Square church a devoted following.
                    But Irving’s views were not in themselves extraordinary, for he was himself a
                    follower of Frere who interpreted the Napoleonic wars in the light of the Bible
                    and espoused, as a result, anti-democratic politics. Irving had offered himself
                    to Frere ‘as your pupil, to be instructed in prophecy’ in 1824.<note n="25"
                        place="foot" resp="editor">S. T. Coleridge, <title>Marginalia</title>, ed.
                        George Whalley and H. J. Jackson, 6 vols (London and Princeton, 1980-2001),
                        vol. II, p. 71n.</note> And his own views revealed Frere’s influence.
                    Coleridge, though by the 1820s sharing their dislike of political radicalism,
                    found them both too literal and blindly subjective: he wrote that they took ‘out
                    of their Bible what they had themselves put in’.<note n="26" place="foot"
                        resp="editor">Ibid.</note> Yet Coleridge himself was sure that the
                    predictions of the Bible prophets would come true, if unsure of when or how. In
                    1830 Thomas Chalmers reported him ‘unfolding his own scheme of the
                    Apocalypse—talking of the mighty contrast between its Christ and the Christ of
                    the Gospel narrative, Mr. Coleridge said that Jesus did not come now as
                    before-meek and gentle, healing the sick and feeding the hungry, and dispensing
                    blessings all around, but he came on a white horse; and who were his
                    attendants?—famine, and war, and pestilence’.<note n="27" place="foot"
                        resp="editor">Chalmers quoted in John Beer, ‘Transatlantic and Scottish
                        Connections: Uncollected Records’, in <title>The Coleridge Connection:
                            Essays for Thomas McFarland</title>, ed. Richard Gravil and Molly
                        Lefebure (London, 1990), pp. 308-43 (p. 327).</note></p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Still millenarian after all those years, Coleridge admired
                    Irving’s prophetic person if not his actual interpretations. In 1829 he declared
                    that the Scot had ‘more of the Head and Heart, the Life, the Unction, and the
                    genial power of MARTIN LUTHER than any man now alive’.<note n="28" place="foot"
                        resp="editor">Coleridge quoted in Beer, ‘Transatlantic and Scottish
                        Connections’, p. 326.</note> Irving seemed to embody the vatic role that
                    Coleridge had previously seen as the prerogative of Wordsworth (whom he likened
                    to a prophet in his ‘Lines to William Wordsworth’). He was a Romantic genius, ‘a
                    mighty wrestler in the cause of Spiritual Religion’, albeit one in need of
                        guidance.<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editor">Coleridge quoted in Beer,
                        ‘Transatlantic and Scottish Connections’, p. 326.</note></p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Ironically enough, it was Irving’s assumption of spiritual power,
                    his attempt to be a prophet in person rather than just, like Frere and Faber, an
                    interpreter of prophecy, that brought about his downfall. By 1831 he was
                    presiding over church services in which those who came to hear his oratory began
                    to writhe in ecstasy. The London air was thick with unknown languages as his
                    followers found themselves, like the apostles, speaking in tongues,
                    ‘prophesying’, and performing miracles of spiritual healing. Irving believed
                    that the Holy Spirit was making itself manifest in their bodies; the renewal of
                    the human by the spiritual that was promised at the millennium materialized in
                    his congregation’s flesh. It was all too literal and untrammelled for the church
                    authorities. Irving was deprived of his ministry and condemned for heretical
                    doctrine. Although Coleridge bemoaned his treatment and regretted his excesses,
                    Irving was set on his path: he established his own church, in which glossalalia
                    and faith healing still featured, until dissension broke it apart and he fell
                    into obscurity.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Irving’s failure was by no means the end of millenarianism. As W.
                    H. Oliver records, exegetes and sect leaders continued, as the nineteenth
                    century wore on, to promise the coming of Christ’s kingdom on earth. But Irving
                    was the last millenarian to make a strong impression on, and to have a strong
                    impression made on him by, Romanticism. By 1832, with the French Revolution and
                    the Napoleonic war long over, millenarianism was no longer a cultural force and
                    religious mode through which young intellectuals defined themselves. The poverty
                    and unrest that helped to fuel it still existed: the year 1831 saw rioting on a
                    countrywide scale as rural labourers suffered hunger. But too many prophets had
                    prophesied, too many days of predicted destruction gone without incident, for
                    most people to view political strife as a sign of the coming apocalypse. If the
                    French Revolution had once seemed a millennial ‘new dawn’ and an apocalyptic
                    ‘blood-dimmed tide’, it had by now become a familiar, compromised affair.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Yet the French Revolution was never the sole cause of the
                    intensification of millenarianism that characterized the Romantic period.
                    Movements such as Southcott’s and Irving’s, with their emphasis on miraculous
                    occupation of the body by the Holy Spirit, bespoke the need of many in the
                    period to restore power to the human, in an country where more and more people
                    were subjected to the inhuman discipline of factory, clock and technology and
                    where knowledge was increasingly institutionalized and bureaucratized, taken out
                    of ordinary people’s hands. Southcott and Irving were, that is to say, extreme
                    cases, physically literal versions, of a response that many in contemporary
                    Britain felt compelled to make, turning to the Bible as one of the few
                    authorities with which they could resist the domination of life by technologies
                    and institutions. Reduced to ‘operatives’, many Britons found their very
                    identity dominated by machines, machines whose concentration of power was such
                    that they, and not the people who worked them, seemed sublime.</p>
                <ab>
                    <hi rend="bold">Southey’s <title>Letters from England</title></hi>
                </ab>
                <p>The principal importance of the account of prophecy given in <title>Letters from
                        England</title> is the detailed portrait of three linked popular millenarian
                    phases—the visit to the Swedenborgian and Masonic prophets of Avignon by John
                    Wright and William Bryan, their and others’ subsequent endorsement of Richard
                    Brothers, and the early mission of Joanna Southcott (she had not yet announced
                    her pregnancy). Southey knew Bryan personally and <title>Letters from
                        England</title> benefits from his testimony. Southey was also friendly with
                    several other followers of Brothers—William Sharp, James Crease and Samuel
                    Whitchurch. Sharp transferred his allegiance to Southcott, who also attracted
                    the support of Southey’s longterm correspondent William Owen Pughe, the
                    translator of medieval Welsh texts. These contacts made Southey the one
                    middle-class journalist and author with extensive connections within the
                    prophetic movements. A thorough researcher, Southey bought and borrowed as many
                    pamphlets as he could in order to deepen his knowledge. He had an extensive
                    collection of Southcott’s publications, owned the very rare
                        <title>Testimony</title> of Bryan, and was familiar with the Brotherite
                    writings of Nathaniel Brassey Halhed. His 1790s friendships with millenarians,
                    continuing interest in Brothers and his followers, and developing knowledge of
                    Southcott, are evidenced in <ref target="../HTML/Prophets.html">his
                        letters</ref>, in which Bryan and Owen Williams Pughe, especially,
                    figure.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> In <title>Letters from England</title>, however, it is not Bryan
                    or Owen Pughe, but Halhed who emerges as the crucial figure in Southey’s
                    analysis of popular millenarianism, precisely because he was of the same,
                    educated gentlemanly class as Southey himself and his readers, and therefore
                    indicated prophecy’s popular appeal beyond the illiterate and ignorant poor. He
                    appears, in fact, as a doppelganger of Southey himself—a scholar drawn to
                    millenarian radicalism by his reading and his acquaintances but who had, unlike
                    Southey himself, abandoned any remaining sceptical independence. Halhed was a
                    East India Company official during the governorship of Warren Hastings. In
                    India, he became a scholar of ancient Hindu laws, which he began to translate as
                    part of Hastings’ effort to rule the colony by adapting its own traditions.<note
                        n="30" place="foot" resp="editor">In 1774 Hastings commissioned from Halhed
                        a translation of the compendium of Hindu law that had already been
                        translated from Sanskrit to Persian. Halhed also composed a grammar of
                        Bengali and several works interpreting Hindu scripture which he left
                        unpublished. See <title>A Code of Gentoo Laws, or, Ordinations of the
                            Pandits. From a Persian Translation, Made from the Original, Written in
                            the Sanskrit Language</title> (London, 1776), and <title>A Grammar of
                            the Bengal Language</title> (Hooghly, 1778). These, and other details
                        about Halhed, are from Rosane Rocher, <title>Orientalism, Poetry, and the
                            Millennium: The Checkered Life of Nathaniel Brassey Halhed
                            1751-1830</title> (Delhi, Varanasi, Patna, 1983).</note> Returning to
                    Britain in 1785, he continued to study Indian scripture, in correspondence with
                    Charles Wilkins, whose translation of the <title>Bhagavadgita</title> suggested
                    parallels between ancient Indian and Christian theology.<note n="31"
                        place="foot" resp="editor">Wilkins, <title>The Bhagvat-Geeta</title>
                        (London, 1785).</note> Halhed, therefore, was part of the most advanced
                    Orientalist scholarship of his day.<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editor">This
                        antiquarian scholarship, begun under Hastings’ governorship and continued by
                        Sir William Jones, culminated in Jones’s discovery of the Indo-European
                        language family. It also constituted part of an attempt to govern India more
                        firmly by manipulating Hindu law and scripture rather than imposing overtly
                        British systems. On the significance of this scholarship in Romanticism, see
                        Javed Majeed, <title>Ungoverned Imaginings: James Mill’s ‘History of British
                            India’ and Orientalism</title> (Oxford, 1992).</note> He did not remain
                    solely a scholar. In 1791 he became an MP, using his position to support the
                    cause of Hastings, who was being prosecuted for his conduct as Governor General
                    by the Foxite Whigs. A supporter of Pitt’s ministry, Halhed had an unremarkable
                    record of hostility to the French Revolution and those who admired it until, in
                    early 1795, he staggered all who knew him. On 29 January he announced himself a
                    follower of Brothers.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Convinced that Brothers was ‘the Man that will be revealed to the
                    Hebrews as their Prince, to all Nations as their Governor, according to the
                    Covenant to King David, immediately under GOD’,<note n="33" place="foot"
                        resp="editor">Nathaniel Brassey Halhed, <title>Testimony of the
                            Authenticity of the Prophecies of R. Brothers and of his Mission to
                            Recall the Jews</title>, 2nd edn (London, 1795), p. iv.</note> Halhed
                    fired off volleys of speeches and pamphlets against the government. It was this
                    defence by a gentleman, scholar and MP that kept Brothers in the news. The
                    polite classes were shocked that an educated man should believe in and defend a
                    popular cult. Pamphlets attacking Halhed abounded,<note n="34" place="foot"
                        resp="editor">See, for example, Thomas Williams, <title>The Age of
                            Credulity: A Letter to Nathaniel Brassey Halhed in Answer to his
                            Testimony in Favour of Richard Brothers</title> (Philadelphia,
                        1796).</note> but they only confirmed him in his belief. He went so far as
                    to sell his library in anticipation of the forthcoming walk to Jerusalem. He
                    even dated the commencement of the new millennium exactly: it would begin on 19
                    November. Despite a violent storm on the preceding day, neither the apocalypse
                    nor the millennium materialized to time. With Brothers still in confinement,
                    Halhed went quiet and became a recluse and a supporter of Brothers’ successor,
                    Joanna Southcott. Brothers himself carried on prophesying from his asylum, but
                    his support had waned. He was released in 1806, largely forgotten by the
                    public.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Southey, however, in the <title>Letter from England</title>
                    reproduced in this edition, remembered him. In the fictional persona of a
                    Spaniard visiting England, Southey described Brothers’ glory days and Halhed’s
                    strange career:
                <quote>Mr. Halhed was the other of these converts, a member of the House of Commons,
                    and one of the profoundest oriental scholars then living. This gentleman was in
                    the early part of his life an unbeliever, and had attempted to invalidate the
                    truths of holy writ by arguments deduced from Indian chronology. The study of
                    Indian mythology brought him back to Christianity, and by a strange perversion
                    of intellect the Trimourtee of the Hindoos convinced him of the doctrine of the
                    Trinity; and as he recovered his faith he lost his wits. To the astonishment of
                    the world he published a pamphlet avowing his belief that Richard Brothers was
                    the Lion of the Tribe of Judah, and that in him the prophecies were speedily to
                    be fulfilled.</quote>
                In Southey’s opinion, it was the Orientalism of Brothers that made Halhed keen to
                    believe in him. The metempsychosis that formed the basis of Brothers’ doctrine
                    was not new but bore ‘a general resemblance to that doctrine as held by the
                    Orientals’. Another critic also detected Indian influences. Brothers, he wrote,
                    would pass for a prophet among the Hindus but not by comparison with Isaiah,
                    Ezekiel and Daniel.<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editor">Williams, <title>The
                            Age of Credulity</title>, p. 11.</note> Halhed himself argued that his
                    faith in Brothers stemmed from the interpretative methods he had honed in
                    decoding ‘the old Hindu writings’. Viewing the ‘Hindu triad of Energies ...
                    Brahma, Vishnu, and Shiva’ as allegories of matter, space and time equipped him
                    to detect specific political allegory in the book of Daniel. He could ‘read the
                    modern history of Europe in the prophetic records of the Old and New Testament’,
                    a reading from which he would confirm the accuracy of Brothers’ prophecies.<note
                        n="36" place="foot" resp="editor">Halhed, <title>Testimony</title>, p.
                        10.</note></p>
                <p rend="indent1">For Southey, what made Halhed’s belief in Brothers especially
                    alarming was what it suggested about Britons’ susceptibility to revolutionary
                    creeds. Fanaticism, on his reading, had brought about regicide and terror in
                    France: Jacobinism was a mental infection stalking the streets in the mobs of
                    Paris. Brothers had revealed its presence among the common people of London but
                    Halhed brought it to the very centre of imperial power, to the arena in which
                    rational judgment about government at home and abroad was made—the House of
                    Commons. For Halhed had protested there when the ministry had had Brothers
                    confined:
                <quote>Mr. Halhed made a speech in parliament ... the most extraordinary perhaps
                    that ever was delivered to a legislative assembly. It was a calm and logical
                    remonstrance against the illegality and unreasonableness of their proceedings.
                    They had imprisoned this person as a madman, he said, because he announced
                    himself as a prophet; but it was incumbent upon them to have fairly examined his
                    pretensions, and ascertained their truth or falsehood, before they had proceeded
                    against him in this manner. Brothers had appealed to the Holy Scriptures, the
                    divine authority of which that house acknowledged; he appealed also to certain
                    of his own predictions as contained in the letters which he had addressed to the
                    king and his ministers; let them be produced, and the question solemnly
                    investigated as its importance deserved. According to the rules of the House of
                    Commons, no motion can be debated or put to the vote, unless it be seconded; Mr.
                    Halhed found no one to second him, and his proposal was thus silently
                    negatived.</quote>
                This passage shows Halhed to have attempted to infect Parliament with the disease
                    of enthusiasm. Rational and logical research into prophetic and miraculous
                    claims was exactly what had characterized Halhed’s research into Hinduism; now
                    that his research had been colonized by belief in the objects of his
                    investigation he had lost his ability to judge where the proper limits of
                    rational enquiry lay. Halhed had asked the Commons to make ‘cool and
                    dispassionate investigation of the grounds of [Brothers’] assertion’ and to
                    receive his own annotated copy of Brothers’ works to save ‘much labour of
                        reference’.<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editor">The speech is printed in
                        Nathaniel Brassey Halhed, <title>A Calculation on the Commencement of the
                            Millennium,</title> 4th edn (London, 1795), p. 144.</note></p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Worried by Halhed and unable to account for his enthusiasm for
                    Brothers, Southey was still more alarmed by the hold that Southcott exerted over
                    men he respected, such as Williams Pughe (as <ref target="../HTML/Prophets.html"
                        >his private correspondence </ref> reveals). Unable to explain Southcott’s
                    mental and spiritual appeal to native Britons, Southey instead identified her as
                    a foul and devilish body, who neither appealed through her beauty nor impressed
                    by her rationality: ‘The filth and the abominations of demoniacal witchcraft are
                    emblematical of such delusions; not the golden goblet and bewitching allurements
                    of Circe and Armida’. Southcott’s popularity showed much of Britain was also out
                    of rational order: ‘where such impious bedlamites as this are allowed to walk
                    abroad, it is not to be wondered at that madness should become epidemic’. By
                    locating Southcott’s appeal in a body he had made witchlike and infectious
                    Southey could argue for an immediate answer to the threat she posed his ideal
                    Britain: he recommended the same physical confinement as that imposed on
                    Brothers.</p>
                <p rend="indent1"> Bodily confinement, however, could not extirpate the public’s
                    desire to follow apocalyptic preachers any more than identifying Southcott’s
                    body as the source of the ‘infection’ could explain it. Bodily confinement in a
                    different sense proved to be the issue that made and unmade Southcott, for in
                    1814 she took her previous hints literally. She identified herself as the ‘woman
                    clothed with the sun’ and claimed to be pregnant with Shiloh, the returning
                    Messiah—thus identifying her body as the seat of her prophetic and holy power in
                    a manner that brought public interest to fever pitch.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Sixty-four years old when she announced her pregnancy, Southcott
                    died four months later (probably of the dropsy from which her body had swollen).
                    Although her body was preserved, the Son of God did not emerge. But if this
                    event showed her body to be limited and mortal rather than to be inhabited by
                    the divine, many of her followers did not believe so, and in 1825 Charles Twort
                    and George Turner both claimed to be the Shiloh she had borne. For the
                    Southcottians, her body remained the flesh in which the human and the divine
                    again met, while for Southey it remained the site of an enthusiastic belief that
                    characterized many Britons and that must, therefore, be kept in check by
                    government in the interests of social order and political stability. Excessive
                    spirituality had become easily stigmatized as the uncertain, diseased flesh of a
                    woman’s body—a body foreign either by birth or by virtue of what was thought to
                    be carried within it.</p>
                <p>Southey’s next published commentary on religious enthusiasm, and the second of
                    the texts presented in this edition was <ref target="../HTML/Holmes.html">his
                        review of Abdiel Holmes’s <title>American Annals</title> (1805)</ref>. This
                    text shows him expanding his survey of enthusiasm to include North America: his
                    account of camp meetings as places where mass self-abandonment occurred would
                    reappear in his later work on the influence of Methodism in England, as is
                    revealed in <ref target="../HTML/Wesley.html">this extract from his <title>Life
                            of Wesley</title> (1820)</ref>. These meetings suggested to him that
                    popular religion was a defining characteristic of every country among the
                    uneducated, who were manipulated by preachers who were either carried away by
                    the excitement of being able to induce excitement in others, or were cynical
                    exploiters of credulity in order to increase the power of the priesthood.
                    Southey returned to this theme in 1822, when <ref target="../HTML/Gregoire.html"
                        >his review of Henri Gregoire’s <title>Histoire des Sectes
                            Religieuses</title></ref> was published in the <title>Quarterly
                        Review</title>. Gregoire’s book had been published a decade earlier; the
                    fact that Southey wrote about it when he did suggests the strength of his need
                    to demonstrate the power and prevalence of prophecy both historically and in the
                    present. Indeed, the review was not so much an assessment of the merits of
                    Gregoire’s book as a report on enthusiasm, deriving its facts not only from
                    Gregoire but also from many other sources, and investigating recent movements
                    that Gregoire did not discuss. Southey’s article was, in fact, perhaps the most
                    comprehensive publication on prophecy and millenarianism to appear
                    in Britain in the first half of the nineteenth century. It was not just a
                    carefully researched report, moreover, but a piece with the pressing purpose of
                    warning the conservative readers of the <title>Quarterly</title> about
                    enthusiasm’s continuing social and political significance.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">
                    <title>Letters from England</title> and the review of Gregoire are both, in a
                    sense, travel narratives, since Southey uses the review format to cite
                    travellers in many different countries, including Bryan and Wright in France,
                    and lay preachers in the US, who bear firsthand witness to prophetic movements.
                    The effect is deliberately to collapse the typical British binary, in which
                    northern Europeans are portrayed as Protestant, rational and moderate, and
                    southern ones as Catholic, emotional and superstitious. Southey shows the
                    Germans and the Dutch to be historically more likely to generate prophetic
                    movements than the Italians and Spanish, and he details how such movements
                    flourished in enlightenment France and present-day Britain. His insight, then,
                    is to show that belief in prophecy, in millenarianism and in charismatic
                    phenomena is not attributable to doctrinal, ecclesiastical, or national causes
                    (though Protestants, having greater liberty of conscience, looser church
                    authority and a greater emphasis on reading and discussion of the Bible were
                    more likely to form sects). Rather, belief stemmed from social causes—from the
                    unguided self-education of artisans, combined with the arousal of social
                    aspirations by demagogues and power seekers in an age of political revolution. </p>
                <p rend="indent1"> The attention Southey paid to prophetic movements in the pieces
                    collected here amply demonstrates their importance in his own thought. The poet
                    of <title>Joan of Arc</title> continued to publish verse centred on the power of
                    spiritual belief to overcome the evidence of the senses. His 1825 poem <title>A
                        Tale of Paraguay</title> focused the beliefs of Jesuits and Indians in the
                    South American missions, adopting an attitude alternately critical and admiring
                    towards the colonial religion, which turned baptism into a sort of magical rite.
                    In 1829 <title>All for Love</title> and <title>The Pilgrim to
                        Compostella</title> dealt with Spanish Catholic stories of miracles and
                    relics, puzzling critics because they demanded admiration as well as derision
                    for the supposedly superstitious characters. Southey remained, that is to say,
                    fascinated by the psychology of enthusiastic belief—his fascination only
                    deepened by his historical research into its social manifestations.</p>
                <p rend="indent1">Was Southey right in his emphasis on prophecy’s social
                    significance in his time? Certainly, his view that its popularity was the
                    product of social factors—of an expanded labouring class with sufficient
                    education to read and discuss, whose political hopes had been frustrated by the
                    repression that followed in the wake of the French Revolution—chimes with that
                    of E. P. Thompson, who drew on Southey as a source in <title>The Making of the
                        English Working Class.</title> More recently, books by Iain McCalman, Jon
                    Mee, David Worrall and Robert Rix<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editor">Iain
                        McCalman, <title>Radical Underworld: Prophets, Revolutionaries, and
                            Pornographers in London, 1795-1840</title> (Cambridge, 1988), Jon Mee,
                            <title>Dangerous Enthusiasm: William Blake and the Culture of Radicalism
                            in the 1790s</title> (Oxford, 1992) and <title>Romanticism, Enthusiasm,
                            and Regulation: Poetics and the Policing of Culture in the Romantic
                            Period</title> (Oxford, 2003), David Worrall, <title>Radical Culture:
                            Discourse, Resistance and Surveillance, 1790-1820</title> (Hemel
                        Hempstead, 1992), Robert Rix, <title>William Blake and the Cultures of
                            Radical Christianity</title> (Aldershot and Burlington VT, 2007).</note>
                    have uncovered an underworld of prophetic and millenarian activity among
                    radicals that shaped artisanal social and political culture. Morton D. Paley,
                    meanwhile, has revealed the attraction of apocalyptic and millenarian discourse
                    for both poets and painters.<note n="39" place="foot" resp="editor">Paley,
                            <title>The Apocalyptic Sublime</title> (New Haven, 1986) and
                            <title>Apocalypse and Millennium in English Romantic Poetry</title>
                        (Oxford, 1999).</note> Southey may have been, with hindsight, alarmist to
                    fear that prophetic movements would undermine the established state, but he was
                    percipient when he first revealed how prevalent they were, without attributing
                    them to a single international conspiracy as Robison and Reid had done. His
                    analysis does ring true, and is remarkable because it was made so early, when
                    very few had made a thorough study and when the methodology for making such a
                    study was in its infancy. His proposed solution to prophecy was less perceptive:
                    in the materials provided here he mostly calls for prophetic leaders to be
                    locked up, either in prison or asylum. Later, in his social thought, he would
                    argue against democratisation and against the empowerment of the labouring
                    classes, fearing their tendency to follow self-proclaimed leaders. Instead, he
                    advocated a return to local paternalism in which a reformed landowning class,
                    mindful of its duties to protect the poor, preserved social and political
                    stability, resisting the commercial nexus which so disadvantaged the labouring
                    classes. Those arguments, set out in <title>Sir Thomas More; or, Colloquies on
                        the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829-31), are beyond the
                    scope of this edition, but nevertheless follow from the texts presented
                    here.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
