<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- “The Lime Trees of <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>: Romanticism’s Psychotic
                Future” -->
                </title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- David Sigler --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Elizabeth Fay --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- TJ AND JESSICA CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE PAUL'S NAMING CONVENTIONS IN THE "toc_file_names_for_links" DOC THAT IS LINKED TO THE SLACK CHANNEL-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2023.psychosis.sigler</idno> <!-- use the file name above as a reference, but do not include .xml -->
                <idno type="resource">psychosis</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- The Lime Trees of <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>: Romanticism’s Psychotic
                Future -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE THE NAMING DOC -->
                        <ptr target="praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.sigler"/>
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- JESS AND TJ CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">psychosis</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">regency culture</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">sexuality</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">gender</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">queer theory</term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Anna Wingfield. 12.6.2023  -->
                <name>Anna Wingfield</name>
                <date>12.6.2023</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
            <p>The Lime Trees of <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>: Romanticism’s Psychotic
                Future</p>
            <p>This essay examines Aurora Leighʼs reactions to an encroaching lime tree in Book I of
                Elizabeth Barrett Browningʼs 1856 novel in verse, <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>. I
                suggest that Aurora's psychotic response to the tree, from the vantage of her
                domestic prison, can be considered part of Barrett Browningʼs complex reaction to
                Samuel Taylor Coleridgeʼs poetry and the legacy of male-authored Romantic poetry
                generally. Drawing on the psychoanalytic concept of “ordinary psychosis” and the
                work on that topic by Jacques Lacan, I suggest that Barrett Browning develops,
                through the account of Aurora's paranoid delusion, a feminist poetics capable of
                situating itself in the future.</p>
                
            <p>In Book I of Elizabeth Barrett Browning’s 1856 novel in verse <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aurora Leigh</hi>, the eponymous protagonist is sent, upon the death of her
                father, to England to live with her aunt at Leigh Hall, which she experiences as a
                prison.<note place="foot" resp="author">This research has been supported by the Social Sciences and Humanities
                            Research Council of Canada, by Insight Grant #435-2017-0037Insight Grant
                            #156722. I thank Elizabeth Fay, Kate Singer, Kaz Oishi, and Alan Bewell
                            for their responses to earlier versions of this essay, and Julie Carlson
                            for her response in this volume.</note> Trapped by the
                ancestral house and the expectations of its residents, Aurora finds pleasure only in
                the library and its books of English poetry. The literary experience, though, does
                not stop her from being wary of the nearby lime tree, visible from the window of her
                study: </p>
                
            <p>First, the lime (I had enough, there, of the lime, to be sure,–</p>
            <p>My morning-dream was often hummed away</p>
            <p>By the bees in it;). (bk. 1, lines 578–580). </p>
                
            <p>The allusion is to Samuel Taylor Coleridge’s conversation poem “This Lime-Tree Bower
                My Prison,” written a half-century prior (1797, published 1800/1817). Like Barrett
                Browning, Coleridge had used a lime tree and garden bower as figures for domestic
                entrapment. Barrett Browning had long admired Coleridge’s verse. In the 1840s, she
                had declared Coleridge “so much the greater” poet than Robert Southey or William
                Wordsworth, and the “grander” and “intenser genius” than the latter; when
                corresponding with Sara Coleridge, she gushed with “reverence for the illustrious
                name you bear, which presented one of the earliest shrines of my hero worship" (Browning and Browning 5: 333, 7: 123, 10:129; Inboden 147). 
                Coleridge’s stated pleasure in how “a deep radiance lay / Full on the ancient ivy,” may be one of the reasons why
                Aurora chooses ivy, instead of bay or myrtle, for her self-made poetic crown (Coleridge, <hi rend="italic">Lime-Tree</hi> 54–55; Barrett Browning 2.40-–52).</p>
                
            <p>Yet Barrett Browning’s lime-tree bower seems a world away from Coleridge’s. In “This
                Lime-Tree Bower My Prison,” as soon as the speaker notices how “the solitary
                humble-bee / Sings in the bean-flower!,” he discovers that being “bereft of promis’d
                good  .  .  .  may lift the soul” (ll. 60–61, 67–68). The bees in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aurora Leigh</hi>, not solitary, are capable only of humming away Aurora’s
                “morning-dream.” The tree is at the edge of Aurora’s consciousness, not the center:
                Aurora’s aunt encourages her to sit </p>
                
            <p>in just the chair she placed,  </p>
            <p>With back against the window, to exclude  </p>
            <p>The sight of the great lime-tree on the lawn,  </p>
            <p>Which seemed to have come on purpose from the woods  </p>
            <p>To bring the house a message. (ll. 1.484–88). </p>
                
            <p>The content of that message is never shared with the reader, or and possibly not even
                with Aurora, but the mood is portentous. If Coleridge advises us that “no sound is
                dissonant which tells of Life” (l. 78), Barrett Browning, appropriating his imagery
                from a different vantage point and turning it into a paranoid delusion, gives voice
                to dissonance itself. Because the chair is turned away from the window, Barrett
                Browning also captures the anxiety that comes with the willful disregard of that
                dissonance.</p>
                
            <p>Generally, critics agree that Barrett Browning venerated Coleridge and was aligning
                herself with his poetic project. Robin Inboden has most thoroughly tracked Elizabeth
                Barrett’s debts to Coleridge, and has discussed the relative dearth of critical
                commentary on those debts; Inboden discusses only the poet’s earlier work under the
                name Elizabeth Barrett, and so does not mention
                <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh </hi> or its lime-tree bower (129).
                Critics who have noted the echoes of “This Lime-Tree Bower” in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aurora Leigh</hi> specifically have presented Barrett Browning as a relatively
                uncritical admirer of Coleridge’s poem. For Maureen Thum, the allusion to
                Coleridge’s poem begins the “mental process of Aurora’s awakening,” helping her find
                “a new alternative view of female identity” (89). In Thum’s reading,
                <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh </hi>effectively replicates the
                trajectory of Coleridge’s lime-tree fantasy, attuning us to “the implicit call of
                the natural world beyond the conventions of the house and the narrowness even of the
                attached garden” (88). For Delores DeLuise and Michael Timko, Coleridge helps Aurora see that her domestic
                prison is not so bad, and the presence of the lime tree in the poem ensures that “it
                is clear that she has not given up the belief in the male poet as genius” (92,99). Such readings have been part of a broader effort to examine <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aurora Leigh</hi>’s debts to British Romanticism (Louis; Kobayashi). </p>
            
                <p>I want to challenge the supposition that Barrett Browning, in Book I of <hi
                    rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>, was paying homage to her Romantic predecessor,
                for I believe that the subtle differences in tone, divergent strategies of
                figuration, and striking disruptions in meter mark Barrett Browning’s distance from
                Coleridge. As I see it, Barrett Browning, far from assenting to Coleridge’s
                conclusions, seems to be repurposing his imagery to enact a psychotic poetics.
                Though many elements in the two poems are the same—blank verse, lime tree, woods,
                prison-like house, daydreaming, bees, a “sort of friend,” and an emphasis on
                affect—Barrett Browning is rearranging these elements into new figures, to open up
                unusual modes of enjoyment and difficult temporalities. Barrett Browning, read in
                relation to Coleridge, can be seen as a belated example of a discursive phenomenon
                known as “fellow Romantics” or “Romantic interactions,” in which male and female
                poets share discursive common ground and productively challenge and repeat one
                another (Lau; Wolfson). The gender politics being negotiated here are complex: even before Barrett Browning arrives onto the scene, the lime-tree bower was is already displaying
                Coleridge’s willingness to appropriate traditionally feminine poetic spaces
                (96; Murray 57). Barrett Browning might be wresting back this space for the women’s
                side; yet in doing so, she is developing a complex response to the immediacy of
                Coleridge’s verse. Although Barrett Browning repeatedly alludes to Coleridge’s
                lime-tree bower in Book I of her text, she does so to flatten Coleridge’s poetic
                world and detach the Coleridgean conversational “I” from its sources of comfort. To
                put the difference in psychoanalytic terms: if Coleridge’s poem proclaims the
                neurosis of the entrapped male poet, who resents being left behind as his friends go
                walking, then Barrett Browning’s poem can be said to be approaching that persona
                psychotically.</p>
                
            <p>It may seem iniquitous to speak of <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi> in terms of
                psychosis. I am not eager to associate one of the most important feminist poems of
                the nineteenth century with abnormal conditions of the mind and mental illness,
                given how readily the nineteenth century wielded psychiatric discourses against
                women. The association may seem especially unfortunate, given the remarkable clarity
                of Barrett Browning’s writing and thought, which is apparent everywhere in the poem,
                and Barrett Browning’s carefully reasoned arguments, through the voice of Aurora
                Leigh, about gender-based oppression. The poem chronicles, in a detailed and
                persuasive way, Aurora’s purposefulness in the face of conventionality. There does
                not appear to be anything particularly psychotic about Aurora’s quest to become an
                artist or transcend the limitations placed upon her—although Daniel Paul Schreber,
                too, was “clear thinking and sober” in pursuit of what he called “cool intellectual
                criticism” (69)-and I am not trying to suggest that the character Aurora Leigh, or that the author
                Barrett Browning, is especially psychotic. Instead, I will explore the category of
                “ordinary psychosis”—a psychosis often indistinguishable from ordinarily neurotic
                states of mind, except insofar as it relates to language and signification (Vanheule). It is psychosis as a method of resisting and refusing patriarchal law—and, as Todd
                McGowan reminds us, “The fundamental law is that of the signifier itself” (48).
                So, by my use of <hi rend="italic">“psychosis</hi>,” in this essay, I merely mean to
                indicates that <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi> understands figuration and
                meaning quite differently from Coleridge, and that those differences, taken as a
                whole, substantially shift the poetic function of Leigh Hall’s menacing lime tree
                into a different register of experience. As figural and syntactic differences emerge
                between Barrett Browning and Coleridge, they become part of Barrett Browning’s
                agenda of feminist resistance. Unwilling to recognize an Other, the poem struggles
                to situate its protagonist in time. Mary Mullen has shown how, “by representing
                multiple, overlapping timescapes,
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Aurora Leigh </hi>questions the dominance of
                linear, progressive time” (64). The strange temporality of <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>’s Book I in
                particular, which arises from its interactions with Coleridge’s text at the level of
                figuration, proves confining for Aurora but enables Barrett Browning to build on a
                tradition of counter-temporal women’s writing inherited from Romantic-era women
                writers like Catherine Macaulay, Mary Wollstonecraft, Charlotte Smith, and Mary
                Shelley. Psychosis, in my reading of the poem, is less a medical or psychiatric
                diagnosis than a way of relating to language, male-authored poetry, and time.</p>
                
            <p>Aurora dreads that the lime tree, and thus perhaps by extension the
                English poetic tradition, may want something from her, and she hesitates to
                contemplate the tree or turn her chair that waytowards it. In what could easily be
                described as a paranoid delusion, she maintains that the tree has come from the
                woods to the house, and seems to be stalking her and attempting to communicate: it
                is here “to bring the house a message.” For Coleridge, the situation is exactly the
                opposite: the lime-tree bower, at first frustrating, becomes an emissary from the
                house to the woods, so that the injured poet can convey his feelings to his distant
                friends and his aspirations for their happiness. Coleridge’s lime tree is
                frustratingly immobile, while Barrett Browning’s seems to have made like a tree and
                left the woods behind; its seeming mobility is what provokes Aurora’s anxiety. The
                tree marks the outside world intruding into Leigh Hall and into the core of the
                subject: <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="103"/>It is the arrival of the outside
                world into Leigh Hall, and then the core of the subject<anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="103"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="103"><date when="2022-08-02T13:41:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please reword this line to avoid the
                            sentence fragment. What do the arrival of the outside world and the core
                            of the subject do?</hi></note></hi>: the tree’sits “message” is
                traumatic and meaningless in itself, and yet indicates “a thing / Beyond it”
                    (1.484<hi style="font-family:Symbol"><seg style="font-family:Symbol;"
                    >-</seg></hi>5).t.<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="109"/>”<anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="109"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="109"><date when="2022-08-02T13:41:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please include line numbers for this
                            quoted material.</hi></note></hi> And yet itThe message becomes part of
                Aurora’s contemplation of “the inner life,” something that she likens to regression:
                Aurora maintains “relations in the Unseen  .  .  .  as a babe sucks surely in the
                dark. / I kept the life, thrust on me, on the outside / Of the inner life” (ll.
                1.473–78). She goes on to suppose that: </p>
            <p rend="No Spacing">“And so, as froward babes, we hide our eyes / </p>
            <p rend="No Spacing">And think all ended.—Then, Life calls to us  .  .  .  Above us, or
                below us, or around:</p>
            <p rend="No Spacing"> / Perhaps we name it Nature’s voice, or Love’s, / </p>
            <p rend="No Spacing">Tricking ourselves.” (ll. 1.672–676). </p>
            <p rend="No Spacing">The second quoted example indicates that “Love”—a signifier to
                which we will shortly return—constitutes an untrustworthy “voice,” generated and
                named by our own psyche, but which imposes itself on us from outside. The
                distinction between inside and outside collapses, and so the voice may come from
                “above us, or below us, or around,” indifferently, or all at once. In both examples,
                Aurora styles herself as an infant only at the level of figuration, as the vehicle
                of a simile: she regresses by placing herself at the mercy of literary language, as
                a way of skirting the Law, in an effort to refuse to relinquish early childhood
                enjoyments.</p>
            <p rend="No Spacing">But her inner life seems to have been installed there from an alien
                source. The movement of the tree between Aurora’s “outer life” and “inner life,”
                which ultimately becomes a way for Aurora to better figure herself as a suckling
                infant, suggests that the psychic mechanism of foreclosure may be at work. <hi
                    rend="i0">The effect is a flattening out of meaning, as “the incoherencies of
                    change and death</hi>” become folded into what Aurora calls the
                “<hi rend="i0" xml:space="preserve">smooth fair mystery of perpetual Life” (l. 1.171–73). </hi>Foreclosure,
                a concept coined by Jacques Lacan in 1956 in the final session of his Seminar on
                psychosis, is the process by which the subject loses access to a primordial
                signifier, known playfully, in Lacanian parlance, as the Name (or No) of the Father
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"fnTX4emK","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar III} 321)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar III 321)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":247,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"itemData":{"id":247,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book III: The Psychoses","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"0-393-03467-4","title-short":"Seminar III","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"translator":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1993"]]}},"locator":"321"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar III</hi> 321). The subject forecloses the signifier of the
                law in a bid to retain access to primordial enjoyment. Yet, even while the paternal
                signifier remains foreclosed from the psychotic subject, it can return in unexpected
                ways: “what is foreclosed does not simply disappear altogether but may return,
                albeit in a different guise, from outside the subject,” explains Russell Grigg
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"YfoppaMb","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Grigg 50)","plainCitation":"(Grigg 50)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2596,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"itemData":{"id":2596,"type":"chapter","title":"From the Mechanism of Psychosis to the Universal Condition of the Symptom: On Foreclosure","container-title":"Key Concepts of Lacanian Psychoanalysis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","event-place":"London","title-short":"From the Mechanism","author":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"editor":[{"family":"Nobus","given":"Dany"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2017"]]}},"locator":"50"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(50).
                The arrival of the lime tree, and thus by extension Coleridge’s entire psychodrama
                of reconstituting “<hi rend="line-text">Friends, whom I never more may meet again”
                    as a permanent presence that can “</hi>keep the heart / Awake,” seems to
                function in <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Aurora Leigh </hi>as an index of
                permanent filial attachment (Coleridge “Lime-Tree” ll. 6, 65–66). But because these
                affective bonds have been foreclosed in <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>, the
                dynamics of loss and memory play out as “relations in the Unseen.” (l. 1.473).</p>
            <p rend="No Spacing">Psychosis arises not out of the daughter’s relationship to either
                mother or father, but to the child’s relationship to the mother’s relationship to
                the father—i.e.that is, it stems from a person’s relationship with their mother’s
                desire
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"6XFce3gc","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}\\uc0\\u201{}crits} 464; Grigg 64)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Écrits 464; Grigg 64)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":819,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"itemData":{"id":819,"type":"book","title":"Écrits: The First Complete Edition in English","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"9780393329254","title-short":"Écrits","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Fink","given":"Bruce"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2006"]]}},"locator":"464"},{"id":2596,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"itemData":{"id":2596,"type":"chapter","title":"From the Mechanism of Psychosis to the Universal Condition of the Symptom: On Foreclosure","container-title":"Key Concepts of Lacanian Psychoanalysis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","event-place":"London","title-short":"From the Mechanism","author":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"editor":[{"family":"Nobus","given":"Dany"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2017"]]}},"locator":"64"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Lacan,
                    <hi rend="italic">Écrits</hi> 464; Grigg 64). Aurora explains,’s explanation is
                that: “<hi rend="i0">I felt a mother-want about the world,</hi> / <hi rend="i0">And
                    still went seeking, like a bleating lamb</hi>” (l. 1.40). Embodying her mother’s
                desire, and refusing to think of either parent as permanently lost, there can be no
                anchoring point for language or meaning for her. We get a sense of this through the
                jumbled syntax and jagged line breaks as Aurora gazes at a portrait of her mother,
                “half in terror, half / In adoration”: “<hi rend="i0">Therefore very strange</hi> /
                <hi rend="i0" xml:space="preserve">The effect was” (1.134–37). </hi>Much like her
                manipulations of Coleridge’s poem in the library of Leigh Hall, Aurora here seems to
                be constructing her own arrangements out of the linguistic ingredients available.
                Consider the remarkable extent to which Aurora experiences her father as an effect
                of language.: <hi rend="i0">Aarriving as an orphan in England, she “heard my [her]
                    father’s language first</hi> /
                <hi rend="i0" xml:space="preserve">From alien lips,” a defamiliarization (or unmooring) of language which that provokes a reaction in her that others found find alarming: “some one near me said the child was mad / Through much sea-sickness” (ll. 1.254–59). The poem, finding an “apocalyptic” relation to language in a sustained effort not to deal with the traumatic loss of the mother and father (l. 1.674), begins to articulate something “very strange” that strikes those around her as madness. We can see the arrival of the lime tree in this light: </hi>“A
                feeling of being intruded upon,” Lacan explains, often playing out in “shared
                delusions,” such as the “delusion of being watched,” which especially arises in
                cases of psychosis connected to “the mother/daughter couple”
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"9P1D93Yk","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}\\uc0\\u201{}crits} 447)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Écrits 447)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":819,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"itemData":{"id":819,"type":"book","title":"Écrits: The First Complete Edition in English","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"9780393329254","title-short":"Écrits","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Fink","given":"Bruce"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2006"]]}},"locator":"447"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Écrits</hi> 447).</p>
            <p> Psychosis can ensue when the father appears to be undeserving or inadequate in the
                face of the mother’s desire, and in the face of the symbolic Law. As Grigg
                explains:</p>
            <p>For Lacan, what is foreclosed is not the possibility of an event’s coming to pass,
                but the very signifier, or signifiers, that makes the expression of impossibility
                possible in the first place. Thus, “foreclosure” refers not to the fact that a
                speaker makes a statement which declares something impossible<hi
                    style="font-size:11.5pt">—</hi>a process closer to disavowal—but to the fact
                that the speaker lacks the very linguistic means for making the statement at all.
                This is where the difference between repression and foreclosure lies.
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"22WiXcbJ","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Grigg 49)","plainCitation":"(Grigg 49)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2596,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"itemData":{"id":2596,"type":"chapter","title":"From the Mechanism of Psychosis to the Universal Condition of the Symptom: On Foreclosure","container-title":"Key Concepts of Lacanian Psychoanalysis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","event-place":"London","title-short":"From the Mechanism","author":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"editor":[{"family":"Nobus","given":"Dany"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2017"]]}},"locator":"49"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(49)</p>
            <p>An impossible event, such as a tree’s seeming “arrival” from the woods to Leigh Hall,
                might at first seem like a fanciful way to describe the return of the repressed. But
                it is not at all the case that Coleridge’s poetry, or his lime-tree imagery, have
                been “repressed” in Aurora’s world: there is a library full of English books, and
                the lime tree is visible just through the window—yes, the reading chair has been
                turned away, but the world outside that window is hardly repressed material.
                Therefore, I would encourage us to think of that tree not as the embodiment of the
                repressed, but rather as the arboreal embodiment of the father’s signifier (“Love,”
                to which Aurora feels she has no access) and the world of literary language more
                broadly. In this sense, it is a symbol of how the work of poetic figuration is kept
                “outside” of Aurora’s view, even when she is immersed in reading. The psychic
                movement from inner to outer—as a way of pretending that one can maintain oneself as
                separate from the expectations that surround one—is crucial to understanding the
                ethos of <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi> and its relationship to Romanticism, as
                Emily Kobayashi has argued
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"AeYsBbhG","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Kobayashi 823)","plainCitation":"(Kobayashi 823)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2314,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/L3T3XCWQ"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/L3T3XCWQ"],"itemData":{"id":2314,"type":"article-journal","title":"Feeling Intellect in <i>Aurora Leigh</i> and <i>The Prelude</i>","container-title":"SEL: Studies in English Literature 1500-1900","page":"823-848","volume":"51","issue":"4","source":"Project MUSE","ISSN":"1522-9270","title-short":"Feeling Intellect","language":"en","author":[{"family":"Kobayashi","given":"Emily V. Epstein"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2011"]]}},"locator":"823"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(823).
                It is also crucial to psychosis in the psychoanalytic tradition. For instance,:
                Schreber even begins his <hi rend="italic">Memoir</hi> with the claim that “the
                total mental life of a human being rests on their excitability by external
                impressions”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"F3qZpdUZ","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Schreber 19)","plainCitation":"(Schreber 19)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2704,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/22WRBPPM"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/22WRBPPM"],"itemData":{"id":2704,"type":"book","title":"Memoirs of my Nervous Illness","publisher":"New York Review Books","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","title-short":"Memoirs","author":[{"family":"Schreber","given":"Daniel Paul"}],"translator":[{"family":"MacAlpine","given":"Ida"},{"family":"Hunter","given":"Richard"}],"editor":[{"family":"MacAlpine","given":"Ida"},{"family":"Hunter","given":"Richard"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2000"]]}},"locator":"19"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(19).
                The lime tree, ominously approaching Leigh Hall, exemplifies this phenomenon.</p>
            <p> “Love” is a special signifier in this text, as it was the father’s emphatic last
                word to his now-orphaned daughter: “His last word was, ‘Love—’ / ‘Love, my child,
                love, love!” (ll. 1.211–12). For Aurora, “love” is not the name for an ethical
                relation nor a sentiment, but a signifier of her father’s lack: in her memory, her
                father is the man “<hi rend="i0">Whom love had unmade from a common man</hi> /
                <hi rend="i0" xml:space="preserve">But not completed to an uncommon man” (ll.1.183–84). Such an association is not unusual in cases of psychosis: </hi>Lacan
                explains that “words of love” are “always a rupture in the system of language,” and
                are thus often pivotal in psychosis
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"5VvmVCxe","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar III} 55)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar III 55)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":247,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"itemData":{"id":247,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book III: The Psychoses","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"0-393-03467-4","title-short":"Seminar III","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"translator":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1993"]]}},"locator":"55"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar III</hi> 55). <hi rend="i0">Orphaned at thirteen, Aurora
                    is alarmed to find her father not only dead but also rendered incomplete and
                    “unmade” by the signifier of his own paternity, which had once been the
                    signifier of her mother’s desire. Hence, when arriving in England, Aurora is
                    alarmed by the extent to which the landscape—recently enclosed—seems to disclose
                    her father’s lack through the cut of its property lines: clearly, she reckons,
                    it was not “my father’s England” because of how the “ground seemed cut up from
                    the fellowship</hi> /
                    <hi rend="i0" xml:space="preserve">Of verdure”—with even the line break marking the violence of the cut—and finding because of the loss of the commons re-inscribed in the “delicate lines” of her Aunt’s face (ll. 1.259–61, 278). Such delineation is, for Aurora, the mark of castration in and through her “my father’s language” (l. 1.254): it is the signifier of the father’s lack. But the primordial word “love,” to which Aurora is traumatically attached, is foreclosed in the experience, and so Aurora moves through the world </hi>“<hi
                    rend="i0">with ears too full</hi> / <hi rend="i0">Of [her]my father’s silence”
                    (ll. 1.227–28). To render this silence in poetry—with one’s own “lines” and the
                    emphatic line breaks of the poem’s aggressive enjambment—is Aurora’s attempt to
                    link this cut to the father, to turn the dead father’s love into just another
                    signifier, instead of accepting it as the Name of the Father. Hence the
                    signifier “love” resounds through the poetry found in her aunt’s library,
                    turning the Name of the Father into just another signifier as the lime tree
                    keeps watch:</hi> “From many a volume, Love re-emphasised / Upon the self-same
                pages” (ll. 1.710–11).</p>
            <p><hi rend="i0"> Without the stabilizing presence of a master signifier, Aurora is
                    “left prey to  .  .  .  the mother’s unregulated desire”:</hi>
                    “<hi rend="i27" xml:space="preserve">I am like, / </hi><hi rend="i0" xml:space="preserve">They tell me, my dear father,” she observes </hi><?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"PKbtxW36","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Grigg 55; Barrett Browning 1.198-99)","plainCitation":"(Grigg 55; Barrett Browning 1.198-99)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2596,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"itemData":{"id":2596,"type":"chapter","title":"From the Mechanism of Psychosis to the Universal Condition of the Symptom: On Foreclosure","container-title":"Key Concepts of Lacanian Psychoanalysis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","event-place":"London","title-short":"From the Mechanism","author":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"editor":[{"family":"Nobus","given":"Dany"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2017"]]}},"locator":"55"},{"id":2691,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/2DACNT4U"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/2DACNT4U"],"itemData":{"id":2691,"type":"book","title":"Aurora Leigh: Authoritative Text, Backgrounds and Contexts, Criticism","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","number-of-pages":"565","edition":"1","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"978-0-393-96298-7","note":"OCLC: 832668130","title-short":"Aurora Leigh","language":"eng","author":[{"family":"Barrett Browning","given":"Elizabeth"}],"editor":[{"family":"Reynolds","given":"Margaret"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1996"]]}},"locator":"1.198-99","label":"line"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?><hi
                    rend="i0">(Grigg 55; Barrett Browning 1.198-–99)</hi><hi rend="i0">. It is a
                    flattening out and undoing of the Oedipal triangle. Again, she refuses to
                    separate the “I” of narration from the “they” who intercedes, syntactically
                    speaking, between sheher and her father. Put in Lacanian terms, she has refused
                    to transfer her enjoyment to the big Other—an imagined repository of signifiers
                    normally held as a tribute to the dead father’s enjoyment, and his ongoing
                    dominance, as per Freud’s totem myth. Aurora’s refusal of this Other, I am
                    suggesting, is a consequence of foreclosure: hence her boast that the lime
                    tree’s “message,” once “</hi>thrust on me,” can be kept “on the outside / Of the
                inner life.” Lacan says, in “On a Question Prior to Any Possible Treatment of
                Psychosis,” that when we arrive “at the point at which the Name-of-the-Father is
                summoned—and we shall see how—a pure and simple hole may thus answer in the Other”
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"dhsqDznc","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}\\uc0\\u201{}crits} 465)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Écrits 465)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":819,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"itemData":{"id":819,"type":"book","title":"Écrits: The First Complete Edition in English","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"9780393329254","title-short":"Écrits","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Fink","given":"Bruce"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2006"]]}},"locator":"465"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Écrits</hi> 465). This hole is the outcome of foreclosure. That
                hole begins to answer in <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi> as Aurora begins to
                “hear the silence open like a flower” (l. 1.683). Although she can sense the
                delivery of that absent message internally, as if emitted from inside of her head,
                its blankness is firmly kept on the “outside.” <hi rend="i0">Grigg warns us against
                    such a dynamic in his account of psychotic foreclosure: “</hi>Yet what is
                foreclosed from the symbolic is not purely and simply abolished. It returns, but,
                unlike the return of the repressed, it returns from outside the subject, as
                emanating from the real”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"6ulMKZD8","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Grigg 56)","plainCitation":"(Grigg 56)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2596,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"itemData":{"id":2596,"type":"chapter","title":"From the Mechanism of Psychosis to the Universal Condition of the Symptom: On Foreclosure","container-title":"Key Concepts of Lacanian Psychoanalysis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","event-place":"London","title-short":"From the Mechanism","author":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"editor":[{"family":"Nobus","given":"Dany"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2017"]]}},"locator":"56"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(56).
                As it returns in <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>, we observe a collapse of
                levels in these lime-tree bower passages: the tree arrives as the externalized
                embodiment of the father’s signifier, and so the poetry renders impossible any
                distinction between inside, outside, and beyond.</p>
            <p> Celeste Langan has done important work in thinking about Coleridge’s theories of
                poetic language—in particular through <hi rend="italic">Christabel</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Biographia Literaria</hi>—in light of Schreber’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Memoir.</hi> For Langan, Schreber’s psychotic “nerve-language” can be read as
                “a ‘pathological’ instance of Coleridge’s poetic theory.” As she explains,: “there
                is an underexamined equivalency between poetry and what can be described as forms of
                speech pathology. Poetry, as it is practiced by Coleridge and Schreber, is the very
                opposite of ‘free’ speech,” given their shared “conditions of constraint”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"snI6c1KK","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Langan 120\\uc0\\u8211{}21)","plainCitation":"(Langan 120–21)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2686,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/2C27YHGA"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/2C27YHGA"],"itemData":{"id":2686,"type":"article-journal","title":"Pathologies of Communication from Coleridge to Schreber","container-title":"The South Atlantic Quarterly","page":"117-152","volume":"102","issue":"1","source":"Project MUSE","ISSN":"1527-8026","title-short":"Pathologies of Communication","language":"en","author":[{"family":"Langan","given":"Celeste"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2003"]]}},"locator":"120-21"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Langan
                120–21). In Coleridge’s “Lime-Tree Bower” poem, something external impresses itself
                upon the speaker’s body, restructuring his affect. The transformation is conveyed by
                a jarring line break: “A delight / Comes sudden on my heart” (ll. 45–46). Aurora’s
                strategy, of keeping “the life, thrust on me, on the outside / Of the inner life,”
                is quite different, though it communicates by similar means. In aspiring to maintain
                a distinction between “outside” and “inner” lives, the very rigor of her attempt
                ensures the collapse of that distinction: hence the rhetoric of unwanted penetration
                (“thrust on me”) and the syntactical way that “on me” is enfolded, as a subordinate
                clause, within the play of “outside” and “inner,” as if “I” were always internal to
                the play that defines <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="226"/>my one’s <anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="226"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="226"><date when="2022-08-02T15:26:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Should this be “one’s own
                            boundaries”?</hi></note></hi>own boundaries. In effect, the speaker of
                    <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi> is treating the Real as the Symbolic: she is
                building a symbolic distinction out of the violent rupture of repressed material,
                flattening the levels out onto a single plane of signification. Coleridge’s epiphany
                is now asked to take on a subjectivity of its own, such that it no longer functions
                as an epiphany. It becomes, over the course of Book I, an engine of “rupture” and
                “break” instead of the “deep radiance” of a “straight path”: “Then, something moved
                me,” Aurora explains, sayingadding: , “here’s a cause / For rupture;—herein we must
                break with Life, / Or be ourselves unworthy” (Coleridge ll. 54, 71; Barrett Browning
                ll. 1.661–70).</p>
            <p> Although such contrasts between the two poems, culled from a close reading of just a
                few small words and their rhetorical function, may seem too subtle to warrant the
                invocation of something as extreme as “psychosis” in Aurora Leigh’s case, it is
                actually only in such subtleties that ordinary psychosis manifests itself. That is
                why Lacan urges his students to focus on the order of words, rather than the words
                themselves (that is, to prioritize the analysis of syntax over diction), in the
                writings of psychotic patients: “a metaphor is above all sustained by positional
                articulation,” he explains, and so we have to study the relationship of signifier to
                signifier, without much consideration of any signified
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"P3PQ3bCm","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar III} 226)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar III 226)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":247,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"itemData":{"id":247,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book III: The Psychoses","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"0-393-03467-4","title-short":"Seminar III","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"translator":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1993"]]}},"locator":"226"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar III</hi> 226). Because “the mainspring of the metaphor
                isn’t the meaning, which is supposed to be transposed” from tenor to vehicle, Lacan
                explains, “the transference of the signified [from vehicle to tenor] is possible
                only by virtue of the structure of language”
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"Kv1vWgIm","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar III} 225)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar III 225)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":247,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"itemData":{"id":247,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book III: The Psychoses","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"0-393-03467-4","title-short":"Seminar III","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"translator":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1993"]]}},"locator":"225"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar III</hi> 225).</p>
            <p>The window is the most obvious perspectival difference between the two poems: Barrett
                Browning emphasizes how the architecture and interior design direct her gaze; they
                limit her capacity, and everyone’s capacity, to hear the “message” of the tree.
                Coleridge’s speaker is directly “in this bower, / This little lime-tree bower,”
                while Aurora shuffles “demurely,” for now, around the “carpeted low rooms” of Leigh
                Hall, occasionally craning her neck toward the window (Coleridge ll. 47–48; Barrett
                Browning ll. 1. 489). Does the fact of looking at the lime tree through a window
                influence the affect it provokes, and the temporality of the “message” it might
                impose? It is not enough to see the presence of a lime tree as “a vestigial remnant
                of male genius,” as DeLuise and Timko would have it, because
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">how </hi>and
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">through what intermediary </hi>we see the
                lime tree is as least as important as its
                status<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> as </hi>a lime tree
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"7HkA7k0g","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(DeLuise and Timko 99)","plainCitation":"(DeLuise and Timko 99)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2307,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/VHVRKYS6"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/VHVRKYS6"],"itemData":{"id":2307,"type":"chapter","title":"Becoming the Poet: The Feminine Poet-Speaker in the Work of Elizabeth Barrett Browning","container-title":"Virginal Sexuality and Textuality in Victorian Literature: Essays in Environmental Philosophy","publisher":"SUNY Press","publisher-place":"Albany","page":"87-104","source":"Google Books","event-place":"Albany","ISBN":"978-0-7914-1283-1","note":"Google-Books-ID: 0YlG3ItVWf4C","title-short":"Becoming the Poet","language":"en","author":[{"family":"DeLuise","given":"Delores"},{"family":"Timko","given":"Michael"}],"editor":[{"family":"Davis","given":"Lloyd"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1993"]]}},"locator":"99"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(99).
                There is a disquieting aura surrounding the Barrett Browning lime tree, which
                becomes, as the tree comes back again and again throughout Book I, thoroughly
                uncanny.</p>
            <p>In his Seminar on anxiety, Lacan explains that: “the magisterial German <hi
                    rend="italic">Unheimliche</hi>, presents itself through little windows. The
                field of anxiety is situated as something framed.  .  .  .  Anxiety is the
                appearance, within this framing, of what was already there, at much closer quarters,
                at home”
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"As15Yj4H","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar X} 74\\uc0\\u8211{}75)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar X 74–75)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1777,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/K3NQ2RNE"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/K3NQ2RNE"],"itemData":{"id":1777,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book X: Anxiety, 1962-63","publisher":"Polity","publisher-place":"Cambridge","event-place":"Cambridge","title-short":"Seminar X","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Price","given":"A.R."}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2015"]]}},"locator":"74-75"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar X</hi> 74–75). To illustrate this, Lacan examines two
                drawings of trees made by psychoanalytic patients: the first and more famous, by the
                Wolf Man, depicting five wolves sitting in the branches of a tree, gazing as if to
                bring the house a message, and the second, by an Italian woman with schizophrenia he
                calls Isabella, depicting a tree with three large humanoid eyes positioned
                vertically along its trunk and cursive foliage that spells out “<hi rend="italic">Io
                    sono sempre vista</hi>,” or, rendered into English, “I am always in view.” Lacan
                is interested in how Isabella’s drawing parallels the Wolf Man’s, and yet the wolves
                have been replaced with signifiers. Lacan stresses the ambiguity of “<hi
                    rend="italic">Io sono sempre vista</hi>,” as it has “two meanings, subjective
                and objective” in the French translation: we cannot know whether the tree is wary of
                being the object of our gaze, or if Isabella might be concerned about her visibility
                to the tree
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"2pqkkCP5","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar X} 73)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar X 73)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1777,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/K3NQ2RNE"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/K3NQ2RNE"],"itemData":{"id":1777,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book X: Anxiety, 1962-63","publisher":"Polity","publisher-place":"Cambridge","event-place":"Cambridge","title-short":"Seminar X","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Price","given":"A.R."}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2015"]]}},"locator":"73"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar X</hi> 73). It is this syntactical ambiguity—never knowing
                whether you are the watcher or the watched—which becomes a wellspring of Isabella’s
                psychotic anxiety. These are striking images, both extremely unsettling, and yet
                Lacan strategically disregards the content of these images in his discussion,
                focusing instead on how their uncanny effects are mediated by a windowpane. Although
                one cannot see the windowpane in either case, Lacan stresses that, in both images,
                “the fantasy is beheld on the other side of a windowpane, and through a window that
                opens. The fantasy is framed”
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"0oxuXilC","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar X} 73)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar X 73)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1777,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/K3NQ2RNE"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/K3NQ2RNE"],"itemData":{"id":1777,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book X: Anxiety, 1962-63","publisher":"Polity","publisher-place":"Cambridge","event-place":"Cambridge","title-short":"Seminar X","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Price","given":"A.R."}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2015"]]}},"locator":"73"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar X</hi> 73).<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"
                            ><p rend="endnote text"> I am here indebted to Celiese Lypka, who, in
                            our work together, has helped me to understand this passage of <hi
                                rend="italic">Seminar X</hi>.</p></note></hi> It is the window,
                connecting but separating the tree to and from the house, which fills the artist
                with dread: an uncanny and terrifying “countryside view” and a tree who has come to
                the house to deliver an ambiguous message
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"cQqEHdEp","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar X} 74)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar X 74)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1777,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/K3NQ2RNE"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/K3NQ2RNE"],"itemData":{"id":1777,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book X: Anxiety, 1962-63","publisher":"Polity","publisher-place":"Cambridge","event-place":"Cambridge","title-short":"Seminar X","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Price","given":"A.R."}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2015"]]}},"locator":"74"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar X</hi> 74).</p>
            <p>As the figural language of the poem begins to be flattened out—by which I mean the
                levels of vehicle and tenor become indistinguishable—the window to Aurora’s bedroom
                begins to be metaphorized as a bower: “the folds / Hung green about the window,
                which let in / The out-door world with all its greenery.<anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="255"/>” (1.572<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="255"
                    /><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor"
                        n="255"><date when="2022-08-02T15:41:00Z"/><hi rend="background(yellow)"
                            >Please include line numbers for this quoted
                    material.</hi></note></hi><hi style="font-family:Symbol"><seg
                        style="font-family:Symbol;">-</seg></hi>4). Once Aurora’s window becomes a
                metaphorical bower, we are forced to notice that the mediating fact of the window is
                what separates Leigh Hall’s lime tree from Coleridge’s. Coleridge is sitting outside
                in his garden bower, a space semi-natural and semi-domestic. For Aurora to liken the
                windowpane to a garden bower is to imagine herself in her own future, already
                outside the house. Yet the windowpane always frames Aurora’s experience of the tree.
                In a reversal of Coleridge, criminological language is associated with the house,
                not the bower: Romney Leigh, Aurora’s cousin and eventual suitor, is ever “agonising
                with a ghastly sense / Of universal hideous want and wrong / To incriminate
                possession” of Leigh Hall (1.519<hi style="font-family:Symbol"><seg
                        style="font-family:Symbol;">-</seg></hi>21)<anchor type="commentRangeStart"
                    n="261"/>.<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="261"/><hi
                    rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="261"
                            ><date when="2022-08-02T15:45:00Z"/><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please
                            include line numbers for this quoted material.</hi></note></hi> That is,
                the house “incriminates” its socially-conscious master in a way that inverts
                Coleridge’s carceral metaphor.: Ffor Coleridge, the bower is effectively a prison,
                whereas for cousin Romney, the bower—in its function as one of the estate’s
                “seasonable delights” (1.518)—is the very crime<anchor type="commentRangeStart"
                    n="267"/>.<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="267"/><hi
                    rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="267"
                            ><date when="2022-08-02T15:47:00Z"/><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please
                            include a line number for “seasonable delights.”</hi></note></hi> In <hi
                    rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>, to enjoy is to be guilty, ; yet one is then
                condemned to enjoy, and one enjoys precisely by being “sentenced,” that is, at the
                lexical and syntactical levels. Barrett Browning, introducing Romney, twists
                Coleridge’s imagery to depict him as a reverse version of Coleridge’s encomium to
                Charles Lamb from the lime-tree bower: Romney is not “gentle-hearted,” but only
                “tender when he thought of it”; he is not “my friend” but rather “a sort of friend”;
                a “delight” does not “come sudden upon [his] heart,” except through his “repressing
                all its seasonable delights”; the lesson for Aurora is not that “Nature ne’er
                deserts the wise and pure,” but that “’Twas natural to like to get away” (Coleridge
                ll. 29–62; Barrett Browning ll. 1.506–14.). Barrett Browning reorganizes the
                elements found in Coleridge’s poem, twisting the function of Coleridge’s words and
                images to give them uncanny moods.</p>
            <p>Like Isabella, Aurora cannot determine if she is looking at the tree, or if the tree
                is beholding her—if it is she, or the tree, that is “always in view.” Coleridge’s
                tree is “always in view” as well, but it’s clearer that the speaker is exercising a
                gaze upon it: in extraordinarily visual diction, the speaker “mark’d,” “watch’d,”
                and “lov’d to see” the lime tree (ll. 48–51). Aurora’s experience is not like that.
                It finds a closer corollary in another moment from Coleridge, this one from “Frost
                at Midnight,” in which the speaker discovers his inner self in an external if
                “companionable form” (“Frost” 19). That is, the lime tree gives substance to
                Aurora’s fantasy, and its enigmatic “message” is Coleridge’s message for the future
                being returned to him in a new contemporary moment, in inverted form
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"yFQevhnr","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}\\uc0\\u201{}crits} 30)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Écrits 30)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":819,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"itemData":{"id":819,"type":"book","title":"Écrits: The First Complete Edition in English","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"9780393329254","title-short":"Écrits","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Fink","given":"Bruce"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2006"]]}},"locator":"30"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Lacan,
                    <hi rend="italic">Écrits</hi> 30). This uncertainty is something that she must
                “await”: in Lacanian terms, it is not a feeling but a premonition and “pre-feeling,”
                as we await the cause of our desire, a confrontation with “that which deceives not”
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"1jWN8xS8","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar X} 76)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar X 76)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1777,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/K3NQ2RNE"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/K3NQ2RNE"],"itemData":{"id":1777,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book X: Anxiety, 1962-63","publisher":"Polity","publisher-place":"Cambridge","event-place":"Cambridge","title-short":"Seminar X","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Price","given":"A.R."}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2015"]]}},"locator":"76"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar X</hi> 76). That happens because Barrett Browning’s
                allusion functions both spatially and temporally: it separates inside from outside,
                as “Frost at Midnight” does in its own figurations of domestic space, but also
                styles Aurora as a baby (as we saw above), and thus as little Hartley Coleridge.
                Aurora is someone of the following generation, a figure from the future of
                Romanticism to whom Coleridge had been sending aspirational wishes. This temporal
                movement, positioning Aurora’s present as Coleridge’s future, —and thus as living
                out one’s life as a someone else’s future projection from the past, —is how, despite
                her claims to the contrary, Aurora’s “inner life” can return, through the
                companionable tree, “on the outside.” Aurora has located her inner experience
                outside of herself, in an effect that Lacanian analyst Stijn Vanheule has called
                “bodily externality”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"qHy5NqMD","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Vanheule 86)","plainCitation":"(Vanheule 86)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2696,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/4P9CXJM6"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/4P9CXJM6"],"itemData":{"id":2696,"type":"chapter","title":"On Ordinary Psychosis","container-title":"Lacan on Psychosis: From Theory to Praxis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","page":"77-103","event-place":"London","title-short":"Ordinary Psychosis","author":[{"family":"Vanheule","given":"Stijn"}],"editor":[{"family":"Mills","given":"Jon"},{"family":"Downing","given":"David L."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019"]]}},"locator":"86"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(86).
                The body never becomes a narcissistically cathected object, and so there is no “ego”
                here, and the subject does not register properly in time. Aurora begins to embody
                what <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="286"/>Anne C. McCarthy <anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="286"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="286"><date when="2022-08-04T09:46:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please add this source to the Works
                            Cited.</hi></note></hi>has called, with reference to “Frost at
                Midnight,” the “future just beyond the poem’s frame that may or may not take place,”
                in response to that poem’s “doubly suspended” “slow, dilated time” (29).</p>
            <p>In so doing, Barrett Browning undoes the central conceit of Coleridge’s two poems,
                and reverses their aspirations for the future. <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>
                resists the law laid down by Coleridge’s use of trope, and we can feel the ripples
                of this difference temporally. “This Lime-Tree Bower My Prison,” like “Frost at
                Midnight,” converts metonymy into metaphor: the lime-tree bower metonymizes the
                house at which the injured poet is stuck, only for that metonym to become the tenor
                of a carceral metaphor: “this lime-tree bower my prison” (l. 2). In Freudian terms
                (as processed through Lacan’s discussion of metonymy and metaphor), Coleridge’s
                figural language works first by displacement, “as I myself were there!” (l. 47),
                only to begin the work of condensation, as if Charles and the speaker were the same
                person, and so they can “contemplate / With lively joy the joys we cannot share”
                (ll. 68–69). This gives a dreamlike quality to Coleridge’s text, which has been seen
                as a source of its unusual temporality: . Aas Francis O’Gorman notes, Coleridge is
                imagining and situating himself within a present, as a way of expressing trepidation
                for the future. He meanwhile treats the present as his own past: “So my friend /
                Struck with deep joy may stand, as I have stood” (ll. 38–39). The figural trajectory
                of Aurora’s lime tree is quite different: the tree appears as an allusion to
                Coleridge, but then becomes a symbol of a world outside the house. The lime tree
                never becomes a metonym for the house, and never a metaphor for a prison; rather,
                the window from which Aurora watches the tree stands in metonymic relation to the
                house, and then the window becomes allegorized as the bars of her prison cell. The
                symbolic tree is viewed from through that mediating frame.</p>
            <p>McGowan explains what is at stake in this difference:</p>
            <p> “The psychotic is capable of registering metonymy and thus can function within the
                symbolic structure. But the psychotic foreclosure of the signifier of law marks a
                refusal of metaphor, which is what condemns the psychotic to a profound unfreedom.
                In this way, the psychotic is the most dangerous psychic structure  .  .  .  because
                its appearance of the ultimate freedom obscures the conformity that characterizes
                it” .
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"7Ef017ur","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(McGowan 63\\uc0\\u8211{}64)","plainCitation":"(McGowan 63–64)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2694,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/U8F3V83B"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/U8F3V83B"],"itemData":{"id":2694,"type":"chapter","title":"The Psychosis of Freedom: Law in Modernity","container-title":"Lacan on Psychosis: From Theory to Praxis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","page":"47-77","event-place":"London","title-short":"The Psychosis of Freedom","author":[{"family":"McGowan","given":"Todd"}],"editor":[{"family":"Mills","given":"Jon"},{"family":"Downing","given":"David L."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019"]]}},"locator":"63-64"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(63–64).</p>
            <p> Thus, the window itself becomes an index of Aurora’s incarceration. We can feel the
                effects of this difference in the temporality of the scene. Coleridge notes, in the
                present tense and in all immediacy, how “A delight / Comes sudden on my heart”
                (“Lime-Tree” ll. 45–46), while Barrett Browning goes out of her way to place the
                experience ambiguously in the past. In a section of <hi rend="italic">Aurora
                    Leigh</hi> with otherwise perfect iambic pentameter, one line alone has an extra
                syllable: “which seemed to have come on purpose from the woods” (l. 1. 484). The
                syntax serves as what Lacan would call a “positional link” in the sentence, and so
                “reappears at all levels and sets up the synchronic coexistence of terms”
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"zuntbnN0","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar III} 225)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar III 225)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":247,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"itemData":{"id":247,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book III: The Psychoses","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"0-393-03467-4","title-short":"Seminar III","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"translator":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1993"]]}},"locator":"225"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar III</hi> 225). That is, it compresses the temporality of
                the scene to mark the disjuncture of time in Barrett Browning’s lime-tree prison.
                The line highlights its deliberate construction: the words “on purpose,” forming a
                spondee, are very emphatic, but not necessary to the line’s meaning; removing them,
                the line becomes surprisingly anapestic (“which seem to have come from the woods”).
                The sonic excess of the extra syllable—an extra bit whichthat cannot be folded into
                the meter or the sense of the line—lends a hint of anxiety to the scene. Although
                “had come” or “seemed to come” would have made more sense syntactically and would
                have better satisfied the metrical requirements, Barrett Browning has gone out of
                her way to say “seemed to have come” instead. She lets the past perfect of <hi
                    rend="italic">it had come</hi> encounter the simple past of <hi rend="italic">it
                    seemed</hi>, creating a temporal division between the perspectives of the tree
                and speaker. From out of this gap, the tree’s purpose is given in the infinitive
                (“to bring the house a message”), as if a message were coming from the future into
                Aurora’s contemporary moment, despite our being able to recollect its past actions
                (and our own, in the time of Aurora’s narration). The poem is opening up two
                asynchronous temporalities—Aurora’s, belonging to Coleridge, in which a poetic past
                is repeated as the present, and the tree’s, in which the past situates us within its
                peculiarly deciduous prophecy—and fuses them into one asynchronous perspective. This
                effectively turns Coleridge’s poem inside-out, given how “This Lime-Tree Bower My
                Prison” was, in O’Gorman’s estimation, one of Coleridge’s boldest attempts “to try,
                however illusorily, to control the direction of the future through the assertion of
                a flawed individual will” and the culmination of his “efforts  .  .  .  somehow to
                know or to anticipate what was to come”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"P6QBNuyg","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(O\\uc0\\u8217{}Gorman 233)","plainCitation":"(O’Gorman 233)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2309,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BFQCC92B"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BFQCC92B"],"itemData":{"id":2309,"type":"article-journal","title":"Coleridge, 'Frost at Midnight', and Anticipating the Future","container-title":"Romanticism","page":"232-244","volume":"14","issue":"3","source":"Project MUSE","ISSN":"1750-0192","language":"en","author":[{"family":"O'Gorman","given":"Francis"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2008"]]}},"locator":"233"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(233).</p>
            <p>Aurora experiences that Coleridgean project of directing the future, ultimately, as a
                source of comfort—but it is comforting only insofar as it offers her a way to
                imagine herself in service to an omnipotent Other, here called Nature, who demands
                her enjoyment:</p>
            <p>It came in softly, while the angels made</p>
            <p>A place for it beside me. The moon came,</p>
            <p>And swept my chamber clean of foolish thoughts.</p>
            <p>The sun came, saying, “Shall I lift this light</p>
            <p>Against the lime-tree, and you will not look?</p>
            <p>I make the birds sing—listen! but, for you,</p>
            <p>God never hears your voice, excepting when</p>
            <p>You lie upon the bed at nights and weep.” (ll. 1. 653–60)</p>
            <p>The beams of light, the all-seeing sun and moon, which control the birds, the terror
                of being inaudible to God except under certain conditions: the poem seizes on the
                lime tree to articulate a remarkably Schreberian vision. The tree becomes the focal
                point of a paranoid structure. The confusion about who is speaking that arises when
                poetry encloses itself in quotation marks, as happens here, is a particularly
                Coleridgean inheritance and a signal of its alliance with Schreber’s psychotic
                discourse, as Langan indicates in her reading of <hi rend="italic">Christabel</hi>
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"XHlPeTXT","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Langan 147\\uc0\\u8211{}48)","plainCitation":"(Langan 147–48)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2686,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/2C27YHGA"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/2C27YHGA"],"itemData":{"id":2686,"type":"article-journal","title":"Pathologies of Communication from Coleridge to Schreber","container-title":"The South Atlantic Quarterly","page":"117-152","volume":"102","issue":"1","source":"Project MUSE","ISSN":"1527-8026","title-short":"Pathologies of Communication","language":"en","author":[{"family":"Langan","given":"Celeste"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2003"]]}},"locator":"147-48"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(147–48).
                I want to highlight, here, the sun’s use of the word “shall,” which, as Russell
                Grigg reminds us, epitomizes psychotic discourse: in the face of the utterance
                “shall,” the subject is asked to commit to the plan of the other
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"ueZ1kz1T","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Grigg 61)","plainCitation":"(Grigg 61)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2596,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"itemData":{"id":2596,"type":"chapter","title":"From the Mechanism of Psychosis to the Universal Condition of the Symptom: On Foreclosure","container-title":"Key Concepts of Lacanian Psychoanalysis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","event-place":"London","title-short":"From the Mechanism","author":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"editor":[{"family":"Nobus","given":"Dany"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2017"]]}},"locator":"61"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(61).
                In making this point, Grigg draws on Lacan’s discussion of the word “shall” in
                Schreber’s hallucinatory conversations with God. Lacan’s sees language as an
                “endurance test” for Schreber, who receives “interrupted messages, by means of which
                a relationship is sustained between the subject and his divine interlocutor”
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"olP9EF8q","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}\\uc0\\u201{}crits} 451)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Écrits 451)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":819,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"itemData":{"id":819,"type":"book","title":"Écrits: The First Complete Edition in English","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"9780393329254","title-short":"Écrits","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Fink","given":"Bruce"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2006"]]}},"locator":"451"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Écrits</hi> 451). God tests Schreber with incomplete phrases like
                “Now I shall . . .…” and “I shall . . . …,” to which Schreber must fill in what
                remains of the sentence in a way that “indicate[s] the subject’s position on the
                basis of the message itself”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"NEwP4K72","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}\\uc0\\u201{}crits} 452)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Écrits 452)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":819,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"itemData":{"id":819,"type":"book","title":"Écrits: The First Complete Edition in English","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"9780393329254","title-short":"Écrits","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Fink","given":"Bruce"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2006"]]}},"locator":"452"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(452).
                The sun’s “shall I” in
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Aurora Leigh </hi>functions quite similarly.:
                as As Aurora quotes her hallucination of the sun, it addresses a “you” that, at one
                level, interpellates Aurora, but at another level, because Aurora is quoting the
                sun’s voice, forces Aurora to imagine herself as outside of herself, as seen by the
                omnipotent sun and its angels. The double interpellation is especially disquieting
                because Aurora’s name, meaning “dawn,” indicates her own readiness to “lift this
                light / Against the lime-tree.”: Sshe is forced to experience herself as the divine
                agent of her own manipulation;: swept clear of her own thoughts, she is being placed
                “beside me” by her remade relation to the lime tree. Michelle C. Martinez emphasizes
                how the first lime-tree passage in
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Aurora Leigh </hi>signals “an important
                change of register in the text,” as the poem then begins to apostrophize a “You,”
                seemingly the reader, standing outside of Leigh Hall
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"VnaWMnkH","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Martinez 40)","plainCitation":"(Martinez 40)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2698,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/5AQVUN3K"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/5AQVUN3K"],"itemData":{"id":2698,"type":"book","title":"Elizabeth Barrett Browning's <i>Aurora Leigh</i>","publisher":"Edinburgh University Press","publisher-place":"Edinburgh","number-of-pages":"193","source":"Google Books","event-place":"Edinburgh","ISBN":"978-0-7486-5443-7","note":"Google-Books-ID: dZRvAAAAQBAJ","language":"en","author":[{"family":"Martinez","given":"Michele C."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2012",4,12]]}},"locator":"40"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(40).
                The figural work of that apostrophe certainly continues in this passage. For Lacan,
                the work of such a “you” marks the border between psychotic and non-psychotic
                discourse: “The <hi rend="italic">you</hi> is the hooking of the other in the waters
                of meaning,” he explains, as he seeks a way, within psychotic language, “to elevate
                this <hi rend="italic">you</hi> to subjectivity”
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"Wh5HJU3J","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar III} 299)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar III 299)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":247,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"itemData":{"id":247,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book III: The Psychoses","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"0-393-03467-4","title-short":"Seminar III","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"translator":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1993"]]}},"locator":"299"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar III</hi> 299). The “you” of this passage, however, is
                “me,” who is subjected to an omnipotent sun who asks “shall,” as if it had been
                subjected, at dawn, to a yet more powerful “you”: the gap between the ego and Other
                has been foreclosed in this passage.</p>
            <p>If psychotic subjects have foreclosed the Name of the Father, it does not mean that
                they have no recourse to language: as the psychotic patient Mr. Primeau tells Lacan,
                “I create worlds through my poetry, through my poetic speech”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"Sr0UVawT","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, \\uc0\\u8220{}A Lacanian Psychosis\\uc0\\u8221{} 34)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, “A Lacanian Psychosis” 34)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2690,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/KK3BUYNH"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/KK3BUYNH"],"itemData":{"id":2690,"type":"chapter","title":"A Lacanian Psychosis: Interview by Jacques Lacan","container-title":"Returning to Freud: Clinical Psychoanalysis in the School of Lacan","publisher":"Yale University Press","publisher-place":"New Haven","page":"19-41","event-place":"New Haven","ISBN":"978-0-300-03932-0","title-short":"A Lacanian Psychosis","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"container-author":[{"family":"Schneiderman","given":"Stuart"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1987"]]}},"locator":"34"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Lacan,
                “A Lacanian Psychosis” 34). The missing signifier makes it impossible, though, for
                the psychotic subject to resolve herself into the Law: psychosis is a failure of
                language systems to produce meaning, and a confrontation with the absence of
                meaning, rather than an abstention from language itself
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"o9X6u6ft","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Grigg 56)","plainCitation":"(Grigg 56)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2596,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/T5HHS9QD"],"itemData":{"id":2596,"type":"chapter","title":"From the Mechanism of Psychosis to the Universal Condition of the Symptom: On Foreclosure","container-title":"Key Concepts of Lacanian Psychoanalysis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","event-place":"London","title-short":"From the Mechanism","author":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"editor":[{"family":"Nobus","given":"Dany"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2017"]]}},"locator":"56"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Grigg
                56). In the words of Mr. Primeau:<hi rend="i0" xml:space="preserve"> “</hi>I am a
                little disjointed in regard to language. . . .  … Language could present strata and
                substrata”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"66Xxfov6","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, \\uc0\\u8220{}A Lacanian Psychosis\\uc0\\u8221{} 19\\uc0\\u8211{}20)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, “A Lacanian Psychosis” 19–20)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2690,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/KK3BUYNH"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/KK3BUYNH"],"itemData":{"id":2690,"type":"chapter","title":"A Lacanian Psychosis: Interview by Jacques Lacan","container-title":"Returning to Freud: Clinical Psychoanalysis in the School of Lacan","publisher":"Yale University Press","publisher-place":"New Haven","page":"19-41","event-place":"New Haven","ISBN":"978-0-300-03932-0","title-short":"A Lacanian Psychosis","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"container-author":[{"family":"Schneiderman","given":"Stuart"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1987"]]}},"locator":"19-20"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(“A
                Lacanian Psychosis”
                19–20).<hi rend="i0" xml:space="preserve"> That is why </hi>Lacan understands
                psychosis as “a question of the subject’s access to a signifier as such and of the
                impossibility of that access,” in the face of which we find “the separate deployment
                and the bringing into play of the entire signifying apparatus,  .  .  .  laden with
                non-meaningfulness, [and] the decomposition of internal discourse, which marks the
                entire structure of psychosis.” Psychosis, in short—as Lacan sees it—is “the
                encounter, the collision, with the inassimilable signifier,” which then “has to be
                reconstituted”
                    <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"63wli97A","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar III} 321)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar III 321)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":247,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"itemData":{"id":247,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book III: The Psychoses","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"0-393-03467-4","title-short":"Seminar III","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"translator":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1993"]]}},"locator":"321"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(<hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar III</hi> 321).</p>
            <p>In reading <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Aurora Leigh </hi>as the psychotic
                decomposition of Romantic discourse, I am trying to situate the poem within recent
                debates about the clinical approach to psychosis within Lacanian psychoanalysis, and
                specifically what is called “ordinary psychosis.” WithIn cases of “ordinary
                psychosis,” explains Vanheule, one must consider not an array of dramatic symptoms,
                but only “how speech structures the subject”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"Ceq8nxNh","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Vanheule 78)","plainCitation":"(Vanheule 78)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2696,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/4P9CXJM6"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/4P9CXJM6"],"itemData":{"id":2696,"type":"chapter","title":"On Ordinary Psychosis","container-title":"Lacan on Psychosis: From Theory to Praxis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","page":"77-103","event-place":"London","title-short":"Ordinary Psychosis","author":[{"family":"Vanheule","given":"Stijn"}],"editor":[{"family":"Mills","given":"Jon"},{"family":"Downing","given":"David L."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019"]]}},"locator":"78"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(78).
                This is part of a movement, now ongoing with Lacanian psychoanalysis, to define
                psychosis not by means of a “hegemonic authoritarian psychiatry” but “as a
                conceptual framework or philosophical perspective supported by descriptive narrative
                and symptomatic phenomenology that challenges preconceived notions of what we
                typically consider psychosis to entail,” according tos Jon Mills explains
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"QRgrMjVS","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Mills 2)","plainCitation":"(Mills 2)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2693,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/VUBTB3JL"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/VUBTB3JL"],"itemData":{"id":2693,"type":"chapter","title":"Introduction: beyond <i>nous</i>","container-title":"Lacan on Psychosis: From Theory to Praxis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","page":"1-10","event-place":"London","title-short":"Introduction","author":[{"family":"Mills","given":"Jon"}],"editor":[{"family":"Mills","given":"Jon"},{"family":"Downing","given":"David L."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019"]]}},"locator":"2"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(2).
                As Mills suggests, “contemporary Lacanian’s [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] are in hot
                debate over what constitutes psychosis, including defining the ordinary from
                pathological variants that have historically defined that phenomena as a mental
                illness”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"M0poYFTS","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Mills 1\\uc0\\u8211{}2)","plainCitation":"(Mills 1–2)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2693,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/VUBTB3JL"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/VUBTB3JL"],"itemData":{"id":2693,"type":"chapter","title":"Introduction: beyond <i>nous</i>","container-title":"Lacan on Psychosis: From Theory to Praxis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","page":"1-10","event-place":"London","title-short":"Introduction","author":[{"family":"Mills","given":"Jon"}],"editor":[{"family":"Mills","given":"Jon"},{"family":"Downing","given":"David L."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019"]]}},"locator":"1-2"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(1–2).
                For Vanheule, this is what makes Lacan’s approach to psychosis better suited for
                this historical moment of ours: it is poised to make headway in cases of “ordinary
                psychosis” because it begins from the premise of the subject’s relation to language
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"Q5tEKTCT","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Vanheule 78)","plainCitation":"(Vanheule 78)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2696,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/4P9CXJM6"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/4P9CXJM6"],"itemData":{"id":2696,"type":"chapter","title":"On Ordinary Psychosis","container-title":"Lacan on Psychosis: From Theory to Praxis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","page":"77-103","event-place":"London","title-short":"Ordinary Psychosis","author":[{"family":"Vanheule","given":"Stijn"}],"editor":[{"family":"Mills","given":"Jon"},{"family":"Downing","given":"David L."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019"]]}},"locator":"78"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(78).
                McGowan, echoing Vanheule, prizes Lacan’s approach to psychosis for the way that it
                stresses a “fundamental kinship” between the purportedly normal subject and the
                psychotic—much as Freud has done for neurosis
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"sbyXsILR","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(McGowan 50)","plainCitation":"(McGowan 50)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2694,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/U8F3V83B"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/U8F3V83B"],"itemData":{"id":2694,"type":"chapter","title":"The Psychosis of Freedom: Law in Modernity","container-title":"Lacan on Psychosis: From Theory to Praxis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","page":"47-77","event-place":"London","title-short":"The Psychosis of Freedom","author":[{"family":"McGowan","given":"Todd"}],"editor":[{"family":"Mills","given":"Jon"},{"family":"Downing","given":"David L."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019"]]}},"locator":"50"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(50).
                We are seeing such a kinship play out in Book I of <hi rend="italic">Aurora
                    Leigh</hi>, as Barrett Browning reckons with Coleridge’s legacy. In her
                interactions with Coleridge’s text, we can see her closely listening to a partner’s
                voice, to parse its “interrupted messages”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"2OXoQh0q","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}\\uc0\\u201{}crits} 451)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Écrits 451)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":819,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"itemData":{"id":819,"type":"book","title":"Écrits: The First Complete Edition in English","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"9780393329254","title-short":"Écrits","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Fink","given":"Bruce"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2006"]]}},"locator":"451"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Lacan,
                    <hi rend="italic">Écrits</hi> 451). This, as Lacan explains, is the crux of
                psychosis, even in the absence of noticeable symptoms.</p>
            <p>Roland Barthes suggests that symbol is “analogical and inadequate” to its referent,
                and thus takes an inexact relation to signification
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"bsFYK2Cm","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Barthes 38)","plainCitation":"(Barthes 38)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2337,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/VI8C4JFA"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/VI8C4JFA"],"itemData":{"id":2337,"type":"book","title":"Elements of Semiology","publisher":"Hill and Wang","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","author":[{"family":"Barthes","given":"Roland"}],"translator":[{"family":"Lavers","given":"Annette"},{"family":"Smith","given":"Colin"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1968"]]}},"locator":"38"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(38).
                It is for this reason, perhaps, that symbolization becomes the limit point of
                psychosis. To be psychotic is to refuse the cut of the signifier and thus to be
                rendered unable to demarcate the realm of symbolic meaning from other levels of
                apprehension. In this context, we might find new ways of understanding Aurora’s
                offhand admonition that, “By the way, / The works of women are symbolical” (ll. 1.
                455–56): the statement might not refer to the tendency for women artists to use
                symbolism, or to produce, through their domestic craftworks, tokens of their own
                marginal status, but rather might suggest that women’s works directly
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">are </hi>symbolical, with the “are” doing the
                work of a metaphor. That is, women’s texts begin to function as a replacement for
                the symbolic register itself. By “works,” Barrett Browning means quasi-artistic
                productions that will be used by men in the domestic space—the mending of a
                husband’s slippers, the construction of a stool, or “at best, a cushion” (ll. 1.
                458–61). Note how these “works” are not “symbolical” in the sense that they function
                symbolically: Barrett Browning seems to mean that they function metonymically, as
                slivers of evidence of women’s subordination. They attest to a sexual nonrelation,
                by leaving material traces of women’s domestic labour around the house. These traces
                are “symbolical” to the extent that they reveal a truth about everyday life—a hidden
                resentment of women and devaluation of their work—in an assemblage of seemingly
                minor examples. Now, to make such a sweeping statement about “the works of women”
                tout court is an outrageous generalization, as Barrett Browning clearly knew
                well—and this, in a poem, itself very ambitious in scope, which valorizes the
                dignity of women’s artistic ambitions. The point is not, though, that women artists
                have an innate special relation to symbol; it may rather be that Aurora Leigh—the
                fraught “I” of the “novel in verse”—cannot comfortably differentiate her own ego
                from the category “woman” in general.: Sshe is, through her foreclosed redeployment
                of symbolic language, becoming-woman in Schreber’s sense and : she is finding new
                arrangements for enjoyment that do not depend upon the cut of castration
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"lSf6VC99","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Schreber 18 n.1)","plainCitation":"(Schreber 18 n.1)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2704,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/22WRBPPM"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/22WRBPPM"],"itemData":{"id":2704,"type":"book","title":"Memoirs of my Nervous Illness","publisher":"New York Review Books","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","title-short":"Memoirs","author":[{"family":"Schreber","given":"Daniel Paul"}],"translator":[{"family":"MacAlpine","given":"Ida"},{"family":"Hunter","given":"Richard"}],"editor":[{"family":"MacAlpine","given":"Ida"},{"family":"Hunter","given":"Richard"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2000"]]}},"locator":"18 n.1"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Schreber
                18 n.1). Just as, in Paul de Man’s assessment, “the symbol is always part of the
                totality that it represents,” and thus functions as a species of synecdoche, so too
                in Lacan’s exposition of psychosis, in whichdoes the subject, becoming “the
                mouthpiece of a discourse that is not his own,” find that “he cannot speak without
                hearing himself”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"ZDbFvf6Y","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(de Man 190\\uc0\\u8211{}91; Lacan, {\\i{}\\uc0\\u201{}crits} 447)","plainCitation":"(de Man 190–91; Lacan, Écrits 447)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1518,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/C92NEWJH"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/C92NEWJH"],"itemData":{"id":1518,"type":"chapter","title":"The Rhetoric of Temporality","container-title":"Blindness and Insight: Essays in the Rhetoric of Contemporary Criticism","collection-title":"Theory and History of Literature","collection-number":"7","publisher":"University of Minnesota Press","publisher-place":"Minneapolis","page":"187-228","edition":"2","event-place":"Minneapolis","title-short":"Rhetoric of Temporality","author":[{"family":"Man","given":"Paul","non-dropping-particle":"de"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1983"]]}},"locator":"190-191"},{"id":819,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/ZXCQZF6R"],"itemData":{"id":819,"type":"book","title":"Écrits: The First Complete Edition in English","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"9780393329254","title-short":"Écrits","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"translator":[{"family":"Fink","given":"Bruce"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2006"]]}},"locator":"447"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(de
                Man 190–91; <hi rend="italic">Écrits</hi> 447). Barrett Browning, as she inhabits
                and speaks Coleridge’s symbolic discourse, finds that Aurora cannot detach herself
                from her own poetic utterances.</p>
            <p> Romanticism, in de Man’s view, was the movement away from allegory and toward
                symbol; he found in the dialectical interplay of these tropes forms of repetition
                that could organize images in time. In symbol, says de Man, “time is merely a matter
                of contingency,” whereas in allegory, which functions through repetition instead of
                synthesis, “time is the originary constitutive category”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"xEvammyu","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(de Man 207)","plainCitation":"(de Man 207)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1518,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/C92NEWJH"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/C92NEWJH"],"itemData":{"id":1518,"type":"chapter","title":"The Rhetoric of Temporality","container-title":"Blindness and Insight: Essays in the Rhetoric of Contemporary Criticism","collection-title":"Theory and History of Literature","collection-number":"7","publisher":"University of Minnesota Press","publisher-place":"Minneapolis","page":"187-228","edition":"2","event-place":"Minneapolis","title-short":"Rhetoric of Temporality","author":[{"family":"Man","given":"Paul","non-dropping-particle":"de"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1983"]]}},"locator":"207"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(207).
                Symbol functions spatially, by simultaneity: it refuses the repetitions that
                characterize allegory, undoing “an authentically temporal destiny,” yet as it
                collides with allegory it creates its own temporalities. Coleridge is of course de
                Man’s primary case in point
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"3vIZurF7","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(de Man 206)","plainCitation":"(de Man 206)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":1518,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/C92NEWJH"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/C92NEWJH"],"itemData":{"id":1518,"type":"chapter","title":"The Rhetoric of Temporality","container-title":"Blindness and Insight: Essays in the Rhetoric of Contemporary Criticism","collection-title":"Theory and History of Literature","collection-number":"7","publisher":"University of Minnesota Press","publisher-place":"Minneapolis","page":"187-228","edition":"2","event-place":"Minneapolis","title-short":"Rhetoric of Temporality","author":[{"family":"Man","given":"Paul","non-dropping-particle":"de"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1983"]]}},"locator":"206"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(de
                Man 206). Barrett Browning is undoing that figural work, recasting Coleridge’s
                metonymy as symbol and then sequestering the symbol from any allegorical processes,
                to create something asynchronous and not totalizing, although its mood is often
                stifling. Where there is repetition in <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>’s
                allusions to Coleridge, it does not stem from the negation of Romantic totalities;
                rather, repetition is there from the start, built in tointo the poem through the
                allusion to Coleridge—and so Barrett Browning can sidestep the signature dialectics
                of Romantic figuration. The poem’s lime-tree symbolism, both strategic and
                deliberate,strategic and deliberate lime-tree symbolism becomes an important part of
                its feminist poetics.</p>
            <p rend="No Spacing">Such is the atemporal “message” that the lime tree brings to the
                house in <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>: the poem’s report of the tree’s
                arrival directly <hi rend="italic">is</hi> the “message,” and so further elaboration
                would be impossible. Barrett Browning, or perhaps Aurora, reconstitutes Romantic
                language in such a way as to create subtle ruptures in time. This is consistent with
                Lacan’s account of psychosis as a “turning away” from the diachronic aspects of
                discourse. Schreber himself remains uncertain if certain phases of his life were
                taking place over “a few earthly months only and not of centuries”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"9yEkRJ2x","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Schreber 69)","plainCitation":"(Schreber 69)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2704,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/22WRBPPM"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/22WRBPPM"],"itemData":{"id":2704,"type":"book","title":"Memoirs of my Nervous Illness","publisher":"New York Review Books","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","title-short":"Memoirs","author":[{"family":"Schreber","given":"Daniel Paul"}],"translator":[{"family":"MacAlpine","given":"Ida"},{"family":"Hunter","given":"Richard"}],"editor":[{"family":"MacAlpine","given":"Ida"},{"family":"Hunter","given":"Richard"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2000"]]}},"locator":"69"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(69).
                It is far from clear, in Book I of <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>, that “Times
                followed one another” (l. 2. 1), and the poem in general is, “deliberately untimely”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"r8me3X8i","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Mullen 73)","plainCitation":"(Mullen 73)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2460,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/S8966QZL"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/S8966QZL"],"itemData":{"id":2460,"type":"article-journal","title":"Two Clocks: <i>Aurora Leigh</i>, Poetic Form, and the Politics of Timeliness","container-title":"Victorian Poetry","page":"63-80","volume":"51","issue":"1","archive":"MLA International Bibliography","note":"See document for quotations.","title-short":"Two Clocks","language":"English","author":[{"family":"Mullen","given":"Mary"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2013"]]}},"locator":"73"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Mullen
                73). If, under typical Saussurean conditions, “there is no discourse without a
                certain temporal order,” then in psychosis we witness language becoming “a set of
                several lines, a stave,” according to which “certain elements become isolated,
                laden, take on a value, a particular force of inertia, become charged with meaning,
                with a meaning and nothing more”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"KEtpgMr4","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, {\\i{}Seminar III} 54)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, Seminar III 54)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":247,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/BWJ79UVN"],"itemData":{"id":247,"type":"book","title":"The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book III: The Psychoses","publisher":"Norton","publisher-place":"New York","event-place":"New York","ISBN":"0-393-03467-4","title-short":"Seminar III","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"translator":[{"family":"Grigg","given":"Russell"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1993"]]}},"locator":"54"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(Lacan,
                    <hi rend="italic">Seminar III</hi> 54). Along these lines (as it were), one can
                place <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi> within a tradition of Romantic-era women’s
                writing that, through its manipulations of figurative language and the materiality
                of the signifier, began to think about time asynchronously. Such a tradition, which
                does not always or usually avail itself of psychotic structures to create
                alternative temporalities, would include authors works such as Mary Wollstonecraft’s
                “The Cave of Fancy,” Helen Maria Williams’s <hi rend="italic">Paul and
                Virginia</hi>, Charlotte Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Beachy Head</hi>, and Mary
                Shelley’s “The Mortal Immortal.” Because Barrett Browning’s contribution to this
                tradition exploits the elements of psychotic language, and the reconstitution of
                existing signifying structures, then in order to show how this flattened temporality
                emerges in Barrett Browning’s poem, we have needed to examine Barrett Browning’s
                lime tree in relation to Coleridge’s, with careful attention to the rhetoric of
                temporality of both poets, to show how this flattened temporality emerges in <hi
                    rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>. What had been, for Coleridge, a series of
                interlocking tropes designed to create intimacy with nature and one’s friends has
                been rewritten so as to stress the anxiety attendant upon that scene once the
                different levels that support it collapse.</p>
            <p rend="No Spacing">Aurora Leigh imagines herself as a “wild bird” trapped within her
                Aunt’s “cage-bird life” (ll. 1. 310, 305). At one level, the contrast in the text
                would seem to be between a bird captured from the wild and a bird raised in
                captivity, given as two models of Victorian womanhood. Yet the image also reveals a
                doubleness of experience, the feeling of being wild and caged simultaneously. Mr.
                Primeau expresses his experience of psychosis in just such terms, much to Lacan’s
                evident frustration:<hi rend="i0" xml:space="preserve"> “</hi>The fact of speaking
                of these solitary circles and of living without boundaries; there is no
                contradiction. In my mind I do not see a contradiction. How can I explain that? I am
                in a solitary circle because I am broken off from reality”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"qdsWaNAP","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, \\uc0\\u8220{}A Lacanian Psychosis\\uc0\\u8221{} 33\\uc0\\u8211{}34)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, “A Lacanian Psychosis” 33–34)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2690,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/KK3BUYNH"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/KK3BUYNH"],"itemData":{"id":2690,"type":"chapter","title":"A Lacanian Psychosis: Interview by Jacques Lacan","container-title":"Returning to Freud: Clinical Psychoanalysis in the School of Lacan","publisher":"Yale University Press","publisher-place":"New Haven","page":"19-41","event-place":"New Haven","ISBN":"978-0-300-03932-0","title-short":"A Lacanian Psychosis","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"container-author":[{"family":"Schneiderman","given":"Stuart"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1987"]]}},"locator":"33-34"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>
                (“A Lacanian Psychosis” 33–34). That is, psychosis can confer the experience of
                freedom upon those living within severe confinements. “In relation to the solitary
                circle, I live without boundaries,” Primeau explains to Lacan, adding,: “But in
                relation to the real, I live
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">with </hi>boundaries”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"jsaCvfCF","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Lacan, \\uc0\\u8220{}A Lacanian Psychosis\\uc0\\u8221{} 34)","plainCitation":"(Lacan, “A Lacanian Psychosis” 34)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2690,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/KK3BUYNH"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/KK3BUYNH"],"itemData":{"id":2690,"type":"chapter","title":"A Lacanian Psychosis: Interview by Jacques Lacan","container-title":"Returning to Freud: Clinical Psychoanalysis in the School of Lacan","publisher":"Yale University Press","publisher-place":"New Haven","page":"19-41","event-place":"New Haven","ISBN":"978-0-300-03932-0","title-short":"A Lacanian Psychosis","author":[{"family":"Lacan","given":"Jacques"}],"editor":[{"family":"Miller","given":"Jacques-Alain"}],"container-author":[{"family":"Schneiderman","given":"Stuart"}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["1987"]]}},"locator":"34"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(34).
                Like Mr. Primeau, Aurora Leigh finds in poetic language—in the figural work of
                allusion and symbol, and in the disruptions of meter, syntax, and lineation—a way to
                create an unbounded confinement in the absence of a master signifier.</p>
            <p> Coleridge’s work resonates through Book I of <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>,
                but Barrett Browning, by shifting the tropes and by framing the experience through a
                window, undoes the imaginative work of “This Lime-Tree Bower” as part of its
                innovative feminist poetics. This might be termed an “impasse of the feminine” which
                that “is central to psychosis in women,” according to Willy Apollon, Danielle
                Bergeron, and Lucie Canton: Aurora’s unwriting of “the social link, the requirement
                of the cultural construction of the feminine, removes the possibility [for her] to
                address a reliable Other for an essential dimension of [her life]”
                <?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_ITEM CSL_CITATION {"citationID":"Tnvoc8qZ","properties":{"formattedCitation":"(Apollon et al. 132)","plainCitation":"(Apollon et al. 132)","noteIndex":0},"citationItems":[{"id":2695,"uris":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/4YP2XCE4"],"uri":["http://zotero.org/users/71093/items/4YP2XCE4"],"itemData":{"id":2695,"type":"chapter","title":"Problems of Femininity in the Psychoanalytical Treatment of Psychotic Women","container-title":"Lacan on Psychosis: From Theory to Praxis","publisher":"Routledge","publisher-place":"London","page":"132-158","event-place":"London","title-short":"Problems of Femininity","author":[{"family":"Apollon","given":"Willy"},{"family":"Bergeron","given":"Danielle"},{"family":"Canton","given":"Lucy"}],"editor":[{"family":"Mills","given":"Jon"},{"family":"Downing","given":"David L."}],"issued":{"date-parts":[["2019"]]}},"locator":"132"}],"schema":"https://github.com/citation-style-language/schema/raw/master/csl-citation.json"}?>(132).
                Such an impasse arises, in its temporal dimension, once symbol and meter escape
                their boundaries and overflow the signifying processes of Coleridge’s text. Instead
                of choosing to adopt a Coleridgean hopefulness or to pledge generosity toward an
                absent friend, Barrett Browning creates an anxious and uncanny encounter with the
                cause of the friend’s desire—one that has repetition built into its very premise and
                premises, so that it does not need to wait for repetition to be generated out of the
                work of metonymy and symbol. In so doing, Barrett Browning registers Romantic poetry
                as a discourse both alien to the subject and internal to it, an ambiguity that
                registers in Aurora as an unnamable site of anxiety. The ambiguity leaves
                Romanticism vulnerable to its future, which here never stops being written.</p>
            <p><pb/></p>
            <p style="text-align: center;">Works Cited</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography"
                ><?biblio ADDIN ZOTERO_BIBL {"uncited":[],"omitted":[],"custom":[]} CSL_BIBLIOGRAPHY?>Apollon,
                Willy, et al. “Problems of Femininity in the Psychoanalytical Treatment of Psychotic
                Women.” <hi rend="italic">Lacan on Psychosis: From Theory to Praxis</hi>, edited by
                Jon Mills and David L. Downing. , Routledge, 2019, pp. 132–58.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Barrett Browning, Elizabeth. <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh:
                    Authoritative Text, Backgrounds and Contexts, Criticism</hi>, edited by Margaret
                Reynolds, 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> ed., Norton, 1996.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Barthes, Roland. <hi rend="italic">Elements of Semiology</hi>.
                Translated by Annette Lavers and Colin Smith. , Hill and Wang, 1968.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Browning, Robert, and Elizabeth Barrett Browning. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Brownings’ Correspondence</hi>, edited by Phillip Kelley et
                al., Wedgestone Press, 1984.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Coleridge, Samuel Taylor. "Frost at Midnight." <hi rend="italic"
                    >Romantic Circles</hi>,
                https://romantic-circles.org/editions/poets/texts/frostatmidnight.html. Accessed 2
                Apr. 2019.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">———.---. "This Lime-Tree Bower My Prison." <hi rend="italic"
                    >Romantic Circles</hi>,
                https://romantic-circles.org/editions/poets/texts/limetree.html. Accessed 2 Apr.
                2019.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">de Man, Paul. “The Rhetoric of Temporality.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Blindness and Insight: Essays in the Rhetoric of Contemporary Criticism</hi>,
                2nd ed. U of Minnesota P, 1983, pp. 187–228.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">DeLuise, Delores, and Michael Timko. “Becoming the Poet: The
                Feminine Poet-Speaker in the Work of Elizabeth Barrett Browning.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Virginal Sexuality and Textuality in Victorian Literature: Essays in
                    Environmental Philosophy</hi>, edited by Lloyd Davis. , SUNY Press, 1993, pp.
                87–104.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">de Man, Paul. “The Rhetoric of Temporality.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Blindness and Insight: Essays in the Rhetoric of Contemporary Criticism</hi>,
                2nd ed., U of Minnesota P, 1983, pp. 187–228.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Grigg, Russell. “From the Mechanism of Psychosis to the Universal
                Condition of the Symptom: On Foreclosure.” <hi rend="italic">Key Concepts of
                    Lacanian Psychoanalysis</hi>, edited by Dany Nobus. , Routledge, 2017.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Inboden, Robin L. “Damsels, Dulcimers, and Dreams: Elizabeth
                Barrett’s Early Response to Coleridge.” <hi rend="italic">Victorian Poetry</hi>,
                vol. 46, no. 2, 2008, pp. 129–50.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Kobayashi, Emily V. Epstein. “Feeling Intellect in <hi
                    rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Prelude</hi>.” <hi
                    rend="italic">SEL: Studies in English Literature 1500-–1900</hi>, vol. 51, no.
                4, 2011, pp. 823–48.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Labbe, Jacqueline M. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Visualities:
                    Landscape, Gender, and Romanticism</hi>. Palgrave Macmillan, 1998.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Lacan, Jacques. <hi rend="italic">Écrits: The First Complete
                    Edition in English</hi>. Translated by Bruce Fink, Norton, 2006.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">———. “A Lacanian Psychosis: Interview by Jacques Lacan.” <hi
                    rend="italic">Returning to Freud: Clinical Psychoanalysis in the School of
                    Lacan</hi>, edited by Jacques-Alain Miller. , Yale UP, 1987, pp. 19–41.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">---. <hi rend="italic">Écrits: The First Complete Edition in
                    English</hi>. Translated by Bruce Fink. Norton, 2006.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">---———. <hi rend="italic">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book III:
                    The Psychoses</hi>, edited by Jacques-Alain Miller. , tTranslated by Russell
                Grigg. , Norton, 1993.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">---. ———. <hi rend="italic">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book X:
                    Anxiety,</hi> edited by Jacques-Alain Miller,. tTranslated by A.R. Price. ,
                Polity, 2015.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Langan, Celeste. “Pathologies of Communication from Coleridge to
                Schreber.” <hi rend="italic">The South Atlantic Quarterly</hi>, vol. 102, no. 1,
                2003, pp. 117–52.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Lau, Beth. “Introduction.” <hi rend="italic">Fellow Romantics:
                    Male and Female British Writers, 1790-–1835</hi>, edited by Beth Lau. , Ashgate,
                2009, pp. 1–16.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Louis, Margot K. “Enlarging the Heart: L. E. L.’s ‘The
                Improvisatrice,’ Hemans’s ‘Properzia Rossi,’ and Barrett Browning’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">Victorian Literature and
                    Culture</hi>, vol. 26, no. 1, 1998, pp. 1–17.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Martinez, Michele C.
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Elizabeth Barrett Browning’s </hi>Aurora
                Leigh. Edinburgh UP, 2012.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">McCarthy, Anne. C. <hi rend="italic">[Please add a complete
                    citation for this source.]Awful Parenthesis: Suspension and the Sublime in
                    Romantic and Victorian Poetry</hi>. U of Toronto P, 2018.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">McGowan, Todd. “The Psychosis of Freedom: Law in Modernity.” <hi
                    rend="italic">Lacan on Psychosis: From Theory to Praxis</hi>, edited by Jon
                Mills and David L. Downing. Routledge, 2019, pp. 47–77.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Mills, Jon. “Introduction: Beyond <hi rend="italic">Nous</hi>.”
                    <hi rend="italic">Lacan on Psychosis: From Theory to Praxis</hi>, edited by Jon
                Mills and David L. Downing. , Routledge, 2019, pp. 1–10.</p>
            <p>Mills, Jon, and David L. Downing, editors. <hi rend="italic">Lacan on Psychosis: From
                    Theory to Praxis</hi>. Routledge, 2019.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Mullen, Mary. “Two Clocks: <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh</hi>,
                Poetic Form, and the Politics of Timeliness.” <hi rend="italic">Victorian
                    Poetry</hi>, vol. 51, no. 1, 2013, pp. 63–80.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Murray, Chris. <hi rend="italic">Tragic Coleridge</hi>. Ashgate,
                2013.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">O’Gorman, Francis. “Coleridge, ‘Frost at Midnight’, and
                Anticipating the Future.” <hi rend="italic">Romanticism</hi>, vol. 14, no. 3, 2008,
                pp. 232–44.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Schreber, Daniel Paul. <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of My Nervous
                    Illness</hi>., Eedited by Ida MacAlpine and Richard Hunter. , Translated
                translated by Ida MacAlpine and Richard Hunter. , New York Review Books, 2000.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Thum, Maureen. “Challenging Traditionalist Gender Roles: The
                Exotic Woman as Critical Observer in Elizabeth Barrett Browning’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aurora Leigh</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">The Foreign Woman in British Literature:
                    Exotics, Aliens, and Outsiders</hi>, edited by Marilyn Button and Toni Reed. ,
                Greenwood, 1999, pp. 79–93.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Vanheule, Stijn. “On Ordinary Psychosis.” <hi rend="italic">Lacan
                    on Psychosis: From Theory to Praxis</hi>, edited by Jon Mills and David L.
                Downing. Routledge, 2019, pp. 77–103.</p>
            <p rend="Bibliography">Wolfson, Susan J. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Interactions: Social
                    Being and the Turns of Literary Action</hi>. The Johns Hopkins UP, 2010.</p>
        </front>
    </text>
</TEI>
