<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author>Kate Singer</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-07-28</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2023-11-01T03:36:39Z</date><name>Kate Singer</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>“I feel it coming in the air tonight”: <hi rend="color(222222)">Mephitical Vapors,
                    Pestiferous Plagues, and the</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="color(222222)">Psychosis of Materiality in Wollstonecraft</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="color(222222)">Kate Singer, Mount Holyoke College</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="color(222222)">ksinger@mtholyoke.edu</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="color(222222)">Abstract:</hi></p>
            <p>Although Mary Wollstonecraft is most squarely known as the post-Enlightenment
                progenitor of feminist reason and is often seen as allergic to the sexual body, this
                essay argues that throughout her works she evinces more posthuman and malleable
                forms of materiality and alternative psychic arrangements that subtend any
                “"reasonable”" law of the father. Figures of vapor, pestilence, palpable
                atmospherics, and other instances of dynamic materiality in <hi rend="italic">The
                    Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Maria; or the Wrongs
                    of Woman</hi>, and
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Norway, Sweden, and Denmark </hi>evince
                fluid forms of materiality that bespeak a certain language of psychosis, or the
                ability to speak underneath or beyond the symbolic order of the father via an
                alternative Real that is richly flexible, material, and feminist. Such writings can,
                even more broadly help us rethink the relationship between the Ssymbolic and the
                Real and, the role of psychosis as a literary method, and while also helping us
                bridge psychoanalysis and new materialism.</p>
            <p> Mary Wollstonecraft, during one of her most energetic rebukes in <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi> (1792), upbraids her own Trumpish
                king and luxury-addled aristocrats not only for their insane policies but for
                creating an atmosphere that poisons everyone: “What but a pestilential vapour can
                hover over society, when its chief director is only instructed in the invention of
                crimes, or the stupid routine of childish ceremonies?” (18–-19). In a philosophical
                pamphlet so devoted to gaining rights for women (and asking men to actually earn
                their rights as equitable citizens), such a dispersed, nonhuman figure strangely
                lurks in such a supposedly humanistic treatise. While she dwells on the aristocrats,
                soldiers, and coquettes whose lack of virtue corrupts the nation, this figure of
                vapor, and others like it in her writing, suggest something more than human is
                responsible for the nation’s sickening haze, its miasmatic ambience. Created by its
                chief dilldocks, even as it pervades and alters them, and such contagious
                materiality suggests a complicated entanglement between matter and humans that
                redraws <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Vindication </hi>as more than a
                bid for women’s entrée into Enlightenment humanism.</p>
            <p> Inherent in Wollstonecraft’s invective is what Jane Bennett has described as human
                and nonhuman materials in vibrant assemblage: human actions within the consumerist
                climate of London create the foul atmosphere of the modern city, an airborne toxic
                event in which nonhuman vapors take on an infectious life of their own<anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="24"/><anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="25"
                    />.<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="24"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="24"><date when="2022-07-27T22:07:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please include a page number citation
                            for the paraphrase.</hi></note></hi><anchor type="commentRangeEnd"
                    n="25"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment"
                        resp="#Kate_Singer" n="25"><date when="2022-09-19T20:14:00Z"/>The Bennett is
                        just the paraphrase of her main argument. If you mean the Wollstonecraft, it
                        would be
                        (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Vindication </hi>18=19).</note></hi>
                Yet, Wollstonecraft is already hip to the pharmakon of the post-Revolutionary
                political climat<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="26"/>e.<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p> For more on climate, atmosphere,
                            and weather as a political and social atmospherics, see Mary Favret’s
                                <hi rend="italic">War at a Distance</hi>, Michelle Speitz’s essay on
                            air in <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and Speculative Realism</hi>, and,
                            in a transatlantic context, Christina Sharpe’s <hi rend="italic">In the
                                Wake</hi>. See also Anne-Lise Francois’ recent work on nonhuman life
                            and atmospherics, represented by her lectures at Columbia University on
                            Sept. 26, 2017, “Fire, Water, Moon: Supplemental Seasons in a Time
                            without Season” and at Brown University on, March 21, 2016, “‘In the
                            cowslips peeps I lye’: Rousseau, Clare, Climate Change and Telling the
                            Time of Day.” Many thanks to Libby Fay for these last
                        references.</p></note></hi> As sShe <anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="26"
                    /><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Kate_Singer"
                        n="26"><date when="2022-09-19T20:17:00Z"/>Please leave as is, as it is a
                        stylistic choice.</note></hi>complicates her own argument: “It is the
                pestiferous purple which renders the progress of civilization a curse, and warps the
                understanding, till men of sensibility doubt whether the expansion of intellect
                produces a greater portion of happiness or misery. But the nature of the poison
                points out the antidote”
                (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Vindication </hi>21). Here, she certainly
                means the toxic aristocracy and royalty who lead through contagious consumption and
                the perversion of reason.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="endnote text"> Wollstonecraft may also be referring to,
                            satirically, the lead-based cosmetics still used by men and women in the
                            eighteenth century as well as the various medicinal cures that may have
                            been to blame for King George III’s decline.</p></note></hi> More
                deviously, she also intimates the purple erect head of a patriarchal penis, the
                phallic pestilence that spreads its tyranny through proud ejaculations of power (and
                venereal disease). Yet, the nature of the poison—the form of new materiality
                inherent within the mephitical vapor—likewise suggests the nature of the cure: that
                fresh airs of a dispersed, revivifying new materiality might diffuse this warped
                pestilence.</p>
            <p rend="annotation text"> The figure of “vapour,” akin to Priestly’s “philogiston” or
                eighteenth-century notions of aether,<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"
                            ><p rend="endnote text"> See Steve Mentz on “Philogiston” in Jeffrey
                            Jerome Cohen and Lowell Duckert’s <hi rend="italic">Elemental
                                Ecocriticism: Thinking with Earth, Air, Water, and
                        Fire</hi>.</p></note></hi> both enacts and figures a kind of new materiality
                that has the possibility of changing our minds, our bodies, and the world. Bennett
                calls something like this “impersonal affect,” while <anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="34"/>Teresa Brennan <anchor type="commentRangeEnd"
                    n="34"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor"
                        n="34"><date when="2022-07-28T13:45:00Z"/><hi rend="background(yellow)"
                            >Please add this source to the Works Cited</hi></note></hi>discusses the
                “atmosphere” of the other as the hormones and pheromones of chemical entrainment;
                even more recently Luce Irigaray’s <hi rend="italic">Through Vegetal Being</hi>
                theorizes air as a material method for universal sharing in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Through Vegetal Being</hi>. Yet, there is another important but neglected
                strand of thinking about fluid materiality in psychoanalytic notions of jouissance,
                especially the way Luce Irigaray and Hélène Cixous think<anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="39"/> of it,<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="39"
                    /><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Kate_Singer"
                        n="39"><date when="2022-09-19T20:19:00Z"/>Please leave as is</note></hi> as
                arising from the motions of body and atmosphere. As Irigaray says in <hi
                    rend="italic">Speculum of the Other Woman</hi>,: “Blood, but also milk, sperm,
                lymph, saliva, spit, tears, humors, gas, waves, airs, fire  .  .  .  light” (237).
                These produce what Lacan calls “jouissance’s beyond” of pleasure and desire, its
                “superabundant vitality” (<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="51"/><hi rend="italic"
                    >Seminar VII</hi>
                <anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="51"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="51"><date when="2022-07-28T14:20:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please add this source to the Works
                            Cited</hi></note></hi>23<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="52"
                    />7).<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="52"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"
                        ><note place="comment" resp="#Kate_Singer" n="52"><date
                            when="2022-09-20T14:59:00Z"/>Can we please add a note: See also Lacan’s
                            <hi rend="italic">Seminar XX</hi> (74-77).</note></hi> Not just the
                repetitive, fricative autoerotics of Irigaray’s two lips touching, not just the
                dispersed arousal of multiple erogenous zones—certainly not the hard finality of
                ejaculation—Wollstonecraft eventually envisions the continual excretion all over,
                everywhere, through every<hi rend="italic">thing</hi>. Cixous and Irigaray’s softer
                jouissance, along with Bennett’s affect, uses the conveyance of dispersal inherent
                in the toxic pestilence, but converts the tyrannic impressment of aristocratic
                poison into a mutual pleasure thanks to a shared affect of coeval origin and
                agency.</p>
            <p rend="annotation text"> Her vapors and other instances of dynamic materiality can
                help us bridge psychoanalysis and new materialism. Affinities between the two have
                been largely unremarked upon, despite being two prominent discourses in the last
                fifty years that deal in feminism and affect. Together, they might help enrich our
                understanding of human and nonhuman entanglement in posthuman studies, to which
                Wollstonecraft has something substantial to contribute. In perhaps the most recent
                attempt to connect the two fields, Alenka Zupančič offers a psychoanalytic account
                of object-oriented ontology in <hi rend="italic">What Is Sex</hi>? Unlike what we
                see in Wollstonecraft’s anticipation of new materiality, she maintains a rigid
                Lacanian perspective that separates objects and subjects. In Zupančič’s account,
                sexual desire for objects appears to be an apotheosis of the Lacanian <hi
                    rend="italic">objet petit a</hi>, with roving, symbolic objects as substitutes
                for human ones that might impossibly fill the hole and crack in the self. Rather
                than understanding the object as substituting particular inanimate objects for the
                mother’s lack of a penis, as Freud does, or a maternal phallus, as Lacan does,
                Zupančič’s objects themselves serve as symbolic proxies for the Lacanian lack at the
                heart of all selves caused by the lapse between the Real and the symbolic order.
                Such an analysis adheres to the object-oriented belief in objects being
                self-contained, withdrawn, and phallic, rather than fluid or porous like
                Wollstonecraft’s vapors.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p> For my
                            reading of the withdrawn object as phallic in its individualism even as
                            it induces a phallic desire to penetrate its allure, see my essay
                            “Surfing the Crimson Wave: Romantic New Materialisms and Speculative
                            Feminisms” in <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and Speculative
                            Realism</hi>.</p></note></hi> Perhaps even more problematic is the
                Lacanian faith in the impossibility of getting beyond the phallic law of the father. </p>
            <p>Wollstonecraft’s own writing, not yet bogged down by psychoanalytic doctrine, however
                proleptic of it, entangles human objects and subjects, miasmatic and vaporous
                materialities in a conceptual swerve that may help us rethink a Lacanian
                relationship to the nonhuman world.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="endnote text"> For a thoroughly Lacanian reading of Wollstonecraft
                            and indeed the Romantic conflict between non-gendered, disoriented forms
                            of enjoyment and sexually differentiated, constrained desire, see David
                            Sigler’s <hi rend="italic">Sexual Enjoyment in British Romanticism</hi>.
                        </p></note></hi> That is, Wollstonecraft certainly acknowledges
                Romanticism’s proleptic, systematic tendency to see objects as necessary
                substitutions in a libidinal economy that gets off more efficaciously (and with more
                than a fetish for singular objects) through a metonymic chain of <hi rend="italic"
                    >objets petits a</hi>. Yet, her anticipatory version of new materialism’s
                invasive idea—that things have vibrant energies which combine with the human in
                weird, unexpected, seemingly impossible ways<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                        place="end"><p rend="endnote text"> Here I am thinking of Jane Bennett’s
                            seminal contribution in <hi rend="italic">Vibrant Matter</hi> that
                            nonhuman things have agency, that human and nonhuman things join in
                            assemblage, and that they interact in confederation via impersonal
                            affect endemic to humans and nonhumans. The fluctuating materiality that
                            Wollstoncraft works with, however, might be even more nebulous and fluid
                            than Bennett’s things, which tend to remain discrete
                        entities.</p></note></hi>—complicates Lacan’s lamentation of the
                impossibility of non-phallic jouissance. Wollstonecraft more harmoniously speaks to
                similar responses from feminist psychoanalysts Julia Kristeva, Luce Irigaray,
                Melanie Klein, D. W. Winnicott, and Bracha Ettinger, yet perhaps goes further than
                them still, when she evanishes subjects and objects altogether into a swirling eddy
                of undisclosed materiality. When, in <hi rend="italic">Letters Written during a
                    Short Residence in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark</hi> (1796), she writes, “my very
                soul diffused itself in the agitated waves, melted in the freshening breeze,” she
                loses herself within the air and water that have themselves become almost mere
                movements, a superabundant vitality that bespeaks an excess of pleasure beyond the
                phallic and even beyond the human (50)<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="65"
                    />.<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="65"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="65"><date when="2022-07-28T15:36:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please include a page number for this
                            quote.</hi></note></hi> Such posthuman vibrancy remains undisclosed to
                the merely human and certainly to the symbolic order, which can only run after its
                flights.</p>
            <p rend="annotation text"> However much such a production of objects and partial-objects
                is the epistemological bent of the symbolic order, feminist or otherwise, what
                Wollstonecraft provokes us to ask is whether her an imagined ontological collapse of
                the subject into a new materiality—which is not repurposed as an <hi rend="italic"
                    >objet petit a</hi>—is a psychotic delusion. How insane is it to think subjects,
                however much a construct of Enlightenment necro-capital, can disperse themselves
                into objects, deforming and reforming bodies and minds into new beings?<anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="70"/><hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"
                            ><p rend="endnote text"> With the term <hi rend="italic"
                                >“necro-capital</hi>,” I am citing drawing from Achille Mbembe’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Necropolitics</hi>, and his notion that rather than a
                            biopolitics that controls life and reproduction, Enlightenment
                            capitalism was built on the right to kill and enslave, thereby
                            constituting the subject itself through a power to kill or to elude such
                            death. While Mbembe’s work tracks the ways that enslaved Africans
                            encounter social and/or ontological death, this essay considers
                            Wollstonecraft’s volition or submission to the collapse of the subject.
                            How such a dispersal might emanate from Romantic-era white privilege or
                            perhaps offer a response to the already problematic nature of the
                            necropolitical white subject has become a project of my subsequent
                            inquiry.</p></note></hi><anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="70"/><hi
                    rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="70"
                            ><date when="2022-07-28T17:06:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)" xml:space="preserve">Mbembe doesn’t appear to use the term </hi><hi
                            rend="italic background(yellow)"
                        >necrocapital</hi><hi rend="background(yellow)" xml:space="preserve"> in the work mentioned, so I have edited your presentation of the word accordingly. I have also omitted the hyphen to be consistent with Mbembe’s and Merriam-Webster’s use of words that begin with the prefix “necro-”.</hi></note></hi>
                Psychoanalytic accounts of psychosis envision such materiality as a kind of Real
                that cannot comprehend the law of the father—the straight-jacketed Ssymbolic that
                defines subjects and objects, even while these same psychotic hallucinations are
                often shot through with the phallic and patriarchal. Wollstonecraft’s psychosis
                dreams itself nearly outside the law of the father. In the attempt to subvert the
                phallus and phallic jouissance, her provocative recombination of different kinds of
                bodies—and the language that deems them as such—would seem to be an impossible
                articulation of matter. Her play of language and materiality attempts to subtend the
                classical Lacanian creed that we cannot get outside the phallus or phallic
                jouissance, which by the very nature of the Oedipus complex dominates the Iimaginary
                and makes our access to the Real the cut of impossibility. Contra Irigaray, who
                polemically stated women had no access to psychosis psychosis—only hysteria,
                —because they had no language to declaim another route from the Rreal to the
                Ssymbolic, Wollstonecraft insists on new materialist relations as a necessary
                psychotic delusion. This psychosis manifests an insane possibility, from the point
                of view of Lacan, of another ontology altogether, a convent of pleasure where the
                symbolically-seeking law of the father has no being and thus no significance. The
                vaporous posthuman entanglement augurs material alliances beyond paternalistic and
                humanist biopolitics. Rather than Rousseau’s bad romances or masturbatory desires of
                ideal women (such as Sophie), Wollstonecraft suggests that imagining our bodies
                being deliciously smorged with all sorts of bodies, especially nonhuman ones in the
                natural world, is a nonsensical dream that might actually make possible new
                ontologies, fathomable outside a phallically able, Oedipal economy.</p>
            <p rend="annotation text"> Such a conception of psychosis is not meant to undermine the
                real pain and mental illness of psychotics, nor is it meant to valorize a slippery
                alter -ego such as Deleuze and Guattari’s anti-Oedipus who refuses to play by
                society’s rules. Rather, it is meant to show how thinking outside the paternalistic
                order, whether in Wollstonecraft’s or our own time, might both appear and be
                necessarily insane when it locates its transformations of ontology as a reality-, or
                Real-yet-to-come. More specifically, we can define Wollstonecraft’s new materiality
                as a delusion of feminine jouissance that works by entangling human and nonhuman, a
                transformation that brings into being something more than an ontology that occurs
                “after” the human. This psychosis is, rather, the hallucination of alchemical magic
                and science, the literal exchange between human and nonhuman, the organic and
                inorganic that transforms them both. It breaks us free from the ideologies and
                binaries, especially the gender binaries that Lacan was attempting to move beyond in
                    <hi rend="italic">Seminar XX</hi>, by imagining an (impossible) jouissance, a
                pleasure and excess that does not route its pleasure through a gendered or sexed
                other. The delusion of posthuman, mutual jouissance concocts a self-fulfilling
                fantasy that imagines the ability to change planetary ontologies into a much more
                free-flowing, nonbinary world. Here, the binary becomes the symbolic ghosting of
                those structures that were determined by gender—including humanism,
                anthropocentrism, sexism, and even, as Claire Colebrook suggests in her essay in <hi
                    rend="italic">Anthropocene Feminisms</hi>, modern capital.</p>
            <p> Wollstonecraft’s brief moments of dispersed, flowing excrescence in <hi
                    rend="italic">The Vindication</hi> serve as foreplay that finally climaxes in
                the varied endings of <hi rend="italic">Maria; or the Wrongs of Woman</hi> and, more
                expansively, in
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters Written during a Short Residence. </hi>Theat
                novel offers us a view into her most closely-thought account of madness, set as it
                is in an asylum, and can help us draw the terms of Wollstonecraft’s debate about
                non-phallic jouissance as a form of psychosis. Our introduction to Maria is
                precisely one at the border of hysteria and psychosis: </p>
            <p>One recollection with frightful velocity following another, threatened to fire her
                brain, and make her a fit companion for the terrific inhabitants, whose groans and
                shrieks were no unsubstantial sounds of whistling winds, or startled birds,
                modulated by a romantic fancy, which amuse while they affright; but such tones of
                misery as carry a dreadful certainty directly to the heart. What effect must they
                then have produced on one, true to the touch of sympathy, and tortured by maternal
                apprehension! (161-–62)</p>
            <p>Here Wollstonecraft depicts the hysterics of the asylum tenants, whose near animal
                sounds are combined with the psychosis of “fancy.” In Coleridge’s definition of the
                fancy, this proliferation of groans, shrieks, whistling, startling, and tones of
                misery offers an associative series of unsynthesized sensations. The hysteric’s
                “discharge of affect” affects both the other, the passerby, but and, more noxiously,
                “their own body” as an “indefinite repetition” (Cixous and Clément 18). These
                hysterical effusions are, as Cixous and Clément notes, both disruptive and
                conservative at the same time: they “revolt and shake up the public, the group, the
                men, the others to whom they are exhibited” and yet they destroy the hysteric in the
                process (5). Cixous and Clément’s commentary on hysteria has affinities to
                Wollstonecraft’s critiques of sensibility in <hi rend="italic">The Vindication</hi>,
                —for instance, how the cult of feeling, luxury, and delicacy evanesce women from the
                male, rational Ssymbolic. Yet, unlike in <hi rend="italic">The Vindication</hi>, in
                    <hi rend="italic">Maria</hi>, Wollstonecraft indicates affect as a contagious
                effusion that has the potential to disrupt the public (asylum visitors,
                conscientious readers) with some disruptive import outside the Ssymbolic from which
                women are exiled. We might read such affect as revolutionary, if we consider the
                walls of the asylum as the cages of the symbolic order that imprison women but for
                their ravaging groans and shrieks that both pervade and move beyond its bars. </p>
            <p>These ululations are answered by Maria’s vision of her baby: “Her infant’s image was
                continually floating on Maria’s sight”
                (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Maria </hi>162). The conjuring of the
                infant’s image interrupts these hysterics with a piece of the Ssymbolic, yet one
                that is not entirely stable there, as it variably exists, “continually floating on”
                the horizon of sight (162)<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="124"/><anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="125"/>.<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="124"/><hi
                    rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="124"
                            ><date when="2022-07-28T18:16:00Z"/><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please
                            include a page number for this quote.</hi></note></hi><anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="125"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Kate_Singer" n="125"><date
                            when="2022-09-20T15:14:00Z"/>It’s a restatement of the quote in the
                        previous sentence, but I added the same citation again if that’s want you
                        were asking for?</note></hi> Here, Wollstonecraft separates herself from
                Irigaray’s famous dictum that women cannot become psychotic because they lack a
                proper signifying system that is not borrowed from a phallic signifying economy,
                “because she remains an outsider, herself (a) subject to their norms”
                (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Speculum </hi>71). Maria’s flimsy delusion
                of her babe keeps her both intoxicatingly fevered and sane at the same time. This
                first object manifests the baby as a maternal possession—the infant as the only
                piece of the Ssymbolic a mother has intimate knowledge of and thus the right to
                possess as she grows through revolutionary breast feeding. The infant likewise
                presents a double of the mother, who, in gestation and early maternity, is
                temporarily inviolable should the biopolitical order wish to succeed. This language
                of the Ssymbolic momentarily offers the entangled infant-and-mother as the delusion
                of a being outside the Oedipal order and yet within the maternal Ssymbolic. Similar
                to Bracha Ettinger, Wollstonecraft offers a glimmer of a maternal Real in a
                matrixial borderspace of interaction and co-creation. Rather than the interactions
                between babe and mother producing iterative part-objects, in
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Maria </hi>they flicker as the delusional
                dream of a Ssymbolic that might glancingly exist outside the law of the father. The
                baby, of course, is born within George Venebles’s grasp as his paternal property,
                yet Maria can still fleetingly imagine the infant as <hi rend="italic">new</hi>born,
                without the stain of the Oedipal. </p>
            <p> Such psychosis, moreover, reveals Maria to be neither simply insane nor rational but
                intensely aware of the law of the father. In one sense, the loathsome Venables has
                wrongfully imprisoned her, and yet her supposed madness marks, for Wollstonecraft,
                women’s position within the patriarchy, as subject to the men castrated by their
                fear of women’s freedom and desires (and men’s own feminizing desires).<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"> By “women’s
                            freedom” I mean the mother’s phallic power, or the phallic woman who has
                            in some sense stolen or otherwise ienvaginated the phallus. The inmates’
                            lofty cries likewise signify a desire that roves outside the phallic
                            order, yet perhaps also men’s desire to be castrated, to have the
                            phallus stolen from them, or to have the symbolic order shaken by
                            women’s alleged perversions.</p></note></hi> The asylum, “a most
                terrific ruins,” with its “fallen column and mouldering arch,” figures the
                patriarchal institution and its Iimaginary crumbling into disarray
                (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Maria </hi>161). These cracks in the
                foundation of the patriarchy signal the threat of castration always immanent to the
                law of the father, or the cut of signification within the Oedipus cComplex that
                resists psychosis. Here, psychosis, in a classical Lacanian sense, would represent
                desire that has not been routed through the supposedly inevitable Oedipal order and
                its Ssymbolic. Wollstoneraft’s arch critique of that order can be found in the
                paranomasiaparonomasia of the ruin as both an exaggerated symbol of castration in
                the fallen institutional building and also as a form of hyperbolic sexual
                fulfillment in its most destructive to women. Yet, it likewise houses those beings
                unleashing of drives, like Maria’s delusion, nearly untouched by the Oedipal cut.
                The moulderingmoldering asylum also gestures to those chaotic drives of men who
                believe that women’s independent desires and proclamations of independence to beare
                hallucinations, an Iimaginary that is deemed impossible because it has no relation
                to the Ssymbolic ruled by the phallus. Maria emoting inside the asylum presents not
                more than simply the impossible dream of feminine jouissance inside a phallic
                economy and an institution always already vexed by its own castration. It also
                evinces the existence of the necessary and existing feminine psychosis of desires
                not routed through the ruined cracks in the phallic order. Another way to think of
                this psychosis might be a speculative or science fiction that is not based on a
                science-to-be-made-real but a sheer desire for a Real, non-phallic jouissance,
                marked by a yet-impossible nonbinary Ssymbolic, figured in the novel, as we shall
                see, by its multiple, alternate endings. </p>
            <p rend="annotation text"> Wollstonecraft’s female desires and psychotic delusion turn,
                again, into a pharmakon of cure and toxin, when Maria and Darnford fall in love
                virtually. While tThe transmission of marginalia in books they share, couriered by
                Jemima from one cell to another, presents an affect that collapses boundaries
                between readers, writers, books, and their affects. Once converted into a more
                heteronormative desire, however, their jouissance becomes caged by the law of the
                father. The desire passed back and forth in such writing—the excess of text, ink,
                and feeling—offers an incipient jouissance, an exciting surplus of signification and
                textual materiality. Such an excess of writing paves an entrance into the Real. It
                does so not onlyin part through the virtual hallucinations of each captive imagining
                the other or through the exchange of affects, personal and impersonal, concatenated
                by the exchange of marginalia. A shared atmosphere of human fantasy and affect,
                books as things in circulation, marginal notes, and the ruins of the asylum create a
                posthuman assemblage through the circulation of partially ineffable affects wrought
                by both fantasy’s psychotic signification and materiality’s collapse of it. The
                paratextual marginalia is not a supplement to the proper Ssymbolic (the tales and
                histories they read and analyze) but rather an instance of signification that
                carries the Real, posthuman materiality of affect (the <hi rend="italic">sub
                    rosa</hi> warmth, liveliness, and intensities), which alter the text and its
                symbolic function. Text and paratext are smorged together in an assemblage of
                human-book-marginalia that generate shared affects that are not simply human. These
                affects, in their virtual and posthuman transmission, bypass the Ssymbolic of the
                institutions of heteronormative marriage, sexuality, and Oedipal law. </p>
            <p rend="annotation text">The fantasy of jouissance as intellectual exchange—enacted
                through the book, its proliferating commentary, and affective exchange—marks a
                desire for the literary animacies of books, and the merger of humans and nonhumans
                in contact with them. Mel Y. Chen has recently written of animacies as the affective
                movements shared by people and things that mark their mutual animation, without an
                    <hi rend="italic">objet petit a</hi> or a substitution of either nonhumans or
                humans for an abyssal, originary lack. Jouissance, for Wollstonecraft, occurs
                through the literal cross-cut or, as Darnford’s name suggests, the hidden crossing
                of human and nonhuman. We see this playing out as Maria translates herself into
                marginalia inside a book, an animacy that circulates to and from Darnford by way of
                entanglement with Jemima’s oral, yet no less material, presence. Their comingling
                with the book and annotations is a kind of literary animacy, or what Nathan Snaza
                has recently called “animate literacy.” As he describes it, “some animals make marks
                that circulate in various media with affective agency and that are in turn attended
                by other animals” producing “collisions among bodies and agencies—many of them
                nonhuman” (Snaza 4, 7). Wollstonecraft’s attention to the collisions of marginalia,
                not unlike the epistolary form she had already experimented with, foments a literal
                circulation of affect within the assemblage of text + commentary + hand + asylum +
                keeper + inmates + fantasy. </p>
            <p rend="annotation text"> Arguably, it is when Maria and Darnford get together as a
                human dyad (without Jemima) that they fall into desire predicated on the <hi
                    rend="italic">objet petit a</hi>, because they are substituting themselves for
                what seems to be a lack, but which is really a mistaken understanding of the need
                for the human-nonhuman smorgy. Wollstonecraft intimates here that the way to outrun
                symbolic traps is to integrate the nonhuman. Another way to put this would be that
                the phallic Ssymbolic is human while a nonphallic Ssymbolic would need to be
                posthuman. Wollstonecraft might be thinking, as Lacan does, in terms of a desire
                that is nearly always subtended to something external to the subject. Yet, and this
                is where she departs from Lacan, such an object is neither withdrawn from other
                forms of materiality (i.e.,is not an “object” in the sense of having perforated
                boundaries), nor does it act as a substitute for an originary lack. Rather, a
                posthuman, shared materiality becomes a medium that materially shapes desire’s
                signifiers, ontologies of desire, and its constitutive elements. </p>
            <p> It may be important to remember that Wollstonecraft’s critique of phallic human
                fantasies derives from the dirtier aspects of Rousseau’s sensibilities. As she
                writes in <hi rend="italic">The Vindication</hi>:</p>
            <p>Even his virtues also led him farther astray; for, born with a warm constitution and
                a lively fancy, nature carried him toward the other sex with such eager fondness,
                that he soon became lascivious. Had he given way to these desires, the fire would
                have extinguished itself in a natural manner; but virtue, and a romantic kind of
                delicacy, made him practise self-denial; yet, when fear, delicacy, or virtue,
                restrained him, he debauched his imagination, and reflecting on the sensations to
                which fancy gave force, he traced them in the most glowing colours, and sunk them
                deep into his soul. He then sought for solitude, not sleep with the man of nature;
                or calmly investigate the causes of things under the shade where Sir Isaac Newton
                indulged contemplation, but merely to indulge his feelings. (91)</p>
            <p>In this famous passage, Wollstonecraft avoids chastising Rousseau for the warmth of
                his feelings and the liveliness of his fancy, but she criticizes the delicacy that
                leads to abstinence. The movement through self-denial to self-debauchery (via the
                imagination) and then to sleep later forms the template for P. B. Shelley’s
                “Alastor,” as it signifies the failure of egocentric, masculine desire. It does not,
                as some Wollstonecraft critics would have it, suggest that the virginal philosopher
                shies away from sexual desire itself.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"
                            ><p rend="endnote text"> See Cora Kaplan, “Wild Nights:
                            Pleasure/Sexuality/Feminism,” and Mary Poovey, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Proper Lady and the Woman Writer</hi>. For alternative versions of
                            Wollstonecraftian sexuality, see Orrin N. C. Wang’s chapter on
                            Wollstonecraft and Rousseauean masturbation in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Fantastic Modernity</hi>, and Chris Washington’s article on
                            Wollstonecraft and the Anthropocene, “The Last Sex on Earth,”
                            forthcoming from Romantic Circles <hi rend="italic">Pedagogy
                                Commons</hi>.</p></note></hi> Rather, she worries over Rousseau’s
                fantasies of desire, how the object of desire can become conflated with the <hi
                    rend="italic">objet petit a</hi>. Such object confusion creates within the
                imagination a fantasy of woman as other and, concomitantly, the desire to be a woman
                in order to become the hole at the heart of a knot that slips the noose of
                patriarchal law that nonetheless desires the evanishing, feminine object. This
                fantasy, most problematically, can only be enjoyed through the vigorous and frequent
                recapitulation of the proliferating fancy of the Oother as absent object lacking or
                failing to meet the strictures of the Oedipal order. </p>
            <p> As opposed to such debauched imagination, Maria, Darnford, and Jemima’s sequential
                autobiographical tales set out to identify the Ssymbolic and the castrating sign of
                the oppressive father, as they respectively tell of imprisonment in marriage,
                militarism, and prostitution. These stories, though they offer critiques of the
                patriarchal order, when they retell the woes of phallic law may perversely reinforce
                the more hetero-norm-core desires when they retell the woes of phallic law, and they
                subsequently cause Maria and Darnforth to have unprotected prison sex and to veer
                into a potentially reproductive marriage plot. The consummation of phallic desire
                diverts Maria away from the jouissance found in the marginalia’s shared posthuman
                affect, —that textual assemblage of vibrant matter, —and locates her back in the
                phallic Iimaginary of protection and property and inevitably leads to a capitulation
                to phallic institutions. This plot, which replaces the possibility of non-phallic
                jouissance with real, hetero-sex, is the inverse of the sequence within
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters Written during a Short Residence, </hi>where
                Wollstonecraft’s real sex and actual child with Gilbert Imlay are replaced by a
                posthuman textual jouissance. Here Wollstonecraft entangles herself and the image of
                Fanny with Scandanavian skies, forests, and waterways. Such enmeshment with the
                non-verbal environment offers the possibility, though not the eventuality, of
                subtending the symbolic order and entering the realm of the Real. In
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Maria </hi>we can see the reinstitution of
                phallic desire in Darnford’s release from the asylum after he re-establishes his
                phallic power in consummation and the freedom to desert Maria, not to mention his
                potential betrayal of her in some of the novel’s potential endings archived by
                Godwin. What we might see as the polymorphous desire of the marginalia and the
                triadic friendship between Darnford, Maria, and Jemima, becomes caged by the
                cultural and legal demands that, as David Sigler has argued, constitute desire
                through sexual difference and constrain sexual identity (8-10)<anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="212"/>.<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="212"/><hi
                    rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="212"
                            ><date when="2022-07-28T19:38:00Z"/><hi rend="background(yellow)">Can
                            you provide a page number for this paraphrase
                    reference?</hi></note></hi> While Maria, Darnford, and Jemima already constitute
                a perversion of the psychoanalytic triad (mother-father-child), they collapse into
                the dyadic fantasy of Maria and Darnford’s restitutional heteronormativity. Such
                control of enjoyment encourages perversion and cultivates archetypal fantasies of
                gendered others, as the dyad becomes installed into a romance plot that leaves much
                to be desired in the way of female independence. </p>
            <p>Even so, the text does not completely evanish the earlier polymorphousness of the
                triangulated marginalia, as if the text, once familiar with another form of
                jouissance, cannot help to proliferate itself. Maria and Darnford’s desire made real
                within their psychosis almost autonomously diffuses a dissipating Real that exudes
                the story’s impossible, multiplicitous, indeterminate endings. While most
                denoumentsdenouements assume the infant has died and Maria falls prey to the law of
                the father that condemns her by the literal patriarchal law in divorce proceedings,
                the return of the vision of her infant resurrects the hallucination of a jouissance
                outside the phallic Ssymbolic. At least one ending imagines that Jemima brings her
                back to Maria, and the three of them create a female homosocial space safe from
                either Venebles or Darnford. The idea that the babe might not be dead, or even might
                haunt the text and the family history it presents, offers an undead Ssymbolic of the
                future of a non-heir who might recreate the Ssymbolic altogether, however deranged
                our (and Maria’s) wish for her existence. </p>
            <p>The survival of the child amid the mad, bad, and dangerous asylum hysterics attests
                to Wollstoncraft’s early intimation that feminine delusion may be a necessary
                psychosis, one which wards off paralytic hysterics that would permanently imprison
                one inside the asylum’s institutional phallic order. Such a non-phallic
                imaginaryImaginary, it seems, can be created within the interstitial space of the
                asylum, but its existence, the possibility of its ontology, will always be labeled
                psychotic by the law of the father. Thus, if we were to take Wollstonecraft’s point
                of view, the Lacanian insistence in on the impossibility of non-phallic jouissance
                (and its impossible Ssymbolic) is itself another decrepit asylum built by
                acquiescence to the phallic law. This law of the father assumes that sanity adheres
                to the naturalization of a two-sex, gendered romance as much as the separation of
                human subjects and nonhuman objects. It is the immense creativity of language and
                being itself, which we shall see most fully
                in<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Letters</hi>, that has the capacity to
                imagine something other, something attached to all number of creative, porous
                processes themselves. The novel thus resists heteronormative closure in its desire
                for impossible futurities, in an excess of a speculative Ssymbolic, that surfeits
                the Real through Wollstonecraft’s literary imagination. </p>
            <p> Wollstonecraft more fully explores the freedom to play with delusions of feminine,
                or even nonbinary, jouissance in <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>. Autobiographically,
                we might think of these letters as a hiatus between Wollstonecraft’s two suicide
                attempts that struggle with the absence of her “real” personal object of desire (or
                Imlay’s repudiation of her as a desiring subject). In psychoanalytic terminology, we
                might say that she successfully substitutes various nonhuman or partial objects as
                an even greater epitome than Imlay or her self-representation of the <hi
                    rend="italic">objet petit a</hi>. Yet, while the actual letters sent to Imlay
                never arrive at their intended destination, their vagrancy eventually allows
                Wollstonecraft to rewrite them into a love letter to a jouissance freed from all of
                the following: a human object, the symbolic law of (Fanny’s) father, any singley
                object, or indeedand the notion of a discrete, self-enclosed object that would try
                to but fail to substitute for the lack at the heart of the phallus. Parted, however
                unintentionally, from her human desire and its biopolitical teleologies, the
                narrator lets her desires roam in, around, and through a series of landscapes and
                subjects that she cannot quite define. She successively meanders into more vibrant
                materials that occasionally flow one into another, whose creating an entanglement
                itself that momentarily obviates the lack and absence at the heart of psychoanalytic
                desire.</p>
            <p>
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters </hi>dialectically oscillates between
                sociological, ethnographic observations about Scandinavia and some intense mutual
                masturbation of Wollstonecraft and nature itself. This pleasure occurs most
                intensely when the speaker experiences jouissance with the landscape as she
                literally exchanges materiality with it. She describes this phenomenon through
                language that slips and slides through its substitutive signifiers. Having
                established her “desultory manner” quite soundly by the time she arrives in Norway,
                the speaker of the letters, particularly when describing nature’s materiality and
                the affects circulating within these scenes, rises to a lyrical lilt whose <hi
                    rend="italic">écriture</hi> creates something of a posthuman jouissance
                    (25)<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="251"/>.<anchor type="commentRangeEnd"
                    n="251"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment"
                        resp="#Copyeditor" n="251"><date when="2022-08-01T14:45:00Z"/><hi
                            rend="background(yellow)">Please include a page number for the quoted
                            material in this sentence.</hi></note></hi> Resounding a fairly keening
                pitch while looking down upon the ocean from a precipice outside Tønsberg, she
                writes, “With what ineffable pleasure have I not gazed—and gazed again, losing my
                breath through my eyes—my very soul diffused itself in the agitated waves, melted in
                the freshening breeze, or, taking its flight with fairy wing, to the misty mountains
                which bounded the prospect, fancy tript [sic] over new lawns . . .”
                (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters </hi>50). She follows this
                description, in the next paragraph, with the very quotable line, “I endeavoured to
                calm an impetuous tide—laboring to make my feelings take an orderly course.—It was
                striving against the stream” (50). This feminine gush may partake in the vibrations
                of sensibility so often wrought through metaphors of swiftly titlingtilting winds
                and waters. Yet, here, the description also registers that gush and pull of
                desire—the pleasures of gazing and losing breath, the diffusion and loss of the
                subject into others, a series of objects that are themselves already indiscrete. The
                agitated waves, <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="256"/>the freshening breeze, the
                fairy wing,<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="256"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"
                        ><note place="comment" resp="#Kate_Singer" n="256"><date
                            when="2022-09-19T20:36:00Z"/>Please keep the articles “the” in front of
                        each of these because that is how Wollstonecraft articulates them in the
                        text (rhythmically and deictically).</note></hi> misty mountains, and new
                lawns all bespeak a fluxing materiality, perhaps something closest, in
                psychoanalytic terms, to what Bracha Ettinger would call a part-object or
                part-subject. The intermingling of the human and nonhuman occurs in, or leads to,
                those maternal tides of labor and laboring, just as Wollstonecraft’s chiastic
                description of one in terms of the other—the tide as female ejaculation, the
                speaker’s body as literally melting into thin air. The laboring to make and unmake
                feelings, —those new materialist impersonal affects, that matter and energy that
                circulates through human and nonhuman, <anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="266"
                />entanglinges them both<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="266"/><hi
                    rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="266"
                            ><date when="2022-08-01T15:17:00Z"/><hi rend="background(yellow)">This
                            sentence is a bit unclear. Is “feelings” the subject that is doing the
                            entangling? And “human and nonhuman” are the direct objects that are
                            being entangled? I’ve edited the sentence based on this assumption.
                            Please advise if I have guessed wrong at the subject and
                        objects.</hi></note></hi> entangle speaker and land into something more than
                the feminized natural body of part-objects and part-subjects. </p>
            <p> As I’ve argued elsewhere, Wollstonecraft, like many other women writers of the
                Romantic period often uses this type of personification not to anthropomorphize
                nature, but to intertwine irretrievably human and nonhuman —on a material level, not
                just metaphorically.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p> “Surfing the
                            Crimson Wave: Romantic New Materialisms and Speculative </p><p
                            rend="endnote text">Feminisms.”</p></note></hi> At a later moment, in
                the forests of Tønsberg, Wollstonecraft takes the reverse tactic of personifying the
                trees: “Not nymphs, but philosophers, seemed to inhabit them—ever musing; I could
                scarcely conceive that they were without some conscious existence—without a calm
                enjoyment of the pleasure they diffused”
                (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters </hi>57). Sounding rather like F. W.
                Schelling writing of plant souls, the speaker poses trees as musing philosophers who
                spread their consciousness and musings through diffusion.<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"> See Michael
                            Marder’s <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Plant Thinking </hi>and
                            William Davis’s chapter on Schelling and the becoming of the world soul
                            in <hi rend="italic">Romanticism, Hellenism, and the Philosophy of
                                Nature</hi>.</p></note></hi> Though <hi rend="italic">to
                    diffuse</hi> could be material or immaterial, the word may hint at least, or
                anticipate two material meanings arising, according to the OED, at the start of the
                nineteenth century—to cause two substances to intermingle or and to spread one’s
                limbs out. Such a dispersal literally, physically extends pleasure mutually enjoyed
                through a posthuman jouissance. That is, a surplus of enjoyment transpires in the
                diffusion of human and nonhuman, through intertwined play of materialities and é<hi
                    rend="italic">criture</hi>. </p>
            <p>While such apostrophes begin in anthropomorphic play, they end in something much more
                mutual and entangled, as language enables pleasure to pass over (or through) the
                (Oedipal) Ssymbolic and <hi rend="italic">objet petit a</hi>, or the speaker’s
                desire to be amused by the phallic philosopher. Instead, we end in a nebulous
                pleasure jointly enjoyed through the intermingling of language and materiality,
                human and nonhuman pondering. As Zupančič writes, “language cannot be neatly
                separated from the Real,” just as jouissance blurs the lines between animal and
                human: “enjoyment is what disturbs this animal, wakes it up to a different reality,
                wakes it up to metaphysics (or politics), makes it do all kinds of strange ‘human’
                or inhuman things” (69, 90). In these passages in <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>,
                Wollstonecraft balances between, on the one hand, extreme the extreme disruption
                caused by unbridgeable difference and, on the other, a drastic merging or
                assimilation into identity. We might turn to Michael Marder’s notion of “vegetal
                democracy,” a common soul that adheres to “the principles of inherent divisibility
                and participation” in plant life “which traverses all other modes of living while
                preserving their differences,” constituted by a “giving itself without reserve to
                everyone and everything that lives” (51, 52).</p>
            <p> In this moment of seeming Romantic intersubjectivity, what begins as the
                synthesthesiasynesthesia of losing breath or air through the eyes, or receiving the
                tree’s airy thoughts, becomes a blurring of subject and object, as Wollstonecraft’s
                soul diffuses into the waves, and, finally, her material deliquescence, her affect,
                becomes one with the tide. This vivacious tongue-lashing of Wollstonecraft’s—what
                she calls her “<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="291"/>ineffable pleasure<anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="291"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="291"><date when="2022-08-01T16:32:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Should this term be inside quotation
                            marks and cited with a page number?</hi></note></hi>”—is no mere
                sublimation of her panting desire for an absent Imlay, the name of the father, the
                He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named, who would identify her (feminine) sex and sexuality as
                subordinated to the phallic (50). Neither is such pleasure simply a form of feminine
                jouissance “beyond the phallus,” defined against the phallus, along the lines of
                Lacan’s intimations in <hi rend="italic">Seminar XX</hi>. Rather, this is
                Wollstonecraft at her most psychotic, who imagines her soul leaves her body and
                diffuses—materially, spiritually—into the scene—both the moving affect of breeze and
                waves as well as the scene’s own fluid Ssymbolic. </p>
            <p> Such psychosis, the ability to talk with the elements, to be them, speaks to a
                broader trajectory of feminine writing that we can trace from <anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="296"/>Charlotte Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Elegiac
                    Sonnets</hi><anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="296"/><hi
                    rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="296"
                            ><date when="2022-08-01T16:40:00Z"/><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please
                            add this source to the Works Cited.</hi></note></hi>, where the lunatic
                in sonnet LXX “lies / Murmuring responses to the dashing surf” (8), through <anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="298"/>Shelley’s <hi rend="italic">“Witch of
                    Atlas</hi><anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="298"/><hi
                    rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="298"
                            ><date when="2022-08-01T16:41:00Z"/><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please
                            add this source to the Works Cited.</hi></note></hi>,” whose mother, in
                her own alien jouissance, “was changed into a vapour / And then into a cloud,” and
                finally into a star (65-–66). These works neither naturalize women’s coincidental
                intimacy with nature nor reveal a the hole that is women’s relation with nature,
                which the psychotic world of delusional fantasy will come to fulfill (Lacan, <hi
                    rend="italic">Seminar III</hi> 45). From a Lacanian perspective, we might say
                that the Wollstonecraftian subject recognizes herself as not a symptom of man, or a
                compensatory, sentimental other, but rather as no subject at all, a lack that nature
                attempts to recover. In order to swerve from mistakes like Maria’s with Darnford
                (and Wollstonecraft’s catastrophic disaster with Imlay), the speaker of the
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters </hi>turns from any realization of
                her sex as a subject pregnant with the desire to recognize a father and procreate.
                Combatting the inhumanity of the always already binaristic Iimaginary, she becomes
                partially nonhuman, or something other than human altogether. Her entanglement with
                nature speaks to another ontology entirely—the ability to shift her shape and being
                from one always in relation to the phallus, always liable to or resisting its
                penetrating ways, to something vaporous and labile, already intermingled with a
                being alien to sexed desire or gendered lacking.</p>
            <p> Such an inkling of the dynamically material nonhuman is already present in Irigaray
                and Cixous. In <hi rend="italic">Speculum</hi>, Irigaray is, perhaps hyperbolically,
                skeptical of women’s ability to evince a psychosis that would produce a Ssymbolic
                outside the paternalistic order. Hysteria, she says, women’s cough and catarrh, her
                bodily symptoms of repression of herself as a symptom, is all women have left.
                However unable women supposedly are to arouse their signifiers and get it up to
                enunciate the Ssymbolic, Irigarary eventually masturbates her way out of the
                Iimaginary using a fluid materiality where women lack sexual self-identification and
                really lack everything but the slip and slide of their being. In the chapter on
                “Volume-Fluidity,” she writes: “Lips of the same form—but of a form that is never
                simply defined—ripple outwards as they touch and send one another on a course that
                is never fixed into a single configuration. This will already have taken place
                without the consent or assent of any object, or subject. This is an other
                topo-(logy) of jouissance”
                (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Speculum </hi>230). Not only is the woman
                not one, due to her two lips constantly touching themselves, not only does she break
                the double-specularization of woman and mother, not only does she never close up
                into a volume (233, 239), but she excretes and flows into multiple forms of matter
                (233, 239. ): “Blood, but also milk, sperm, lymph, saliva, spit, tears, humors, gas,
                waves, airs, fire  .  .  .  light” (237). This excrescence not only overwhelms a
                woman’s sexual identity as a reproductive vessel, not only threatens to deform the
                man with his tumescent phallus, not only undoes subject boundaries, it surely remits
                a dynamic flow of matter. Rather than a Medusan castration into stone that can never
                kiss or reach jouissance, Irigaray’s airs, like Wollstonecraft’s, anticipate a
                posthuman new materiality that flows, differentially, through many kinds of
                matter.</p>
            <p> Irigaray, Lacan’s student, is surely working from his challenge to get beyond the
                phallic jouissance, yet her series of fluids intimates how matter might overflow the
                boundaries of the phallus so as to negate them as an originary reference point.
                Moreover, her linguistic play, like Wollstonecraft’s sentences in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Letters</hi>, which continue without the dialectical or cyclical structure of
                her periods in <hi rend="italic">The Vindication</hi>, suggests not so much an
                object-oriented list of things but rather a series of already intermixing and
                flexible forms of matter. By the time Irigaray reaches her “light,” it no longer has
                reference to darkness or castration, but is instead is the epitome of matter as
                energy that pervades all things. Here, we can bring Irigaray, and Wollstonecraft
                with her, full circle to Schelling’s definition of light in his nature philosophy. </p>
            <p> Wollstonecraft’s passages might likewise bring to mind Julia Kristeva’s notion of
                abjection, as another post-Lacanian attempt to explain the double intertwinement and
                repudiation of the other. As Kristeva writes in <hi rend="italic">Powers of
                    Horror</hi>: “‘subject’ and ‘object’ push each other away, confront each other,
                collapse, and start again—inseparable, contaminated, condemned, at the boundary of
                what is assimilable, thinkable: abject” (18). Wollstonecraft’s use of the nonhuman
                in<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Letters</hi>, however, trespasses on the
                mother-child symbiosis, and the dark, loathesomeloathsome feminine that must be
                sloughed off. Bracha Ettinger’s post-Lacanian-Kristevan-Kleinian analysis of the
                matrixial border space, where part-objects, are once created, mingle, and are
                re-created, offers yet another post-Lacanian attempt to move past the phallic
                Iimaginary. While Ettinger’s theories anticipate new materialism’s iteratively,
                co-produced materialities, such part-objects still reference the late intrauterine
                encounters that serve as a foundational, human referent for “the shareable
                dimensions of subjectivity” and a “multidimensional change and exchange on the
                borderlines of [human] perceptibility” (Ettinger <anchor type="commentRangeStart"
                    n="352"/><anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="353"/>64.5<anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="352"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="352"><date when="2022-08-01T17:29:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please check this page number against
                            the original.</hi></note></hi><anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="353"
                    /><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Kate_Singer"
                        n="353"><date when="2022-09-19T20:40:00Z"/>She numbers her pages
                        unconventionally; this is correct.</note></hi>). Zupančič’s consideration of
                the inanimate world (and of object- oriented ontology) similarly attempts to show
                how Lacanian jouissance’s intersection at the abyss of the Real and the lack within
                the signifier might entwine human and nonhuman. She claims that life “is an
                interruption, a disturbance of the inanimate, a gap appearing in it” much as the
                sexual is the “ ‘crack’ shared (and repeated) by different drives,” jouissance being
                the “‘glue’” that binds “the original negativity (call it primal repression,
                one-less, minus, rift, or crack” to various signifiers and the Real, “where a ‘new
                signifier’ could eventually intervene” in the phallic order (Zupančič 97, 116,
                117).</p>
            <p> Wollstonecraft’s descriptions of nature in her
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters </hi>and its ineffable pleasure even
                more thoroughly attempts to leave the phallic behind. Her model leverages a
                synesthetic admixture of materialities (breath, waves, light) whose elemental nature
                moves underneath the human or maternal body to augur a pervasive, shape-shifting
                changeability. Perhaps her biggest intervention is the way that different
                materialities, which have no static or fixed shape, succeed, suffuse, and alter one
                another. The imbrication of human with nonhuman undoes either sexual dimorphism or
                the gender binary that shapes the phallic order in the first place. </p>
            <p> It is no coincidence that Wollstonecraft follows this jouissance with a declaration
                that she will no longer strive against the stream. As one metaphor touches, and
                flows into, another, the human and nonhuman materials slide with, against, and
                through each other in a material unconscious, but one evoked through symbolic play
                that bypasses any sedimented Iimaginary. Air, light, waves, affects, tides, streams
                combine with some “humid eyes,” heavy breathing (“I pause, again, breathless”), and
                “vivacity of youth” to boot (50)<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="364"/>.<anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="364"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="364"><date when="2022-08-01T17:38:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please include page numbers for the
                            quoted material in this sentence.</hi></note></hi> Wollstonecraft’s
                symptoms may be directed toward her own body, yet they suggest how subjectivity
                might give way to Bennett’s human-nonhuman assemblage, joined by shared affect,
                those material movements among and between bodies. While Bennett does not give much
                idea as to how one material might recombine with another, Karen Barad’s new
                materialism theorizes that phenomena (objects or subjects) do not exist as such
                until shaped<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="367"/>created <anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="367"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="367"><date when="2022-08-01T17:44:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Consider different word choice to avoid
                            the repetition (created through apparatuses that create). Produced?
                            Initiated? Established? Developed?</hi></note></hi>or “cut” through
                apparatuses that create, and re-create, them into various materialities. For Barad,
                even “the ‘past’ and the ‘future’ are iteratively reworked and enfolded through the
                iterative practices of spacetimemattering” (Barad 315). In this account, time,
                space, and matter are all iteratively recreated through<anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="371"/> intractionsinteractions of matter that is not
                already ontologically defined. While Barad terms these
                    intractionsinteractions<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="371"/><hi
                    rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Kate_Singer" n="371"
                            ><date when="2022-09-20T15:08:00Z"/>Please use intra-actions as this is
                        the Baradian term.</note></hi> “cuts,” where matter can be cut apart and
                together, Wollstonecraft’s liquid suffusions seem to bypass such a phallic
                methodology of change based on disruption, cracks and holes, or cuts—severing one
                from another. Not necessarily based on gradualism, she augurs a change endemic to a
                shifting, excessive jouissance, an openness to mixing materialities. </p>
            <p> Wollstonecraft is quick to guard against readers supposing—and desiring to
                suppose—that she is speaking entirely of sex itself—of two bodies involved in the
                sensual instant gratification she is so quick to resist in <hi rend="italic">The
                    Vindication</hi>. A few sentences later she directly addresses the reader: </p>
            <p>“My bosom still glows, —Do not saucily ask, repeating Sterne’s question, ‘Maria, is
                it still so warm?’ Sufficiently, O my God! has it been chilled by sorrow and
                unkindness—still nature will prevail—and if I blush at recollecting past enjoyment,
                it is the rosy hue of pleasure heightened by modesty; for the blush of modesty and
                shame are as distinct as the emotions by which they are produced.”
                (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters </hi>50). </p>
            <p>In repudiating the Sternian innuendo about her breast being “still warm” and
                tumescent with the friction of love making, she entreats a modesty that invokes the
                “rosy hue” of jouissance—an excess of pleasure that is not necessarily tied to sexed
                bodies but extends into the nonhuman air-sun-sea assemblage of dawn. This figure, of
                course, alludes to her earlier, now -famous, passage describing the “rosy tint of
                morning” that involutes Fanny Blood, Fanny Imlay, and the dawn, not to mention the
                “Blood, but also milk, sperm, lymph, saliva, spit, tears, humors, gas, waves, airs,
                fire  .  .  .  light” that circulates among them. : </p>
            <p>The grave has closed over a dear friend, the friend of my youth; still she is present
                with me, and I hear her soft voice warbling as I stray over the heath. Fate has
                separated me from another, the fire of whose eyes, tempered by infantine tenderness,
                still warms my breast; even when gazing on these tremendous cliffs, sublime emotions
                absorb my soul. And, smile not, if I add, that the rosy tint of morning reminds me
                of a suffusion, which will never more charm my senses, unless it reappears on the
                cheeks of my child. (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters </hi>39)</p>
            <p>Although we might be tempted to view such a provocative scene as the first of several
                reverberations of same-sex desire (or a feminine gaze) in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Letters</hi>, as Debra Weiss has, we can understand the multiple substitutions
                in the passage (Fanny Blood for Imlay; Fanny Imlay for Fanny Blood; the rosy hue for
                all of them) to be not about the repeated substitution of a feminine for a phallic
                sexuality but rather a material movement from the “transient sensations” to the
                posthuman “warbling” of Fanny Blood as a bir<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="402"
                    />d<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="402"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="402"><date when="2022-08-01T18:02:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please provide a page number for
                            “transient sensations.”</hi></note></hi>, through the “fire,” “warmth,”
                and “rosy tints” of a posthuman materiality that circulates through all as a mutual
                “suffusion.” (39).</p>
            <p> Repeatedly, Wollstonecraft’s emotions drive her to talk of death (or immortality),
                which further inclines her to figure a release into a dynamic, suffusing state of
                nature. The death drive and sex/life drive intertwine and propel her into a
                jouissance where the delusion of unifying with the pulsing waves or winds bespeaks
                no <hi rend="italic">petite mort</hi> of phallic jouissance but a winged freedom of
                movement untethered to any particular body, or any body as a discrete, enclosed
                system of materialities. After tromping through a burned forest in Norway, she
                writes, “I cannot tell why-but death, under every form, appears to me like something
                getting free—to expand in I know not what element; nay I feel that this conscious
                being must be as unfettered, have the wings of thought, before it can be happy”
                (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters </hi>88-–89). Lest we assume that
                these “wings of thought” are a stock metaphor, here the speaker imagines herself,
                through the ungirding of jouissance, becoming another being combined with
                undisclosed elements and evidenced by nonhuman wings. Like Fanny’s own “warbling,”
                the narrator’s “wings” re-create her as epistemologically free, but more directly,
                perhaps as part human-part bird, as ontologically altered. </p>
            <p>After this moment, she rushes onto the cascade, and, as she notes, the “impetuous
                dashing of the rebounding torrent from the dark cavities which mocked the exploring
                eye, produced an equal activity in my mind”
                (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters </hi>89). Such epistemological
                shifts, anticipating and sourcing “Mont Blanc,” at first attest to an analogy
                between the everlasting flows of nature and mind. Yet, such a seeming parallel track
                between nature and mind soon intermingles body and nature: “it seemed as impossible
                to stop the current of my thoughts, as of the always varying, still the same,
                torrent before me—I stretched my hand out to eternity, bounding over the dark speck
                of life to come” (89). Once again, the entanglement of human and nonhuman moves
                through the jouissance of both that means death to the phallic human into a “life to
                come,” a being on the make. For all Godwin’s posthumous casting of Wollstonecraft
                after her death as an overwrought woman of sensibility, “a female Werther,” he might
                have gotten it right when he describes her as “a serpent upon a rock, that casts its
                slough, and appears again with the brilliance, the sleekness, and the elastic
                activity of its happiest age” (<hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> 88). Underlying such
                emotions, sorrow or happiness, is the serpentine sloughing off and turning of an
                elastic new materiality. Her speck of new life comes not through her sexed
                autobiography, even with Godwin, but within the material life of her <hi
                    rend="italic">être écrivain</hi>.</p>
            <p> For Cixous and Clément as well, nonbinary being and gender come together. She They
                writes that the hysteric “goes in the direction of animality, plants, the inhuman 
                . . . … [and] embodies somewhere an incompatible synthesis—bisexuality” (Cixous 8).
                Wollstonecraft’s delusion, wrought as it is at once through the Ssymbolic and the
                Real, certainly goes in the direction of the nonhuman; but rather than bisexuality
                or Romantic androgyny, I’d characterize her jouissance with nature as a discovery of
                a nonbinary sexuality. Nature is not the ever-loving Big Other tied to an Old
                Testament God or his New Son,. Nor nor does it substitute for the <hi rend="italic"
                    >objet petit a</hi> of Imlay’s spurned attention <anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="436"/>and,or <anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="436"
                    /><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note place="comment" resp="#Kate_Singer"
                        n="436"><date when="2022-09-19T20:43:00Z"/></note></hi>Wollstonecraft’s
                denial of her sexuality or its sloughed revivification with Godwin. Rather, she
                finds a jouissance in an alternative Real that shatters the specularization of the
                Iimaginary through the sinuous and changing shapes of her description. When her
                breath moves through her eyes, she replaces specularity or Enlightenment vision with
                the haptics of breath, air, waves—movement that entails suffusion, and diffusion.
                She breaks a potentially sexualized Iimaginary and the binaristic, dimorphic logic
                that might constitute the <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters </hi>as her
                last desperate pleas to Imlay in order to reconstitute herself as a nonbinary being
                with a posthuman sex and sexuality that subverts human heterosexuality.</p>
            <p> There are other passages that do similar laboring, all of which occur during
                Wollstonecraft’s meditations on nature. Preparing to depart for Gothenberg, the
                speaker meditates on a summer’s evening, wondering “what . . .  … is this active
                principle which keeps me awake?”
                (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters </hi>11). Watching her child sleep
                and thinking of home, Wollstonecraft shifts into the register of natural science: “I
                have then considered myself as a particle broken off from the grand mass of mankind;
                —I was alone, till some involuntary sympathetic emotion, like the attraction of
                adhesion, made me feel that I was still part of a mighty whole, from which I could
                not sever myself” (12). This talk of energy, animation, and matter continues during
                Wollstonecraft’s passage critiquing embalmment in Norway as “worse than natural
                decay”: “‘Ashes to ashes!’ thought I—‘Dust to dust!’” (48). This contemplation
                wanders to a theory of new materialist reincarnation, where matter becomes other
                forms of matter, and embalmment is denigrated as preserving a form (and in ways that
                anticipate the necessity of material decay into the elemental within Shelley’s
                “Ozymandias”): </p>
            <p>Life, what art thou? Where goes this breath? This <hi rend="italic">I</hi>, so much
                alive? In what element will it mix, giving or receiving fresh energy?—What will
                break the enchantment of animation—For worlds, I would not see a form I
                loved—embalmed in my heart—thus sacrilegiously handled!—Pugh! My stomach turns.—Is
                this all the distinction of the rich in the grave?—They had better quietly allow the
                scythe of equality to mow them down with the common mass, than struggle to become a
                monument of the instability of human greatness. (48)</p>
            <p>Here, death could be seen be a form of symbolic castration that levels supposedly
                natural hierarchies. It more radically, however, suggests a fluid continuity between
                forms, like those of the two-sex model or the human itself, which seem as monuments
                but, in fact, reveal a vital instability. The speaker’s breath once again mixes with
                some new “element” in a reciprocal “giving or receiving” that revivifies with “fresh
                energy.” Wollstonecraft celebrates material forms as that blend with other elements,
                in a shape-shifting, matter that produces new being. This new exclamatory
                jouissance, formed as it is through a question about elemental interactions,
                suggests a polymorphous intermixture of multiple potential materialities, whose act
                of entanglement would produce something new and already instable. This jouissance
                gestates new ontologies outside the binaristic, phallic order (through neither
                masculine heat nor agential force) but by way of the nebulously elemental
                recomposing. This method constitutes the Shelleyan magic of reanimation, the
                creation of new life through posthuman, not human, means, through a jouissance whose
                linguistic structure and bodily form have decomposed into the potentiality of
                unbeholden matter. </p>
            <p> Such psychosis, I want to argue, constitutes a kind of new materialist witchcraft.
                New materialism is the delusion of magic then and now that has a far more trenchant
                past and future than Victor Frankenstein’s obsession with Cornelius Agrippa. The new
                materialist swerve toward Deleuzean immanence has been frequently chastised for its
                new agey, non-dialectical religiosity by Marxists such as Christopher Nealon.<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"> Christopher
                            Nealon, “Infinity for Marxists.” See also Julia Kristeva on the mystical
                            abject in <hi rend="italic">Powers of Horror</hi>.</p></note></hi> Yet,
                we might understand such delusions of grandeur as necessary psychotic delusions in
                the age of the Anthropocene. These symbolic, topological conjurations do not simply
                disrupt the Ssymbolic with the Real, or intertwine Iimaginary, Ssymbolic, and Rreal.
                As Lacan writes of the sinthome, “language eats into the real”
                (<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Seminar XXIII </hi>21). Delusion is a
                provocative thing because it is not an illusion but an epistemological error that
                allows Wollstonecraft to exit her Iimaginary, however temporarily, and enter the
                alternative Real. The Real here is an omnipresence of the universal without excising
                difference, and whichthat is, nonetheless, reachable through the delusion of
                transcorporeal materiality. This is the power of positive, delusional thinking, the
                transformation of the feminist Lacanian psychoanalyst into the Irigaray of <hi
                    rend="italic">Speculum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Vegetal Being</hi>, the shape-
                shifting of the Wollstonecraft so antagonistic to luxurious sensibility into the
                Wollstonecraft of airy, blushing suffusion and posthuman jouissance in <hi
                    rend="italic">Letters</hi>. Wollstonecraft’s jouissance is, differently, the
                coming that is present and future in the eternal orgasm of being, which exists
                within the continual material motion of coming itself. Posthumanism, like new
                materiality, then may be the delusion of ultimate nonbinary human-nonhuman
                relations, the eternal, consensual, mutual orgasm that keeps changing, in
                revolutionary ways, body and being.</p>
            <p>Works Cited</p>
            <p>Bennett, Jane.
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Vibrant Matter: A Political Ecology of Things. </hi>Duke
                UP, 2010.</p>
            <p>Barad, Karen. <hi rend="italic">Meeting the Universe Halfway: Quantum Physics and the
                    Entanglement of Matter and Meaning</hi>. Duke UP, 2007.</p>
            <p>Bennett, Jane.
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Vibrant Matter: A Political Ecology of Things. </hi>Duke
                UP, 2010.</p>
            <p><anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="478"/>Brennan, Teresa.<anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="478"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="478"><date when="2022-08-07T13:03:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please add a full citation for this
                            source.</hi></note></hi><hi rend="italic">The Transmission of
                    Affect</hi>. Cornell UP, 2004.</p>
            <p>Carman, Colin. <hi rend="italic">The Radical Ecology of the Shelleys: Eros and
                    Environment</hi>. New York: Routledge, 2018.</p>
            <p>Chen, Mel Y. <hi rend="italic">Animacies: Biopolitics, Racial Mattering, and Queer
                    Affect</hi>. Duke UP, 2012. </p>
            <p>Cixous, Hélène, and Catherine Clément. <hi rend="italic">The Newly Born Woman</hi>.
                Translated by Betsy Wing. U of Minnesota P, 1986.</p>
            <p>Colebrook, Claire. “We Have Always Been Post-Anthropocene: The Anthropocene
                Counterfactual.” In <hi rend="italic">Anthropocene Feminism</hi>, edited by Richard
                Grusin,. U of Minnesota P, 2017, pp. 1-–20.</p>
            <p>Davis, William S. <hi rend="italic">Romanticism, Hellenism, and the Philosophy of
                    Nature</hi>. Palgrave, 2018.</p>
            <p>Ettinger, Bracha. <hi rend="italic">The Matrixial Borderspace</hi>., Eedited by Brian
                Massumi. U of Minnesota P, 2006.</p>
            <p>Favret, Mary. <hi rend="italic">War at a Distance: Romanticism and the Making of
                    Modern Wartime</hi>. Princeton UP, 2009.</p>
            <p>Francois, Anne-Lise. “Fire, Water, Moon: Supplemental Seasons in a Time without
                Season.” Lecture at Columbia University, Sept. 26, 2017.</p>
            <p>———. “‘In the cowslips peeps I lye’: Rousseau, Clare, Climate Change and Telling the
                Time of Day.” Lecture at Brown University, Mar. 21, 2016.</p>
            <p>Godwin, William.
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Memoirs of the Author of </hi>A Vindication
                of the Rights of Woman., edited Edited by Pamela Clemit and Gina Luria Walker,.
                Broadview, 2001.</p>
            <p>Goldsmith, Steven. “Of Gender, Plague, and Apocalypse: Mary Shelley’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Last Man</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">The Yale Journal of
                    Criticism</hi>, vol. 4, no. 1, 1990, pp. 129-73. </p>
            <p>Gottlieb, Evan. “Jouissance, Obscene Undersides, and Utopian/Dystopian Formations in
                Sarah Scott’s <hi rend="italic">Millenium Hall </hi>and Mary Shelley’s <hi
                    rend="italic">The Last Man</hi>.” In <hi rend="italic">Lacan and
                    Romanticism</hi>, edited by Daniela Garofalo and David Sigler. SUNY Press, 2019,
                pp. 157-76.</p>
            <p>Irigaray, Luce. <hi rend="italic">Speculum of the Other Woman</hi>. Translated by
                Gillian C. Gill. Cornell UP, 1985.</p>
            <p>Irigaray, Luce, and Michael Marder. <hi rend="italic">Through Vegetal Being: Through
                    Two Philosophical Perspectives</hi>. Columbia UP, 2016.</p>
            <p>Kaplan, Cora. “Wild Nights: Pleasure/Sexuality/Feminism.” In <hi rend="italic">Sea
                    Changes: Essays on Culture and Feminism</hi>. , Verso, 1986, pp. 34-–50.</p>
            <p>Kristeva, Julia. <hi rend="italic">Powers of Horror: An Essay on Abjection</hi>.
                Translated by Leon S Roudiez,. Columbia UP, 1982.</p>
            <p>Lacan, Jacques. <hi rend="italic">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book III: The
                    Psychoses</hi>., Eedited by Jacques-Alain Miller,. Translated translated by
                Russell Grigg. Norton, 1997.</p>
            <p rend="endnote text">———.
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book </hi><anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="545"/><hi rend="italic">VII:</hi><anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="545"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="545"><date when="2022-08-07T15:08:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please add full citation for this
                            source.</hi></note></hi><hi rend="italic">The Ethics of Psychoanalysis,
                    1959-1960.</hi> Edited by Jacques-Alain Miller, translated by Dennis Porter.
                Norton, 1997.</p>
            <p>-----. ———. <hi rend="italic">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book XX: On Feminine
                    Sexuality, The Limits of Love and Knowledge. Encore Psychoses</hi>., edited
                Edited by Jacques-Alain Miller,. Translated translated by Bruce Fink,. Norton,
                1998.</p>
            <p>-----. ———. <hi rend="italic">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book XXIII: The
                    Sinthome</hi>., Eedited by Jacques-Alain Miller<hi rend="italic">.</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">,</hi> tTranslated by A. R. Price. , Polity Press, 2016.</p>
            <p>Marder, Michael. <hi rend="italic">Plant-Thinking: A Philosophy of Vegetal Life</hi>.
                Columbia UP, 2013.</p>
            <p>Mbembe, Achille. <hi rend="italic">Necropolitics</hi>. Translated by Steven Corcoran.
                , Duke UP, 2019.</p>
            <p>Mentz, Steve. “Philogiston.” <hi rend="italic">Elemental Ecocriticism: Thinking with
                    Earth, Air, Water, and Fire</hi>, edited by Jeffrey Jerome Cohen and Lowell
                Duckert,. U of Minneapolis P, 2015, pp. 55-–76.</p>
            <p>Nealon, Christopher. “Infinity for Marxists.” <hi rend="italic">Mediations: Journal
                    of the Marxist Literary Group</hi>, vol. 28, no. 2, 2015, pp. 47–63..
                http://www.mediationsjournal.org/articles/infinity-for-marxists. Accessed 2 Jan
                2020.</p>
            <p>Poovey, Mary. <hi rend="italic">The Proper Lady and the Woman Writer</hi>. U of
                Chicago P, 1984.</p>
            <p>Sharpe, Christina. <hi rend="italic">In the Wake: On Blackness and Being</hi>. Duke
                UP, 2016.</p>
            <p>Shelley, Mary. <hi rend="italic">The Last Man</hi>, edited by Morton D. Paley. Oxford
                UP, 1994.Shelley, Percy Bysshe.
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Witch of </hi><anchor
                    type="commentRangeStart" n="584"
                /><hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Atlas, </hi>in <hi rend="italic">Shelley’s
                    Poetry and Prose</hi>, edited by Donald Reiman and Neil Fraistat. Norton,
                    2002..<anchor type="commentRangeEnd" n="584"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"
                        ><note place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="584"><date
                            when="2022-08-07T13:08:00Z"/><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please add a
                            full citation for this source.</hi></note></hi></p>
            <p>Sigler, David. <hi rend="italic">Sexual Enjoyment in British Romanticism: Gender and
                    Psychoanalysis 1753-–1835</hi>. McGill-Queen’s UP, 2015.</p>
            <p>Singer, Kate. “Surfing the Crimson Wave: Romantic New Materialisms and Speculative
                Feminisms.” In <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and Speculative Realism</hi>, edited by
                Chris Washington and Anne C. McCarthy. , Bloomsbury, 2019, pp. 111–32.</p>
            <p><anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="602"/>Smith, Charlotte.<anchor
                    type="commentRangeEnd" n="602"/><hi rend="annotation_reference"><note
                        place="comment" resp="#Copyeditor" n="602"><date when="2022-08-07T13:09:00Z"
                            /><hi rend="background(yellow)">Please add a full citation for this
                            source.</hi></note></hi> “Sonnet LXX” in <hi rend="italic">The Poems of
                    Charlotte Smith</hi>, edited by Stuart Curran. Oxford UP, 1993.</p>
            <p>Smith, Orianne. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Women Writers, Revolution, and Prophecy:
                    Rebellious Daughters, 1786</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1826.</hi> Cambridge UP,
                2013. </p>
            <p>Snaza, Nathan. <hi rend="italic">Animate Literacies: Literature, Affect, and the
                    Politics of Humanism</hi>. Duke UP, 2019.</p>
            <p>Speitz, Michelle. “Affect and Air: The Speculative Spirit of the Age.” In <hi
                    rend="italic">Romanticism and Speculative Realism</hi>, edited by Chris
                Washington and Anne C. McCarthy. Bloomsbury, 2019, pp. 37–56.</p>
            <p>Wang, Orrin N. C. <hi rend="italic">Fantastic Modernity: Dialectical Readings in
                    Romanticism and Theory</hi>. Johns Hopkins UP, 1996.</p>
            <p>Washington, Chris. “The Last Sex on Earth.”
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Pedagogy Commons. </hi>Romantic Circles.
                Forthcoming.</p>
            <p>Washington, Chris, and Anne C. McCarthy, editors. <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and
                    Speculative Realism</hi>. Bloomsbury, 2019.</p>
            <p>Weiss, Deborah. “Suffering, Sentiment, and Civilization: Pain and Politics in Mary
                Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="italic">Short Residence</hi>.”
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Studies in Romanticism, </hi>vol. 45, no. 2,
                2006, pp. 199-–221.</p>
            <p>Wollstonecraft, Mary. <hi rend="italic">Letters Written during a Short Residence in
                    Sweden, Norway, and Denmark</hi>., Eedited by Tone Brekke and Jon Mee,. Oxford
                UP, 2009.</p>
            <p>---. ———. <hi rend="italic">Mary, A Fiction and The Wrongs of Woman, or Maria</hi>.,
                Eedited by Michelle Faubert. , Broadview, 2012.</p>
            <p>---. ———. <hi rend="italic">A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi>., Eedited by
                Deidre Shauna Lynch. , 3rd<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> ed., Norton, 2009.</p>
            <p>Zupančič, Alenka. <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">What Is Sex? </hi>MIT,
                2017.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
