<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce42</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.42</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                        c. 22.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters
                            of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        15–20; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 171–175 [in
                        part; as two separate letters dated 25 January and 12 February 1793,
                        respectively].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="42" type="letter">
<head>42. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1793-01-25">25 January –8
                        [February] 1793</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: G C Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/
                        Westminster<lb/>Stamped: OXFORD<lb/>Postmark: [partial] E/ 11/ 93<lb/>
                        Watermarks: Figure of rampant lion holding a scimitar, and another figure;
                        crown with a circle with Lloyd written underneath<lb/>Endorsement: 25
                            Janr<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1793<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                        c. 22<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New Letters
                            of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        15–20; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 171–175 [in
                        part; as two separate letters dated 25 January and 12 February 1793,
                        respectively].</note>
</head>
<p rend="indent1">
<date when="1793-01-25">Friday. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. &lt;1793&gt;</date>
<time>6 in the evening</time>. such is the hour when I begin this letter when it
                    will be finished — is uncertain. expecting <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> to drink tea with me every
                    moment I have not yet patience to wait without employment &amp; know of none
                    more agreeable than this of writing to you — my Mentor whilst he prohibits my
                    writing much nevertheless allows an exception in your favour &amp; believe
                    me I look upon it as one great proof of my own reformation or what ever title
                    you please to give when I can pass a whole week without composing one word. over
                    the pages of the philosophic Tacitus<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Publius Cornelius Tacitus (c. AD 56–c. AD 117), historian, whose works
                        include the <title level="m">Histories</title> and the <title level="m">Annals</title>.</note> the hours of study pass rapidly as even those
                    which are devoted to my friends &amp; I have not found as yet one hour which
                    I could wish to have employed otherwise this is saying very much in praise of a
                    collegiate life — but remember that a mind disposed to be happy will find
                    happiness everywhere &amp; why we should not be happy is beyond my
                    philosophy to account for — Heraclitus<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraclitus of Ephesus (535–475 BC). Allegedly of a melancholy disposition,
                        he was later known as ‘the weeping philosopher’.</note> certainly was a fool
                    &amp; what is much more rare an unhappy one. I never yet met with any fool
                    who was not pleasd with the idea of his own sense but for your whimpering sages
                    let sentiment say what it will they are more possessed with Envy than
                    Wisdom.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<date when="1793-02-02">Saturday. Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 2</date>. <time>five
                        in the morning</time> — now <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> this is more than
                    you would do for me — quit your bed after only five hours rest — light a fire
                    &amp; then write a letter — really I think it would not have tempted me to
                    rise unless assisted by these inducements. to-day I am going to walk to Abingdon
                    with three men of this college &amp; having made the pious resolution (your
                    good health in a glass of red negus) of rising every morning at five to study
                    that the rest of the day may be at my own disposal I procured an alarm clock
                    &amp; a tinder box. this morning was the first — I rose calld up a neighbour
                    &amp; read about three hundred lines of Ho[MS obscured] found myself hungry
                    — the bread &amp; cheese were calld in as auxiliaries &amp; I made some
                    neg[MS obscured] as I spiced it my eye glanced over the board &amp; the
                    assemblage seemed so curious that I laid all aside for your letter a Lexicon
                    Homer inkstand candles snuffers wine bread &amp; cheese nutmeg grater
                    &amp; hour glass. but I have given up time enough to my letter — the glass
                    runs fast &amp; for once the expression is not merely figurative.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<date when="1793-02-08">Friday 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
</date> how rapidly does
                    Time hasten on when his wings are not clogged by Melancholy — perhaps no human
                    being ever more forcibly experienced <hi rend="ital">this</hi> than myself —
                    often have I counted the hours with impatience when tired of Reflection
                    &amp; all her unpleasant train I wished to forget myself in sleep. now I
                    allow but six hours to my bed &amp; every morning before the watchman cries
                    past five my fire is kindled &amp; my bed cold — this is practical
                    philosophy — but every thing is valued by comparison &amp; when compared
                    with my neighbour I am no philosopher! Two years back <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Seward</ref> drank wine, eat butter
                    &amp; sugar, now merely from the resolution of abridging the luxuries of
                    life water is his only drink — tea &amp; dry bread his only breakfast. in
                    one who professed philosophy this would be only practising its tenets but it is
                    quite different with <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Seward</ref>. to the
                    most odd &amp; uncommon appearance he adds manners which as they grow
                    accustomed are the most pleasing. at the age of fourteen he began learning
                    &amp; the really useful knowledge which he possesses must be imputed to a
                    mind really desirous of improvement. do you not find your attention flag? said I
                    to him as he was studying Hutchinsons<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Hutcheson (1694–1746; <title level="m">DNB</title>), whose Latin
                        works included <title level="m">Philosophiae Moralis Institutio
                            Compendiaria, Ethices et Jurisprudentiae Naturalis Elementa
                            Continens</title> (1742).</note> moral philosophy in Latin — if our
                    tutor would but make our study interesting we should pursue them with pleasure.
                    certainly we should he replied but I feel a pleasure even in studying this
                    because I know it is my duty. this I take to be true philosophy of that species
                    which tends to make mankind happy because it first makes them good. we had
                    verses here upon the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>— to
                    the memory of Charles the martyr<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles
                        I (1600–1649; reigned 1625–1649) was executed on 30 January and subsequently
                        declared a saint by the Church of England.</note> &amp; it is a little
                    extraordinary that you should quote those very lines to poor Louis<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis XVI (1754–1793; reigned 1774–1792) was
                        executed on 21 January 1793.</note> which I prefixed to my ode. ‘his virtues
                    plead like angels trumpet tongued against the deep damnation<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title level="m">Macbeth</title>, Act 1, scene
                        7, lines 19–20.</note> of his taking off. the subject was as you must
                    suppose a very irksome one to me &amp; more than once was I ready to
                    apostrophize Milton — prudence however prevailed &amp; in pitying the man I
                    drew a viel over the faults of the monarch. with respect to the ill fated Louis
                    you cannot feel more repugnant to his death than I do but “non civium ardor
                    prava jubentium mente quatit solida?<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Horace (65–8 BC), <title level="m">Odes</title>, Book 3, no. 3. The Latin
                        translates as: ‘is not shaken from his firm resolve by hot-headed citizens
                        urging him to do wrong’.</note> to me it must matter little which way the
                    balance of power incline so my money &amp; life be not thrown into the
                    scales — last night the revenues of the clergy were the subject of debate. <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Seward</ref>
<ref target="people.html#LewisRichard">Lewis</ref> contending that 200 per annum
                    was sufficient for the superior ranks &amp; that they never ought to exceed
                    that or run lower than 100 — I supported &amp; we had the best of the
                    argument — perhaps it was not a little enforced by our being all three designed
                    for the church. were I not convinced of the inutility of repeating them you
                    should have our arguments — but upon this subject I flatter myself that our
                    opinions coincide. meekness humility &amp; temperance are the emblematic
                    virtues of Xtianity &amp; whatever may be my opinion upon speculative points
                    of faith there is to me no human character so truly enviable as that of a true
                    Xtian — morose austerity &amp; stern enthusiasm are the characteristics of
                    Superstition — but what is in reality more chearful or more happy than Religion
                    — I have in my own knowledge more than one instance of this &amp; doubt not
                    but you have likewise. ought not therefore that wretch who stiles himself a
                    philosopher to be shunned like pestilence who because Xtianity has to him no
                    allurements seeks to deprive the miserable of their only remaining consolation?
                    what I have written are my real sentiments yet <ref target="people.html#VincentWilliam">Dr V</ref> would call me an atheist
                    &amp; the Dean of Ch Ch proscribes me as a pest of society — if I had no
                    other cause of grief than this would occasion I verily believe that Oxford would
                    not contain a happier being than RS.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> the man who gaind the last English verse prize in Oxford has
                    since published two odes which he calls Songs of the Aboriginal Britains<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">George Richards (<hi rend="ital">c.</hi>
                        1767–1837; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Songs of the
                            Aboriginal Bards of Britain</title> (1792).</note> — of these the Review
                    speaks very well &amp; yet to me who as you know have written upon the same
                    plan these odes appear ill planned &amp; ill executed — some metaphors are
                    good but young <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref> observation
                    is just that he should have mistaken the odes for burlesque. if I could write BA
                    &amp; MA or DD after my name my odes would meet with commendation were I to
                    publish them unowned unpuffed &amp; unassisted they would go to the grocers
                    shops. poor Chatterton! <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas
                        Chatterton (1752–1770; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> often do I
                    think upon him &amp; sometimes indulge the idea that had he been living he
                    might perhaps have been my friend —</p>
<p rend="indent1"> the objection you start I think easily remedied — why not adapt
                    your metre (as Mason<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">William Mason
                        (1725–1797; <title level="m">DNB</title>), ‘Musaeus: a Monody to the Memory
                        of Mr Pope, in Imitation of Milton's Lycidas’ (1744).</note> has in Musæus)
                    to the bards you speak of? or supposing this scheme meets not your approbation
                    as it does not quite please me the ideas &amp; many of the verses may be
                    preserved in an irregular ode &amp; thus those lines which are weak may be
                    altered of the two best odes I have ever written this one contains about ten of
                    the original lines the other not one. I speak of Poetry &amp; Contemplation.
                    perhaps there is vanity in thus exemplifying myself but you will excuse me
                    &amp; a little vanity may be allowed to one who can boast of no other
                    recommendation than that of composition — yet <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> I would not
                    exchange my black tassel &amp; bombazeen gown with all it covers for the
                    handsomest gold &amp; silk ones in the University. alls for the best says
                        D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pangloss<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        sentiments of a character in Voltaire’s (1694–1778), <title level="m">Candide, ou l’Optimisme</title> (1759).</note> &amp; had my
                    situation in life been more elevated I had probably been proud &amp; vicious
                    — when Prudence very nearly allied to Necessity forbids from vice bad indeed
                    must be that man who can run counter to her dictates</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have written so rapidly that perhaps you will find some
                    difficulty in understanding me — but you know that when I am hurried on it is
                    not always I can attend to propriety of expression much less to kalography —
                    this word for instance is hot from the mint of my brain. do you not really think
                    that affluence &amp; prosperity are dangerous blessings? occupied by variety
                    of pleasure &amp; reclining upon the couch of happiness man is but too apt
                    to forget from whence those blessings flow. the enjoyments which his fortune
                    &amp; rank bestow he looks upon as his own — whilst the liberal minded Xtian
                    who plucks a dinner of herbs pours out his gratitude to that God who supplies
                    them. I know not whether Lucullus<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Lucius
                        Licinius Lucullus (c. 110–57 BC), Roman consul and famed gourmet.</note> was
                    a Stoic but surely Fabricius<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Gaius
                        Fabricius (d. c. 270 BC), Roman hero, famed for honesty and
                        incorruptibility.</note> &amp; Cincinnatus<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Lucius Quinctius Cincinnatus (C5 BC), a Roman hero who,
                        according to tradition, was appointed Dictator in 458 BC. He routed the
                        invading Aeqians and then renounced public life.</note> were religious. if I
                    continue in this stile you will fancy me about to turn devotee — for a being of
                    this class heaven never formed me — I can practise self denial for it is
                    attended with temporal advantages but the cup of martyrdom would prove too
                    bitter.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Charles Collins</ref> has been so busy
                    with his Lent verses that I see little of him — he is my monitor be you his — I
                    catch him frequently reading the Basia of Johannes Secundus<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Johannes Secundus (1511–1536), whose <title level="m">Liber Basiorum</title> (<title level="m">Book of
                            Kisses</title>) was published in 1541.</note> — he pleads the elegance
                    of the composition but that will not atone for the whole tenor of the work. he
                    laughs at my admonitions I however follow his &amp; am almost glad to behold
                    somethings of the fallability [MS obscured] nature in <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref>. it reconciles me more to
                    myself. he seems to fear lest the little sleep I take should hurt me. this
                    apprehension is very friendly — when I find myself the worse it is but again to
                    return to the habits of Luxury whilst I do not I must think six hours rest
                    enough for Nature &amp; a great deal to lose. you see I am grown an
                    oeconomist with regard to Time.</p>
<p rend="indent1">the sum you paid <ref target="people.html#BarnesFrederick">Ginger</ref> for me I
                    am unable to return at present. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> I blush whilst I
                    write but I ought to feel more unpleasantly could I hesitate to confess it. why
                    is there not some corner of the world where wealth is useless! or rather why was
                    not I like Emilius<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Book 3 of
                        Jean-Jacques Rousseau (1712–1778), <title level="m">Émile</title> (1762),
                        insisted that every male child should be taught a trade.</note> taught a
                    trade! is humanity so very vicious that society cannot exist without so many
                    artificial distinctions linked together as we are in the great chain why should
                    the extremity of that chain be neglected. at this moment I could form the most
                    delightful theory of an island peopled by men who should be Xtians not
                    Philosopher. where Vice only should be contemptible Virtue only honourable.
                    where all should be convenient without luxury all satified without profusion —
                    but at the moment when Imagination is almost wrought up to delirium the ticking
                    of the clock or the howling of the wind reminds me what I am &amp; I sigh to
                    part with so enchanting a delusion. if the Bounty mutineers<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The mutiny on the ship <title level="m">HMS
                            Bounty</title> in 1789.</note> had not behaved so cruelly to their
                    officers I should have been the last to condemn them — Otaheitii independant of
                    its women had many inducements not only for the sailor but the philosopher. he
                    might cultivate his own ground &amp; trust himself &amp; friends for his
                    defence — he might be truly happy in himself &amp; his happiness would be
                    increased by communicating it to others he might introduce the advantages
                    &amp; yet avoid the vices of cultivated society.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I am again getting into my dreams &amp; sober Reason has so
                    little to balance them that I can scarcely wake myself — where Ignorance is
                    Bliss tis folly to be wise<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Gray
                        (1716–1771; <title level="m">DNB</title>), ‘Ode on a Distant Prospect of
                        Eton College’ (1747), lines 99–100.</note> — we were once going to write a
                    paper upon this subject — alas poor Flagellant never am I alone but I always
                    recur to thee &amp; wish for such a vehicle for thought — the ardent
                    sensibility of youth is not suited to the cold blooded &amp; ungenerous
                    temper of mankind — theory &amp; boyish sentiments are the epithets given to
                    the ebullition of an open &amp; not naturally bad heart &amp; success
                    must only hoped for in the beaten tract of prudence &amp; dullness. I would
                    not at this moment give up the production of N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 5<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s authorship, in the fifth issue
                        of <title level="j">The Flagellant</title> (29 March 1792), of an essay
                        which claimed flogging was an invention of the devil and parodied the
                        Athanasian creed, caused a scandal and led ultimately to his expulsion from
                        Westminster School.</note> for the highest title Europe could bestow — the
                    gem has cost me dear &amp; I am proud to wear it.</p>
<p rend="indent1">I keep a daily journal for myself as an account of Time which I ought to be
                    strict in but this only destined for my own eye is uninteresting &amp;
                    unimportant. Boswell<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Boswell (1740–1795;
                            <title level="m">DNB</title>), biographer of Samuel Johnson (1709–1784;
                            <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> might compile a few quartos from
                    the loose memorandums but they would tire the world more than he has already
                    done. twenty years hence this journal will be either a source of pleasure or of
                    regret, that is if I live twenty years &amp; for life I have really a very
                    strong predilection. not from Shakesperes fearfully beautifull passage ay but to
                    die &amp; go we know not whither? <note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                        paraphrase of <title level="m">Measure for Measure</title>, Act 3, scene 1,
                        line 117.</note> but from the the hope that my life may be serviceable to my
                    family &amp; happy to myself — if it be the longer live the better —
                    existence will be delightful &amp; anticipation glorious. the idea of
                    meeting a different fate in another world is enough to overthrow every
                    atheistical doctrine. the very dreadful trials under which Virtue so often
                    labours must surely be only trials — Patience will withstand the pressure
                    &amp; Faith will lead to Hope — Religion soothe every sorrow &amp; make
                    the bed of Death a couch of felicity — make the contrast yourself — look at the
                    warrior the hypocrite &amp; the libertine in their last moments &amp;
                    reflection must strengthen every virtuous resolution — may I however practise
                    what I preach — let me have 200 a year &amp; the comforts of domestic life
                    &amp; my ambition aspires not farther.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent3">most sincerely yours</salute>
</closer>
<closer>
<signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
