<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce269</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.269</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>British Library, Add MS 30,927.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections From the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 46–47.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="269" type="letter">
<head>269. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey [brother]</ref>, <date when="1797-11-11">11 November 1797</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Thomas Southey/ H.M.S. Mars/ Plymouth/ Single<lb/>Stamped: BATH; PLYMOUTH; PLYMOUTH/ DOCK<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30,927<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title level="m">Selections From the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 46–47.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<date when="1797-11-11">11 November. 1797.</date>
<address>
<placeName>Bath</placeName>
</address>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Tom</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent2">		I have been some fortnight at Bristol, with <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref>, where the time passed with most pleasant speed. last night we returned. I heard complaints that you had not written to <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref>, &amp; saw your letter. twere needless to say with what satisfaction I read the account of your new situation.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos Cottles</ref> translation of the Edda is published, &amp; I have brought over a copy for you. you know it was my intention to write him some lines that might be prefixed, &amp; perhaps sell some half dozen copies among my friends. you will find them there.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s ‘To A. S. Cottle’ apeared in Amos Simon Cottle, <title level="m">Icelandic Poetry, or the Edda of Saemund Translated into English Verse</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp. xxxi–xlii.</note> the book itself will not interest you. it is only calculated for those who study mythology in general, the antiquities of the north, or who read to collect images for poetry. it happens to suit me in all these points.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	We go for London on Monday week. if you do not write sooner, <ref>my Mother</ref> will inform you my town direction as soon as I have one. Do you know that <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> has written a novel,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Lloyd, <title level="m">Edmund Oliver</title> (1798). Southey had previously used the same title for a planned novel of his own.</note> &amp; that it is going immediately to the press?</p>
<p rend="indent1">	I would I had ought to inform you of. that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> has found some person to take her house, she must have informed you. (<del rend="strikethrough">I have written to Thomas to come with all speed. &amp; John May has offered me money for her small debts. you also know that Margery is become tutoress at a school</del>) For myself — the most important personage in my drama of life — (in which drama, by the blessing of God I would have very few characters — this in a parenthesis) for myself — nothing has occurred to me worth pen ink &amp; paper to record it — save only that after having inured myself to all weathers without a great coat for five years — I have mustered one at last, &amp; now the old gentleman goes out in a bear skin wrapper to take care of himself. my new edition is in the press. <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The second edition of <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title>, published in 1798.</note> you will stare at the laborious alterations — perhaps <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, the business &amp; the uncertainty of life may prevent me from ever finishing Madoc,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title level="m">Madoc</title> was not published until 1805.</note> on which I would wish to build my reputation — &amp; so I would make the other as perfect as I can. my Letters<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A second edition of <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> appeared in 1799.</note> are all sold. more work! &amp; as the Arabian said — the work is long — the day is short.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is adapting ‘The tale of Beryn’, a fifteenth-century interpolation into <title level="m">The Canterbury Tales</title>, line 3631.</note> but we shall have prints to the new edition — in the best stile of aqua-tinta. this is settled.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The second edition of <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> was not illustrated.</note> you are on the seas — if at any time, the morning or evening appearance of the water strikes you as singularly beautiful — or strange — &amp; you should not dislike to register the appearance — do keep some little log book of this kind for me. tell me its tints at sun rise &amp; at sun set &amp;c &amp;c. but long habit has nauseated you of every thing belonging to the sea — &amp; it has now perhaps no beauties for your eyes.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	I have learnt to bind books. a great virtue — &amp; moreover it may be useful in those days when a man will be glad of an honest trade. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love — &amp; <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref>. &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> would send hers were she in the room.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	now God bless you — &amp; grant us no very distant meeting.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent4">					yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent5">						Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">My Mother</ref> is very much better than when you left us.</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
