<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce149</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.149</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>.  Previously  published: Adolfo
                        Cabral, Southey e Portugal (Lisbon, 1959), pp.
                        424–429 [in part]; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I,
                        pp. 267–271 [in part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="149" type="letter">
<head>149. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1796-02-24">24 February – 2
                        March 1796</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address:
                        For/ Grosvenor Charles Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/
                        Westminster<lb/>Stamped: PORTSMOUTH<lb/>Postmark: AMR/ 17/
                        96<lb/>Watermarks: Figure of Britannia; J LARKING<lb/>Seal: Red wax [design
                        illegible; trace of crest]<lb/>Endorsement: 24 Feb. to 2. March 1796<lb/>MS:
                        Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb/>Previously published: Adolfo
                        Cabral, <title level="m">Southey e Portugal</title> (Lisbon, 1959), pp.
                        424–429 [in part]; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I,
                        pp. 267–271 [in part].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<date when="1796-02-24">Wednesday. Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 24. 1796.</date> Lisbon from which God grant me a speedy
                        deliverance!</dateline>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> I am bitterly disappointed in not finding the Flagellant<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s first publication, the schoolboy
                        magazine <title level="j">The Flagellant</title> (1792).</note> here. of
                    which I sent my only copy to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">my
                        Uncle</ref>. twas my intention to have brought it home again with me. you
                    see Grosvenor this relic is already become rare. have you received the original
                    Joan of Arc<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The manuscript of the first
                        version of <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title>, begun at the Bedfords’ home
                        in Brixton in summer-autumn 1793. It is now in the Houghton Library, MS Eng
                        265.</note>
<del rend="strikethrough">as</del> written at <ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton</ref>, bound decently — &amp;c? I left it with <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> to send with your copy; he
                    has the transcript<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The fair copy of
                            <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title>, which Southey made in late 1793
                        and presented to Joseph Cottle. The manuscript is now in the University of
                        Rochester Library, AS727.</note> of it himself, which he begged with most
                    friendly devotion &amp; I believe values as much as a Monk does the parings
                    of his tutelary Saints great toe nail. is not the Preface a hodge podge of
                    inanity? I had written the beginning only before I quitted Bristol. — the <del rend="strikethrough">xxxx on the</del> latter days of my residence there
                    were occupied by concerns too nearly interesting to allow time <del rend="strikethrough">for</del> or collectedness for composition — &amp;
                    you will believe that after quitting <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> on Sunday evening, I was little fit to write a preface Monday
                    morning. I never saw the whole of it together, &amp; I believe that after
                    making a few hasty remarks on epic poems I forgot to draw the conclusion, for
                    which only they were introduced. n’importe, the ill-naturd Critic may exercise
                    malignity in dissecting it, &amp; the friendly one his ingenuity in finding
                    out some excuse. by the by add the Reviewer to your portraits in the <hi rend="ital">celeberrimated</hi>
<del rend="strikethrough">G</del> Clavis,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a reference to something Grosvenor Charles Bedford was writing,
                        but which has not survived.</note> tis not the worst of his characters.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> What has all this to do with Lisbon — say you. take a sonnet for
                    the Ladies imitated from the Spanish of Bartolomè Leonardo, <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Bartolomè Leonardo de Argensola (1561–1631),
                        priest, poet and historian.</note> in which I have given the author at least
                    as many ideas as he has given me.</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3">Nay cleanse this filthy mixture from thy hair</l>
<l rend="indent4"> And give the untrickd tresses to the gale!</l>
<l rend="indent4"> The Sun as lightly on the breeze they sail</l>
<l rend="indent3">Shall gild the bright brown locks. thy cheek is fair —</l>
<l rend="indent3">Away then with this artificial hue</l>
<l rend="indent4"> This blush eternal! Lady to thy face</l>
<l rend="indent4"> Nature has given no imitable grace.</l>
<l rend="indent3">Why these black spots obtruding on the view</l>
<l rend="indent3">The lilly cheek? &amp; these ear jewels too</l>
<l rend="indent4"> That ape the barbarous Indian’s vanity!</l>
<l rend="indent3">Thou needest not with that necklace there invite</l>
<l rend="indent3">The prying gaze — we know thy neck is white —</l>
<l rend="indent4"> Go to thy dressing room again — &amp; be</l>
<l rend="indent4"> Artful enough to learn simplicity. <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A revised version of this translation appeared in
                            Southey’s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in
                                Spain and Portugal</title> (1797).</note>
</l>
</lg>
<p>Could not you swear to the author if you had seen this in the newspaper? you must
                    know <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> I have a
                    deadly aversion to any thing merely ornamental in female dress. let the dress be
                    as elegant (i.e. as simple) as possible — but hang on none of your gewgaw<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> eye traps.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Do write to me. &amp; promise me a visit at Bristol in the
                    summer — for after I have returned to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> I will never quit her again — so that we shall remain there
                    till <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> I settle doggedly to law, which I hope
                    will be during the next winter.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I wrote to you &amp; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> by the last packet. do write to me &amp; very long letters.
                    for the greatest pleasure I have is in finding the wind fair for Lisbon. when I
                    set foot again on English ground! — <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> I would lose a
                    finger for the luxury of shaking off your hand at that moment — I am afraid I
                    shall hug one of the boatmen for joy.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I am unchristian enough to wish all the Portugueze were converted
                    to the Jewish faith — for a reason which you may find in the twenty third
                    chapter of Deuteronomy &amp; the thirteenth verse.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘And thou shalt have a paddle upon thy weapon; and it shall
                        be when thou wilt ease thyself abroad, thou shalt dig therewith, and shalt
                        turn back and cover that which cometh from thee’, <title level="m">Deuteronomy</title> 23: 13.</note> the half that are Israelites live in
                    such fear that they not only eat pork to avoid suspicion but even
                    &lt;live&gt; like pigs. &amp; as for washing themselves — what
                    Catholic is Turk enough to perform the ceremony of ablution!</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<date when="1796-02-26">Friday 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
</date>. Timothy
                        Dwight<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752–1817),
                        poet, leader of the Hartford Wits and President of Yale (1795–1817).</note>
                    (— <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> I defy you
                    &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Shandy<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Shandy, father of the eponymous hero of Laurence Sterne (1713–1768;
                            <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Life and Opinions of
                            Tristram Shandy, Gentleman</title> (1759–1767).</note> to physiognomize
                    that mans name rightly —) (what historian is it who in speaking of Alexanders
                    feast says they listened to <hi rend="ital">one Timothy</hi> a musician?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The legend that Alexander the Great
                        (356–323 BC; reigned 336–323 BC) was moved to burn the city of Persepolis in
                        330 BC after listening to music played at a feast, was best known through
                        John Dryden’s (1631–1700; <title level="m">DNB</title>) <title level="m">Alexander’s Feast:
                        The Power of Music</title> (1697). It seems to originate with Dio Chrysostom (c. AD
                        40–120), <title level="m">Orations</title>.</note>) Timothy Dwight an
                    American publishd an heroic poem on the Conquest of Canaan in 1785.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight, <title level="m">The Conquest of
                            Canaan</title> (1785).</note> I had heard of it &amp; long wishd
                    to read it in vain — but now the American minister<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">David Humphreys (1752–1818), American minister to Portugal
                        (1791–1796) and Spain (1796–1801). A soldier and poet, he was a member of
                        the Hartford Wits. He was later responsible for importing Merino sheep into
                        America.</note> — (a good humourd man whose poetry is worse than any thing
                    except his criticisms) has lent me the book. there certainly is some merit in
                    the poem — but when Colonel Humphreys speaks of it he will not allow me to put
                    in a word in defence of John Milton. if I had written upon this subject I should
                    have been terribly tempted to take part with the Canaanites, for whom I cannot
                    help feeling a kind of brotherly compassion. there is a fine ocean of ideas
                    floating about my brain pan for Madoc — &amp; a high delight do I feel in
                    sometimes indulging them till self forgetfulness follows. truely <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> if heaven be
                    only that <del rend="strikethrough">hymn</del> psalm singing place that some
                    have supposed it I should like to make interest for the laureates place
                    &amp; write a few hymns occasionally for the Cherubim &amp; Seraphim
                    that continually do cry.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title level="m">Isaiah</title> 6: 3.</note> strange concatenation of ideas!
                    when we meet I will shew you a most elegant piece of latin on the eternity of
                        <del rend="strikethrough">future</del> punishment extracted from Thomas
                    Burnett — Author of The Theory of Earth<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Burnet (<hi rend="ital">c</hi>. 1635–1715; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Sacred Theory of the Earth</title>
                        (1684–1690). However, this is probably a reference to a passage in Burnet’s
                            <title level="m">De Statu Mortuorum</title> (1720).</note> a book which
                    equals Milton in sublimity, &amp; which for ingenuity never perhaps was
                    equalled. I heard Crowe<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">William Crowe
                        (c. 1745–1829; <title level="m">DNB</title>), clergyman and poet, he held
                        the post of public orator at the University of Oxford from 1784 until his
                        death.</note> in a sermon speak of heaven as a state of continual
                    progression — &amp; if it were not it would cease to be heaven — but of all
                    these things <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>
                    we shall know &lt;more&gt; when we have passed thro the gates of the
                    grave. I was at the funeral of a young man last Sunday — &amp; funerals make
                    me very melancholy — nothing is so gloomy as to contemplate the ravages Death
                    makes among the little circle of our friends — do you remember an alcaic
                        ode<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey’s letter to
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 26 December 1793 (Letter 77). The poem was
                        published in a revised form as ‘Ode Written on the First of January, 1794’
                        in <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797).</note> I sent you one New Years
                    day — “that soon thy pious grief” may wail &amp;c? these ill looking lines
                    very often occur to me — perhaps the most striking &amp; eloquent passage I
                    ever wrote is the declamation on Suicide in the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> book of
                        Joan.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey, <title level="m">Joan
                            of Arc, An Epic Poem</title> (Bristol and London, 1796), pp.
                        322–325.</note> — &amp; the answer to it will shew — how tame is Reason
                    when compared with Feeling. Grosvenor keep all these things for your own eye
                    only — perhaps you can follow the chain that connects them.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Tis a vile kind of philosophy that for tomorrows prospect glooms
                    to day — apropos — sit down when you have no better employment &amp; find
                    all the faults you can in the Retrospect<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The Retrospect’ had been published in Southey’s and Robert Lovell’s <title level="m">Poems</title> (1795).</note> against I return — it wants the
                    pruning knife before it be republishd.</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">Another mountain yet! I thought this brow</l>
<l rend="indent2">Had surely been the summit. but they rise</l>
<l rend="indent2">Cliff above cliff amid the incumbent skies</l>
<l rend="indent2">And mock my labour. What a giddy height!</l>
<l rend="indent2">The roar of yonder stream that foams below</l>
<l rend="indent2">Meets but at fits mine ear: ah me my sight</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Shrinks from this upward toil, &amp; sore opprest</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Sad I bethink me of my home of rest.</l>
<l rend="indent2">Such is the lot of man! up lifes steep road</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Painful he drags beguiling the long way</l>
<l rend="indent3"> With many a vain dream on the future day</l>
<l rend="indent2">With Peace to sojourn in her calm abode.</l>
<l rend="indent2">Poor fool of Hope — that day will never come</l>
<l rend="indent2">Till Time &amp; Care have led thee to the tomb. <note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">A revised version appeared in
                            Southey’s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in
                                Spain and Portugal</title> (1797).</note>
</l>
</lg>
<p>there is a melancholy sonnet <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>. composd on the mountains of Galicia when my mind &amp;
                    body were equally fatigued.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> last night — nay I must mend the pen — last night I was at the
                        Tonkins.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Friends of Southey’s uncle,
                        Herbert Hill, and residents of Lisbon. Southey was also on good terms with
                        their daughter Ann.</note> the room is a very large one &amp; I walked
                    up &amp; down it thinking of my play — till I got at last into the high
                    Tragedy trot (much about the same pace with <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace’s</ref> march up school
                    after breakfast on Monday mornings — with his weekly note) — never was place so
                    infested with boobies as Lisbon. I always think of the Lady at <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins’s</ref> when I hear one of these
                    fellows talk nonsense to a woman.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Ερως
                    δ’κ
                    ηρκεσε
                        Μοιρας<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">A quotation from Musæus (fl. c. early 6th
                        century), <title level="m">The Loves of Hero and Leander</title>. The Greek
                        translates as ‘passion as allotted was quite sufficient’. Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford’s translation of the poem was published in 1797.</note> — so said
                    the Sphinx in the last letter I received. &amp; if I had been Oedipus<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">In most versions of the Greek legend,
                        when Oedipus solved the riddle of the Sphinx, she committed suicide.</note>
                    &amp; as puzzled then as I am now I would have saved Sphinx the guilt of
                    suicide by launching her down the rock. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref> how
                    many letters have you written to me without once mentioning the name of M— shall
                    I go on? if I had <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisles</ref>
                    wings I would cross the damned Bay of Biscay — &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">tell</del> show you all the ways &amp; windings of
                    the female heart — you must however, as I am &lt;a&gt; poor unfledged
                    biped, come to Bristol in June, &amp; there take a brothers place in one of
                    the best. twould be disagre<hi rend="ital">abell</hi> to be taken prisoner on my
                    return &amp; still more so to be drowned. under which last apprehension I
                    did grievously suffer on coming to Corūna. remember <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> to pay the
                    English postage when you write otherwise the letter will be detained. direct
                    with the <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">R. Herbert Hill</ref> Lisbon.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> if Joan of Arc reaches a second edition — &amp; I have reason
                    to believe it will — I shall make considerable alterations.</p>
<p>
<del rend="strikethrough">What think you of xxxxxxx the xxxxxx the School for
                        Scoundrels xxxxxx xxxxxxxxxx of a newsworthy sergeant? xx xxxx xxx xx xxxxx
                        xxxxxx xxx xxxxx xxxx xxxxx xxxx xxxxx &lt;xxxxx&gt; xxxx xxxxxx
                        xxxx the xxxx of xxxxxxxxx xxxxxxxxxx &lt;xx xx&gt; — xx xxxx in xx
                        xxxxxx xxxx xxxx xx xxx And xxxxx a xxxxxxxx xxx xxxx xxxx. Let the xxxx x
                        xxx xx xxxxxxxxx xx xxxxxxx xxx xxxx xxxxx xxxxxxxx.</del>
</p>
<lb/>
<p>
<date when="1796-03-01">March 1st</date>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I was going to finish the letter &amp; bid you remember S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Davids day 1792 — our birth day of authorship<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">The first issue of <title level="j">The
                            Flagellant</title>, a collaboration between Southey, Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford and other school friends, appeared on 1 March 1792.</note> when your
                    letter came. is it right to encourage Hope when Disappointment is possible?
                    without answering the abstract &amp; useless question I will venture to say
                    that (if there be no previous attachment) you have no cause to doubt success.
                    men of the world — those gay empty braind &amp; empty hearted coxcombs for
                    whom I have something like a natural antipathy, make acquaintance more easily
                    than you &amp; I should do. <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> they will
                    play with a Ladys fan &amp; converse with her with an ease that you
                    &amp; I wonder at — but when we require more than acquaintance — more than
                    friendship — then we have all the advantage. I never found it difficult to
                    become intimate with any woman except <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">then</del> in her company I
                    experienced always that unquiet state of delight which made me embarrassd
                    &amp; sometimes made me wish myself away: yes <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>, it is very
                    easy to resolve to speak — but the minute before guillotting is luxury to the
                    opening the mouth on such an occasion. one of these days we will walk round the
                    garden at <ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton</ref> &amp; talk of
                    this. no resolution of celibacy (except in the disappointed) can be stable. if
                    there be another candidate be you more earnest — for her sake as well as you own
                    for with no one will she be so happy as with you. make her acquainted with you,
                    &amp; it is impossible that you should not succeed. I am glad you have seen
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> — the facts you corrected for
                    him I can not conjecture. if <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> had
                    had a good education he would have made no small progress — he is now too good
                    for a sailour — I offered <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">my Uncle</ref>
                    to fit <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> for taking orders,
                    &amp; his living, &amp; urged arguments for it, which <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> as well as myself
                    thought sufficiently strong. my interference was of no avail. &amp; I had
                    prudence enough to say nothing of the matter to my brother. — </p>
<p rend="indent1"> &amp; so you really think notes ought to have some connection
                    with the text? I could laugh at you in some moods, but the book must be its own
                    advocate, &amp; you do not remark faults (as you think them) only. if you
                    read Joan a second time, keep a little book by you &amp; make all your
                    objections I hope to spend three months in correcting it for another edition. I
                    heard nothing from you at Madrid — &amp; know nothing of the Letters you
                    mention but that I am equally obliged as if they had arrived. — </p>
<p rend="indent1"> have you not sometimes read as M A— ? Nebuchadnezzar<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">The reference is obscure. Nebuchadnezzar II,
                        King of Babylon (605–562 BC).</note> will slip out by &amp; by — take
                    some opportunity of doing this &amp; then you <del rend="strikethrough">will</del> may find out — that comments may wander a good way from the
                    text, &amp; yet lead to good. if I was in London you should introduce me.
                    but this execrable ocean is between us &amp; tho I long to mount the vessel
                    I almost turn sick in anticipation. I have run on before your letter came, in
                    such a strange manner that I have no room to tell you a very melancholy story —
                    n’importe Ill een begin another sheet. heigh ho! <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> — I am a very
                    solitary minded animal — &amp; should &lt;have&gt; no one of my own
                        <hi rend="ital">species</hi> to speak to — had I not made <del rend="strikethrough">my</del> &lt;a&gt; female friend<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified, though this could be Ann Tonkin,
                        the daughter of friends of Southey’s uncle, Herbert Hill, who is mentioned
                        later in this letter.</note> — with whom I can talk of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> till “I play the woman”<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">An adaptation of <title level="m">A
                            Midsummer Night’s Dream</title>, Act 1, scene 2, line 47.</note> — which
                    some people would call playing the fool. At the posada where we slept at Villa
                    Franca was a young woman whose short &amp; melancholy history affected me
                    very much. she was the daughter of the host (you know how very miserable a
                    Spanish inn is — infinitely worse than the worst English alehouse) a young man
                    with property enough for all the comforts of life, but which went away at his
                    death, married this girl, &amp; they were as happy as <del rend="strikethrough">bxx</del>
<hi rend="ital">we</hi> can imagine two people united solely from affection. he
                    died &amp; left her with two very young children; totally destitute she
                    returned to the wretched home of her parents, where hard labor hardly procures a
                    miserable existence. I saw her — she was about three &amp; twenty, &amp;
                    even if I had not known her story I should &lt;have thought&gt; her face
                    the most beautiful I had seen in Spain. there was a melancholy in her dark eyes
                    beyond any description. her dress was suitable to her situation yet her manners
                    indicated one accustomed to better scenes; &amp; a clean white stocking
                    displayd that shaping of the foot &amp; ancle which may be deemd the general
                    distinction of the class who do not work. within a very few weeks after her
                    husbands death an Irish man offered to take this woman into keeping. I can
                    conceive her look when she answered him “you say you love me Senōr — &amp;
                    yet you can insult me by this wicked offer.” <ref target="people.html#MaberGeorgeMartin">Ld Butes chaplain</ref> who travelled
                    to Madrid with us, was present, &amp; from him I learnt the anecdote. you
                    know not the impression all this made upon me. my next mornings walk produced
                    these lines — I am ill satisfied with them</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">And does there then Teresa live a Man</l>
<l rend="indent2">Whose tongue unfaltering could to such foul thoughts</l>
<l rend="indent2">Yield utterance? — tempt thee to the hireling bed!</l>
<l rend="indent2">Buy thee Teresa to anothers arms —</l>
<l rend="indent2">Thee sufferer — thee forlorn &amp; wretched one,</l>
<l rend="indent2">Ere yet upon thy husbands grave the grass</l>
<l rend="indent2">Was green! oh is there one whose monstrous heart</l>
<l rend="indent2">Could with insulted Modestys hot blush</l>
<l rend="indent2">Make crimson the poor widows woe pale cheek!</l>
<l rend="indent2">Was this thing of my species? shaped in the mould</l>
<l rend="indent2">Of Man, &amp; fashiond to the outward show</l>
<l rend="indent2">All human? did he move aloft — &amp; lift</l>
<l rend="indent2">On high his lordly face? &amp; formed of flesh</l>
<l rend="indent2">And blood like mine meandering thro his frame!</l>
<l rend="indent2">I blush for human nature, &amp; would fain</l>
<l rend="indent2">Prove kindred with the brutes. she raisd to heaven</l>
<l rend="indent2">Her dark eyes with a meek upbraiding look</l>
<l rend="indent2">And felt more keen her loss &amp; dropt a tear</l>
<l rend="indent2">Of aggravated anguish. I almost</l>
<l rend="indent2">Could murmur at my lot assigned by Heaven.</l>
<l rend="indent2">And covet wealth, that from the bitter ills</l>
<l rend="indent2">Of Want, I might secure thee, &amp; provide</l>
<l rend="indent2">Some safe asylum for thy little ones.</l>
<l rend="indent2">And from the blasting wind of Poverty</l>
<l rend="indent2">Shield their young opening Reason. I would be</l>
<l rend="indent2">Even as a brother to thee! sit by thee</l>
<l rend="indent2">And hear thee talk of days of happiness</l>
<l rend="indent2">How fast they fled, &amp; of the joys of youth</l>
<l rend="indent2">And Hope — now buried in the grave of Love —</l>
<l rend="indent2">Oh I would listen to thy tale, &amp; weep,</l>
<l rend="indent2">And pour upon Affections bleeding wounds</l>
<l rend="indent2">The balm of pity. — Sufferer fare thee well.</l>
<l rend="indent2">God be thy comforter, &amp; from a world</l>
<l rend="indent2">Of woe, release thee soon. I — on my way</l>
<l rend="indent2">Journeying, remember thee, &amp; think of HER</l>
<l rend="indent2">In distant England; grateful to that power</l>
<l rend="indent2">Who from the dark &amp; tempest-roaring deep</l>
<l rend="indent2">Preserved a life SHE renders doubly dear. <note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">And does ... dear: Verse written in double
                            columns. A revised version appeared in Southey’s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and
                                Portugal</title> (1797).</note>
</l>
</lg>
<p rend="indent6"> ———</p>
<p>This intermediate person. of course I can hardly form a conjecture who she is.
                    yet you want an intermediate, who<del rend="strikethrough">se age</del> being of
                    the same age with yourself may more readily enter into all your feelings — if
                    what you conjecture be true — I know how to pity you on that score. the most
                    painful feelings that ever harrowd my bosom (&amp; I have had my share of
                    painful ones) were when after I had engaged the affection of my heart — <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> &lt;an&gt; amiable <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxxx</del> girl spoke to me in language too plain to
                    be misunderstood. I cannot tell you the acute pain I felt at being obliged to
                    assume a cold indifference of manner, &amp; in shunning one whom I would
                    have chosen for a sister, only because she honord me by deeming me worthy of a
                    dearer connection. once only have we met since that day. I was hurrying along
                    the street &amp; passed her, but immediately turned. — she did the same,
                    &amp; recognised me in a manner of such chastened esteem — that I arrived
                    still melancholy to pass the evening with my <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>. I have nothing wherewith to
                    accuse myself — yet I have from that time indulged a natural reserve, &amp;
                    behaved distantly to those young women who knew not my attachment. I did not
                    dare become the friend of Ann Tonkin<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        daughter of Lisbon-based friends of Southey’s uncle Herbert Hill.</note>
                    before she knew I was the husband of another.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> You <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> have but to win the affections of YOUR M. &amp; to be
                    happy. I hope — that I have only to return &amp; be happy — &amp; for
                    what is past — I will use the experience &amp; little regard the price it
                    has cost. my existence is now linked to my <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>. her face will teach you to
                    expect the gradual developement of every good quality; &amp; in proportion
                    as you know her will you love her. how do I long to see M. — ah <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>! will the days
                    ever arrive that we dream of? yet you carry them but half way when you talk of
                    hardy honest boys — dream of a few girls too — &amp; then see what admirable
                    inhabitants we have found for some of our castles. for me — I have only the Bay
                    of Biscay to <del rend="strikethrough">cross</del> &lt;pass&gt; — but
                    you have not yet crossed the Rubicon. “Ye Gods — annihilate but space &amp;
                        time!”<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander Pope (1688–1744;
                            <title level="m">DNB</title>), ‘Martinus Scriblerus on the Art of
                        Sinking in Poetry’, reprinted in <title level="m">Miscellanies in Prose and
                            Verse... by Jonathan Swift, D.D. and Alexander Pope, Esq.,</title> 2nd
                        edn, 2 vols (Dublin, 1728), II, p. 115.</note> pestilence on the cold
                    blooded cool headed fellow who found out that that was a rant. I honor
                        Dryden<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">John Dryden (1631–1700;
                            <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Of Dramatick Poesie, An
                            Essay</title> (1668).</note> for dashing at such natural absurdity.
                    certainly Time &amp; Space are too very detestable obstacles — porci
                        maximi.<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as
                        ‘very big pigs’.</note> six months hence &amp; Time will fly too fast
                    for me — alas — he creeps with me now as slow &amp; as wearying as a Spanish
                    coach &amp; six.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> This foul place! they empt all their filth into the streets at
                    night. “methinks I smell it now. in my minds’ nose Horatio!”<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">An adaptation of <title level="m">Hamlet</title>, Act 1, scene 2, line 185.</note> that ought to have been
                    said to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">your brother</ref>. by
                    the by where is he? &amp; what does he mean to do with himself?</p>
<p rend="indent1"> when I correct Joan I shall call you in. not as plenipotent
                    amputator — <del rend="strikethrough">but</del> you shall mark what you think
                    the warts wens &amp; cancers, &amp; I will take care you do not cut deep
                    enough to destroy the life. the fourth book is the best. do you know I have
                    never seen the &lt;whole&gt; poem together. &amp; that one book was
                    printing before another was begun? the characters of Conrade &amp; Theodore
                    are totally distinct &amp; yet perhaps equally interesting. there is too
                    much fighting — I found the battles detestable to write — as you will do to
                    read. — tho there are not ten better lines in the whole piece — than those “Of
                    unrecorded name” “Died the mean man, yet did he leave behind &amp;c.”<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">These lines appeared in Southey’s <title level="m">Joan of Arc, An Epic Poem</title> (Bristol and London, 1796),
                        pp. 236–237.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Do you remember the day when you wrote N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        3<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors">The third issue (15 March 1792) of
                            <title level="j">The Flagellant,</title> a schoolboy magazine devised by
                        Southey and his friends, which was forced to cease publication after nine
                        issues.</note> at Brixton? we dined on mutton chops &amp; eggs. I have
                    the note you wrote for <ref target="people.html#DoddJamesWilliam">Dodd</ref>
                    among your letters. I anticipate a very pleasant evening when you shall show the
                    cedar box<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors">According to Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey, a box which contained all the contributions to <title level="j">The
                            Flagellant</title>.</note> to Edith — &amp; <ref target="people.html#PhillimoreJoseph">Joe Phillimores</ref> verses to
                    Louisa. “oh pleasant days of fancy!”<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors">This appears to be a quotation from an unpublished poem (to Louisa) by
                        Southey’s contemporary at Westminster School, Joseph Phillimore. Phillimore
                        was an aspiring poet, though on a somewhat different model to Southey, and
                        in 1793 won a college prize for his Latin verses.</note> by the by if ever
                    you read aloud <del rend="strikethrough">the any</del> that part of the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> book mind that erratum in the description of the Famine.
                    with jealous eye Hating a rivals look <hi rend="ital">the husband hides</hi> His
                    miserable meal.”<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors">These lines appeared in
                        Southey’s <title level="m">Joan of Arc, An Epic Poem</title> (Bristol and
                        London, 1796), p. 182.</note> after I had corrected the page &amp; left
                    town poor <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> whose heart
                    overflows with the milk of human kindness, read it over; &amp; he was as
                    little able to bear the picture of the husband, as he would have been to hide a
                    morsel from the hungry. so suo periculo<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editors">At his own risk</note> — he alterd it to “<hi rend="ital">each man
                        conceals</hi>” &amp; spoilt the climax. I was very much vexed yet I
                    loved <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> the [MS obscured]tter
                    for it. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> this goes by the Magician frigate to Portsmouth. have you
                    received a letter that left Lisbon Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>?</p>
<p rend="indent1"> No <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> you &amp; I shall not talk politics. I am weary of them
                    &amp; little love politicians. for me I shall think of domestic life
                    &amp; confine my wishes within the little circle of friendship. the rays
                    become more intense in proportion as they are drawn to a point. heigh ho! I
                    should be very happy were I in England — with <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> by the fire side — I could
                    listen to the pelting rain with pleasure — now — it is a melancholy music yet
                    fitly harmonizing with my hanging mood.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> farewell. write long letters — &amp; remember me to
                        all friends. &lt;&amp; to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Harry</ref>.&gt;</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> R.S.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<date when="1796-03-02">March 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. 1796.</date>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> once more — be assured that attention from a good man can not
                        fail. you know your own definition of politeness. — oh if I were the
                        intermediate friend! — is it not strange to look back on our own minds —
                        from the history of Martin Schram<note n="39" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a reference to a story or character invented by Southey and
                            his friends at Westminster School.</note> — to all the anxieties of
                        life? &amp; who was Martin Schram says Boswell<note n="40" place="foot" resp="editors">James Boswell (1740–1795; <title level="m">DNB</title>),
                            biographer of Samuel Johnson (1709–1784; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> if he catches this letter. “I have determined that
                        all the powers on earth shall never wrest that secret from me.”<note n="41" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of Mrs E. M. Foster (dates
                            unknown), <title level="m">The Duke of Clarence. An Historical
                                Novel</title>, 2 vols (Dublin, 1795), I, p. 280.</note> Qy — were
                        the Leanders<note n="42" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                            family of Leander, a figure from Greek mythology and subject of
                            Grosvenor Charles Bedford’s translation of Musæus (fl. c. early 6th
                            century), <title level="m">The Loves of Hero and Leander</title>.</note>
                        of the <hi rend="ital">Heroic</hi> race? </p>
<p rend="indent1"> In many parts of Spain they have female shavers. the proper
                        name of one should be <hi rend="ital">Barbara</hi>.</p>
<p>Read this first.</p>
<p rend="indent1">Why is Love like the small pox <del rend="strikethrough">xxx
                            in</del> when <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> procured by art?</p>
<p rend="indent1">because it comes by in-oculation.</p>
<p rend="indent1">Oh execrable conun-<hi rend="ital">drummer</hi>!</p>
<p rend="indent1">Why am I having the Pleasures of Imagination like a man with a
                        broken rib?</p>
<p rend="indent1">because I have an Akenside.<note n="43" place="foot" resp="editors">Mark Akenside (1721–1770; <title level="m">DNB</title>),
                                <title level="m">The Pleasures of Imagination</title>
                        (1744).</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1">Why is a man who plays the fiddle badly like a mischievous
                        school boy?</p>
<p rend="indent1">because he is apt to get into a scrape.</p>
<lb/>
<p rend="indent1"> the common people believe here that Jews have tails. if young
                            <ref target="people.html#ThorpMr">Thorp</ref> ever talks of coming here
                        give him a friendly hint of the Inquisition.<note n="44" place="foot" resp="editors">In many ... Inquisition: Postscript written on fol. 2 v,
                            section originally reserved for address.</note>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
