<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce158</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.158</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>British Library, Add MS 30,927.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 107–109.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="158" type="letter">
<head>158. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey [brother]</ref>, 1 June 1796<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: For/ Thomas Southey/ on board his Majestys Frigate/ Phœbe/ Falmouth/ or elsewhere/ Single<lb/>Stamped: BRISTOL<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30,927<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 107–109.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<date when="1796-06-01">June 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> 1796. </date>
<address>
<placeName>Bristol</placeName>
</address>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Tom</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1">	I was with <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> when your letter arrived. we are in lodgings in Kingsdown &amp; I as usual about to be busied with the printers — &amp; exhibit a volume of Letters written during a short residence in Spain &amp; Portugal. <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> was published between January and mid-February 1797.</note> in September I hope they will be ready &amp; I shall of course forward you a copy to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref>. when you may get them Heaven knows — for your Joan of Arc has been lying at Bath ever since the beginning of December!</p>
<p rend="indent1">	We knew you were off Lisbon &amp; I believe saw the frigate with as much angry impatience as you must have seen the land. your letter never arrived — never trust a Portuguese with any thing — they are the most imposing treacherous sneaking set of rascals that Old Nick ever meddled with &amp; dirted his fingers by touching. it was a merchant-man. that slipped in under your convoy mentioned the name of the frigate.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	You will wonder how I got here without coming to Falmouth. but I came in an American bound for Hull which landed me at Portsmouth after a very fine passage. we left Lisbon on Thursday May 5th &amp; that night &amp; the next day &amp; night were becalmed to the South of the rock in sight. a light SW breeze struck up about nine on Saturday morning so gentle however that we had not lost sight of the rock at night. the wind gradually increasd &amp; never varied two points till on the Saturday following they transferrd me &amp; my fellow passenger to the three brothers of Cowes from whence between eleven &amp; twelve at night we landed at Portsmouth. I took my portmanteau on my shoulders &amp; carried it to the Fountain<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Fountain, a Portsmouth coaching inn.</note> — my aristocratic companions sent Porters for theirs — before the Porters could get there — the Custom house Officers had carried off the things — they were obliged to wait till the middle of the next day without a clean shirt to put on — &amp; pay half a guinea each for fees.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	The election here is just concluded. the blues brought in a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bragge<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The blues’ was a local name for Bristol Tories. Charles Bragge (Bathurst from 1804) (c. 1754–1831; <title level="m">DNB</title>) was an MP for Bristol (1796–1812) who rose to be Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster in the Cabinet (1812–1823). He was a supporter of William Pitt, the Younger (1759–1806; <title level="m">DNB</title>), and brother-in-law of Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757–1844; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> for their member &amp; united with some of the self-styled low party to return that rascal Sheffield<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Baker Holroyd, 1st Earl of Sheffield (1741–1821), an MP for Bristol (1790–1802) who topped the electoral poll in the city in 1796. He was an ex-member of Lord North’s (1732–1792; Prime Minister 1770–1782; <title level="m">DNB</title>) political group and generally supported the government. He was also a strong supporter of the slave-trade.</note> again. a Lord who has voted with the minister upon every motion except the only one where an honest man ought to have joind him — the abolition of the Slave Trade. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomas">T Southey</ref> was the Secretary to Sheffield. the unsuccessful candidate was Hobhouse of Hartram near Chippenham. a man of strong abilities &amp; independant principles who united in his favour the thinking part of the people &amp; the mob.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Benjamin Hobhouse, 1st Baronet (1757–1831; <title level="m">DNB</title>), a politician who campaigned in the Bristol election of 1796 on a Whig, reformist and pro-peace platform. He was elected to Parliament for Bletchingley in 1797 and gradually moved to a more conservative position.</note> but the low party were divided &amp; nothing could be done. our two representatives (— or rather the two representatives of Bristol — for <hi rend="ital">our</hi> is a false word — as <hi rend="ital">I</hi> am not represented — &amp; taxation without representation is tyranny.) will vote for the continuance of the war — &amp; in this case — as Divine Wisdom has ordained in most cases — the &lt;Bristolians&gt; will find their punishment in their crime.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	So much for Bristol news. — poor <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref>! <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary</ref> is better than could be expected — &amp; old <ref target="people.html#Lovellfamily">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> L</ref> provides for her comfortably with affection that does him high honor.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Lovell had died on 3 May 1796, leaving a widow and infant son (Robert, b. 1795). His family did not provide for either.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1">	Joan of Arc has passed thro three Reviews with the greatest success — &amp; has obtained as much reputation as I could desire. </p>
<p rend="indent1">	Of the Somerville estate. I apprehend from an extract of the will which I have — that we have been fooled with hopes totally unfounded. if young Somerville dies without an heir the estates revert to us — but the greater part of these were life-hold &amp; have dropt to the Lord of the Manor.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">James Somerville, 14th Lord Somerville (1727–1796), was Southey’s very distant relation by marriage. Southey hoped to inherit a share of the fortune of John Cannon Southey on the death of Somerville, but his hopes came to nothing. The ‘young Somerville’ referred to here is John Southey Somerville, 15th Lord Somerville (1765–1819; <title level="m">DNB</title>), who inherited his title on the death of his uncle in 1796. He did not die young. Instead he forged a career as an agriculturalist, becoming the largest breeder and owner of merino sheep in England. In 1811, he was involved in the formation of the Merino Society of Great Britain (its first president, Sir Joseph Banks (1743–1820; <title level="m">DNB</title>)).</note> as you are to be an Admiral &amp; I a great Lawyer this matters not. by the by whatever influence in the navy the daughter of Lord Howe has you may look upon as yours — as <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">my Uncle</ref> is very intimate with her &amp; Lord Altamont her husband.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Louisa Howe (1767–1817), the daughter of Richard Howe, Earl Howe (1726–1799; <title level="m">DNB</title>), was married to John Browne (1756–1809), eldest son of the Earl of Altamont. Browne was later created 1st Marquess of Sligo.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love. direct always to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottles</ref>.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent4">				yr affectionate brother</salute>
<signed rend="indent5">						Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> is to go to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls School<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Southey did not go to St Paul’s School or Cambridge University.</note> from whence he will get on the foundation at the University. probably Cambridge. </p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
