<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce174</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.174</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>MS has not survived.  Previously  published: Monthly Magazine, 2 (September 1796), p. 1 [from where the text is taken] under pseudonym ‘B.’. New attribution to Southey; it repeats information found in his letter to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 31 July [–2 August] 1796 (Letter 168).</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="174" type="letter">
<head>174. Robert Southey to the <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Editor of the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>,</ref>
<date when="1796-09-03">3 September 1796</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS has not survived<lb/>Previously published: <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 2 (September 1796), p. 1 [from where the text is taken] under pseudonym ‘B.’. New attribution to Southey; it repeats information found in his letter to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 31 July [–2 August] 1796 (Letter 168).</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>SIR,</salute>
</opener>
<p>YOUR correspondent, who has with such very superior merit translated the Leonora of BÜRGER,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Gottfried August Bürger (1748–1794), who published ‘Lenore’ in 1773.</note> is mistaken when he calls that ballad wholly original.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Taylor, whose translation of ‘Lenora’ had been published anonymously in the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 1 (March 1796), 135–137.</note> He has observed that many of the ballads of the gloomy German are translated with improvements from English originals.− Perhaps the story of Leonora was suggested by a ballad entitled, <title level="m">“The Suffolk Miracle, or a relation of a Young Man, who a month after his death appeared to his sweetheart, and carried her on horseback behind him for forty miles, in two hours, and was never seen after but in his grave.”</title> It is in a collection of ballads, printed 1723.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The Suffolk Miracle’, <title level="m">A Collection of Old Ballads. Corrected from the Best and Most Ancient Copies Extant. With Introductions Historical, Critical, or Humorous</title> (London, 1723), pp. 266–270.</note> The collection extended to three volumes, each published separately, and is now very rare.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A second volume was added to <title level="m">A Collection of Old Ballads</title> in 1723, and a third in 1725.</note> In this tale the Spirit comes at midnight, and the maiden departs with him.</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">When she was got her love behind,</l>
<l rend="indent2">They pass’d as swift as any wind,</l>
<l rend="indent2">That in two hours, or little more</l>
<l rend="indent2">He brought her to her father’s door.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">But as they did this great haste make,</l>
<l rend="indent2">He did complain his head did ache,</l>
<l rend="indent2">Her handkerchief she then took out,</l>
<l rend="indent2">And tyed the same his head about.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">And unto him she thus did say,</l>
<l rend="indent2">“Thou art as cold as any clay!</l>
<l rend="indent2">“When we come home a fire we’ll have,”</l>
<l rend="indent2">But little dreamed he went to grave!<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title level="m">A Collection of Old Ballads. Corrected from the Best and Most Ancient Copies Extant. With Introductions Historical, Critical, or Humorous</title> (London, 1723), p. 268.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<p rend="indent1">	As Bürger is well versed in this branch of English poetry, it is not improbable that this rude but striking tale may have occasioned the sublime ballad of Leonora. However this may be, it certainly contradicts a remark that has not unaptly been made upon that Poem, that the difference between a German ghost and an English one is, that the German rides on horseback, and the English one goes on foot.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1">	The imitation of the following lines from “William’s Ghost”, is, I think manifest. There are the lines of Leonora:</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">“And where is then thy house and home,</l>
<l rend="indent3">	“And where thy bridal bed?”</l>
<l rend="indent2">“’Tis narrow, silent, chilly, dark,</l>
<l rend="indent3">	 “Far hence I rest my head.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">“And is there any room for me,</l>
<l rend="indent3">	“Wherein that I may creep?”</l>
<l rend="indent2">“There’s room enough for thee and me,</l>
<l rend="indent3">	“Wherein that we may sleep.”<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A quotation, with slight variations in spelling, of the translation published in the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 1 (March 1796), 136.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<p>Compare them with these of the English ballad:</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">Now she has kilted her robes of green,</l>
<l rend="indent3">	A piece below her knee,</l>
<l rend="indent2">And a the live-long winter night</l>
<l rend="indent3">	The dead corpse followed she.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">“Is there any room at your head, Willie?</l>
<l rend="indent3">	“Or any at your feet?</l>
<l rend="indent2">“Or any room at your side, Willie,</l>
<l rend="indent3">	“Wherein that I may creep?”</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">“There’s no room at my head, Margaret, </l>
<l rend="indent3">	“There’s no room at my feet;</l>
<l rend="indent2">“There’s no room at my side, Margaret,</l>
<l rend="indent3">	“My coffin is made so meet.”<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Sweet William’s Ghost. A Scottish Ballad’; see Thomas Percy (1729–1811: <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Reliques of Ancient English Poetry</title>, 3 vols (London, 1765), III, p. 130. Southey had quoted the two final stanzas in a letter to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 31 July [–2 August] 1796 (Letter 168).</note>
</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<p rend="indent1">	Leonora is in parts equal to any composition I have ever read. The moral however is very exceptionable, and they who may abhor the vindictive justice of God, will think the punishment of Leonora exceeds her offence. The other ballad of the Parson’s Daughter<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Bürger’s ‘The Lass of Fair Wone’ was published in the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 1 (April 1796), 223–234. The translator was William Taylor.</note> is, in my opinion, superior. The abruptness of the beginning, and the recurrence to it at the end are unequalled.</p>
<closer>
<signed rend="indent11">B.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<date when="1796-09-03">
<hi rend="ital">Sept</hi>. 3, 1796.</date>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
