<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce234</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.234</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.182.  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections From the
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        37–40.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="234" type="letter">
<head>234. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey
                        [brother]</ref>, <date when="1797-07-16">16 July [1797]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: For/ Mr Southey/ Phoebe
                        Frigate/ Falmouth./ Single<lb/>Stamped: RINGWOOD<lb/>Postmark: BJY/ 17/
                        97<lb/>MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.182<lb/>Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title level="m">Selections From the
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        37–40.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<date when="1797-07-16">Sunday. July 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</date>
<address>
<placeName>
<ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>
</placeName>
</address>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Tom</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> I have a very pleasant piece of intelligence to begin.
                        Boutet<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The French naval captain
                        Boutet (first name and dates unknown), who had previously been kind to
                        Thomas Southey, and whose release Southey had helped to procure.</note> goes
                    by the first cartel — I had moved many enquiries to get him out, &amp;
                    luckily the first succeeded. the same post brought your letter this morning
                    &amp; his in which he thanks me, sends a thousand friendships to you
                    &amp; says his future address in Nantes. God bless him wherever he goes. A
                    friend of <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottles</ref> by name Birt or
                    Burt or Bird,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaiah Birt (1758–1837),
                        Minister of the Baptist Church at Plymouth Dock. Joseph Cottle was one of
                        the booksellers responsible for distributing his <title level="m">A
                            Vindication of the Baptists, in Three Letters, Addressed to a Friend in
                            Saltash</title> (1793).</note> has been the means of serving him
                    &amp; the Commissary communicated it to Boutet himself. he was likewise
                    offered money — so you see every thing has been done, &amp; you will rejoice
                    with me that it has been effectual.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I mean strongly to urge <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> to let her house for whatever she can, even half price, for
                    it is better to sink 50 than 100 a year; &amp; come live with us. this would
                    make her very happy &amp; us too, &amp; I have enough to live
                    comfortably upon. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">my Uncle</ref> wrote to
                    me a few days back &amp; said he would from time to time do what he could to
                    serve me; thank God I want not his assistance. my literary labours find me what
                    books &amp; luxuries I allow myself (&amp; books make the only ones
                    perhaps). I have the necessary comforts of life besides. would to God you could
                    come to us — do not let an opportunity pass you. thank God I have always a home
                    for you.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Your communications I very much thank you for; they suit the
                    purpose better than I expected, &amp; you shall see them in print.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Information about the navy and French
                        prisons sent to Southey by Thomas; see Southey to the Editor of the <title level="m">Monthly Magazine</title> [c. August 1797] (Letter 241).</note>
                    I earned from the Monthly Magazine last year seven pounds &amp; two pair of
                    breeches in eight months which as I give them only a few leisure mornings in a
                    month &amp; what would not be printed in any collection of my own is not
                    amiss. it is an excellent Magazine. I will mark your copy with the authors names
                    wherever I know them, &amp; this will render it more interesting to you.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">his brother</ref> have been visiting me;
                    they remained only a few days, but they were very happy days, &amp; we shall
                    neither of us soon forget them. to escape from a shop counter is very
                    delightful, indeed change of scene is always agreable, if we do not find
                    yourselves when in a new place wholly among new faces. I am now domesticated
                    here, &amp; have even more acquaintance than suits with my oeconomy of
                    time.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Perhaps you may wish to know what I have on the stocks. Madoc
                    slowly goes on, but altogether to my own satisfaction which is saying much. a
                    second edition of the little volume of poems is in the Press. I am getting ready
                    a tragedy to be called The Martyrdom of Joan of Arc<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s play was not published and, indeed, was probably
                        not completed.</note> to go to press when they are finished, &amp; a new
                    edition of the poem<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The second edition of
                            <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title>, which appeared in 1798.</note> in
                    two pocket volumes much altered, succeeds that — so that my printer <ref target="people.html#BiggsNathaniel">Biggs</ref> is almost monopolized. all
                    these you will of course receive as soon as they are finished.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Your imprisonment has alarmed all the circle of my acquaintance,
                    &amp; the subsequent history highly interested them. my acquaintance are
                    wonderfully increased. — so much is a man esteemed according to the worlds
                    opinion of him! people call upon me, &amp; if I do not like them I never
                    return the visit; &amp; I have had the satisfaction of refusing some dinner
                    invitations from persons who had never seen me, because I hate impertinent
                    curiosity. what is somewhat strange I never had any friends at Bristol till I
                    was left to myself there. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> This is a pleasant place, I have half a cottage here &amp; a
                    maid for the time we stay, we have a spare bed which I do not love to have
                    empty, &amp; my neighbour <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Biddlecombe</ref>, a very agreable man, can always
                    lend me another. here is fine fishing — fine swimming — pleasant walks &amp;
                    excellent prospects. we have but one nuisance — the notorious old Lady
                        Strathmore<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Eleanor Bowes
                        (1749–1800; <title level="m">DNB</title>), heiress, botanist and author of a
                        five act play, <title level="m">The Siege of Jerusalem</title> (1769). Her
                        first husband was John Lyon (1737–1776), 9th Earl of Strathmore and
                        Kinghorne, her second the fortune-hunter Andrew Robinson Stoney (1747–1810).
                        In 1789, her abusive marriage to Stoney ended in an acrimonious and
                        scandalous divorce. The sexual and domestic scandal that tarnished her
                        reputation can be seen in James Gillray’s (1756–1815; <title level="m">DNB</title>) <title level="m">The injured Count, S—</title>
                        (c. 1786), which depicts Lady Strathmore drinking gin with her servants and
                        suckling two cats (a reference to the rumour that she was fonder of her pets
                        than of her son). Her marriage to Stoney is said to have inspired William
                        Makepeace Thackeray’s (1811–1863; <title level="m">DNB</title>) novel <title level="m">Barry Lyndon</title> (1844).</note> of news-paper &amp;
                    Doctors Commons reputation — who persecutes us with invitations. now it is
                    neither agreable or creditable to visit such a wicked old woman, I cannot tell
                    her this, &amp; she will not be satisfied with refusals.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">My Uncles</ref> addition as Chaplain to
                    the Staff is 10 shilling a day besides perquisites. he has sent me drawings of
                    the views we saw on our journey. I wish you were here to see them. it is my
                    intention to have some engraved for the next edition of my Letters,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A second edition of Southey’s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title>
                        was published in 1799.</note> which have I believe sold very well. unluckily
                    now my name is established I must have done with it, for to publish whilst
                    studying law would materially injure me. so I assume the name of Walter
                        Tyler,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">In the mid to late 1790s,
                        Southey occasionally used variations on the pseudonym ‘Walter Tyler’ to sign
                        his magazine and newspaper publications. He liked to joke that he was a
                        (collateral) descendant of the leader of the Peasant’s Revolt of 1381,
                        pointing to the surname of his aunt, Elizabeth Tyler, as proof of
                        this.</note> in honour of my good old Uncle, an ancestor of whom I am very
                    proud &amp; with reason.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love. she wishes much to see
                    you. the post will pass us in a minute. God bless you.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
