<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2128</idno><idno type="nines">rce3399</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856) .  Previously  published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    287–290.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2128" type="letter"><head>2128. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1812-07-29">29 July
                        1812</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856) <lb/>Previously published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    287–290.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1812-07-29">July 29. 1812.</date></dateline><salute>My Dear Neville,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I returned home on Saturday after an absence of twelve days, and a round of 300 miles, more than two of which were
                    performed on foot, – a seasonable change of air and occupation to freshen me up for resuming my wonted employments, which, it
                    seems, must commence again with shorter intermission than I had proposed. Letters were awaiting me to urge the necessity of
                    expediting the “Register,”<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813).</note> so that the volumes for the future may be published in March
                    instead of July, which is said to be essential to the interest, and almost necessary to the continuance of the work. This will
                    interfere no farther with my plans than that my journey to London must be postponed till the next volume is done; that is, till
                    March. In March, then, I must hope to see you, and to make some arrangements for seeing your excellent mother and one of your
                    sisters<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary White, née Neville (1755–1833). She had three daughters; Hannah White (c. 1779–1813); Frances Moriah White (1791–1854); Catherine Bailey White (1795–1889).</note> here, at the ensuing summer holidays, if
                    we are all living and well-doing at that time.</p><p rend="indent1"> I had a letter from <ref target="people.html#WhiteJames">James</ref> a little while before my departure: just such
                    a one in matter and manner, as his best friends would wish to receive from him. I was particularly pleased with what he said
                    respecting the controversy which Dr. Marsh has raised;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Herbert Marsh (1757–1839;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Lady Margaret Professor of Divinity at Cambridge. He had preached a sermon at St Paul’s on 13 June
                        1811 that was critical of the interdenominational British and Foreign Bible Society (founded 1804) and urged that Anglicans
                        should found their own Bible society. Southey had read the pamphlet form of the sermon, <title>The National Religion the
                            Foundation of National Education: A Sermon Preached in the Cathedral Church of St. Paul, London</title> (1811). Its
                        arguments were rebutted by Edward Daniel Clarke (1769–1822; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to Herbert Marsh, D.D.,
                            F.R.S. … in Reply to Certain Observations Contained in His Pamphlet Relative to the British and Foreign Bible
                            Society</title> (1812). In late 1811 the dispute spread to Cambridge, where students proposed forming an auxiliary group
                        of the British and Foreign Bible Society. Marsh publicly opposed this in his <title>Address to the Members of the Senate of
                            the University of Cambridge</title> (1811). The students gained support from Lord Hardwick (1757–1834; <title>DNB</title>)
                        and the Duke of Gloucester (1776–1834; <title>DNB</title>), Chancellor of the University. The first meeting of their new
                        society was a great success, and Marsh backed down. James White had joined this new Cambridge bible society; see Southey to
                        James White, 16 February 1812, Letter 2040.</note> for <ref target="people.html#WhiteJames">James</ref>, with a proper mixture
                    of feeling and judgment, perceives at the same time the strength of the Professor’s argument, and the unfitness of exciting any
                    controversy upon such a subject; when, however right in his main view, upon the first broad statement of the case he must
                    necessarily appear wrong, and that in the most obnoxious way. I do not doubt that <ref target="people.html#WhiteJames">James</ref>
                    will prove a highly valuable member of the profession which he has chosen.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> James White
                        became an Anglican clergyman.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> In a few days, as soon as I have cleared off the arrears of letters which have accumulated upon my hands, I will
                    transcribe the pieces from <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry’s</ref> manuscript volume.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Neville White, 20 September 1812, Letter 2147.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> During my journey I saw many of the finest things in the north of England, – the falls of the Tees, Mr. Moritt’s
                    grounds at Rokeby,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Bacon Sawrey Morritt (1771–1843; <title>DNB</title>), traveller,
                        classical scholar and member of the Society of Dilettanti. He had gained the nickname ‘Troy’ for his endeavours to prove that
                        the city had been a real place, not an invention of Homer. He owned the Rokeby estate, where he entertained a large circle,
                        including Humphry Davy and Walter Scott.</note> Richmond, in Yorkshire, one of the most striking towns which I have ever seen
                    – Wensley Dale, the Yorkshire Caves, and Gordall Scar, – a most impressive and extraordinary place. A mountain stream, forcing its
                    way through the rocks, appears issuing from under an arch of stones, and falls from a height down a cleft in brown and naked
                    rocks, that hang over you, like the cliff under which Evangelist met Christian when he had been persuaded to leave the right
                        way.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> An incident from in John Bunyan (1628–1688; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            Pilgrim’s Progress</title> (1678).</note> The rocks resemble the scoria of some furnace more than anything else, both in
                    colour and texture, being full of cavities. Whenever you can find time to come and see me by my own fireside, you should allot a
                    day to this place and the caves, which may easily be seen in that time. The Leeds coach passes through Settle on its way to Kendal
                    every Friday and Saturday. It reaches Settle at three in the afternoon, and in summer, with a guide and a pony, you may see the
                    Scar that evening. To Ingleton from Settle is ten miles; get there to breakfast. The caves form a round of twelve miles, and at
                    five the coach which you left on the preceding day will take you up and convey you on to Kendal.</p><p rend="indent1"> My hopes are not very sanguine respecting the war in the North; in Alexander<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander I (1777–1825; Emperor of Russia 1801–1825). French forces had invaded Russia on 24 June 1812.</note> we may
                    calculate upon any degree of folly and of madness, and in his counsellors upon any baseness. Yet if he would continue to act as he
                    seems to have begun, Bonaparte would rue the day in which he ever invaded Russia. Let what will happen I trust some good will
                    accrue to Poland; and, unless things are most miserably mismanaged, a great deal will be done toward the deliverance of Spain, –
                    the point upon which my hopes have always rested. Of the political resurrection of that country I have never doubted. Would that
                    it were possible for me to look on with equal hope to its moral regeneration, and a reformation of its abominable religion; but
                    how this is to begin I cannot see. Even if a reformation were to begin in the very head of the Church, – in Rome itself, – which
                    it might easily be supposed to do, whenever Bonaparte makes his uncle<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Cardinal Joseph
                        Fesch (1763–1839), Archbishop of Lyon from 1802 and a noted art collector. He had served as an intermediary between France and
                        the Papacy, but was out of favour with the French government by 1812.</note> Pope, its immediate effect would be to produce a
                    schism in Spain, when the old Catholic Church would anathematise the new heresy.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">Dr. Bell’s</ref> system is likely to be introduced at Westminster and the Charter-House,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The major London public schools Westminster (Southey’s alma mater) and Charterhouse
                        (founded 1611). Westminster does not seem to have used Bell’s system, though Charterhouse did in 1813–1818.</note> as far as
                    it is applicable; that is, in its two fundamental laws of teaching everything thoroughly, and making every boy find his own level.
                    This will have the effect of abridging the term of classical education at least one half, for all of quick capacities; and of
                    making those learn well, who now learn imperfectly, and come away almost as ignorant as they went.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> desires to be remembered to you. Believe me, my dear Neville,</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yours affectionately,</salute><signed rend="indent3"> R. Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>