<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1731</idno><idno type="nines">rce3002</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 185–188 [in
                    part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1731" type="letter"><head>1731. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, [started before and continued on] <date when-iso="1810-01-09">9 January 1810</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/
                        H.M.S. Lyra/ Plymouth Dock<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 185–188 [in
                    part].</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I look daily to hear that you are superseded, &amp; to say the truth shall be glad to hear it. These tremendous
                    gales have often made me wish you back on the three-decker. As for <del>the</del> &lt;such&gt; wretched small craft &lt;as the
                        Lyra&gt;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">HMS <hi rend="ital">Lyra</hi>, a 10-gun class brig-sloop, launched in
                        1808.</note> Government had better cut them up for fire wood than keep them in commission at the expence of life which they
                    occasion.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> has accepted <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> &amp;
                    must resign <ref target="places.html#StauntonOnWye">Staunton</ref> in consequence, – now whether I told you this before or not I
                    cannot recollect, but rather think I did.</p><p rend="indent1"> Here is the great Life of Nelson sent me to review &amp; I am to have 20 guineas a sheet for doing it. By way of
                    deserving this price I have just invented a new mode of criticism, – which is to send the book to Miss Crosthwaites<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Sarah (Sally) Crosthwaite (c. 1771–1817), a member of the extensive Crosthwaite clan who
                        ran one of the two museums in Keswick, and also a mercers, drapers and grocers shop.</note> to be weighed, &amp; then
                    calculate its <del>xxxx</del> faults by the pound. It is the largest book I ever saw being actually five inches thick, <del>xx
                        xxx</del> &amp; at least one half consisting of matter which had been better away, – yet not so bad a book neither, as might
                    have been expected from Stanier Clarke. I <del>xx</del> hope to condense its whole pith into about forty pages of the
                        Quarterly.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765–1834; <title>DNB</title>) and John McArthur
                        (1755–1840; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of Admiral Lord Nelson, K.B. from his Lordship’s Manuscripts</title> (1809).
                        Reviewed by Southey alongside: John Charnock (1756–1806; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Biographical Memoirs of Lord Viscount
                            Nelson, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.; with Observations, Critical and Explanatory</title> (1806); James Harrison (d. 1847),
                            <title>The Life of Lord Nelson</title> (1806); T. O. Churchill (fl. 1800–1823), <title>The Life of Lord Viscount Nelson,
                            Duke of Bronté, &amp;c</title> (1808), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218–262. Southey's article
                        was later expanded into a full-scale <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Today I shipt off the first six sections of Kehama<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of
                            Kehama</title> (1810).</note> to <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref>. It is to be printed in quarto
                    for the sake of my dignity. I have been correcting this portion <del>xx</del> over &amp; over again, &amp; so doggedly sometimes
                    as to grow half out of humour with it, that the first proof will brighten me up again. I wished a frontispiece but was easily
                    dissuaded by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, on account of the great probability of getting a bad
                    design.</p><p rend="indent1"> The other day I told <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Herbert</ref> there was a book coming with
                    pictures, &amp; it was about Lord Nelson. – What <ref target="people.html#WilsonMrs">Wilsy’s</ref> cat? said he – &amp; greatly
                    astonished was he to find there had ever been another Yord Nelson, as he calls him, in the world. – When a warriors name finds its
                    way to fishing-smacks, ale house signs, dogs, cats &amp; tulips, – then indeed he may truly be said to be famous.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> writes me word that he has bound the American Madoc<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably the edition of <title>Madoc</title> published in Boston in 1806.</note> &amp; that it is on the road
                    with the Cyclopædia<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Abraham Rees (1743–1825; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Cyclopaedia</title> (1802–1820). Southey possessed a 45 volume set of 1819, no. 2361 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note> &amp; periodicals. – I am rather sorry he has bound it, – but he thought he was doing wisely. – So you must
                    tell me what was said on the covers. My periodicals are lessened in number by the completion of the Censura Literaria,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Samuel Egerton Brydges (1762–1837; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Censura Literaria, Containing
                            Titles, Abstracts, and Opinions of Old English Books, with Original Disquisitions, Articles of Biography, and Other
                            Literary Antiquities</title>, published in 10 volumes, 1805–1809. Southey’s copy was no. 381 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note> &amp; the demise of the Athenæum &amp; Annual.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                            <title>Athenaeum</title> (1807–1809) and <title>Annual Review</title> (1803–1809). Southey had contributed to both
                        periodicals.</note> They now consist only of – 1 Pinkertons Voyages.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">John Pinkerton
                        (1758–1826; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A General Collection of the Best and Most Interesting Voyages and Travels in All Parts
                            of the World</title> (1808–1814); no. 2335 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> 2. <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbetts</ref> State Trials.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Cobbett’s
                            Complete Collection of State Trials</title>, published in 33 volumes 1809–1826. Southey’s copy was no. 2734 in the sale
                        catalogue of his library.</note> 3 Beauties of England &amp; Wales,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John Britton
                        (1771–1857; <title>DNB</title>) and Edward Wedlake Brayley (1773–1854; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Beauties of England and
                            Wales</title>, published in 25 volumes, 1801–1815. Southey’s copy was no. 141 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note>
                    4 Medical Review, 5 M Mirror,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The London Medical Review</title> (1808-1812) and the
                            <title>Monthly Mirror</title> (1795–1811). Southey seems to have subscribed from 1807, no. 1990 in the sale catalogue of
                        his library.</note> 6 M Magazine,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Monthly Magazine</title> (1796–1843). Southey
                        had been a contributor in the past and had a set running from 1796 to 1817, no. 1989 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note> 7 Missionary Transactions, &lt;do Periodical <del>xxxxxxx</del> Accounts&gt;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Periodical Accounts of the Baptist Missionary Society</title>, 1800–1817. Southey owned a five volume
                        set, no. 2213 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> 8 Cyclopædia. 9 Hewletts Bible<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hewlett (1762–1844; <title>DNB</title>), who was publishing an edition of the Bible in monthly
                        parts.</note> &amp; 10 Quarterly Review – to which as soon as the new year<del>s</del> begins I am about to add the
                    Evangelical Magazine,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Evangelical Magazine</title> (1793–1904), an
                        inter-denominational periodical, but at this time mainly Congregationalist. Southey had a complete set covering 1811–1841, no.
                        1014 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &amp; the Edinburgh Annual Register will make up <del>xxxx</del>
                    &lt;thirteen&gt;. I wish I could afford a few more. There are about half a dozen magazines which I covet &amp; desire. I am indeed
                    getting a few other books which come out volume by volume, such as Phillips Cont. Voyages,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Richard Phillips, <title>A Collection of Modern and Contemporary Voyages and
                            Travels</title>, published in 10 volumes, starting in 1805. Southey’s copy was no. 2234 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note> the Somers Tracts which <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> gives me, &amp; which will be 14
                    quartos at three guineas each,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Scott was the editor of John, Baron Somers (1651–1716;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Collection of Scarce and Valuable Tracts</title>, published in 13 volumes from 1809–1815.
                        Southey’s copy was no. 2613 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> – The Hist. of Printing is in five three guinea 4tos
                    which I subscribe to,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Frognall Dibdin (1776–1847; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Typographical Antiquities, or, The History of Printing in England, Scotland and Ireland</title>, published in 4
                        volumes, 1810–1819. Southey’s copy was no. 905 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> – &amp; the publications of old
                    Thomas Hearne,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">An edition of the works of the antiquary Thomas Hearne (c. 1678–1735;
                            <title>DNB</title>), which began publication in 1810. Southey owned 4 volumes, no. 1299 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note> – which I subscribe to also &amp; which are to be 42 octavo volumes at 15/ each. Then I have two
                        <del>xxx</del> daily papers, (which cost me nothing) &amp; the Friend<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge’s
                            <title>The Friend</title>, published in 26 weekly instalments, 1 June 1809–15 March 1810.</note> comes once a week. – So
                    that you see Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey I have always something to look for with joyous expectation, &amp; it falls
                        <del>xxx</del> &lt;to&gt; my lot to dally with delight in the shape of a knot upon a parcel, as often as to that of any
                    private Gentleman in his Majestys dominions.</p><p rend="indent1"> By the by the Naval Chronicle<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Naval Chronicle</title> (1799–1818),
                        an annual account of navy affairs.</note> of which I have the volume for 1808 (the Register year) is a better book than I
                    expected it to be – there are some good letters there upon the state of the navy, &amp; a great deal of interesting matter. I
                    should think it a book likely to do considerable good.</p><p rend="indent1"> It would be very agreeabell to me if they were to turn you ashore in time for you to come to your old moorings
                    before I finish Lord Nelson. You would be of great use at my elbow.</p><p rend="indent1"> I do not think my Register<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was writing the historical section of
                        the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810).</note> work is more than half done, – but that is much. they
                    have only sent me four proofs, &amp; I am very glad they do not hurry me. In the last there was a broadside of bitterness against
                    Whitbread for his base apologies for Buonaparte.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey attacked the radical MP Samuel
                        Whitbread (1764–1815; <title>DNB</title>) for asserting ‘that Buonaparte, for every charge preferred against him, might show
                        that his accusers have been guilty of a parallel crime’, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1. (1810),
                        64.</note> What other effect this years history may produce upon my character Heaven knows, but it is pretty plain that it
                    will establish it for honesty &amp; plain speaking. The last proof of the History reached to page 608. </p><p rend="indent1"> I believe you are acquainted with my Fleet of kissing ships, we have lately launched a new ship, the
                    Aballeboozobanganorriboship &lt;a ten decker&gt; <del>xx</del> with which my son is exceedingly well pleased: His feet are quite
                    as they should be, &amp; he is as round as a dumplin, – the nicest kissing, &amp; sweetest-play fellow. We have now nine kisses
                    for the nine Muses, three for the Graces, Ten for the Predicaments, another half score for the Commandments. Nine &amp; Thirty for
                    the Church Articles &amp; seven for the Deadly Sins. </p><p rend="indent1"> ___</p><p><date when="1810-01-09">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 9 1810</date></p><p rend="indent1"> Yours of Xmas day has relieved me from some anxiety for I have been looking very fearfully for news of the Lyra in
                    consequence of the dreadful weather. I found on my desk the beginning of an &lt;old&gt; letter in which I <del>xx xxx</del> told
                    you of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> intended removal &amp; will here copy it. [MS torn] <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> is about 900 a year but is so expensive a situation that he does not expect to
                    be a gainer by giving up 6 for it. It is between five &amp; six miles from London, the Surry side, about ten miles from <ref target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonnes</ref>, – who no doubt rejoices more at this than any body else; –
                    whenever I go southward this will of course be my head quarters, &amp; I shall be in the habit of seeing her almost as frequently
                    &amp; familiarly as at Lisbon. He will not remove there before summer. You &amp; I will contrive to meet there one of these days,
                    &amp; take D Manuel<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">The fictitious narrator of Southey’s <title>Letters From
                            England</title> (1807).</note> with us to see all the unknown parts of London.</p><p rend="indent1"> Ld Mulgraves<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">The politician Henry Phipps, 1st Earl of Mulgrave (1755–1831;
                            <title>DNB</title>), First Lord of the Admiralty 1807–1810.</note> answer is that a Commander has already been appointed
                    to the Lyra. <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George</ref> expected to see him soon &amp; would then speak to him
                    about you. I have not much hope here, – but very great hope if ever Ld Melville gets back to the Admiralty,<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville (1742–1811; <title>DNB</title>), First Lord of the Admiralty
                        1804–1805.</note> or any person with whom <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">W Scott</ref> has interest. – No proof of
                    Kehama yet tho the copy has been gone nearly a month. The last proof of the History<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        first volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title>, published in 1810.</note> came yesterday, – except the Notes. The
                    Yankee Madoc is arrived in good binding – a handsome book, but they have done ill not to reduce the letters of the title to
                    proportion them to the smaller size of the page. – I trust you will have enjoyed <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> defence of his words against Buonoparte in the Courier.<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">In
                        Coleridge’s sixth ‘Letter on the Spaniards’, <title>Courier</title>, 21 December 1809.</note> God bless you – I live in hope
                    that you will soon be turned out to graze among the mountains. You will find your room carpeted, &amp; with a new bed-furniture
                    [MS torn] &amp; the usual kisses. </p><closer><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p>Another book of Kehama tomorrow, – the first half-dozen lines will make you admire the bare-breechd poetry that you speak of.
                        The job of transcribing <del>xxx</del> &lt;for&gt; the press is rather more than half done. I daily expect the first proof,
                        &amp; great joy it will be when it comes.Today I cut a good walking stick – a holly, – &amp; have named it in honour of <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> – the Contunder.<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">An in-joke about
                            Cottle’s lack of classical education: based on his misuse of the Latinate ‘contunder’ in <title>Alfred, an Epic Poem, in
                                Twenty-four books</title> (1800), Book 16, line 113; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 6 November 1800, <title>The
                                Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 557.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>