<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2408</idno><idno type="nines">rce3679</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 350–352 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2408" type="letter"><head>2408. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1814-04-26">26 April
                        1814</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey. R. N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helens/ Auckland <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb/>Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 350–352 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1814-04-26">April 26. 1814.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I wish you had been here when the whole news came.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Napoleon was exiled to
                        Elba under the terms of the Treaty of Fontainebleau, signed on 11 April 1814, and was given sovereignty over the island and
                        permitted to retain the title Emperor. Newspapers on 25 April 1814 carried the news that Napoleon had left for Elba and Louis
                        XVIII (1755–1824; King of France 1814–1824) was on his way to Paris.</note><ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Bedford</ref> sent me a fifth edition of the Courier (my regular one was but the second)
                    &amp; Courtenay<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Peregrine Courtenay (1782–1841; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Totnes
                        1811–1832 and Secretary of the Board of Control 1812–1828. He had previously been a civil servant at the Exchequer, where he
                        probably met Grosvenor Bedford.</note> sent me a printed bulletin, – the first I ever saw. It brought <ref target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calvert</ref> down, &amp; we drank a bottle
                    of wine with better relish than ever wine had before, for tho Calvert was a great fearer &amp; doubter all thro the contest, – his
                    opinions never in the slightest degree affected his wishes, &amp; he was as well disposed toward Buonaparte as I myself. – Now
                    that we may look onward with coolness to the consequences I see two things to be deprecated, <del>xxxx xxx xxx</del><hi rend="ital">candour</hi> &amp; <hi rend="ital">liberality</hi>, – that is to say the continuation of folly, weakness &amp;
                    want of principle, <del>to</del> which are at present known by those names. We shall probably see much irretrievable mischief done
                    by both.</p><p rend="indent1"> You have seen Calvus’s last letter in the Courier.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor had published
                            <title>Letters Addressed to Lord Liverpool: And the Parliament on the Preliminaries of Peace</title> (1814), under the
                        pseudonym ‘Calvus’. This demanded that Napoleon be deprived of all his power, preferably his life, and that France at least be
                        stripped of all territory acquired since the French Revolution. The <title>Letters</title> were modelled on Junius’s. Landor
                        had originally sent 3 of the letters to the <title>Courier</title>. He then prepared them for separate publication, adding a
                        fourth letter. The <title>Courier</title> had published part of this fourth letter on 12 January 1814.</note><ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> is the writer. I entirely agree with him that this is the time for
                    undoing the mischief which was done by the Peace of Utrecht.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Treaty of Utrecht (1713)
                        ended the long-running War of the Spanish Succession. It was widely-criticised in Britain for being too lenient to the
                        French.</note> Woefully has it been shown that France was then made too strong for the repose of Europe. She ought now to be
                    stript of Alsace Lorraine &amp; Franche-Compte. There is certainly no possible pretence for expecting that we should restore any
                    of our conquests. I am willing that it should be done, because the French colonists never will be English, &amp; it will be better
                    for them to be under their native government than ours: but for this we have a right to demand something, &amp; I would have the
                    compensation in money which <del>xx</del> should form the basis of a fund for increasing the pay of army &amp; navy upon the
                    system <del>xxx</del> which you &amp; I have so long recommended. France cannot pay at present; – the conquests should be retained
                    till she could, &amp; “no trust.”</p><p rend="indent1"> Here we shall be told of liberality; – the cry is already begun, the French know what it means. The Whitbreads
                    &amp; the Grey-Geese<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Whigs, as supporters of Samuel Whitbread (1764–1815;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Charles Grey, 2nd Earl Grey (1764–1845; Prime Minister 1830–1834; <title>DNB</title>).</note> use
                    it because it is a pretty word, &amp; as our ministers are much more likely to be flattered with being called liberal by their
                    opponents that to console themselves with the thought of being called wise by posterity, liberal I dare say they will be. We shall
                    hardly &lt;in our time&gt; feel the evil <del>xx xxx xxxx</del> which must result but we may distinctly see the good which is
                    lost.</p><p rend="indent1"><hi rend="ital">Candour</hi> is already mischievously successful. Alexander,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander I
                        (1777–1825; Tsar of Russia 1801–1825).</note> a weak tho a good man has been to breakfast with Ney,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Michel Ney (1769–1815), Marshal of France. He had played a key role in the French campaigns in the Iberian
                        peninsular in 1808–10, but in April 1814 had been instrumental in forcing Napoleon to abdicate. <title>The Times</title>, 21
                        April 1814 reported that Alexander had breakfasted with Ney on 16 April.</note> – &amp; there is not a thief ruffian &amp;
                    murderer among all those who have acted up to the full spirit of Buonapartes system, who will &lt;be&gt; hissd out of society;
                        <del>xxx</del> &lt;as for&gt; Cardinal Maury, he suffers as a Cardinal who has sinned against the Pope, &amp; as a man who if
                    he had not gone over to the wrong side would have had the most signal merits to plead <del>for his xxxxxxx</del> in behalf of the
                        Bourbons.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean-Sifrein Maury (1746–1817), Archbishop of Paris since 1810, had been
                        imprisoned in the Castel Sant’Angelo for disobeying Papal orders to surrender his functions as archbishop during the
                        Napoleonic regime. He had previously been a servant of the exiled French monarchy, acting as their ambassador to the Papal
                        court.</note> You know how earnestly I <del>xxxxxx</del> used to urge that while we were at war, we should distinguish between
                    Buonaparte &amp; the French people. The fitness of that distinction is proved by the act of deposing him &amp; <del>xx</del>
                    making peace with the world being one &amp; the same. But we must not let this rob the French army of the whole merit of their
                    conduct in his service. Certes it was B. who <hi rend="ital">sent</hi> them into Spain; but <del>it is the</del> who did the work
                    there – who were they who robbed, ravished, burnt, tortured &amp; murdered wherever they went? they were the soldiers the officers
                    &amp; &lt;the&gt; generals of the most amiable of nations. It was not Buonaparte who did all this, it was <del>xxxxxxxx</del> Jean
                    F. – or Jean B – in his own damnably appropriate designation, – &amp; it shall not be my fault if the people of Spain &amp;
                    Portugal do not admit the French to that place in their affections which used to be occupied by the Jews. They ought to be the
                    Jews of Europe; – a people politically excommunicated, &amp; never to be forgiven, &amp; above all never to be trusted.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will guess that if ever I go to Paris it must be before my history<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, eventually published 1823–1832.</note> is published. – I shall
                    therefore when when next I go to London, whenever that may be, run over &amp; take a round of five or six weeks.</p><p rend="indent1"> I receive many congratulations upon the accomplishment of my hopes &amp; expectations, &amp; am in some danger of
                    being suspected for a prophet, – a danger of which my friends the Edinburghers are quite clear. The cudgels were taken up for me
                    with good effect in the Times, &amp; I have &lt;had&gt; my last thundering Ode reprinted there to accommodate <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref>, &amp; enable him to bring my hopes &amp; predictions to the same test
                        <del>whereby I</del> to which I brought <del>them</del> &lt;his&gt;, – by comparing them with the events.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s feud with Jeffrey continued unabated. The notes to ‘Carmen Triumphale’, published in
                        the <title>Courier</title>, 8 January 1814, had attacked the personalities and politics of the <title>Edinburgh
                        Review</title>. The review of the ‘Carmen’ in <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 22 (January 1814), 447–454, retorted: ‘For our
                        own parts, when we are seriously occupied with the destinies of Europe, or of mankind, we should think very contemptibly of
                        ourselves, if we could permit the recollection of our differences with Mr Southey to intrude either into our writings or our
                        thoughts’ (452), before going on to criticise his support of the Spanish and acceptance of the Laureateship. <title>The
                            Times</title>, 7 April 1814 had printed an attack on the <title>Edinburgh</title>’s criticisms of Southey; and <title>The
                            Times,</title> 21 April 1814 reprinted the ‘Ode Written During the Negotiations with Bonaparte’, in a corrected version
                        and retitled ‘Ode; Written in January, 1814’. A short headnote again defended Southey against the criticism levelled against
                        him in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>.</note> – I shall have at him again in <hi rend="ital">more notes</hi> &lt;to
                    another ode&gt;.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Southey’s proposed – but unexecuted – ode celebrating the peace
                        of 1814.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I am in the 18 book of Roderick.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> We are all well &amp; shall be right glad to see your Lordship.
                    Huzza for marooning parties. I wish <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> were to accompany you. We must have you all
                    bag &amp; baggage when you are unhoused. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love &amp; mine &amp; so </p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you </salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>