<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1862</idno><idno type="nines">rce3133</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, RS 165.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1862" type="letter"><head>1862. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1811-02-02">2 February
                        1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>Endorsement: RS/ 2 Febry 1811<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 165<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1811-02-02">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 2. 1811</date></dateline><salute>My dear Rickman</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Thank you for your last. – How much of its matter I have profited by you will perceive, &amp; what is now left
                    untouched stands over for <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdetts</ref> business in 1810.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had used documents relating to the politician Sir Francis Burdett and sent to him by Rickman, for the
                        latest volume of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> that dealt with events in 1809. He had reserved some for the
                        volume that would cover 1810 – an exciting year for Burdett as he was committed to prison by the House of Commons on 5 April
                        1810 for breach of privilege. He barricaded himself into his house until 9 April and the resultant riots in London caused
                        great concern in government circles.</note> I am in the midst of the subject, &amp; <hi rend="ital">ni fallor</hi><note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘if I err not’.</note> am handling it well.</p><p rend="indent1"> L Goldsmid is ordered upon your advice. His <hi rend="ital">book</hi> is at hand – a most rascally one, so rascally
                    that I had fully believed he was employed by Buonaparte to over-act Anti-Gallicism, &amp; serve him by uttering calumnies too
                    outrageous to be believed.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lewis Goldsmith (c. 1763/4–1846; <title>DNB</title>). His
                            <title>The Secret History of the Cabinet of Bonaparte</title> (1810) argued that Britain could never make a secure peace
                        with Napoleon. Goldsmith’s narrative combined accurate information with wild allegations, including atrocity stories and tales
                        of sexual misconduct. It was a bestseller, going into 6 editions by 1811.</note><ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> assured <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>
                    that this fellow had a sort of devilish acuteness in him, – I cannot perceive one trace of it in his book. His newspaper<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Goldsmith had launched a Sunday newspaper, the <title>Anti-Gallican Monitor</title>, earlier
                        in 1811. His backers possibly included supporters of the exiled French monarchy and the British government.</note> seems to
                        <del>xxx</del> place him in the same scale of morals &amp; utility with the Bow street officers,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first professional London police force, founded by the author and magistrate Henry Fielding (1707–1754;
                            <title>DNB</title>) in 1749.</note> – useful subjects tho greater rascals than those whom they hang. – How is it that the
                    Country Newspapers which in Pitts time<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Pitt (1759–1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime
                        Minister 1783–1801, 1804–1806.</note> were all Pittite, are now as universally <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdettite</ref>? This is an evil sign. – Thank you about the Chronicle,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Presumably
                        the London newspaper the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>.</note> – when there appears any thing with a mark of blacker
                    damnation about it, send me the paper.</p><p rend="indent1"> I apprehend the French lines before Cadiz are strong, or some attack would have been made upon them while we had a
                    strong force there. Still the pokers &amp; Tongs have <del>xx</del> not been employed as they should be. It would have been a good
                    plan to have sent out a detachment of yellow-fever-men on purpose to be made prisoners. I am quite of Pasleys<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Charles William Pasley (1780–1861; <title>DNB</title>), who had served in the British army in
                        Spain in 1808 and 1809. His <title>Essay on the Military Policy and Institutions of the British Empire</title> (London, 1810),
                        p. 241, argued that the British should have demanded ‘the chief command of every combined army in Spain’.</note> opinion about
                    our directing the Spaniards. A most essential measure would be to send officers to Coruna &amp; discipline an army in Galicia. Sir
                    Robert Wilson is the fit man to be employed. In six weeks he raised his legion &amp; took the field with them at the very time
                    when Moore began to run away. –<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Robert Wilson (1777–1849; <title>DNB</title>),
                        commander of the Loyal Lusitanian Legion, raised from Portuguese refugees and officered by British soldiers. He was credited
                        with being the first to demonstrate that Portuguese recruits could be trained and organised into successful fighting units.
                        Wilson served in the Peninsular in 1808–1809 and, after the defeat and death of Sir John Moore (1761–1809; <title>DNB</title>)
                        at Corunna, had held open vital communication lines and kept the French armies in check.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> says ‘any ministry must recall our troops from Spain.” – this then is plainly
                    the <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Grenville</ref> plan. I am sure it cannot be <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Ld
                        Hollands</ref>. God send the King<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738–1820; King of the United Kingdom
                        1760–1820; <title>DNB</title>). His mental health had collapsed again in October 1810 and he was incapable of conducting
                        public business. The question of a regency for him was hotly-debated as it was believed that his heir and the natural choice
                        as regent, George, Prince of Wales (1762–1830; Prince Regent 1811–1820; King of the United Kingdom as George IV 1820–1830),
                        favoured opposition politicians.</note> well again &amp; give him a long lease of life to keep these wretches out!</p><closer><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> The inclosed per twopenny.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>