<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2458</idno><idno type="nines">rce3729</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously  published: Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London
                        and New York, 1965), II, pp. 101–103.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2458" type="letter"><head>2458. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas
                    Southey</ref>, <date when="1814-07-10">10–14 July 1814</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey.
                        R. N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helens/ Auckland <lb/>Postmark: KESWICK/ 298
                        <lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London
                        and New York, 1965), II, pp. 101–103.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1814-07-10">Sunday evening. 10 July 1814.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> In writing a poem a man may be as much out in his estimates as in
                    building a house. I have written like a lion, if you know how lions write, ever
                    since you left us.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was
                        hurrying to complete <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                        (1814).</note> On the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of June the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> section was finished, &amp; that same evening the first memoranda
                    for the Odes<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Congratulatory
                            Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness The Prince Regent, His Imperial Majesty
                            The Emperor of Russia, and His Majesty the King of Prussia</title>
                        (1814).</note> were made in the manner which you may remember – those odes
                    with the interruptions of Miss Hutchinson &amp; the Frenchman,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wordsworth’s sister-in-law, Sarah
                        Hutchinson (1775–1835): and the French officer, Eustace Baudouin (b. c.
                        1792). He served in the army of Louis Gabriel Suchet, 1st Duc d’Albufera
                        (1770–1826), Marshal of France, and saw action at the first siege of
                        Tarragona, 1811. In the same year he was captured by the guerilla army of
                        Joaquin Cuevas Ibanez y de Valonga, Baron de Eroles (1784–1825). Baudouin
                        spent time in Britain as a prisoner of war, and at one point was held at
                        Oswestry, in Shropshire. On his release, he visited the Wordsworths before
                        returning to France. Baudouin had made contact with Wordsworth in 1812 via
                        mutual acquaintances: his brother was engaged to Caroline (1792–1862),
                        daughter of Wordsworth and Annette Vallon (1766–1841). Caroline and Jean
                        Baptiste Baudouin (b. c. 1780) married in February 1816. Southey travelled
                        to France and visited them and their infant daughter in 1817, when he also
                        renewed his acquaintance with Eustace Baudouin; see Southey to Edith
                        Southey, 17 May 1817.</note> detained me from the greater work till the
                        15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> on which day I began the 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>
                    book, – &amp; I am now advanced as far as the 331<hi rend="sup">st</hi> line of
                    the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> – It seems scarcely possible that there can be more
                    than a hundred more requird to compleat it, &amp; I go to bed in full hope that
                    when I shall lie down tomorrow, it will be finished, &amp; then O be joyful<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Psalm</title> 100, line
                        1.</note> St Helens Auckland &amp; <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta
                        Hall</ref> – being I believe <hi rend="ital">all the lands</hi> upon which I
                    am entitled to call on this occasion. The whole extent of the poem will be
                    somewhat more than 6800 lines, – I did not think it would have exceeded 5000.
                    Many parts of these <del>conclude</del> latter books are as good as anything I
                    can ever hope to produce. Orelio even disputes the preference with Nobs in my
                        affections.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Orelio was Roderick’s
                        horse in <title>Roderick, the last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 25;
                        Nobs was Dr Dove’s horse in <title>The Doctor</title>
                    (1834–1847).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I am still too full of what remains to be done to know how I
                    shall feel when my mind has laid down its burthen. But <del>xxxx</del> my
                    shoulders have been so long used to it that I shall probably soon feel the
                        <del>xxxx</del> want of another to keep them warm. My next undertaking in
                    verse however will be upon a <del>xx</del> much smaller scale “A Tale of
                        Paraguay”,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Tale of
                            Paraguay</title> (1825). Southey’s source was Martin Dobrizhoffer
                        (1717–1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus</title> (1783–1784).</note> –
                    which will hardly exceed 1000 lines the circumstances which are true, are very
                    few, very simple, but exceedingly curious &amp; impressive. There is little or
                    no passion in it. The character of the poem will be descriptive &amp; thoughtful
                    &amp; the feeling melancholy but in no degree painful. – The story has lain
                    among my preexistences for seven years. It will most probably be written in
                    rhyme, for I am perfectly aware of the danger of repeating myself, &amp;
                    contracting a mannerism in pursuing one key too long.</p><p><date when="1814-07-14">Thursday 14 July.</date></p><p rend="indent1">Monday came &amp; I continued at my task, still writing like a
                    Lion, – it was like going up a mountain, the termination seemed to recede as I
                    advanced. So I was still at it on Tuesday middleday, when in came a Laker to
                    interrupt me. I was very glad to see him – first because my head was too full of
                    the subject &amp; yet nothing but such an interruption could have called me off
                    when the end was so near, – &amp; secondly because he was a person &lt;to&gt;
                    whom I was very glad to have an opportunity of showing some civility: – a <ref target="people.html#GoodenJames">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gooden</ref> who
                    collected books &amp; manuscripts in Brazil, for the purpose of lending them to
                    me. He came from Penrith <del>for the xx xx</del> purposely to see me, &amp; I
                    made him stay over the next day, showing him all my treasures, which none but
                    those who know something about Portugal &amp; its history &amp; literature can
                    properly estimate. This morning I went again to work, &amp; just at dinner time
                    finished a poem which was begun 2 December 1809. The last book has extended to
                    580 lines, &amp; the whole work to 7000, <del>xxx</del> some twenty more or
                    less. – Hourra! your Serene Highness! – O be joyful S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                    Helens Auckland &amp; <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Having some 700 lines to transcribe my head is not compleatly
                    discharged of the subject, so that it will pass off gradually. Other [MS torn]
                    it would leave <del>something like</del> a strange sort of feeling for during
                    the last six months it has been the chief object of my thoughts. I do not feel
                    exactly as Gibbon<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Gibbon
                        (1737–1794; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the Decline and Fall
                            of the Roman Empire</title> (1776–1788).</note> did, who knew that it
                    was impossible for him ever to execute <del>xxxx</del> &lt;another&gt; work of
                    equal magnitude with his great history; – <del>but I</del> for I neither want
                    subjects nor inclination for fresh attempts. But this poem has been 4 ½ years in
                    hand, &amp; had been thought of as many years before it was begun: &amp; it is
                    impossible not to feel how very doubtful it is whether I may ever again compleat
                        <del>a poem</del> &lt;one&gt; of equal extent, – or <del>xx xx</del> of
                    equal merit, – tho never at any part of my life better disposed for it in will
                    or in power than at the present time.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> Love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> – &amp; God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p>The parcel is not arrivd, but may perhaps make its appearance to night</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>