<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1778</idno><idno type="nines">rce3049</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of
                        Scotland, MS 3879.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 284–287.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1778" type="letter"><head>1778. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter
                        Scott</ref>, <date when="1810-05-11">11 May 1810</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Scott Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Edinburgh<lb/>Stamped: Durham 263<lb/>Postmark: [partial] MY/
                        15<lb/>Seal: [partial] <lb/>Watermark: shield/ 1805/ T
                        BOTTING<lb/>Endorsement: R. Southey/ 11 May 1810<lb/>MS: National Library of
                        Scotland, MS 3879<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 284–287.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName>Durham.</placeName></address><date when="1810-05-11">May 11. 1810</date></dateline><salute>My dear Scott</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Yesterday evening on my return from the Race Ground<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been attending the race meeting
                        at Newcastle, particularly to observe the famous Long Main cock
                        fight.</note> I found your Poem<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Scott’s <title>The Lady of the Lake</title> (1810). It sold over 20,000
                        copies in the year of its publication.</note> lying on the table, – a
                    provoking engagement called me from it for two or three hours, but
                    notwithstanding this, &amp; my obstinate habit of getting early to bed, I did
                    not go to rest till I had finished the book. Every readers first thought, when
                    he begins to think at all, will be to compare you with yourself, – if I may
                    judge from my own feelings the Lady will be a greater favourite than either of
                    her elder brethren.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Lay of
                            the Last Minstrel</title> (1805) and <title>Marmion</title>
                        (1808).</note> There is in all the same skilful inscrutability of story till
                    the artist is pleased to touch the spring which lays the whole
                        <del>mechanism</del> machine open, – but while <del>on</del> the plot is
                        <del>xxx</del> thus well wound up in the <del>xxxxx</del> &lt;new poem&gt; I
                    think the narrative is more uniformly perspicuous than in the two former
                        <del>poems</del>. There is in all <del>the same</del> &lt;a&gt; like
                    originality &amp; beauty of circumstances, – I am not willing to admit that some
                    of the situations in the Lay &amp; Marmion <hi rend="ital">can</hi> be outdone,
                    – &amp; if I thought they <hi rend="ital">were</hi> outdone last night, &amp;
                    still incline to think so, it is probably because new impressions are more vivid
                    than the strongest recollection.</p><p rend="indent1"> I wished most of the songs<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Lady of the Lake</title> embeds a series of separate lyrics
                        and ballads (as well as tales and descriptive set pieces) into the
                        overarching framework of the poem.</note> away <del>when</del> on the first
                    perusal – on recurring to them I was glad they were there; – yet whenever they
                    interrupt the narrative without in any way tending to carry on the business of
                    the story, my admiration of the things themselves does not prevent me from
                    thinking them misplaced. – your title is likely to be a popular one, – &amp; for
                    that very reason I wish it had not been chosen. Of course it led me to expect
                    some tale of Merlin, <del>&amp;</del> &lt;or&gt; King Arthurs days, – but what
                        <del>it</del> is of <del>some</del> &lt;real&gt; consequence to one who
                    loves old lays is that whenever hereafter the Lady of the Lake will be
                    mentioned, most readers will suppose <del>xxxx</del> your Ellen is
                        intended,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. readers will from
                        henceforth think of Ellen Douglas, heroine of Scott’s poem, as the ‘Lady of
                        the Lake’, and not the character from Arthurian legend, who fell in love
                        with Lancelot.</note> – &amp; in this way a sort of offence against
                    antiquity has been committed. This is something in the manner of Momus’s
                        criticism<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. unfair criticism,
                        in the spirit of Momus, the Greek god of censure, satire and mockery.</note>
                    – to find fault with the trinkets of the Lady &amp; with her name. But I
                    heartily give you joy of the poem &amp; congratulate you with perfect confidence
                    upon the success which you have a right to expect, which you deserve, &amp;
                    which you will find. – The portrait seems more like the more I look at it, –
                    &amp; my friend Camp is &lt;now&gt; doubly immortalized.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott’s favourite dog was his bull-terrier, named Camp,
                        who died in 1809. He appeared in a portrait of Scott by James Saxon (fl.
                        1795–1828) painted in 1805, which was used as the basis for the frontispiece
                        engraving of Scott in <title>The Lady of the Lake</title>.</note> This
                    reminds me of the dog in the poem, – an incident so fine that it bears as well
                    as courts <del>xx</del> comparison with one of the most affecting passages in
                        Homer.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Stumah (Faithful), a dog
                        who stands guard over the corpse of his master; see <title>Lady of the
                            Lake</title> (Edinburgh, 1810), p. 119. The comparison is with the
                            <title>Odyssey</title>’s portrayal of Argos, the loyal hound who
                        recognises his master, Odysseus, on his return to Ithaca.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> was instructed to send you
                    my Brazil.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of
                        Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810).</note> I hope to get a
                    long spell at the concluding volume<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey, in fact, still had two volumes of his Brazilian history to write:
                        these were published in 1817 and 1819, respectively.</note> before it is
                        <del>xxxx</del> necessary to fall seriously to work upon the second
                        Register.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register for 1809</title> (1811).</note> What you will think of
                        Kehama<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of
                            Kehama</title> (1810)</note>. I am not quite sure, – of what the public
                    will think I can have &amp; never have had the slightest doubt. No subject could
                    have been devised more remote from human sympathies, &amp; there are &lt;so&gt;
                    few persons who are capable of standing aloof from them, that the subject must
                    be admitted to have been improvidently chosen, – if in chusing it I had had any
                    other motive than that of pleasing myself, &amp; some half-a dozen others.
                        <del>xxxx</del> If it had been my intention to provoke censure I could not
                    have done it more effectually, – for without intending any innovation,
                        <del>&amp;</del> or being at first sensible of any I have fallen into a
                    style of versification <del>xxxx</del> as unusual as <del>xxx</del> the
                    groundwork of the story. With this however I am well satisfied. It seems to me
                    to unite the powers of rhyme &amp; blank verse better than has ever before been
                    done. – I have written the first canto of Pelayo,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early incarnation of what became <title>Roderick,
                            the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> in blank verse, &amp;
                    without machinery. This promises to be a striking poem, &amp; if it were ready
                    now might perhaps in some degree be a useful one.</p><p rend="indent1"> The metre of the Lady is to me less agreable than the more varied
                    measure; –there is an advantage in writing in a metre to which <del>you h</del>
                    one has been little accustomed; it necessarily induces <del>xxxx</del> a
                    &lt;certain&gt; change of style, – &amp; this <del>xxx xxx</del> enables the
                    writer to clothe his old conceptions in so different a garb that they appear new
                    even to himself. The alteration which you have made is not sufficiently great to
                    obtain this advantage, &amp; <del>variety is sacrificed without acquiring</del>
                    there is a loss of variety, from which I should have predicted a loss of freedom
                    &amp; a loss of power. This however is amply confuted by the poem, which
                    certainly <del>was</del> is never deficient either in force or freedom.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall return home in the course of a fortnight, – a short
                    interval of idleness makes me feel impatient to get once more to my books &amp;
                    my desk.</p><p rend="indent1"> pray remember me to <ref target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">Mrs Scott</ref> &amp;
                    believe me</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> very affectionately yours</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>