<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2096</idno><idno type="nines">rce3367</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, RS 186.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 341–344 [in
                        part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2096" type="letter"><head>2096. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1812-05-18">18 May
                        1812</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>Endorsement: RS/ 18 May/ 1812<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 186<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 341–344 [in
                        part].</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1812-05-18">Monday. May 18. 1812.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Rickman</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The fate of poor <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> has made me quite unhappy ever since I
                    heard of it, not merely from the shock &amp; the private misery which it is impossible to put out of mind, but from the whole
                    train of evils to which this is but the beginning.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Perceval was assassinated on 11 May
                        1812.</note> I would fain have believed the report that <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Abbott</ref><note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        See Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 14-[15] May 1812, Letter 2094.</note> was to take his place in the H. of Commons, – because if he could have found tongue, I
                    knew where whatever &lt;else&gt; might have been wanting was to be found. But it was not likely that he should quit a better
                    situation for one of so much anxiety &amp; labour.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">Wellesley</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> I doubt not
                    ratted upon the Cath. question because they expected the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> upon that
                    ground would eject <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> &amp; then they should have a better chance than the
                        <hi rend="ital">Early Friends</hi>. If they come in, as I fear they will, we may have the war carried on, but we shall have
                    Catholick concessions, – after which the Church property is not worth seven years purchase. They will sell the tythes, – the next
                    step will be to put up the Establishment <del>xxx situation</del> &lt;to sale&gt; in the way of contracts, the minds of the people
                    (which God knows need no farther poison,) will then be totally unsettled, – &amp; the ship will part from her last cable, on a lee
                    shore <del>xx</del> in the height of the storm.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Perceval’s death produced some uncertainty
                        about his successor and the Cabinet’s attitude to Catholic Emancipation. Robert Banks Jenkinson, 2nd Earl of Liverpool
                        (1770–1828; Prime Minister 1812–1827; <title>DNB</title>), was finally confirmed as Prime Minister on 8 June 1812. His Cabinet
                        did not include either Wellesley or Canning and took a ‘neutral’ attitude on Catholic Emancipation.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> At this moment the Army is the single plank between us &amp; destruction, &amp; <del>no</del> I believe the only
                    thing doubtful is whether we shall a military despotism <hi rend="ital">before</hi> we go thro the horrors of a <hi rend="ital">Bellum servile</hi>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. a slave war.</note> – or <hi rend="ital">after</hi> it.
                    This I am certain of, that nothing but an immediate suspension of the liberty of debate &amp; the liberty of the press can
                    preserve us. Were I minister I would instantly suspend the Habeas Corpus,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        long-standing legal principle that anyone imprisoned must be brought to trial.</note> &amp; have <del>x</del> every Jacobine
                    Journalist confined, so that it should not be possible for them to continue their treasonable vocation. There they should stay
                    till it would be safe to let them out, which it might be in some seven years. I would clear the Gallery whenever one of the
                    agitators rose to speak: &amp; if the speech were printed I would teach him <del>his p</del> that his privilege of attempting to
                    excite rebellion did not extend beyond the walls of Parliament; – that he might talk treason to those walls as long as he pleased,
                    – but that if he printed <del>it</del> &lt;treason&gt;, he was then amenable to the vengeance of his country.</p><p rend="indent1"> I did not <hi rend="ital">forget</hi> the main question about reading. – One month suffices for a <del>xxxx
                        xxxxxx</del> dozen or a score pair of ears in the <del>p</del> tap rooms &amp; pot houses, where <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref> &amp; Hunt<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The radical Henry ‘Orator’ Hunt
                        (1773–1835; <title>DNB</title>).</note> are read as the Evangelists of the populace. There is no way of securing the people
                    against this sort of poison but by the old receipt of Mithridates,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mithridates VI, King of
                        Pontus (132–63 BC; reigned 123–72 BC), who swallowed small doses of poison to build up immunity.</note> – dieting them from
                    their childhood with antidotes, &amp; making them as ready to die for their church &amp; state as the Spaniards. We are beginning
                    to attempt this when it is <del>xxx</del> too late. A judicial <del>xx</del> fatuity seems to have <del>fallen</del> been sent
                    among us, – <del>we have one set of op</del> Romanists, Sectarians of every <del>kind</del> &lt;description&gt;, your
                    Liberality-men, &amp; your Philosophers of every kind, &amp; of every degree of folly &amp; emptiness, are united for the blessed
                    purpose of plucking up old principles by the roots, – each <del>with</del> &lt;for&gt; their own separate ends, but all sure of
                    meeting with the same end if they are successful. We who see this <del>xx</del> danger have no power to prevent it, &amp; they who
                    have the power cannot be made to see it. – I think sometimes <del>that</del> it is not without good reason that I take so especial
                    an interest in the affairs of Spain, – that country may be <del>free when I shall no longer be able to live in this</del> open to
                    me &amp; my children when we shall no longer be able to live in this.</p><p rend="indent1"> This is a melancholy strain. We must however work the ship till she sinks, &amp; a vigorous minister <del>xx</del>
                    might take advantage of the feelings of the sound part of the country at this moment, &amp; the avowal which the <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdettites</ref> have made – for strong measures of prevention &amp; vengeance. The greatest
                    immediate danger <del>it</del> is from the army, – if the <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdettites</ref> had not
                        <del>xxxx</del> luckily <del>xxxx</del> so often insulted &amp; abused them, that damnable business of flogging would at this
                    moment turn the scale.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The flogging of British soldiers was intensely controversial.
                        Cobbett spent two years in prison in 1810–1812 for denouncing the flogging of some militiamen who protested about deductions
                        from their pay.</note> I am desirous that means should be taken of winning their attachment, – the best way of securing their
                    obedience, – by the institution of honorary rewards; <del>&amp;</del> increase of pay with length of service, &amp; certain
                    provision after a certain number of years. By such measures they might be <del>xxxx</del> secured, – I would give the poor
                    gratuitous education in parochial schools, – a boon which all among them who care for their children, would rightly estimate, –
                    &amp; if the work of coercion kept pace with that of conciliation we might hold on till our battle in Spain <del>f</del> ended in
                    the <del>ruin of</del> overthrow of the enemy. But alas where is the Dictator who <del>has cour</del> is to save the
                    Commonwealth?</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> had a character which was worth as much as his talents. The only
                    statesman who has this advantage in any approaching degree is Ld Sidmouth,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The former
                        Prime Minister (1801–1804), Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757–1844; <title>DNB</title>), who became Home Secretary
                        1812–1822.</note> but he wants those abilities which in <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">P.</ref> seemd always to
                    grow according to the measure of the occasion. Yet he would be the best head of a ministry for the weight which his good
                    intentions would give him. Vansittart would do for Ch. of Exc.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicolas Vansittart, 1st
                        Baron Bexley (1766–1851; <title>DNB</title>) became Chancellor of the Exchequer on 20 May 1812.</note> If there were any other
                    efficient minister in the Commons. There is Sir J. Mackintosh<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> On his return to Britain
                        from India in 1811, the writer and politician Sir James Mackintosh (1765–1832; <title>DNB</title>) had been courted by
                        Perceval and the Tories. He was elected to Parliament in 1813 as MP for Nairn and became a leading spokesman for the
                        Whigs.</note><del>to be</del> &lt;upon sale,&gt;<del> but whose</del> &lt;<del>would be&gt; tongue &amp; talents &lt;brain xxxxxx&gt; may be
                        worth taking xxxx xxxxxx the</del> draw<del>back of xxxx all the rest</del> – the carcase is in bad odour, but the tongue
                    &amp; the brains might be worth a high price.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am going to write upon the French Revolution for the Q. R.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> A review of
                            <title>Biographie Moderne: Lives of Remarkable Characters who have Distinguished themselves from the Commencement of the
                            French Revolution to the Present Time</title> (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (June 1812), 412–438.</note> a
                    well-timed subject, – the evil is that it is writing to those readers <del>only</del> who are in the main of the same way of
                    thinking. Our contemporaries read not <del>for</del> &lt;in&gt; <del>xxxxx</del> &lt;hope&gt; of being instructed, but to have
                    their own opinions flattered. – <del>xxx if you</del> cannot &lt;you&gt; persuade some body to run the risque of being murdered
                    for closing the gallery when Burdett speaks? Your county member Fuller would be an exceedingly proper subject, – <del>xxxxxx</del>
                    he does not want courage, &amp; has a sort of <del>mob</del> credit &lt;with the mob&gt; <del>x</del> for his fluent honesty!<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The politician and eccentric John (‘Mad Jack’) Fuller (1757–1834; <title>DNB</title>),
                        county member for Sussex 1801–1812. He was renowned for his intemperate and often ridiculous interventions in debates. For
                        example, in a debate on the slave trade, 30 May 1804, he tried to persuade auditors that the living conditions of slaves on
                        plantations were superior to that of the labouring-poor in Britain. (Fuller’s vast wealth owed much to his estates in the West
                        Indies.) On 27 February 1810 he was forcefully ejected from the House of Commons for drunken and rowdy conduct. He spent two
                        days in custody, apologised to the House and was reprimanded. Fuller consistently proclaimed his independence and attacked
                        sinecures and other abuses. He retired from parliament at the dissolution in 1812. He devoted his remaining years to his other
                        interests: patronage of science and the arts, and folly building.</note> If they should murder him you know the gallery would
                    of course be closed for ever more, &amp; he would become the Decius of our <del>Parliament</del> history.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Publius Decius Mus was the name of three generations of Roman consuls (in 340, 312 and 279 BC). In legend all
                        ‘devoted’ themselves on the field of battle, an act by which a commander deliberately courted death whilst praying to the gods
                        for victory, in order to win the day for the Romans.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I want to furnish your Lobby with a statue of <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref>, &amp; have
                    sent <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> to <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>
                    in hope that it may be attempted.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 16 May 1812.
                        No statue of Perceval was built in the Lobby of the House of Commons.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I am in great odour at Cadiz. The (Zaragozan) Countess of Bureta<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> María de
                        la Consolación Azlor y Villavicencio (1775–1814), a Spanish aristocrat who took an active role in the two sieges of Zaragoza
                        in 1808–1809.</note> has written me a letter. – Thank the <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Capitaneus</ref> for me. I
                    have not heart at this time to reply to him about his klinkers<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Robert Southey to
                        James Burney, 19 January 1812, Letter 2019. Burney wished to discuss Dutch colonial history.</note> &amp; vowels &amp; bowels
                    as I should wish.</p><closer><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>