<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2585</idno><idno type="nines">rce3856</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously 
                        published: Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 401–404.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2585" type="letter"><head>2585. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1815-04-10">10 April 1815</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/
                            Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey. R. N. / S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helens/ Auckland <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb/>Previously
                        published: Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 401–404.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1815-04-10">10 April. 1815</date></dateline><salute>My Lord Imperaunce</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> As people may <hi rend="ital">bekla’agen</hi><note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘pity’.</note> themselves so methinks they may congratulate themselves also,
                    &amp; therefore I never write mere letters of congratulation or of condolence. There could be no occasion to tell you that I was glad to hear <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> was safe, &amp; that the new comeling had proved to be of the more worthy gender,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom Southey’s first son,
                        Herbert Castle Southey (1815–1865) had just been born.</note> – because you knew it already. Moreover I am not fond of consuming ink unnecessarily, my inevitable consumption
                        <del>occasion</del> compelling me to replenish the ink stand more often than is agreable. – You do well in <hi rend="ital">castling</hi> your boys – &amp; if you christen the
                    next Bernard, it may serve as a reason (for want of a better) why he should represent a neighbouring town in parliament hereafter.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Barnard Castle in Co. Durham.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I shall come to you as soon as I am a free man; that is to say as soon as this Quarters work is performed, on the performance of which my next half-yearly payments
                    depend. There will be two long articles, both well timed. The first upon Buonapartes expedition to Egypt.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacques François Miot
                        (1779–1858), <title>Mémoires pour servir à l’Histoire des Expéditions en Egypte et en Syrie</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 1–55.</note> The
                    second edition of a French history first published ten years ago gives occasion for this, – because it contains the details of the Jaffa massacre by the author who was an eye
                        witness.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The rape and murder by French troops of the population of Jaffa after the city fell on 3 March 1799. For Miot’s first-hand
                        account, <title>Mémoires pour servir à l’Histoire des Expéditions en Egypte et en Syrie</title> (Paris, 1814), pp. 140–148.</note> Half this article is done. There are some
                    very <del>xx</del> impressive circumstances in it: – none more so than the fact mentioned by a French writer that when Buonaparte travelled across the desert <del>xxx xx</del> to
                    Suez the nights being as piercingly cold as the days were intolerably hot &amp; nothing else which was combustable to be found, <del>xx xx</del> a fire was made to warm him &amp;
                    his staff of the bones &amp; dry bodies with which the way across the desert is strewn!<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey mentioned this anecdote in
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 23. His source was Dominique Jean Larrey (1766–1842), <title>Memoirs of Military Surgery, and Campaigns of the French
                            Armies</title> 2 vols (1814), I, pp. 154–155.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The other article is upon a catchpenny, or rather catchshilling Life of <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> which I have only
                    begun, &amp; for which I am to be paid the ridiculous price of 100£.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed George Elliott (dates unknown), <title>The Life of
                            the Most Noble Arthur Duke of Wellington, from the Period of his first Achievements in India, down to his Invasion of France, and the Peace of Paris in 1814</title> (1814),
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 215–275. He went on to review a further series of books relating to Wellington in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13
                        (July 1815), 448–526.</note> As soon as these jobs are off my hands, for which six weeks may be allowed, I shall visit you.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is mournful to perceive the imbecillity &amp; cowardice of Ministers at this time. There is a peace party in the Cabinet! including I suspect <ref target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lord Liverpool</ref>: whom it is said Ld Castlereagh<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Stewart, Viscount Castlereagh
                        (1769–1822; <title>DNB</title>), Foreign Secretary 1812–1822.</note> would willingly turn out upon this quarrel. Todays paper sufficiently shows the difference of their temper.
                    But with whom can Castlereagh ally himself? As for the <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Grenvilles</ref> – I have a letter from <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, which as it was written from Dropmore<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dropmore House in Buckinghamshire, the home of Lord Grenville.</note> may
                    certainly be understood as speaking the exact sentiments of Giant Despair.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> A figure in John Bunyan (1628–1688; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Pilgrim’s Progress</title> (1678). Southey used the name to describe the pessimistic <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord Grenville</ref>.</note> They know
                    that war is inevitable, &amp; that at this time it ought not to be avoided if it could: but they believe that it cannot be carried on more than two years without incurring a
                    national bankruptcy, &amp; they congratulate themselves that they are not in power at a time when they think no vigour &amp; no talents could save an Administration from ruin &amp;
                    disgrace! – I lose all patience when I hear such nonsense as this; &amp; am vexed when I see <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> worrying the ministry by idle
                    recurrances to what has been, instead of coming forward with the manly profession of what his own heart &amp; intellect tell him, that War is the only path of safety: &amp; that
                    vigorous war must be succesful.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall print my Inscriptions<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s series of Inscriptions on the Peninsular War. Only 18 of the projected 30 poems
                        were completed and they were not collected together until they were published in <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837–1838), III, pp. 122–156.</note> as soon as
                    they are finished &amp; I am taking them seriously in hand. There are now ten written, – being about a third of the proposed series: &amp; I shall probably add an Ode to the
                    British people: &amp; perhaps one to Buonaparte himself.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> These two poems were not written.</note> Think of the wretch turning round to
                    prate of liberty, courting the Jacobines, &amp; abolishing the Slave Trade<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> During the ‘Hundred Days’ Napoleon gave France a
                        Constitution, with a Chamber of Peers, elected Chamber of Representatives and a guarantee of freedom of the Press. This ‘Acte Additionel’ to the original Bonapartist regime was
                        approved by a plebiscite. He also definitely and finally abolished the French slave trade.</note> – he who tortured and murdered Toussaint!<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francois-Dominique Toussaint-Louverture (1743–1803), leader of the slave rebellion in Haiti; effective ruler of the country 1795–1802 and of the whole
                        island of Hispaniola 1801–1802. Arrested by the French army in 1802 and died in prison in France.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> If we had a more decided spirit in the Cabinet I should entirely agree with you, that war is better now than some years later. The last work was left most wickedly
                    incomplete &amp; what has now occurred is a memorable lesson that no policy can be sound in which the principles of justice are for a moment set aside: Buonaparte &amp; the
                    Marshals to the Gallows – the rest of the army to Siberia &amp; Cayenne: there should be nothing short of this. And if Paris be burnt in the conflict, I for one shall acknowledge
                    the hand of righteous Retribution. </p><p rend="indent1"> The voice of the country is for war: the better part feel that we have in honour &amp; in self-preservation &amp; in duty no other course: the farmers have an eye to
                    their corn, &amp; the landholders to their rents; &amp; the merchants also to their direct interests, which require that France should not rival them in <del>xxx</del>
                    manufactures. But Buonaparte has many friends &amp; they are like himself, active in mischief.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have found out another opus for you when you have compleated the West Indies.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom Southey’s <title>Chronological
                            History of the West Indies</title> (1827).</note> – By the by Beatsons Military Memoirs (or some such title) is likely to be of use to you.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Beatson (1741–1818; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Naval and Military Memoirs of Great Britain, from the year 1727 to the present time</title>
                        (1790).</note> I think it must be in the Newcastle Library, being a modern book. The new opus would require that you should learn Latin (tho it is not absolutely indispensable)
                    – but this is so much the better. I will write concerning it in my next. – Here is hardly room to add <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> congratulation to
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> – which yet I must not forget – God bless you. RS.</p></div></body></text></TEI>