<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1879</idno><idno type="nines">rce3150</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, RS 168.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1879" type="letter"><head>1879. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1811-03-04">4 March
                        1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>Endorsement: RS./ 4 March 1811<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 168<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Rickman </salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The spirit moves me very strongly to throw all your overflowing hints into the form of a pamphlett, keeping the
                    secret perfectly close between you &amp; I &amp; the publisher, so that it might have all the advantage of ‘whose can it be?’ to
                    further its circulation &amp; sale. While I had all the freedom which arises from writing <del>anonymously</del> &lt;unknown as
                    well as unnamed.&gt; <del>The best xxx</del> &lt;It might be in the&gt; shape <del>must be that</del> of a letter to <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref>, showing in what manner he might become the greatest minister of any age
                    or country, &amp; thus every thing connected with the improvement of the British Empire might fitly be introduced, home &amp;
                    foreign politics, – the extirpation of the French language in our conquered colonies, – Ireland &amp;c – &amp; here we would
                    advertise for our party of Englishmen, – which I have not been able to do in the reviewal. Pasley <del>was</del> &lt;is&gt; too
                    full of matter to leave room for much addition after I had gone through his arguments. There will be a thundering conclusion –
                    &amp; I have knocked the husbanding politicians fairly on the head by the two grand illustrations of this system – in husbanding
                        <hi rend="ital">money</hi>, – by the Greeks of Constantinople, – &amp; <hi rend="ital">men</hi> by Prussia. Then comes our
                    friend the <hi rend="ital">Yogue</hi> to compleat the picture.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Charles William Pasley
                        (1780–1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Essay on the Military Policy and Institutions of the British Empire</title> (1810).
                        Southey’s review (which Rickman had assisted him with) was deemed by <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> to
                        be ‘perfectly incorrect and dangerous’ with the result that the version published in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5
                        (May 1811), 403–457, was much altered by <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, in consultation with Gifford
                        and <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>; see <ref type="l" target="/reference/qr/index/10.html">Jonathan Cutmore, <title>The Quarterly Review Archive</title></ref>. For the conclusion, and ‘husbanding <title>money</title>’, see
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5, 435–437. The ‘Yogue’ was renamed ‘the Hindoo devotee, who sits with his hands before
                        him in the same position of devotion for weeks and months together, husbands his muscles till he loses the use of them!’ (p.
                        436). Southey’s review of Pasley did not become a pamphlet.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> A pamphlett is but little longer than a long reviewal. It gives me full liberty, – whereas <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">G.</ref> has always the Ministry before his eyes, &amp; I have little doubt will sacrifice
                    all my anti-Neapolitan arguments to our precious Treaty of Subsidy.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Charles William
                        Pasley (1780–1861; <title>DNB</title>) had questioned whether British conduct to Sicily had been unwise and had suggested
                        Britain should have ‘taken possession of Sicily for ourselves’, <title>Essay on the Military Policy and Institutions of the
                            British Empire</title> (London, 1810), pp. 171, 163. Southey undoubtedly agreed with this, making the interventionist case
                        in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 99. The Treaty of Alliance between Britain and Sicily
                        (1808) included a provision that Britain would pay Sicily £300,000 p.a., backdated to 1805.</note> Should it swell to a volume
                    no matter. The manner will ensure the sale, – (the Quarterly proves that I have learnt how to write popularly in prose) – &amp;
                    these things are soon written when there is no labour of research or reading required, but you have only to pour out from a full
                    mind. The plan of such things costs more than the execution. After you &amp; I had talked over the matter it might be done
                    presently.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will not see me till the first week in May, &amp; there is a long spell of work to be got thro by that time.
                    This volume will outstretch the last by full 200 pages, tho not upon a more extensive scale of narration. Spanish events must
                    occupy as much as they did.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey’s account of events in Spain, <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 470–574.</note> Parl. Proc. as much again,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey’s narrative of Parliamentary proceedings, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1
                        (1811), 1–353.</note> – &amp; there is the Austrian war,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 600–659, detailing Austria’s defeat by France in 1809.</note>
                        Flushing<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The siege and capture of Flushing by British troops was part of the ill-fated
                        Walcheren campaign of 1809. For Southey’s account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811),
                        660–692.</note><hi rend="ital">cum multis aliis quæ nunc perscribere longum est</hi>,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘With many other
                        matters that it would be tedious now to write in full’.</note> to boot. I am just finishing what seems to me a good account of
                    the Basque Roads affair, collected with excellent pains from Gambiers <del>Court</del> Trial, &amp; the N. Chronicle.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Naval Chronicle</title>, published since 1799.</note> And I have been so cautious in
                    handling terms which I do not thoroughly understand that there is little possibility of any blunder, – however to guard against
                    any, the proofs shall be sent to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. Lord Gambier is a good old man, &amp; I do not
                    like <del>the</del> him the less for his psalm-singing – I should be sorry to say any thing which could give him pain, – but the
                    opinion which I have formed from a very careful examination of the evidence is that more could have done if Cochrane had had the
                    command. Cochrane is a great man upon the seas, &amp; must if possible be separated from the <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdettites</ref><del>in</del> both in his own &amp; the public feeling. We have no other man who can tread in the steps of Nelson. Why is he not
                        employed?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The controversy surrounding the Battle of the Basque Roads in April 1809.
                        Although they achieved some success, the British fleet failed to destroy the French navy completely. Captain Thomas Cochrane,
                        later 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775–1860; <title>DNB</title>), who had led a highly effective fireship attack at the start of
                        the battle, accused his commanding officer, the evangelical Admiral James Gambier, Baron Gambier (1756–1833;
                            <title>DNB</title>), of being reluctant to pursue the attack and thus achieve a complete victory. Cochrane was also an MP
                        with a reputation for exposing abuses of office, and, in the weeks after the battle, he pursued his campaign against Gambier
                        via parliamentary speeches. Gambier demanded a court-martial at which he was exonerated and, by implication, Cochrane was
                        convicted of libelling a superior officer. Whilst Gambier received public thanks from parliament for his actions in the
                        battle, Cochrane was not permitted to rejoin his ship for a few months. When he received new orders to serve in the
                        Mediterranean, Cochrane refused and went on half-pay, devoting his time to exposing abuses in the Admiralty. For Southey’s
                        account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 364–379.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> It is said in the Lit. Panorama that the number of Local &amp; Personal Acts past in the Session of 1809 was 192
                    “Also those not printed 112.”<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Literary Panorama</title>, 6 (1809), col. 1272.</note> – <del>xx</del> Does this mean that the 112 were <hi rend="ital">past</hi> also, or that they were brought before the House &amp; did not pass? – for I thought all Acts were
                    printed. <del>by I</del> Explain this to me in a single line, – that I may make no blunder in stating the sum of real business
                    performed by Parliament. The List of Public Acts I shall add to the Appendix as a proper addition to the Documents for the
                        year.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> See <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), Appendix,
                        viii–xvi.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> You are glad that the system of the Œconomists is not an English invention.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Modern economic theory can be traced to France as well as Britain, for instance in the work of Francois Quesnay
                        (1694–1774).</note> For your comfort I have discovered that the Stone-Ships also are of French extraction.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> There had been a plan in 1804 to block the French port of Boulogne with stone ships. The First
                        Lord of the Admiralty at the time was John Jervis, Earl of St Vincent (1735–1823; <title>DNB</title>).</note> They were tried
                    at Calais by the Duke of Burgundy<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Philip III, ‘the Good’ (1396–1467), Duke of Burgundy,
                        and leader of the attack on English-controlled Calais in 1436.</note> in 1436, – where six of them were duly sunk. – At low
                    water men &amp; women came out of the town, – pulled them to pieces &amp; hauled away the materials “to the great astonishment,
                    says Monstrellet, of the Duke &amp; his Admirals” – who were looking on &amp; no doubt wondering that they should never have
                    thought of the possibility of this before. <note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Johnes (1748–1816; <title>DNB</title>)
                        [trans.], <title>The Chronicles of Enguerrand de Monstrelet</title>, 4 vols (Hafod, 1809), III, p. 185.</note> This is a noble
                    article for the Omniana.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey and Coleridge, <title>Omniana, or Horae
                            Otiosiores</title>, 2 vols (London, 1812), II, pp. 31–32.</note> Tell me who was the English <del>xxxxxxxx</del>
                        &lt;<del>xxxxxxx</del> inventor&gt; of this grand project – that who was the First Lord at that time? – See the blessed
                    effects of stripping history of all its circumstances. Our First Lords may be expected to read Hume,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> David Hume (1711–1776; <title>DNB</title>), author of a monumental <title>History of England</title>
                        (1754–1762).</note> – &amp; if this fact had found its way into <del>xxx</del> Hume, the nation would have been saved 100,000
                    £!</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="right"><date when="1811-03-04">March 4. 1811.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>