<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2069</idno><idno type="nines">rce3340</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2069" type="letter"><head>2069. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1812-03-31">31 March
                        1812</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey/ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helens/ Auckland/ Durham <lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1812-03-31">March 31. 1812.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> As my own treatise upon <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">Bell</ref> &amp; the <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Dragon</ref> came to me yesterday, I suppose that by this time your parcel from <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has reached Durham.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>The
                            Origin, Nature and Object, of the New System of Education</title> (1812), an expansion of his advocacy of Andrew Bell in
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (August 1811), 264–304. It contained numerous attacks on Lancaster and on his defenders
                        in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>. See also see Southey to John Murray, 10 March 1812, Letter 2058.</note> It contains a
                    copy for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bowyer<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reynold Gideon Bouyer (1741–1826;
                            <title>DNB</title>), a Prebendary of Durham Cathedral 1791–1826. His <title>A Comparative View of the two New Systems of
                            Education of the Infant Poor, in a Charge delivered to the Clergy of the Officialty of the Dean and Chapter of Durham, at
                            Berwick-upon-Tweed, on Tuesday, May 12, 1811</title> (1811) had been one of a series of writings on the Bell-Lancaster
                        controversy noticed by Southey in his <title>Quarterly Review</title> article.</note> which I have desired <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> to deliver to him. The book is now a compleat statement of the case in
                    its personal &amp; political bearings. The Quarterly is to be in such binding as it is usually kept in for sale, – &amp; yet I
                    shall be almost afraid of having the future volumes sent, as volumes, lest they should not prove uniform. – Both J of Arc &amp;
                    Madoc are nearly thro the press.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A fourth edition of <title>Joan of Arc</title> and a
                        third of <title>Madoc</title> appeared in 1812.</note> as soon as they are ready I will repeat the order to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have been reviewing the Iceland<del>ic</del> Travellers<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir George
                        Steuart Mackenzie (1780–1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in the Island of Iceland, in the Summer of the Year
                            1810</title> (1811) and Sir William Jackson Hooker (1785–1865; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of a Tour in Iceland,
                            in the Summer of 1809</title> (1811), reviewed by Southey alongside, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (March 1812),
                        48–92. Southey’s copy of Mackenzie – which had some coloured plates and marbled leaves – was no. 1654 in the sale catalogue of
                        his library.</note> &amp; Jorgensen the Dane,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jorgen Jorgensen (1780–1841), Danish
                        adventurer, captured by the British in 1808. The following year he travelled to Iceland, declared its independence from
                        Denmark, proclaimed himself Protector and Commander-in-Chief by Sea and Land and promised to establish a liberal regime.
                        Danish rule was restored by the arrival of HMS <hi rend="ital">Talbot</hi> some two months later. Jorgensen was taken back to
                        England and tried for breaking his parole. He was released in 1811. The following years were spent in England and mainland
                        Europe. He worked as a spy, published pamphlets and newspaper articles, accumulated large debts, spent spells in prison and in
                        1825 was transported to Australia. He settled in Tasmania, where he led several explorations and took part in the Black Line
                        aboriginal clearances of 1830. Southey’s account of Jorgensen’s Icelandic activities is in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7
                        (March 1812), 87–90.</note> telling him I thought the old score of which he reminded us had been paid off at Copenhagen.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jorgensen claimed descent ‘in a direct line from those ancient and warlike tribes who
                        trampled on Rome and Britain … [He] needed not have reminded us of this; for our arrears to his ancestors have been paid off
                        at Copenhagen’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (March 1812), 89. But as the British fleet had defeated the Danes at
                        Copenhagen in 1801 and 1807, the ‘old score’ was ‘paid off’.</note><ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landors</ref> play may perhaps be reviewed also in time for this number.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Count Julian</title> (1812), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (September 1812), 86–92.</note>
                    For the next I shall endeavour to be ready with Humboldts Mexico,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander von Humboldt
                        (1769–1859), <title>Political Essay on the Kingdom of New Spain</title>, an English translation of which was published by
                        Longman in 1811. Southey did not review it.</note> &amp; perhaps with the French Biography<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Biographie Moderne: Lives of Remarkable Characters who have Distinguished themselves from the Commencement of the
                            French Revolution to the Present Time</title> (1811), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (June
                        1812), 412–438.</note> – a text for the Revolution. The Revolution is almost the only part of their history in which any
                    virtues appear as a set off against the almost unmingled wickedness of their political transactions. I do not believe that the
                    history of the rest of Europe <del>can xx</del> contains so many instances of wickedness as are to be found in that of France from
                    Louis XI to Louis XV.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. c. 1461–1774, the period from the reign of Louis XI
                        (1423–1483; King of France 1461–1483) to Louis XV (1710–1774; King of France 1715–1774).</note> It teams with every thing that
                    is unprincipled, profligate, perfidious &amp; inhuman.</p><p rend="indent1"> There are some letters in the Times signed Vetus which I suspect to be <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Cannings</ref>; they manifestly speak his politics &amp; seem to me to savour strongly of his mode of thinking &amp;
                        writing.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The letters appeared in <title>The Times</title> between 10 March and 10 May
                            1812. They were condemnatory of <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval’s</ref> administration. They were
                        published in book form as <title>The Letters of Vetus</title> (1812). Southey was mistaken about their author. Vetus (‘old’)
                        was the Irish journalist Edward Sterling (1773–1847; <title>DNB</title>), who later in 1812 accepted a leader writing post on
                            <title>The Times</title>.</note> Much as I should like to see exertions made in Spain upon the scale which <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M. Wellesley</ref> employed in India, still I am better pleased that the power should
                    remain with <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref>, than that the perilous experiment of concession to the
                    Catholics should be tried. It would not prevent a rebellion in Ireland, – but under any ministry indifferent enough to our own
                    Church Establishment to give up the Test Act,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Test Act (1673) effectively excluded
                        non-Anglicans from public office.</note> it would lead to the measure of selling the Tythes. Tythes may be very injurious to
                    agriculture, I admit, – for that there may be a remedy, or it may even be very desirable to devise some means of commuting
                        them,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tithes were paid in kind, as one tenth of the produce of land. The Tithe
                        Commutation Act (1836) converted them into cash payments.</note> – I believe it would, – but what Government will do, if they
                    meddle with the subject, will be to sell them, fund the money as a convenient supply of ways &amp; means take the payment of the
                    clergy into their own hands, – &amp; thus render the whole body dependant for ever more upon the existing ministry for that
                    proportionate rise of income, which it is the peculiar advantage of the present system always to supply. The Catholic
                        Counties<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. most of the county constituencies in Ireland.</note> would return none
                    but Catholic Members, <del>who</del> upon all of whom a Minister might depend in a measure of this kind. – The next evil which
                    would grow out of this would be a Methodist Establishment, – for it would very soon be found convenient to let the Church to the
                    lowest bidder, &amp; then for the old days of fire &amp; faggot.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am therefore will pleased to see <del>things</del> the present <del>administration</del> arrangement in
                    administration. <ref target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lord Liverpool</ref> has long appeared to me the best informed &amp;
                    wisest of our political performers. Lord Sidmouth<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The former Prime Minister (1801–1804),
                        Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757–1844; <title>DNB</title>), who became Home Secretary 1812–1822.</note> a
                    thoroughly honest man &amp; <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> the fittest prime minister, because he has
                    plenty of political courage, &amp; is equally ready to resist Paddy Rampant, &amp; to stand by the Spaniards. – Yorke retires I
                    believe merely from ill health,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Philip Yorke (1764–1834; <title>DNB</title>). In
                        1812 he retired as First Lord of the Admiralty, a post he had held since 1810.</note> as you may judge by his brother
                    remaining in office.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The naval officer Sir Joseph Sydney Yorke (1768–1831;
                            <title>DNB</title>), who had joined the Board of Admiralty in 1810. He did not follow his elder brother into retirement
                        and in October 1813 he became First Naval Lord.</note> You are mistaken about Ld Melville, <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> tells me that as much will be gained by the change at the Admiralty as will be
                    lost at the Board of Controul.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Saunders Dundas, 2nd Viscount Melville (1771–1851;
                            <title>DNB</title>), who had become First Lord of the Admiralty earlier in 1812. He had previously been President of the
                        Board of Control.</note> without admitting this as any proof that Y. was not a good first Lord, it may be taken as a fair
                    admission of Ld Melvilles reputation for ability. I am glad to see him there, because it gives me hope that the great measure of
                    Troop Ships may be effected.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ships specially adapted to convey troops on long sea
                        voyages. Melville proposed to construct such ships on 21 May 1810.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> We shall probably have a battle before Badajoz.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Badajoz was successfully
                        besieged by an Anglo-Portuguese army 16 March-6 April 1812.</note> This if <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Earl Wellington</ref> intends to fight one is probably intended to favour some decisive <del>movements</del> exertion against
                    French at Cadiz, where Doyle has been active in disciplining the Spaniards.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Charles
                        William Doyle (1770–1842; <title>DNB</title>), British liaison officer to Spanish forces in Catalonia 1809–1811. On his way
                        back to Britain he stopped in Cadiz and was asked by the British ambassador to accept command of a new depot for the training
                        of conscripts. He accepted and achieved some success. However, his poor relationship with <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Wellington</ref>, meant that he was unsuccessful in obtaining another
                        command in the field or on the army staff.</note> The new Regency<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Once the new Cortes
                        met in Cadiz in 1812, it appointed a new Council of Regency to be the executive authority. Its members were: Pedro de
                        Alcantara Alvarez de Toledo, 13th Duke of the Infantado (1768–1841); Joaquin de Mosquera y Figueroa (1748–1830); Juan Maria de
                        Villavicencio (1755–1830); Henry O’Donnell, 1st Count of Bisbal (1769–1834); and Ignacio Rodriguez de Rivas (dates
                        unknown).</note> seems to have given hopes at least, &amp; to have bestirred itself. – I think you will find in my next volume
                    of the Register a more clear &amp; satisfactory view of the causes of the misconduct of the Junta, &amp; the Regencies which
                    preceded it, than has yet been <del>xxx</del> given.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.1 (1812), 352–380.</note> The volume is about half printed, &amp; I have
                    still a great part of it to write.</p><p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref>, &amp; a kiss to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretdauTomandSarah">Margaret</ref>. – I have at last got Counsels opinion upon <del>the
                        Somerville affair</del> Cannon Southeys will,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s distant cousin, Cannon
                        Southey (d. 1768), who owned the Fitzhead estate in Somerset. His exceptionally complex will led to much litigation.</note> it
                    gives me no hopes of any thing from the Fitzhead fields &amp; furniture, – but think, that if his butcher-Lordship<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Southey Somerville, 15th Lord Somerville (1765–1819), was Southey’s third cousin. He died
                        without heirs, but Southey did not inherit anything.</note> dies without issue it may then be worth a struggle for the rest of
                    the property for the remainder of a term of 99 years. This is a game which I should be very unwilling to play it, even if the
                    opportunity were to offer. The Counsel said he never had any case which gave him so much perplexity.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>