<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2283</idno><idno type="nines">rce3554</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2283" type="letter"><head>2283. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1813-07-18">18 July
                        1813</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb/>Postmarks: 10 o’Clock/ JY 21/ 1813 FNn; E/ 21 JY 21/ 1813<lb/>Seal: Black wax, capital S, Latin motto ‘In Labore
                        Quies’ <lb/>Watermark: [partial] 1807<lb/> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1813-07-18">July 18. 1813</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your envelope enclosing Mr Bs letter &amp; the paper of hints, bears date June 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A ‘paper of hints’ (i.e. suggestions) sent by William Barlow (1759–1839), a neighbour of Herbert
                        Hill’s in Streatham. In 1813 Southey was commissioned by the Barlows to write a defence of the conduct of William Barlow’s
                        brother, Sir George Hilaro Barlow (1763–1846; <title>DNB</title>), Governor of Madras 1807–1813. The result was the
                        anonymously published pamphlet <title>An Exposure of the Misrepresentations and Calumnies in Mr Marsh’s Review of Sir George
                            Barlow’s Administration at Madras. By the Relatives of Sir George Barlow</title> (1813).</note> – I thought to have been
                    with you by this time. But in the interim the illness of <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">Ediths brother</ref> has
                    terminated fatally, – &amp; as you may suppose, for some time before the event my house was entirely disordered. <del>Xxx</del> –
                    This evening I have a letter from <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, who urges me to put off my journey till
                    November, or till the meeting of Parliament, because at this season, <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref>, <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref>, &amp; <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M. Wellesley</ref>, all of
                    whom it is <del>necessary</del> &lt;expedient&gt; that I should see, will be out of town. – The fitness of seeing these persons is
                        obvious,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey needed to consult them for his <title>History of the Peninsular
                            War</title> (1823–1832), recently contracted by Murray.</note> &amp; certainly if the Madras business<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. the defence of Sir George Hilaro Barlow.</note> can be done here I should rather delay my
                    visit. The nature of the reply seems to be clearly chalked out, &amp; my thorough knowledge of the character of the man who is to
                    be answered gives me no little advantage. If you think <del>xx xxx</del> my personal appearance at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham </ref><del> xxx</del> is not necessary, send me Marshs<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The barrister and MP Charles Marsh (c.
                        1774–1835; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Review of Some Important Passages in the Late Administration of Sir G. H. Barlow,
                            Bart., at Madras</title> (1813). This attacked Barlow’s conduct as Governor of Madras.</note> book &amp; the other
                    documents (except the papers laid before Parliament, which I already have) – &amp; I will forthwith take him in hand. Believe me I
                    should be heartily glad to find reason for believing that Sir GB. was as right in every part of his conduct, as he was in the
                    great points of dispute. <del>However</del> Be this as it may I shall know how to take the strong ground, &amp; to read Marsh a
                    lecture upon subordination.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> offers me for the history of the Spanish affairs, in two quartos, a thousand
                    guineas. – Whether I shall accept it requires some consideration. It is certain that tho what I have written in the Register<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> must be recast, yet the materials there, &amp; the knowledge which I have
                    acquired, are of such import that my work is in reality half done. This however is not to be considered in the price. – The book
                    is to be a splendid one, with &lt;plans&gt; views &amp; portraits, &amp; head &amp; tail-pieces to every chapter.</p><p rend="indent1"> Will you write to Sealey<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Sealy (d. 1821), Lisbon merchant and
                        father-in-law of Henry Herbert Southey.</note> – or to any body at Lisbon who will take the trouble to procure the books for
                    me <del>xxx</del> which I have specified on the opposite leaf. They are all new publications, – some of them printed at the Rio,
                    but these no doubt are procurable at Lisbon. I have found <del>the</del> notice of them in <del>the</del> London Portugueze
                    Journals. Let them be consigned to <ref target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">Koster</ref> for me, &amp; payment for them shall
                    be made <del>wherever</del> at <del>xx</del> any place which may be appointed. Some of them as you will perceive are indispensable
                    for my new work, &amp; I take the opportunity of sending for the rest, – of which the most worthless will turn to account. – Of
                    the Portugueze Journals I have only mentioned one, but I should be glad of as many as can be procured, &amp; if it were possible
                    to obtain a series of the Gazetas,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s collection eventually ran to 24 volumes of
                        Spanish <title>Gazetas</title>, 1808–1813, no. 3472 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> – I am sure the chaff would
                    amply repay sifting. I should find some of those stray facts &amp; particulars which are the life of history.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall soon have compleated my task on the Register. The affairs of Sp. America have made it grow under my
                        hands.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 367–421. In Buenos Aires and the surrounding area, the country
                        was torn by conflicts between different regions and those for and against independence from Spain. In Mexico a protracted War
                        of Independence (1810–1821) was in progress, which Southey compares to the Irish uprising of 1798. Brazil was more peaceful
                        and was still controlled by the Portuguese government, which had fled there in 1808.</note> For those of B Ayres I had good
                    private documents, – it is a dismal story, without any thing to relieve it. In Mexico the <del>war</del> state of things very much
                    resembles that of Ireland during the rebellion. The proscriptions confiscations &amp;c which are going on at B Ayres might save
                    Brazil from the same calamities, if nations were ever made wiser by their neighbours example. But whenever the Government returns
                    to Lisbon it is most probable that the plague will break out, &amp; throw the country back for a century.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> tells me 1200 copies of the Nelson<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> have sold, &amp; that he never published any book which has given such
                    compleat satisfaction. What a business his namesake has made at Tarragona!<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In June 1813
                        Lieutenant General John Murray, 8th Baronet (1768?-1827; <title>DNB</title>), despite having superior numbers, failed to
                        capture the Spanish port of Tarragona.</note><ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord W.</ref> however is so entirely master of the field, that Suchet,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Gabriel Suchet, Duc d’Albuferra (1770–1826), French Marshal.</note> able as he is,
                    will hardly effect his escape.</p><p rend="indent1"> All well. Remember me to <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> – How goes on <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">the Man</ref> &amp; his brothers?</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> RS.</salute></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1">Gama. poema por Joze Agostinho de Macedo.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> José Agostinho de Macedo
                            (1761–1831), <title>Gama, Poema Narrativo</title> (1810); no. 3420 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p><p rend="indent1">Memorias Botanicas de D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ant: Joze das Neves Mello.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        An unidentified work by Antonio Jose das Neves e Mello (1770-fl. 1830s), director of the Museo Botanico, Coimbra. Probably the
                        <title>Varias Memorias Botanicas</title> advertised in <title>O Investigador Portuguez</title>, 3 (1812).</note></p><p rend="indent1">Memoria Economica sobre a raça do Gado Lanigero na Capitania do Ceara. Pelo Tenente Cor. Joaõ da Silva
                            Feijo<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joao da Silva Feijo (1760–1824), <title>Memoria Economica sobre a raça de
                                Gado Lanigero da Capitania do Ceara</title> (1811).</note></p><p rend="indent1">Indice Systematico da Legislaçaõ Brasiliense.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexandre Jose Curado de
                            Figueiredo e Albuquerque (dates uknown), <title>Indice Systematico da Legislacao Brasiliense</title> (1812).</note></p><p rend="indent1">Libambo, Metamorphose do Paõ d’Assucar. Poema.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Paulino Joachin Leitao
                            (1779–1831), <title>Libambo: Metamorfose do Pao d’Assucar</title> (1811).</note></p><p rend="indent1">Uruguay. poema de Joze Basilio.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> José Basilio da Gama (1741–1795),
                                <title>O Uruguay: Poema-Epico</title> (1769); no. 3999 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p><p rend="indent1">Historia Geral da Invasaõ dos Francizes em Portugal, por José Accurcio das Neves.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> José Accursio das Neves (1766–1834), whose four volume <title>Historia Geral da Invasão dos Francezes em
                                Portugal, e da Restauração deste Reino</title> was published in Lisbon in 1810; no. 3164 in the sale catalogue of
                            Southey’s library.</note></p><p rend="indent1">Os Sebastianistas <del>xxx</del> P. Joze Agostinho de Macedo: &amp; the tracts in answer to &amp; in defence of
                            it.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> José Agostinho de Macedo (1761–1831), <title>Os Sebastianistas</title>
                            (1810); no. 3420 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p><p rend="indent1">Observaçoẽs sobre a prosperidade do Estado pelos liberaes principios da nova legislaçaõ do Brazil. por Joze da
                        Silva Lisboa.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> José da Silva Lisboa (1756–1835), <title>Observaçoẽs Sobre a
                                Prosperidade do Estado Pelos Liberais Principios da Nova Legislaçaõ do Brazil</title> (1810).</note></p><p rend="indent1">Observaçoẽs sobre a franquize da industria, &amp;c no Brazil. por Joze da Silva Lisboa.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> José da Silva Lisboa (1765–1835), <title>Observaçoẽs Sobre a Franqueza da Industria, &amp;c no
                                Brazil</title> (1810).</note></p><p rend="indent1">Dissertaçoẽs sobre a historia e jurisprudencia ecclesiastica e civil de Portugal, publicadas por ordem da
                        Academia Real. pelo sen Socio Joam Pedro Ribeiro.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> João Pedro Ribeiro (1758–1839),
                                <title>Dissertaçoẽs Sobre a Historia e Jurisprudencia Ecclesiastica e Civil de Portugal, Publicadas por Ordem da
                                Academia Real</title> (1798–1810); no. 3713 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p><p rend="indent1">Demonstraçaõ analytica dos barbaros procedimentos adoptados pelo Imperador dos Francezes para usurpaçaõ de
                            Portugal.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> José Antonio de Sá (fl, 1801–1812), <title>Demonstraçaõ analytica dos
                                barbaros procedimentos adoptados Como Meios Dos Justiça pelo Imperador dos Francezes para usurpaçaõ do Throno Da
                                Serenissima e Augustissima Case de Bragança, e da Real Coroa de Portugal</title> (1810).</note></p><p rend="indent1">Segredo Revelado, on grito de verdade contra os Pedreiros Livres, – &amp; the other tracts upon this
                            subject<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> José Agostinho de Macedo (1761–1831), <title>Segredo Revelado, ou
                                Manifestação do Systema des Pedreiros Livres, e Illuminados, e sua Influencia na fatal Revoluçao Franceza</title>
                            (1809); no. 3420 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p><p rend="indent1">Memorias de Literatura Port: Tom 7. &amp; 8.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Memorias de Litteratura Portugueza</title> (1792–1796), published by the Academia Real das Sciencias, Lisbon; no.
                            3532 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p><p rend="indent1">Coleccion de Memorias para la Hist: de las naciones Ultramarinas.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Coleção de Noticias para a História e Geografia das Nações Ultramarinas</title> (1812) published by the Academia
                            Real das Sciências. For Southey’s copy, see no. 3273 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note></p><p rend="indent1">Coleccion de viages a los dominios ultramarinas<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">
                            Unidentified.</note></p><p rend="indent1">Jornal de Coimbra.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey acquired an eight-volume set of the
                                <title>Jornal de Coimbra</title> (1812–1820), no. 3498 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>