<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2550</idno><idno type="nines">rce3821</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2550" type="letter"><head>2550. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1815-02-08">8 February 1815</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To / G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> / Exchequer / Westminster.<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E / 11 FE 11/ 1815<lb/>Endorsement:
                        8 February 1815 <lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> The Pionia<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A river mentioned frequently in <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814), for example Book 13, line 241.</note> is a small river which falls into the Sella, &amp; which is
                    now called the Bueña, – most likely not to be found in <del>ma</del> any general map. The Deva<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> A stream mentioned frequently in <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), for example Book 16,
                        line 59.</note> certainly is not, this stream must be like one of our Borrodale becks, – it falls <del>into the x Pionia</del>
                    at Soto into another mountain stream called Reynazo &amp; that into the Pionia. <del>Xx xxx</del> Of course it was not necessary
                    that I should enter so minutely into the topography as to mention this. Morales to whom the note refers has given a full
                    description of all this, for which God bless him;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The geography is important to the poem
                        because it describes the Vale of Covadonga, site of the battle in 722 against the Moors, which concludes the poem. The note to
                            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 16, line 159 refers to Ambrosio de Morales (1513–1591),
                            <title>Los Cinco Libros Postreros de la Coronica General de Espana, que Continuava Ambrosio de Morales</title> (Cordoba,
                        1586), Book 13, ff. 3r-5r. Southey possessed an edition of the <title>Coronica</title> from 1791–1793, no. 3557 in the sale
                        catalogue of his library.</note> – &amp; the old geography I collected from the Espana Sagrada,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Enrique Florez (1702–1773) and Manuel Risco (1735–1801), <title>Espana Sagrada, Teatro-Geografico Historico de
                            la Iglesia de Espana</title>, 45 volumes (1754–1801), no. 3468 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> a work
                    of prodigious labour, great extent &amp; great value.</p><p rend="indent1"> You ask me about Julians speech to Orpas – my meaning is that his look made Orpas understand what the words were
                    intended to convey to him &amp; none but him. – <del>that Roderi</del> Julian had described what sort of a Christian Orpas had
                    been, &amp; in using the words We Musslemen<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 20, line 223.</note> implied that the one was just such a
                    Mussleman as the other, each knowing that the other did not believe the faith which they both professed.</p><p rend="indent1"> Roderick looks sternly toward Siverian, without any thought of the person at whom he is looking (this is carefully
                    observed) – His feeling is a sudden impulse of indignation that such an action should be excused which he feels, after every
                    palliation, to be inexcusable: And as the word <hi rend="ital">absolve</hi> is what rouses him,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 17, line 114.</note> Siverian is put upon a false scent by that
                    word, – as if the Priest were offended by it. The sternness of Roderick is a feeling toward himself.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The opening of the letter provides information requested by Grosvenor Bedford for his forthcoming review of
                            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814); published in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815),
                        83–113.</note></p><p rend="center"> ____</p><p rend="indent1"> Woe be to <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref>! I have now seen his reviewal of the
                        Excursion.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Jeffrey’s review of Wordsworth’s <title>The Excursion</title> (1814),
                        see <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 24 (November 1814), [1]-30. It began: ‘This will never do’ ([1]).</note> I have seen also
                    his account of <ref target="people.html#WilsonJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wilsons</ref> nonsensical Isle of Palms, – a volume
                    made up of the grossest imitations of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, with not a few from
                        myself.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Wilson, <title>The Isle of Palms and Other Poems</title> (1812). The
                        article in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 19 (February 1812), 373–388, began: ‘This is a new recruit to the company of
                        lake poets; – and one who, from his present bearing, promises, we think, not only to do them good service, and to rise to high
                        honours in the corps; but to raise its name, and advance its interests even among the tribes of the unbelievers. Though he
                        wears openly the badge of their peculiarities, and professes the most humble devotion to their great captain, Mr. Wordsworth,
                        we think he has kept clear of several of the faults that may be imputed to his preceptors; and assumed, upon the whole, a more
                        attractive and conciliating air, than the leaders he has chosen to follow’ (373).</note> It is well for <ref target="people.html#WilsonJohn">Wilson</ref> that he happens to be intimate with <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref>; – <del>or he would have come in</del> &amp; that I
                    just know enough of him <del>not</del> to prevent me from giving him the very hard knock which would otherwise fall to his share.
                    But as for <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> if I do not hit him harder than <ref target="people.html#CoplestonEdward">Copplestone</ref> has done,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Copleston had engaged in
                        a public feud with the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>. His <title>A Reply to the Calumnies of the Edinburgh Review against
                            Oxford</title> (Oxford, 1810) reacted to an attack on ‘classical learning as currently taught in England’,
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 15 (October 1809), 40–53. Copleston noted in response that no one would ‘apply to the
                        Edinburgh Review for information about the Classics’ (<title>Reply</title>, p. 118). For the reviewers’ reaction; see
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 16 (April 1810), 158–187. Copleston followed up with <title>A Second Reply to the
                            Edinburgh Review</title> (1810) and <title>A Third Reply to the Edinburgh Review</title> (1811). See also Southey to
                        Richard Heber, 9 April 1811, Letter 1900.</note> – may <del>x</del> my right hand be palsied! – I have opened a black book on
                    his account; – the materials are collecting, &amp; I shall soon begin to fire away: – I would fain do it before he reviews
                    Roderick; – the letters will not bear my signature, but they will be recognized <del>for</del> as mine, – &amp; I have taken care
                    to make my intention known in quarters where it will reach him.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not write his
                        proposed articles.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I have been lately taking a heat at the History of the War.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> If the first chapter were finished to my mind I should
                    wish <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> would put me upon my mettle by sending it to press.</p><p rend="indent1"> Is it among things possible that you can take a six weeks run in France with me this autumn? You will easily
                    conceive that I should rather visit that country before my history is published than after. My plan is to go from Brighton, &amp;
                    stay a day or two at Caen, <del>&amp;</del> to make an Englishman who is settled there useful in directing me thereabouts. Paris
                    will soon satisfy me. Thence I go to Tours where I shall find <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>, – down
                    the Loire as far as Orleans, then to the south &amp; home by way of the Rhine. Mina is the only person in France whom I shall want
                    to see; – if he be there.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish guerrilla leader Francisco Espoz de Mina
                        (1781–1836). He had led an unsuccessful rising against the absolutist royal government at Pamplona on 25–26 September 1814 and
                        fled into exile. He did not return until the Revolution of 1820.</note> But I can get letters to La Fayette, for whom I have
                    some respect;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French politician and solider Marie-Paul-Joseph-Roch-Gilbert Motier,
                        Marquis de La Fayette (1757–1834), celebrated figure in the American Revolution and the early years of the French Revolution.
                        Southey had admired him since he was a schoolboy.</note> – &amp; if there were a French tongue in my head I would call upon
                        Carnot.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lazare Nicolas Marguerite, Comte Carnot (1753–1823), member of the Committee
                        of Public Safety 1793–1794, Director 1795–1797, Minister of War 1800. An old Jacobin, for whom Southey retained some
                        admiration.</note> Neither my tongue, nor my ears will be of much use to me, – but I shall make good use of my eyes.</p><p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Deus Lunus</ref> has his Catechistic book, &amp; I suppose it will
                    make part of his Sundays forms.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. the Church of England’s <title>Book of Common
                            Prayer</title> (1662).</note> I am neither orthodox enough to put it into his hands myself, nor heterodox enough to keep
                    it out of them.</p><p rend="indent1"> God bless you. I am glad to hear of Belisarius Narses Hodge, of whom honourable mention will be made in The Book of
                        D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Daniel Dove &amp; his Horse Nobs.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e Southey’s novel
                            <title>The Doctor</title> (1834–1847). Nobs appeared there, but not Belisarius Narses Hodge.</note> Remember me at home
                    –</p><closer><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1815-02-08">8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1815</date></p><p rend="indent1"> I could help you to plenty of faults in Roderick, – but as I do not give my censures <del>that are</del> credit
                        for judgement enough to find out the blots, it is <del>better</del> as well not to point them out. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> will most likely figure in the next number,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was mistaken. George Ellis’s review of Scott’s <title>The Lord of the Isles</title> (1815)
                            appeared in the next but one issue, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (July 1815), 287–309.</note> so that if you were
                        ready, you would hardly obtain insertion. – I hope my article upon Lewis &amp; Clark will be in,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meriweather Lewis (1774–1809) and William Clark (1770–1838), <title>Travels to the Source of the Missouri
                                River, and Across the American Continent to the Pacific Ocean</title> (1814), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly
                                Review</title>, 12 (January 1815), 317–368.</note> – for a very material reason which you may easily guess.</p><p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>, &amp; ask him if Admiral Hallowell has any
                        thing which could help me in my history besides what will appear in the printed trial? – I mean relative to any other
                        operations in Catalonia.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Admiral Sir Benjamin Hallowell (1760–1834;
                                <title>DNB</title>) had landed a British army at Tarragona on 2 June 1813, in order to besiege the town. But
                            Lieutenant-General Sir John Murray (c. 1768–1827; <title>DNB</title>) ordered a hurried retreat and re-embarked his troops
                            on 11–12 June 1813, fearing the approach of a French army. His actions led to a court martial in January 1815, which only
                            admonished him for abandoning his guns.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>