<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2669</idno><idno type="nines">rce3940</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text is taken from
                        Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, ‘The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826’ (unpublished PhD, Harvard,
                        1967), pp. 440–443.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 1–4.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2669" type="letter"><head>2669. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1815-11-09">9 November
                        1815</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker/ Greta Hall/ Keswick/
                        Cumberland<lb/>Postmark: FREE 9 NO 9 1815; London Ninth November 1815; Free J. Rickman<lb/>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from
                        Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, ‘The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826’ (unpublished PhD, Harvard,
                        1967), pp. 440–443<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 1–4.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> I am afraid Senhora that the letters which I wrote from Brussels did not reach their destination, for there is no
                    allusion to them in those which we have received from the <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Venerable</ref> &amp;
                    the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Juvenile Moon</ref>. Once was a second letter of wonders, carrying us if I recollect
                    rightly, to Ghent, – the other was to yourself &amp; brought our history as far as Brussels.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey to Mary Barker, 1 October 1815, Letter 2657.</note> I found it impossible to write anything more than
                    my Journal,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Journal was finally published as <title>Journal of a Tour in the
                            Netherlands in the Autumn of 1815</title> (1902).</note> which occupied every minute I could spare, even on those days
                    when we were stationary. You know how little leisure is to be obtained in a foreign country, when your curiosity is always on the
                    alert, &amp; eyes &amp; ears both upon active service from morning till night.</p><p rend="indent1"> You shall however have our whole history in due form when we return. My Journal is very full. That portion which
                    relates to the fields of battle I shall extract &amp; affix either as preface or postscript to my projected poem.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816). Southey did not carry out his intention to include parts of his
                        Journal.</note> The rest I may arrange &amp; fill up at leisure to leave among my papers. Here in London I can find time for
                    nothing, &amp; to make things worse the Devil, who owes me an old grudge, has made me sit to Phillips for a picture for <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Phillips (1770–1845;
                            <title>DNB</title>), portrait painter.</note> I have in time been tormented in this manner so often &amp; to such little
                    purpose, that I am half tempted to suppose the Devil was the inventor of portrait painting.</p><p rend="indent1"> Today (Thursday) we are to see the Lord Mayor’s Show. It is raining &amp; will continue to rain. We go in about an
                    hour to Rickmans, to see the water part of the pageant. Then to <ref target="people.html#ConderJosiah">Josiah Conders</ref> in S
                    Pauls Church Yard to see the procession by land. Tomorrow for <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>, between which
                    place &amp; Champion Hill (<ref target="people.html#GonneMrs">Mrs. Gonnes</ref>) we shall remain till the Saturday of next week, –
                    on that day we go to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John Mays</ref>, &amp; return from his house to London on the Monday; then
                    after four or at the utmost five days we set off on our return, for which we are all equally impatient. I am weary of this
                    continual movement &amp; bustle, &amp; long most heartily to be once more at home, &amp; at work, – the best kind of rest.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have brought for the Mountain Marshal<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> A nickname for Mary Barker.</note>
                    a cuirassiers pistol from the spoils at Waterloo, &amp; also a piece of kickmanjiggery from Aix-la-Chapelle which being a very
                    out-of-way sort of thing &amp; pretending to be useful is more fit for the said Marshal than for any body else. There is as yet no
                    news of any of my books. – There are some Dutch volumes among them (lives of the painters) with heads by Houbracken,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Arnold Houbracken (1660–1719), <title>De Groote schouburgh der Nederlands konstschilders en
                            schilderessen</title> (1718–1721), no. 1455 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – some of the very finest
                    of his works.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am writing upon <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herberts</ref> desk, – &amp; I mend my pen with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herberts</ref> knife, – a knife of queer cut from Namur containing two blades, a
                    corkscrew, a steel for striking fire to light his pipe, &amp; an instrument for picking the pipe: – the latter will serve to untie
                    parcels, &amp; I have a flint from Waterloo with which he may strike light when we want a fire by the lake side. – We have a friar
                    apiece for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> , a friar
                    on horseback for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> &amp; two nuns who are to be disposed of I know not how.
                        Betty<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Betty Thompson (dates unknown), a servant at Greta Hall.</note> will be glad to
                    hear that I have been remindful of her commission, &amp; bought four spunges yesterday, taking <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Shedaw</ref> for my councellor in the choice. We are to spend one whole morning in
                    shopping before we leave London.</p><p rend="indent1"> Whether I am one of those persons who know how to spend &amp; how to spare is not for me to determine: but I have
                    been both spending &amp; sparing more than I wished. ‘My gold has fled like chaff before the wind’<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Job</title>, 21: 18.</note> – You will lend me 100£ on my return, to set all straight as they say in Cumberland, –
                    &amp; it will not be very long before I shall be able to set that account straight also. Roderick<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> is doing well, &amp; has given me a good lift: its work is not
                    done yet, &amp; it may possibly set me fairly afloat in smooth water. My Waterloo poem will get me more credit than money. There
                    is one friend to whom I look for both, – that eminent physician whose house I reconnoitred at Doncaster.*<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s projected book on the fictional Dr Daniel Dove of Doncaster eventually became <title>The
                            Doctor</title> (1834–1847).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> God bless you. Love from all &amp; to all, – &amp; kisses, as many as you please to give, to the kissable part of
                    the family. The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctor</ref> in particular desires his remembrances. You must not go
                    to London this winter &amp; perhaps next year I may accompany you to visit the ruins of Paris. I <hi rend="ital">almost</hi>
                    expect a massacre of the allied troops &amp; the destruction of that city.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The eastern
                        borders of France were occupied by 150,000 allied troops until France had paid off an indemnity of 700,000 francs.</note> [MS
                    torn]</p><p rend="indent1"> The first Mina<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Javier de Mina (1789–1817), nephew of General
                        Espoz de Mina (1781–1836) and guerrilla leader in Navarre 1808–1810. He, too, had fled Spain after his uncle’s failed rising.
                        However, he went to France, rather than Britain.</note> is in London &amp; I shall see him. My letters need not be sent. –
                    Remember me to the <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#PeachyMrs">Mrs.
                        Peachy</ref>. The other General (<ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs Coleridges</ref> friend) I have seen. he is living
                    with a Jewish quack, who calls himself an Italian. – the most impudent of his fraternity: this fellows name is on the door, &amp;
                    I believe he lives upon the General, whose credulity in such things amounts to absolute insanity.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> Once more God bless you. I long to sing my
                    bravura at home once more</p><closer><salute rend="indent6"> Yrs affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent8"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1815-11-09">Thursday 9 Nov. 1815.</date><note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Barker adds note at end of MS: ‘* His premeditated work, “Doctor Daniel Dove,
                            of Doncaster,” which was to have been dedicated to me. Mary Slade.’</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>