<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1851</idno><idno type="nines">rce3122</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1851" type="letter"><head>1851. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1811-01-10">10 January
                        1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Bristol<lb/>Endorsement: 1811/ 10 Jany<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1811-01-10">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 10. 1811.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Danvers</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The box has arrived safe, &amp; your boy &amp; girl with the transferable heads have been the astonishment &amp;
                    amusement of young &amp; old. They are to be taken such care of, that my grandchildrens grandchildren have a fair chance of having
                    them handed down in high preservation among the other treasures of the family. – The half binding is very neat &amp; to my taste,
                    – only my black letter S was understood a little too literally, or rather misunderstood. I did not mean that a common S should be
                    stamped in black, but that a black letter S should be stamped in gilding, – however this is of no consequence – &amp; I am
                    exceedingly well pleased with my cargo.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Danvers, 13 November 1810,
                        Letter 1827.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> On the very day that the box came, I received two parcels, – this was rather vexatious, inasmuch as three pleasures
                    in one day are something like a grand dinner after a public breakfast, &amp; then again a great supper after the dinner, – more
                    than one has room for. – The booksellers as I grow more useful to them become more attentive to me in the way of presents, – which
                    I approve greatly. I have just had Weber’s Metrical Romances<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Weber (1783–1818;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Metrical Romances of the Thirteenth, Fourteenth, and Fifteenth Centuries</title> (1810); no.
                        2990 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> from <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, &amp; the new
                    edition of the Arabian Tales<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Arabian Nights Entertainments, Carefully Revised, and Occasionally Corrected from the Arabic. To which is Added, a
                            Selection of New Tales</title> (1811). The six volume edition was edited by the orientalist Jonathan Scott (1753–1829;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> from <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>. My presentation copies now amount
                    to a considerable number in the course of the year.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have handled the Barrister &amp; his Hints roughly in the last Quarterly<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Hints to the Public and the Legislature, on the Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title>
                        (1809), reviewed in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 480–514.</note> &amp; if the subject had not led me on
                    to something of more consequence than the exposure of his sophistry, &amp; impudent misstatements, whole pages might have been
                    filled upon this topic, for in my life I never perused a controversial book so thoroughly disgraceful to its author. – Of course
                    you will not like what I have said of Socinianism; – but I think you will not dislike the manner in which it is said, <del>x</del>
                    &amp; for all that follows respecting Methodism I think you will agree with me. A few passages have been cut out, – one was of
                    some importance – as it recommended an approximation to the Methodist system, by restoring the old order of Cathechists,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the Catholic Church, lay people who help instruct children in the basics of the Church’s
                        teachings.</note> hinted at the adoption of Lay-preachers, &amp; advised that the Clerk<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Parish Clerk, who provided assistance to Anglican clergymen. The Clerk could be full or part-time and duties varied
                        enormously from parish to parish. They might include reading lessons in church, organising the choir, serving at the altar and
                        leading the responses, opening the church, ringing the bell and even digging graves if there was no sexton.</note> should be
                    made a character of more respectability, – &lt;both of&gt; which might easily be done by engrafting some innovation of this kind
                    upon the systems of parochial education <del>upon</del> &lt;after&gt; <ref target="people.html#BellJohn">Bell’s</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Lancaster’s</ref> plan. <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> was afraid
                    of venturing this, – but I shall find a place for it elsewhere, together with some hints against sermons, which of course I did
                    not propose to the Quarterly.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey developed these ideas in his <title>The Origin,
                            Nature, and Object, of the New System of Education</title> (1812).</note> This review is gaining ground, &amp; very
                    deservedly. I know not who took my History in hand, – if he had read, markd &amp; inwardly digested my history of the year 1808,
                    he might have seen <del>xxxx</del> clearly there that it is not my opinions which have alterd in any main point, but that
                    different circumstance have given them a different bearing, – they remaining the same; – in other words that the revolutionary
                    ground of hope is Spain instead of France, &amp; that Buonaparte is the Antichrist who <del>xxxx xxx the xxx xxxx</del> opposes
                    all amelioration of the state of mankind.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The article on the first part of Southey’s
                            <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 454–474, had noted, ‘We no
                        longer find in the productions of his pen that querulous discontent under the existing state of society and that undefined
                        aspiration after fair dreams of unattainable liberty’ (473). Its unnamed author was <ref target="people.html#HeberReginald">Reginald Heber</ref>.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Have you seen Pasley’s Essay on our Military Policy?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Pasley
                        (1780–1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Essay on the Military Policy and Institutions of the British Empire</title> (1810).
                        For Southey’s appraisal see <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5 (May 1811), 403–437.</note> He is intimate with <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>,
                    &amp; is an extraordinarily able man, as I know by his letters. He is of the right political religion.</p><p rend="indent1"> You have surely had Kehama<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> before this time, – I directed copies for you &amp; <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref>, I have received but few
                    accounts of it yet, – as far as they go, the story seems less a stumbling black than I had expected.</p><p rend="indent1"> I care little about these Regency disputes,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738–1820; King of
                        the United Kingdom 1760–1820; <term>DNB</term>) had become too deranged to conduct public business in 1810. This led to a
                        political crisis as the government feared the most obvious candidate to stand in for his father as Regent, George, Prince of
                        Wales (1762–1830; Prince Regent 1811–1820, King of the United Kingdom as George IV 1820–1830; <title>DNB</title>), favoured
                        opposition politicians. After a prolonged controversy the Regency Bill was passed on 5 February 1811, appointing the Prince of
                        Wales Regent, without a Regency Council, but with some restrictions on his powers in his first year of office.</note> &amp;
                    only wish that the Kings recovery may render them as useless as they are wearisome, – for any change would be for the worse. It is
                    of great consequence that <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> should possess the entire
                    confidence of the Cabinet, &amp; be heartily &amp; sincerely supported.</p><p rend="indent1"> Send me the ages of your brother Jacks children,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Danvers (d. 1812),
                        the younger brother of Charles Danvers, was a surgeon and apothecary in Woolwich, but had been made bankrupt in 1808.</note>
                    &amp; I will try all in my power. My best chance will be thro <ref target="people.html#SmithThomasWoodruffe">Smith the
                        Quaker</ref>, or thro <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, – but it is useless to apply till I can go with
                    chapter &amp; verse as to their age, because the possibility of getting them into a school may depend upon that. I should be glad
                    to hear their father as well as their mother was at rest; – any amendment is hopeless in this world – but I do not believe it to
                    be so in the next. – This naturally reminds me of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref>, of whom the last news
                    (some eight or ten month old) was, that he had again joined a strolling company in Devonshire.</p><p rend="indent1"> We have had a good deal of sickness among the children, they are recovered thank God, – nevertheless I sometimes
                    wish <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> were at hand. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> has an
                    induration of one of the cervical glands – on the right side – it is rather larger than a sixpence – not very hard, &amp;
                    moveable. It has resisted calomel, &amp; mercurial friction. Ask <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> what we should do
                    for it? An old fellow collegian of mine who is now also an M.D. of some years standing<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Possibly Dr James Douglas (1775–1846) of Kelso, an old friend from Balliol College, Oxford, who visited Southey
                        in December 1810.</note> advised carbonate (I think) – of lime.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p>Many a happy new year to you.</p><p>I must not forget the childrens joyful thanks.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> I must not … thanks: Written at top of
                            fol 1r.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>