<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2031</idno><idno type="nines">rce3302</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47891.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2031" type="letter"><head>2031. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BrowneWade">Wade Browne</ref>, <date when="1812-02-06">6 February
                        1812</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Wade Browne Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Ludlow<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47891<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1812-02-06">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 6. 1812.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Perceiving by the Psalms which <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> &amp; her cousin <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara</ref> have received from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wolseley<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Robert Wolseley (c. 1768–1815), <title>A Poetical Paraphrase, of a select portion of the Book of
                            Psalms</title> (1811). Wolseley had been at head of school at Westminster at the time Southey went there; see Robert
                        Southey to Thomas Southey, 3 August 1808, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3</title>, Letter 1483.</note>
                    that Wade<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wade Browne (1796–1851) was the only son of Wade Browne. He became a country
                        gentleman at Monkton Farleigh in Somerset.</note> is returned to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fawcetts,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly James Fawcett (1751–1831; <title>DNB</title>), a Leeds clergyman who became Norrisian Professor of
                        Divinity at the University of Cambridge 1795–1815 and Rector of Thursford and Great Snoring in Norfolk 1801–1831.</note> I
                    hope you will allow me to bespeak him as a companion for <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref>, for as
                    long a time as he can be spared at Easter.</p><p rend="indent1"> I thought much earlier to have thanked you for your letter of the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> December, but waited thus
                    long in expectation of the arrival of the Grate.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The grate arrived later that month; see
                        Southey to Wade Brown, 27 February 1812, Letter 2050.</note> It has not yet appeared, so that it is either unreasonably
                    delayed by the way, or perhaps was not sent off so soon as you imagined – which as I have not received any advice <del>xx</del>
                    concerning it from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bradley<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly James Bradley (dates unknown),
                        an iron-founder, based in Southwark.</note> may possibly have been the case.</p><p rend="indent1"> This evening’s paper brings the not-unexpected news of the fall of Valencia. Blake is a man upon whom all
                    experience has been thrown away.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish general Joaquin Blake y Joyes (1759–1827).
                        After a series of defeats, Blake and his forces were trapped in Valencia, where they surrendered on 8 January 1812.</note> –
                    &amp; unhappily the Spanish Government partakes too much of the same fault. It is absolute madness to shut up an army in a
                    beseiged town, unless there be a determination, as at Zaragoza,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Zaragoza had fallen to the
                        French in 1809 after two sieges.</note> to sell the place by inches; – the Valencians did not want resolution for this, &amp;
                    had Blake been a man like Palafox,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> José Rebolledo de Palafox y Melzi (1780–1847), Spanish
                        general, who commanded the defending forces at the siege of Zaragoza. The city fell to the French after an outbreak of disease
                        and Palafox was imprisoned.</note> or a Mariano Alvarez,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mariano Álvarez de Castro
                        (1749–1810), Spanish general in charge of the garrison at the siege of Gerona 1809. His forces held out against French troops
                        for eight months before capitulating. Álvarez was imprisoned by the French and died shortly afterwards.</note> the city might
                    indeed have been destroyed, but Suchets<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Gabriel Suchet, 1st Duc d’Albufera
                        (1770–1826), Marshal of France and key figure in the French campaign in the Iberian peninsula. He captured Valencia in January
                        1812.</note> army would have been destroyed also, for the French in Spain are not now in a condition to afford such a
                    consumption of men as Zaragoza cost them. The evil sustained is by no means commensurate to the advantage which might have gained
                    had Suchet been defeated in his attempt – such a defeat would in its consequences have cleared the whole south of Spain; – his
                    victory only puts Valencia in his power, &amp; as much of the province as its garrison can command. And his army instead of having
                    an army to contend with, inferior to itself in every thing which constitutes an army, will have to carry on a harrassing &amp;
                    hopeless warfare with the Guerillas. I shall regard the recovery of Ciudad Rodrigo<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        city of Ciudad Rodrigo had been captured from the French on 19 January 1812.</note> (if it has really taken place) as more
                    than compensating the loss of Valencia, because it is a strong hold, &amp; the invasion of Portugal <del>xx</del> will not be
                    again undertaken on that side till the French have again captured it, an operation which cost Massena<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French Marshal André Massena (1758–1817), one of the commanders of the invasion of Portugal in
                        1810.</note> many weeks in 1810.</p><p rend="indent1"> Blake was the man who prevented the Spanish Government from training their army and British Officers. It is well
                    therefore that he is out of the way. I wish Mahi<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> General Nicolas de Mahy y Romo
                        (1757–1822) prevented his troops being trapped inside Valencia after the battle outside the city on 26 December 1811. Despite
                        Southey’s doubts he ended his career as Governor of Cuba 1821–1822.</note> had been taken too. for there is reason to suspect
                    him. Zayas<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish commander José Pascual de Zayas y Chacón (1772–1827), famed for
                        his skill and daring. He was captured when the Spanish army in Valencia surrendered, and imprisoned in France
                        1812–1814.</note> is a great loss to the Spaniards – he was one of their most promising officers. But it is in vain to look
                    for any success from regular armies there, till they will suffer us to form them, as has been done in Portgual. Till that is done
                    a single individual like Mina<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Espoz y Mina (1781–1836), since 1810 commander of
                        the guerrilleros of Navarre against French troops.</note> or the Empecinado<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Juan
                        Martin Diez (1775–1825), known as ‘El Empecinado’, ‘the Undaunted’, guerilla leader who by 1811 commanded some 3,000 men and
                        disrupted French communications between Madrid and Burgos.</note> is of more service than a dozen ill-formed regiments, where
                    the men can have no confidence in themselves because they have none in those who lead them on.</p><p rend="indent1"> Our own movements in the peninsula indicate a growing spirit of enterprize, tending to give both the men &amp;
                    officers a feeling of their own superiority to the enemy. If our counsels are not stricken with the dead palsy of husbanding
                    politicians I look confidently forward to a career of glory for the British arms, not inferior to that of Marlborough<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough (1650–1722; <title>DNB</title>), British general who had
                        achieved a series of vital military victories during the War of the Spanish Succession (1701–1714). His most famous victory,
                        Blenheim (1704), provided a backdrop to Southey’s anti-war poem ‘The Battle of Blenheim’ (1798).</note> in its splendour, or
                    far transcending it in the importance of its consequences. It has been proved that we can baffle in Portugal the largest force
                    which Buonaparte could assemble against us, – should we ever beat such a force in fair battle, – which is the same thing as
                    saying, should we ever chuse to oppose him with an equal force, his sun would set for ever.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will be surprized to hear that I have not seen Trotters book,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Bernard Trotter (1775–1818; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Latter Years of Charles James Fox</title> (1811). It
                        went into three editions within the year of publication, but was criticised for misrepresentation of Fox’s religious views and
                        for insinuations against his family.</note> – tho if you saw me up to the eyes as I am in books of all kinds which my various
                    occupations require, you would not wonder that I have not found time even to wish for it. I am closely engaged upon the Register
                    for 1810,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title> (1812).</note> – yet not so closely but that my evenings are reserved for
                    other pursuits. You would trace me in this last number of the Quarterly upon the Inquisition,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The History of the Inquisitions; including the Secret Transactions of those Horrific Tribunals</title> (1810);
                            <title>Letter upon the Mischievous Influence of the Spanish Inquisition as it actually exists in the Provinces under the
                            Spanish Government. Translated from El Español, a periodical Spanish Journal published in London</title> (1811);
                            <title>Narrativa da Perseguição de Hippolyto Joseph Da Costa Pereira Furtado de Mendonça, Natural da Colonia do
                            Sacramento, no Rio-da-Prata, prezo e Processado em Lisboa pelo pretenso Crime de Fra-Maçon, ou Pedreiro Livre</title>
                        (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (December 1811), 313–357.</note> &amp; upon <ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomerys</ref> Poems:<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Montgomery,
                            <title>The West Indies, and other Poems</title> (1810) and <title>The Wanderer in Switzerland, and other Poems</title>
                        (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (December 1811), 405–419.</note> for the next I am busy upon the travels in Iceland
                    of Sir G Mackenzie &amp; Hooker,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir George Steuart Mackenzie (1780–1848;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in the Island of Iceland, in the Summer of the Year 1810</title> (1811) and Sir
                        William Jackson Hooker (1785–1865; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of a Tour in Iceland, in the Summer of 1809</title>
                        (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (March 1812), 48–92.</note> both good books. &amp; if there should be time I
                    propose to preface an article upon the modern French Biography,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Biographie Moderne: Lives of Remarkable Characters who have Distinguished themselves from the Commencement of the
                            French Revolution to the Present Time</title> (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (June 1812), 412–438.</note> –
                    that is in other words upon the French Revolution. In the course of a few weeks I propose to send you the reviewal of the <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">Bell</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Lancaster</ref> controversy in a
                    separate form, somewhat altered, enlarged, &amp; I believe materially improved, so as to contain a full, clear &amp; I am sure a
                    very faithful view of the whole subject.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s defence of Bell’s system over
                        Lancaster’s had originally appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (August 1811), 264–304. This formed the basis of
                        his <title>The Origin, Nature, and Object, of the New System of Education</title> (1812).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wolseleys Psalms are better than most attempts of that kind: yet I confess it swept oer me
                    that persons who feel the sublimity of the Psalms strongly should not perceive <del>how</del> that the <del>com</del> version in
                    the Psalter<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> The psalms in the Church of England’s <title>Book of Common Prayer</title>
                        (1662).</note> is &amp; must be superior to any versification of <del>xxxxxxx</del> &lt;it&gt; because it adheres more closely
                    to the original. The use of these versions is gone by. They were employed at the Reformation as weapons against Popery, &amp; put
                    into rhyme as Fuller says that they might be ‘more portable in peoples memories.’<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas
                        Fuller (1607/8–1661; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Church History of Britain</title> (London, 1655), p. 406.</note> Hymns
                    must now serve all purposes of devotion as well.</p><p rend="indent1"> No better reason can be essayed for poor Tommys<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> fate
                    than that his brother did so before him forty years ago, – an odd thing to run in a family. It seems to have been a sudden fit of
                    insanity – precisely what the common people mean when they say the Devil put such a thing into his head. Yet one might think that
                    when there was such a person as Buonaparte in the world, the Devil might have let poor Tommy alone.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey</ref> &amp; her sisters<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sarah Coleridge</ref> and <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary
                        Lovell</ref>.</note> beg to be remembered &amp; join me in remembrances to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> and Miss Brownes.<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably a reference to Wade Browne’s daughters by his first marriage, Lydia (c.
                        1789–1864), Elizabeth (dates unknown) and Sarah (c. 1793/1794–1860s).</note> Little Mary<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Browne (dates unknown), Wade Browne’s only child by his second marriage.</note> I suppose is again grown
                    out of our knowledge. Our young ones would delight in seeing her.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs most truly &amp; respectfully</salute><signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors"> let poor … Robert Southey: Written at top of fol.
                            1.</note></signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>