<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2077</idno><idno type="nines">rce3348</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian
                        Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2077" type="letter"><head>2077. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1812-04-13">13 April 1812</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ 16 AP 16/ 1812<lb/>MS: Bodleian
                        Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1812-04-13">April 13. 1812.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I wrote to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> a few days ago, inclosing a hasty letter to the <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Czar</ref>, relating to a purposed movement of his own great corps into these parts this
                        season.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> These letters do not appear to have survived.</note> I wish we could look
                    forward with as much pleasure to the movement which the other Czar <del>w</del> is making with all his corps toward the
                        Vistula.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Franco-Russian relations had irretrievably broken down. France had 400,000
                        men stationed near the River Vistula, the Russian border, and Alexander I (1777–1825; Emperor of Russia 1801–1825) left St
                        Petersburg to join his troops on 21 April 1812.</note> – Most of my friends have the same cause of complaint against me as
                        <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, every one of them I believe except yourself, – to whom it so happens that
                    I oftener <del>xxxxxx</del> &lt;find&gt; myself writing than to any other person, owing to Pelayo<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was sending Bedford drafts of the poem that became <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                        (1814). Paragraphs 4–9 of this letter relate to Bedford’s critique of Book 4.</note> &amp; Pension &amp;c<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had received a government pension since 1807.</note> – you come in for letters as agent,
                    &amp; franker-under-favour as well as in your own capacity.</p><p rend="indent1"> O Lord! O Lord! how will every body who has read Latimer<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The preacher,
                        Bishop of Worcester and Protestant martyr Hugh Latimer (c. 1485–1555; <title>DNB</title>). Southey owned a collection of his
                            <title>Fruitfull-Sermons</title> (1575), no. 1614 in the sale catalogue of his library. Southey is possibly responding to
                        something Wynn had said.</note> stare at finding power translated into ornament<del>ed</del>! power is the word, &amp; many
                    are the odd things that that oddest of all good Bishops deduced from it. It surprizes me that <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> should not have recognized it, I thought he must have known Latimers sermons,
                    which form one of the most amusing books in the language, &amp; contain invaluable pictures of the manners &amp; feelings of his
                    age.</p><p rend="indent1"> For God’s sake if your side warms you take flight again to the mountains, &amp; come down with <ref target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco</ref>, without delay.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your remarks upon Pelayo shall all be duly perpended – not merely now, but as often as I read or transcribe it.
                    First as to the Porter. You will observe that the transition of tone has been gradual, – the lines which describe Rodericks course
                    from Auria<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 4, lines 88–97.</note> produce a natural fall to the end of the
                    paragraph, &amp; the next may open in <del>xx</del> as low a key as suits the <del>message</del> transition. Now then remember
                    that the Porter is not a Great Mans Porter with a shoulder knot, – but <del>a regular</del> one of the brethren himself, that you
                    are to have <del>an</del> a Benedictine Abbey before your eyes, &amp; a monk at the gate; – &amp; finally – lookez-vous M.
                    Bedford, – what this monk says is as it were the catch word to Odoars speech in reply by which the dialogue is well
                        introduced.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 4, lines 103–106.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> It is necessary to assure Odaor that it is Adosinda, – <del>his speech</del> for he had supposed her dead, – &amp;
                    his <del>first</del> mention of her name is a burst of hope that it <del>must be</del> &lt;is&gt; her.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 4, lines 141–174.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I think I could find you fifty instances of the word doting in its parental sense, but it cannot be mistaken in
                    this place.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 4, line 154.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Perceiving that Urban is the Primate, you see why he is brought forward, the ordination of Roderick is preparatory
                    to one of the final scenes of the poem, which ought to be one of the finest.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 4, lines 284–313.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The two last lines are botches, &amp; stand only for want of <del>xx</del> better.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 4, lines 312–313.</note> You need not be told that both in history
                    &amp; poetry the things which it requires most skill to manage are the transitions, – every thing there depending upon the manner.
                    Thirty’s brow<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 4, line 228.</note> must be referred to a Jury of Poets, <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> has not objected to it. Certainly I should have said “the brow of Thirty”
                    in preference if the metre had allowed it.</p><p rend="indent1"> “With that”<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Used only once in <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814), Book 4 at line 175.</note> is right sterling old English phrase, – no doubt I have used it too
                    often, – <del>&amp; p</del> &amp; this proves its marvellous convenience. You are very right in what you say of the ears taking
                    alarm. Where that is the case any thing becomes obnoxious, – therefore especial care should be taken not to <hi rend="ital">make</hi> it the case.</p><p rend="indent1"> I wish when Curwen speaks in the house about scarcity &amp; the distresses of the Poor, somebody would haul him
                    over <hi rend="ital">his own</hi> coals.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The wealthy colliery owner and Whig MP for
                        Carlisle 1786–1790, 1791–1812, 1816–1820, John Christian Curwen (1756–1828; <title>DNB</title>). <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 98, noted Curwen’s speech in the House of Commons on 11 March 1811, in which he
                        blamed the government’s policy towards America for manufacturing and agricultural distress – ‘the theory of
                        opposition’.</note> Eight years ago I paid 6<hi rend="sup">s</hi> – 6<hi rend="sup">d</hi> a cart thro the year
                        <del>xxxxx</del> – I now pay 10/ for the same quantity, which as I consume not less than sixty carts a year, amount to a
                    direct tax of ten guineas levied upon me by the Pit Holders of whom <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref>
                    &amp; Curwen are the chief. Their last rise was of a shilling upon the cart at the pits – somewhat about thirty per cent. They
                    have <del>xxxxxxxx</del> outwitted themselves, – the ship-masters have forsaken them, the Irish market is now supplied with Scotch
                    coals. Curwen cannot pay his men, &amp; the report is that at this time he dares not show that ugly face of his <del>at</del>
                    &lt;in&gt; Workington.</p><p rend="indent1"> I ought to have replied to what you said about giving <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">Bell</ref> &amp; the
                        <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">dragon</ref><note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Origin, Nature, and Object of the New System of Education</title> (1812), an expansion of Southey’s appraisal of
                        the educational systems advocated by Andrew Bell and Joseph Lancaster, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (October 1811),
                        264–304.</note> to the franker-general,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Spencer Perceval, the Prime Minister and
                        Chancellor of the Exchequer.</note> &amp; am ashamed that it was neglected. However I shall have a more acceptable book<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly <title>Ominiana, or Horae Otiosores</title> (1812).</note> ready in the course of
                    the summer &amp; then the fault shall be supplied.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Bishop of Pimlicos pastoral charge against the new Kehaman heresy is never likely to find its way here.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> As Bedford lived in Pimlico this may be a reference to the review of <title>Kehama</title>
                        in the <title>British Critic</title>, 39 (March 1812), 272–282 – a review that Southey himself had suggested Bedford should
                        write.</note> Pelayo does not advance so <del>ra</del> steadily as it ought – I am but 200 lines in the next book. however you
                    may receive it sooner perhaps than I at present expect. I have no longer that ardour which carried me thro Thalaba<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Islamic romance <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> in twelvemonths, &amp;
                    produced 1200 of the best lines I ever wrote in a single week: perhaps it may be said that I have no longer nothing else to do, –
                    which is certainly true, – yet if the inclination were stronger, the time would be found. The real case <del>xx</del> is that I
                    feel more strongly the necessity of laying in knowledge <del>more than</del> one year than another: when I knew little, with a
                    youngs man presumption I fancied myself well informed; at present I am well informed enough to be very sensible <del>x</del>
                    wherein my knowledge is deficient, &amp; very earnest to supply what is wanting. So I feed like a silkworm instead of spinning
                    like a spider, &amp; like better to have a book in my hand, than a pen.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is now in the mail on his way to London where he will arrive
                    tomorrow. – Did I ever tell you that <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> spent <del>xx</del> a morning in
                    vainly endeavouring to find you out by a lame direction. If you turn Centaur for <del>a xx</del> the sake of exercise, find
                        <del>you</del> your way to <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">your father &amp; mother</ref>, &amp; the <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Master of the Rolls</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> We have the chicken-pox among us, – <del>which I have never had</del>, Heaven send it may not <del>me</del> claim
                    me as an old Cock, having ever spared me in my chick state. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref> brought it
                    here from school.</p><p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco</ref>. I hope soon to hear that he is coming –
                    tell him he can carry on the Español<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>El Español</title>, the political journal founded in 1810 and edited by Blanco White.</note> here, the proofs may
                    follow him. I shall be in the midst of my Portugueze campaign when he comes for the Register<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s work for the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title> (1812).</note> is still far from its
                    close! Alas I begin to feel that the day is short &amp; the labour long.</p><closer><signed rend="indent2"> God bless you – yrs RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> You will perceive that the halfnotes<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Half-banknotes – a secure way of
                            sending money in the post, by tearing banknotes in half and sending the two halves separately.</note> have reached me<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> You will … reached me: Written at top of fol 1r.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>