<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1920</idno><idno type="nines">rce3191</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        24.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1920" type="letter"><head>1920. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1811-05-10">10 May 1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        24<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1811-05-10">May 10. 1811.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have desired <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> to make ready a statement of his services.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was attempting to secure his brother Tom’s promotion from Lieutenant to Captain.</note>
                    Your letter makes me more in hope for him than I have ever before been. – Did you notice a strange story in the papers about a
                        L<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Cunliffe Owen?<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The naval officer Lieutenant Charles
                        Cunliffe-Owen (1786–1872). British newspapers (e.g. the <title>Caledonian Mercury</title>, 6 May 1811) carried reports from
                        the ‘French papers’ that Cunliffe Owen, while a prisoner at Besancon, had tried to persuade two French officers to become
                        involved in a scheme to capture the port of Belleisle-sur-Mer. The clumsy plot had been uncovered and Owen had told all he
                        knew to the French authorities, resulting in the arrest of his co-conspirators. Owen had been taken prisoner on 10 September
                        1810, when boats from HMS <hi rend="ital">Dreadnought</hi> had captured a Spanish merchant ship, which was moored in a creek
                        near Ushant. The boats came under heavy fire and six British sailors were killed, over thirty wounded and two boats drifted
                        onto the shore and their men were imprisoned; see the account in <title>The Times</title>, 15 September 1810. Despite these
                        disasters, Owen escaped in 1813 and eventually became a Captain in 1852.</note> – a very bad story, &amp; from the character
                    of the man a very likely one. He belonged to the Dreadnought in <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom’s</ref> time &amp; was
                    taken prisoner in one of the most foolish boat-expeditions that ever was attempted, in which by his insolent boastings he in a
                    manner compelled an older &amp; better officer than himself to take part. It was an attempt of almost unprecedented folly, &amp;
                    it was bad enough to set it on foot in the way he did, but the worst part of the affair was that some weeks afterwards he wrote to
                    Admiral Sotheby<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rear-Admiral Thomas Sotheby (1759–1831).</note> to say that if he had been
                    properly supported he should have succeeded, thus shifting off the blame upon the poor fellows who had escaped, most of them
                    dreadfully wounded; &amp; who had heard him <del>scr</del> roaring out lustily for quarter before they left him. These men were
                    kept ignorant of what <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> calls his damnd letter, but it could not be concealed from
                    the other L<hi rend="sup">t</hi> than whom a braver man never lived,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Two lieutenants were
                        wounded in this action: Henry Elton (1786–1858) and Stewart Blacker (d. 1826). From Tom Southey’s account, he is more likely
                        to be referring to Lt Blacker.</note> &amp; who was then under the surgeons hands, having returned with a ball in him which
                    was cut out by the side of his back bone, – as desperate a wound as ever any man recovered from. I have often heard <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> speak with the utmost indignation of this Owens whole conduct in the affair, &amp;
                    he says he knows no one so likely to begin &amp; end in the way the French account has stated. I am afraid by his name he stands
                    in some degree of affinity to the family at Ackton.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Cunliffe family of Acton Hall,
                        Wrexham. Wynn was married to Mary Cunliffe (c. 1785–1838).</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> is perfectly clear in all his reasonings.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Herries’ <title>A Review of the Controversy Respecting the High Price of Bullion, and the State of Our
                            Currency</title> (1811).</note> In the concluding part of his argument he seems to see farther than the scope of his
                    immediate argument leads him. I have <del>not</del> no doubt that the pound sterling is our true standard of value &amp; that gold
                    is raised in price by a greatly increased consumption, &amp; a greatly diminished supply. The question as it appears to me is
                    whether this will not soon render it necessary to alter the coinage, – for as soon as gold is issued at its bullion price the
                    temptation for exploiting it ceases. If we did not want it for foreign expenditure it is perfectly clear to me, that it is
                        <del>quite</del> not necessary for home circulation. The whole outcry against paper, wherever it exists, is owing to country
                    banks; the stoppage of one immediately makes all the country people who lose by it, converts to <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref><note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Cobbett was an opponent of
                        paper money.</note> immediately. We had a specimen of this at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> as you may
                        remember.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> For the failure of a local bank in 1810, see Southey to Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford, 14 December 1810, Letter 1839.</note> They ought to be taxed into respectability. <del>xx</del></p><p rend="indent1"> I can hardly think it possible that Parliament will act upon the opinion of the Bullion Committee; – it would be
                    the most preposterous instance of suicidal policy upon record.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Bullion Committee, a
                        select committee of the House of Commons, had recommended in 1810 that convertability between paper currency and gold bullion
                        (suspended in 1797) should be restored. The Commons started to debate the matter on 6 May 1811 and eventually rejected the
                        Committee’s proposals.</note> And yet seeing the fate of the Distillery Bill<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Distillery Bill passed the House of Commons, but was thrown out by the House of Lords on 6 May 1811. For Southey’s summary,
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 92–94. Essentially, the Bill proposed to readjust the
                        duties on sugar and barley to make sugar more attractive for distilling into alcohol. As such it was seen as hostile to
                        British agriculture. Martinique, a sugar-growing island in the West Indies, had been captured from the French in 1809.</note>
                    my faith in the good sense of parliament (which was never very strong) is shaken. I hope I may be mistaken, but I very much fear
                    that a blind &amp; selfish policy has endangered Martinique &amp; will endanger our own sugar islands.</p><p rend="indent1"> O dear Grosvenor! <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> has cut out my note about <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Gog</ref>, &amp; qualified the text till he has taken all the force <del>of</del> out of
                    it! –<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 3 May 1811, Letter 1915.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Here I am still a close prisoner. 480 pages printed. 100 more in the printers hands, three score in my drawer, –
                    &amp; still three weeks work before me. The moment it is done <del>I st</del> we start, &amp; you may reckon (God willing) upon
                    seeing me by the Birth day, but you must not reckon upon making engagements for me. Eltham indeed is in the road to <del>xxx</del>
                        S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Mary Cray,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> At this time, the home of <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Peter Elmsley</ref>.</note> – but I fear Ealing<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#RobertsBarreCharles">Barré Charles Roberts</ref> was from Ealing, so this may be a reference to the
                        home of his father, <ref target="people.html#RobertsEdward">Edward Roberts</ref>, Deputy and First Clerk of the Pells office
                        of the Exchequer.</note> is in the road to no place &amp; that I shall have less disposable time than ever, in consequence of
                    being the greater part of the time quartered at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Moon</ref> desires that <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">his
                        Godfather</ref> may know he is reading Robinson Crusoe,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Daniel Defoe (1659/1661–1731;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Robinson Crusoe</title> (1719).</note> &amp; that <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">his
                        God Uncle</ref>, &amp; <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">his great God grand father</ref> may know it also. He thinks
                    Robinson exceedingly wrong in going to sea against his fathers <del>inclination</del> consent, &amp; is determined never to be a
                    sailor himself.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> writes me word that he thinks the edition of Kehama will be gone by the time
                    a small one is ready, there being 109 on hand, &amp; the demand continuing.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810); the second, duodecimo edition was published in 1811.</note> Madoc also is gone
                    to press again.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> A third edition of <title>Madoc</title> appeared in 1812.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BunburyHenryWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bunbury</ref> as you have probably heard is gone! He had
                        appeared much better, when on Tuesday noon he was seized with a shivering which left him speechless, motionless, &amp;
                        apparently altogether insensible till midnight when he expired. His servants have shown more affection than I have ever heard
                        of in servants before. – every body talks of their distress.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>