<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2168</idno><idno type="nines">rce3439</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 294–296.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2168" type="letter"><head>2168. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1812-11-02">2 November
                        1812</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/
                        Surry<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmarks: E/ 5 NO 5/ 1812<lb/>MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb/>Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 294–296.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1812-11-02">Nov. 2. 1812</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">another daughter</ref>, &amp; all’s well.</p><p rend="indent1"> You would be amused with a letter which I received yesterday from an <ref target="people.html#LongmireJohnMartyn">Evangelical Parson</ref>, to thank me for the benefit which he had derived from reading – Thalaba.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> This had read <title>Thalaba</title> as an allegory of the powers and virtues of Faith, and drawn parallels
                        between events and characters in Southey’s poem and the bible. For Southey’s reply, see his letter to John Martyn Longmire, 4
                        November 1812, Letter 2172.</note> It has strengthened his faith, he says, &amp; he requested permission to send me “a sketch
                    of the instruction to be drawn from it”.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Longmire did send the ‘sketch’. For Southey’s
                        response to it, see his letter to John Martyn Longmire, 21 November 1812, Letter 2181.</note> I dare say this “Moral” will be
                    as good as a sermon – Kehama<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> also is in great odour with him upon the same grounds. – Did I ever tell you
                    of a Clergyman at Hull who <del>wrote</del> sent me some papers showing the resemblance between Kehama &amp; Nebuchadnezzar?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nebuchadnezzar II (c. 634–562 BC), King of Babylon c. 605–562 BC, conqueror of Jerusalem in
                        597 BC. He features prominently in the Biblical books <title>Daniel</title> and <title>Jeremiah</title>. Whilst the identity
                        of the clergyman is not clear, it was possibly the Anglican cleric and classical scholar Richard Patrick (1769–1815;
                        <title>DNB</title>), who held a living at Sculcoates, Hull. The ‘papers’ were possibly those mentioned in Southey’s letter to an unknown correspondent, 9 September 1811, Letter 1953. </note></p><p rend="indent1"> I had a visit from Lord Somerville<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Southey Somerville, 15th Lord
                        Somerville (1765–1819; <title>DNB</title>), agriculturist and third cousin of Southey.</note> about a fortnight ago. He was
                    obliged to introduce himself, for I had forgotten his person &amp; an odd but easy blunder had occurred about his name. While I
                    sat at breakfast he sent to say he would wait on me in half an hour if I was disengaged, &amp; the maid brought in <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLord">Lord Sunderlins</ref> compliments instead – who happens to be our neighbour.</p><p rend="indent1"> A large cargo of B Ayres Gazettes<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Gazeta de Buenos Ayres</title>, which ran from 7 June 1810 to 12 September 1821.</note> are arrived to day from <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, who is a very trusty purveyor of materials for me. He has sent me some
                    very curious letters from Sicily, by means of which &amp; of Henry Wynns<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Henry Watkin
                        Williams Wynn (1783–1856; <title>DNB</title>), diplomat and Wynn’s brother.</note> which I saw at Llangedwin, I shall be able
                    to give much original matter <del>xx</del> upon that subject.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 422–437.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> This years <del>xxxxx xx</del> Register – or rather last years, will give me room I hope for a chapter upon the
                    negroes in Hispaniola, whom we ought to take every possible means of civilizing.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 192–196.</note> Those islands were not meant for white men, –
                    if they had white men would have been found there, or certes white men would be able to work there. Ultimately they must belong to
                    that race whose constitution <del>are</del> &lt;is&gt; suited to the climate; wise measures <del>will</del> &lt;may&gt; make this
                    an easy, as it is an unavoidable, transition; – but if things are left as they are, a series of massacres will lead to the
                    establishment of negro states like the Algerines &amp; the other Barbary pirates.</p><p rend="indent1"> Do you see the Investigador Portuguez?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>O Investigador Portuguese em Inglaterra</title> (1811–19), no. 3409 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note>
                    – D Domingos<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Domingos de Sousa Coutinho, 1st Conde e Marques do Funchal (1760–1833),
                        member of the Portuguese legation in London 1803–1814.</note> has succeeded in getting up a better journal than Hippolyte da
                        Costa’s,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Correio Braziliense</title> (also known as the ‘Literary
                        Warehouse’) was a journal in Portuguese. Edited by Hipolito Jose da Costa (1774–1823), it was printed in London and ran from
                        1808–1822. It was critical of the Portuguese monarchy and advocated liberal ideas. Southey possessed a complete set, no. 3203
                        in the Sale catalogue of his Library.</note> &amp; it is curious to see the effect of the spirit of the times in this
                    publication &lt;which is&gt; avowedly favoured by the P. Court. There are a few curious notices about Brazil in it. Lisbon it
                    seems swarms with newspapers, – &amp; there is a Coimbra Journal,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Jornal de Coimbra</title> (1812–1820), a monthly journal, no. 3498 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note>
                    which seems to be in the manner of a review. What a fortunate country will Portugal be if it obtains all the good of a revolution,
                    without any other suffering than that of the <del>xx</del> war which has led to it!</p><p rend="indent1"> I am hardly in time for the post.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> Love to <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref></salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>