<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1831</idno><idno type="nines">rce3102</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1831" type="letter"><head>1831. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1810-12-01">1 December
                        1810</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: RS./ 1 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1810.’<lb/> MS:
                        Huntington Library, RS 156<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1810-12-01">Dec. 1. 1810.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Rickman</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The shoes arrived in good time, just as having drank my second cup of tea, I was lighting my candle to proceed up
                    stairs to write a letter to you. They fit as well as possible, – &amp; I consider myself as shod for two campaigns at least. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> will pay you for them, he being my receiver-general at his Majestys
                    Exchequer. I believe he leaves <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref> tomorrow for London, having been three weeks there taking lessons in landscape from
                        Green,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The landscape painter and etcher William Green (1760–1823; <title>DNB</title>),
                        who had based himself in Ambleside in 1800 and had a specialism in Lake District scenes.</note> – <del>a melancholy xxx
                        thing</del> it is well that he can amuse himself thus: but it is a melancholy thing to think of a man in his state of organic
                    disease acquiring any &lt;new&gt; accomplishment. </p><p rend="indent1"> Thank you for papers concerning Reform, – some of the arguments are staggering ones, – I will when occasion offers,
                    as it will shortly do, state them fully, &amp; give them their fair weight, whether they turn the balance in my own mind or
                        not.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 282–294, expressed Southey’s forthright condemnation of
                        Parliamentary Reform.</note><del>xx</del> My letter to <ref target="people.html#RobinsonHenryCrabb">Robinson</ref> proves an efficient one. I received a very
                    friendly reply for him, &amp; he has introduced me to a correspondence with the Duke de Albuquerques <ref target="people.html#AbellaManuel">Secretary</ref>, – to whom I have written once, – &amp; for whom I have proferred some
                    specific queries upon points which he will be able to answer because they relate to affairs in which Albuquerque<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish military commander, Jose Miguel de la Cueva, 13th Duke of Alburquerque (1774–1811).
                        For Southey’s account of his final months as ambassador in England, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1
                        (1813), 296–297.</note> was principally concerned. <ref target="people.html#RobinsonHenryCrabb">Robinson</ref> also put me in
                    the way of obtaining information from Colonel Carol<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Parker Carrol (1776–1842),
                        liaison officer between the British and Spanish forces. Later promoted to Major-General and Field Marshal in the Spanish
                        Army.</note> of Romana’s<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish general Pedro Caro y Sureda, 3rd Marquis of la
                            Romana (1761–1811).</note> movements, thro <ref target="people.html#AmyotThomas">Amyot</ref>, Windhams secretary.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Amyot had been private secretary to William Windham (1750–1810;
                            <title>DNB</title>) since 1806.</note> To him <del>x</del> I write tomorrow. And he promises me news &amp; publications
                    from Cadiz as they reach <del>there</del> him. – This second volume is likely to be less imperfect than the first, unless I fail
                    in the Austrian war,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> See <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811),
                        575–659. An account of Austria’s defeat by France in 1809.</note> – tho here it is to be hoped Schill &amp; the Tyrolese will
                    bear me out;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ferdinand von Schill (1776–1809), Prussian officer who attempted to lead a
                        revolution against French control of northern Germany; a revolt in the Tyrol against France’s ally, Bavaria, had been briefly
                        successful in April–November 1809.</note> – as for the contest between mere French &amp; mere Austrians, had there been
                    nothing but the interest of these two nations at stake, I should take less interest in them than in a Long-Main.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A cock-fight that could last as long as a week.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Gemelli Careri<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Giovanni Francesco Gemelli Careri (1651–1725), Italian
                        traveller and adventurer. The authenticity of his <title>Giro del Mondo</title> (1699) was once questioned, but it is now
                        thought to be genuine.</note> has been generally suspected of being a traveller at home, – but I have seen (&amp; cannot
                    recollect where) some late assertion that his veracity has been now placed out of doubt, &amp; that the suspicions were wholly
                        groundless.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s opinion was not shared by all of his contemporaries. See
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 195, which noted that Gemelli performed a ‘voyage round the world …
                        without stirring out of the city of Naples’. Southey pointed the inaccuracy out to John Murray, 22 April 1810, Letter
                        1771.</note> –––</p><p rend="indent1"> I doubt your Penrith account of the effects of arsenic,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> An account of how
                        arsenic could be used to treat ‘agues’, given to Rickman by an ‘intelligent Medical Man’ he met in an inn at Penrith; see
                        Rickman to Robert Southey, 19 November 1810, Huntington Library MS.</note> – because since Wards<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joshua Ward (1684/5–1761; <title>DNB</title>), medical practitioner and inventor of the patent medicine
                        ‘Ward’s Drops’. Of the three varieties of ‘Drops’ (blue, red, and purple), two contained arsenic.</note> time it has been
                    gradually getting into use, &amp; no such effects have been &lt;generally&gt; observed. <del>My</del> The same thing has been said
                    of foxglove, &amp; may I think easily be explained in both cases, &amp; in all similar cases. Dropsy is a disease of debility,
                    &amp; many a man who recovers from a disease dies of the debility which it leaves behind it – Measles not unfrequently produce
                    dropsy &amp; in this manner, – but the <hi rend="ital">causa causans</hi><note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘The primary cause’.</note> is known, &amp; nobody ever thinks of imputing the effect to
                    the medicine.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have seen to night extracts of letters from Lisbon, written by Sealy<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Richard Sealy (d. 1821), merchant based in Lisbon.</note> (<ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">my
                        sister-in-laws</ref> father) a great friend of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, &amp; a
                    stout-hearted as well as strong-headed man. He is confident of success &amp; in high spirits. People, he says, go from Lisbon to
                    see the lines – just as Londoners go to a Review, at Blackheath. The sailors make a most grotesque scene – they are stationed at
                    Alhandra, a town which has been forsaken by all the inhabitants, &amp; there these fellows sit out in the streets in the huge old
                    fashioned armed-chairs of the Portugueze, smoaking &amp; drinking, &amp; as happy as their hearts can desire. – My own opinion is
                    that Massena<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French Marshal André Massena (1758–1817), one of the commanders of the
                        invasion of Portugal in 1810.</note> will cross the Tagus, – but he must pay dearly if he does it.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>