<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2466</idno><idno type="nines">rce3737</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey,
                        4 vols (London, 1856) .  Previously  published: Lucy Barton,
                            Selections from the Poems and Letters of Bernard Barton
                        (London, 1849), pp. 107–108 [in part]; and John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), II, pp. 370–372.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2466" type="letter"><head>2466. Robert Southey to [<ref target="people.html#BartonBernard">Bernard
                    Barton</ref>], <date when="1814-08-03">3 August 1814</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>,
                        4 vols (London, 1856) <lb/>Previously published: Lucy Barton,
                            <title>Selections from the Poems and Letters of Bernard Barton</title>
                        (London, 1849), pp. 107–108 [in part]; and John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), II, pp. 370–372.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1814-08-03">August 3. 1814.</date></dateline><salute>My Dear Sir,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I should have answered your letter immediately, if I had not been
                    engaged with visitors when it arrived. In the course of my life, I have more
                    than once had reason to be thankful for having done things which would have been
                    left undone if the first impulse had been suffered to pass by; for second
                    thought in matters of feeling usually brings with it hesitation, and demurral,
                    and doubt, from which the whole brood of sins of omission are derived. Your
                    letter affected me. It seems to come from a good heart, and a wounded one; and
                    therefore I will venture to say what is upon my mind, in spite of those obvious
                    considerations which might prevent me. You tell me that your schemes of
                    happiness are for ever frustrated; and this, you say, after years enough have
                    elapsed since your bereavement<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Barton’s wife, Lucy Jessup (1781–1808), died in childbirth after a year of
                        marriage. He never re-married.</note> to have taken away the keenness of
                    grief. But though the object of your earliest attachment is lost, I think you
                    act erroneously in resolving that no other shall supply its place. If I may
                    judge of you by your letter, I can perfectly understand by how natural a process
                    of sorrow you would be induced thus, as it were, to consecrate your affections
                    to her who is in the world of spirits. But if you had a son who, in the same
                    circumstances, were to form the same resolution, you would blame as well as pity
                    him. Our happiness, and I may almost venture to add our virtue also, is in
                    proportion to the duties which we perform. A second attachment will never be
                    like the first in degree, but it may be like it in kind; it would not be
                    difficult to find a woman who would place her whole affections upon you; and in
                    making her happiness you would find your own. The evening of life affords no
                    cheerful prospect to the happiest of us; to him whom it will find in loneliness,
                    a most mournful one.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall be very glad to receive your little volume.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Barton’s <title>Metrical Effusions, or
                            Verses on Various Occasions</title> (1812).</note> If it be left either
                    at <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Messrs. Longmans’</ref>, in
                    <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster Row</ref>, or at <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Mr. Murray’s</ref>,
                    in Albemarle Street, it will find its way to me in a parcel.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The volume was eventually sent to Murray;
                        see Southey to John Murray, [c. 26 November 1814], Letter 2505.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> From what I have heard, I believe that the “Magazine” has given
                    you a portrait of me, as little accurate as its information about my poem.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Two recent magazine biographies of
                        Southey had appeared: A ‘Memoir of Robert Southey, Esq.’ and a portrait
                        ‘Engraved by Blood, from an Original Drawing by Edridge [Henry Edridge
                        (1768–1821; <title>DNB</title>)], in the Possession of G.C. Bedford, Esq.’,
                            <title>European Magazine</title>, 66 (July 1814), [3]-5; and a memoir
                        and portrait (taken from the bust sculpted by James Smith (1775–1815)),
                            <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 1 (January-July 1814),
                        Frontispiece; 566–571.</note> I am a man of forty; younger in appearance and
                    in habits, older in my feelings and frame of mind. I have been married nearly
                    nineteen years, and I have had seven children, two of whom (one being my
                    firstborn) are in a better world.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">Margaret</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma Southey</ref>.</note> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">eldest</ref> now living is
                    in her eleventh year. There is only <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">one
                        boy</ref> among them; he is nearly eight, and has me for his
                    schoolmaster and play-father, – characters which we find it very easy to
                    combine. You call me a fortunate being, and I am so; because I possess the will,
                    as well as the power, of employing myself for the support of my family, and
                    value riches exactly at what they are worth. I have store of books, and pass my
                    life among them, finding no enjoyment equal to that of accumulating knowledge.
                    In worldly affairs, the world would consider me as unfortunate, for I have been
                    deprived of a good property which, by the common laws of inheritance, should
                    have been mine;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The property of
                        Southey’s childless uncles, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John
                            Southey</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTomUncle">Thomas
                            Southey</ref>.</note> and this through no fault, error, or action of my
                    own. But my wishes are bounded by my wants, and I have nothing to desire but a
                    continuance of the blessings which I enjoy.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> Enough of this. Believe me, with the best wishes for
                        your welfare,</salute><salute rend="indent3"> Sincerely yours,</salute><signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>