<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2659</idno><idno type="nines">rce3930</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                    25.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2659" type="letter"><head>2659. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1815-10-03">3 October 1815</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>Postmark: [partial] FOREIGN/ OC 6/<lb/>Endorsement: Brussels 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Octo<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1815<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                    25<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1815-10-03">Tuesday morning. 3 Oct. 1815. </date><address><placeName> Brussels</placeName></address></dateline><salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I write a few hasty lines more as matter of business than as any thing else, because I wish you to advise <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> that I have drawn on him for £50, payable to Engelbert Werth on order a
                    merchant of this place,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Engelbert Werth (dates unknown), a German-born merchant and
                        acquaintance of Southey’s fellow traveller Vardon. Werth later drew a plan of the battle of Waterloo for Southey.</note> who
                    seems very intimately connected with the <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Mag. Rots</ref> friend Hercules Sharp.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hercules Sharpe (d. 1858), of Domons, Nothiam in Sussex. He was a London merchant and
                        historian of the Brabazon family, into which he had married.</note> Finding that this could be done I preferred it to drawing
                    on <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>, especially as I have found no letters here, – a very natural
                    consequence of not knowing where to look for them. I have bought beaucoup de livres,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Lots
                        of books’.</note> – one package (a small one) will go from Ghent, another detachment containing somewhat about 120 volumes
                    from hence. And I have bespoken a set of the Acta Sanctorum<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey met with mixed success
                        on his book-buying expedition in Belgium and France. For a while, he hoped he had bought the complete set of the rare, 53
                        volume <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (Brussels, 1643–1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue of his library. In fact he received
                        from the bookseller a 6 volume edition of 1783–1794, no. 152 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> which will be sent
                    as soon as Verbiest<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean-Baptiste Ver Beyst (1770–1849) was a famous bookseller in
                        Brussels.</note> can compleat it, (a certain thing) &amp; for which he will draw upon me at <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> for 500 franks.</p><p rend="indent1"> As for the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Docstor</ref> heaven knows what has become of him, for
                    neither tale nor tidings can I discover: this only I conclude that as my letter written to him from Ostend is not lying at the
                    post office, he has received it &amp; is gone on. We have joined company with the <ref target="people.html#VardonMr">Vardons</ref>
                    of Greenwich (friends of Knox<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John William Knox (1784–1862), clergyman, scholar and usher
                        at Westminster School 1806–1821.</note> to whom I pray you communicate this) they have with them Miss Forman<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Miss Forman. Unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> niece of <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Ch. Collins’s</ref> widow,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s old
                        schoolfriend, Charles Collins (d. 1806), had married Jane Forman (dates unknown).</note> &amp; <ref target="people.html#NashEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nash</ref> an artist, &amp; <del>x</del> deformed man, but a very
                    interesting one. <ref target="people.html#VardonMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> V.</ref> is a very pleasing woman, her sister is
                    married to George Maule.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Maule (d. 1851); a friend of Southey’s during his time at
                        Oxford, and possibly during his school days. Maule pursued a legal career and in 1818 was made Solicitor to the Treasury. He
                        had married Caroline Forsyth Tarbutt (dates unknown) in 1810.</note> We stayed two nights at Bruges, – a most interesting
                    place. A day longer at Ghent which pleased me less; &amp; here we have been since Thursday night, – the presence of the
                        Emperor<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander I (1777–1825; Emperor of Russia 1801–1825). He was in the
                        Netherlands to attend William I’s (1772–1843; King of the Netherlands, 1815–1840) oath to uphold the new State’s constitution
                        at Brussels on 21 September 1815.</note> having prevented us from getting away sooner. To day we start for Waterloo, &amp;
                    sleep at Jemappe – thence to Namur Liege Spa &amp; Aix la Chapelle, – from whence we turn homeward. The Rhine I leave for another
                    year, – when perhaps you will accompany me there.</p><p rend="indent1"> Here I have bought a histoire du Brazil in three vol. 8vo by Alphonse de Beauchamp<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alphonse de Beauchamp (1769–1832), <title>Histoire du Brésil</title> (1815); no. 138 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey’s library.</note> author of a history of the war in la Vendee &amp;c<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Histoire de la Guerre de la Vendée et des Chouans</title> (1806).</note> – just fresh from Paris. He says in his
                    preface that he could have published the first part many years ago, but that he chose to wait till the whole was compleated &amp;
                    employed seven years in collecting materials &amp; arranging his work, that having finished the two first volumes he thought it
                    necessary to see what farther information could be obtained from recent works, that meantime <del>M. Southey published</del> a
                        <del>first volume of a</del> &lt;<hi rend="ital">compilation</hi> upon the&gt; history of B appeared –<del>a compilation</del>
                    &lt;in London&gt;.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alphonse de Beauchamp (1769–1832), <title>Histoire du Brésil</title>,
                        3 vols (Paris, 1815), I, p. x.</note> “Sans offrir de nouvelles lumieres l’auteur Anglais (M. Southey) faisait esperance qu’un
                    second volume, annoncé pour 1810, compléterait les annales du Bresil<del>e</del>, et donnerait des renseignemens tout<del>e</del>
                    a fait nouveaux sur la géographie et sur la statique de cette vaste contrés. Vain espoir; l’attente de l’Europe littéraire a été
                    encore une fois trompéi. Ce second volume, si emphatiquement promis n’a point paru.”<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        ‘Without offering any new insights the English author (Mr Southey) gave hope that a second volume, announced for 1810, would complete the Annals of Brazil, and would give quite new information on the geography and statistics of that vast country. A vain hope; literary Europe has once again been disappointed. This second volume, so emphatically promised, has not appeared.’</note> – You will already have guessed that this
                    fellow has literally &amp; truly stolen my book<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey’s
                            <title>History of Brazil</title>, published in 1810.</note> &amp; published it as his own. He has added an introductory
                    chapter about the history of the mother country, &amp; left out much, – but chapter after chapter is mere translation. he has
                    absolutely had no other guide, – no other source, – no other original. my first volume carries him one third into his last, &amp;
                    then he hurries over the whole matter of my second &lt;volume&gt; as well as he can. And his list of authorities is copied from my
                    marginal references, – even to the blunder of arranging different parts of the same volume (so done by me for precision) as
                    different works. He quotes my manuscripts also in this list, – &amp; to crown the whole makes blunders which decisively prove that
                    he does not understand Portugueze – &amp; has not even the commonest acquaintance with that language. I have exceedingly amused
                    with this fellows impudence. How comfortable he will feel when <del>some</del> one of his countrymen shall publish a fair
                    translation of my compleat work, – as doubtless one day or other, &amp; probably at no distant day, will be the case. </p><p rend="indent1"> Tell <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> that I have seen the Beguinage at Ghent within &amp;
                    without &amp; that it is the most interesting thing in Flanders. I have begun a letter to him.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to John Rickman, 2[–16] October 1815, Letter 2658.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> We met <ref target="people.html#LockerEdwardHawke">Locker</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LockerEleanor">his wife</ref> at Bruges. In the boat from thence
                    to Ghent we were annoyed by a Baronets carriage, – the two persons who belonged to it kept aloof from all the passengers in a way
                    which was taken for superciliousness, &amp; called forth many sarcastic remarks from officers &amp; others on board. It was
                    however discovered, or surmised, that they were Peel<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Peel (1788–1850;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Chief Secretary for Ireland 1812–1818 and later Prime Minister 1834–1834, 1841–1846.</note> &amp;
                        Saxton.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Charles Saxton, 2nd Baronet (1773–1838), MP for Cashel 1812–1818 and
                        Under-Secretary for the Civil Department in Ireland. Southey had been introduced to him by Wynn in 1804.</note> I do not
                    remember the person of the latter, &amp; he perhaps would not chuse at this time to recognise me.</p><p rend="indent1"><del>I have</del> Now for packing &amp; breakfast &amp; then away for Waterloo. I have heard much concerning it, &amp; planned a
                    poem much to my satisfaction.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title>
                        (1816).</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p>P.S. Read those letters as if they were Hebrew &amp; written without points.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                            diacritic marks which indicate vowels in the Hebrew script. So, ‘P.S.’ might be read as ‘pee is’ – a reference to the
                            resolution of Southey’s own urinary difficulties.</note> They will then properly introduce the information that the Mamuke
                        was <del>in</del> not troubled with any complaint in the urinary passages when I saw him on Friday.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>