<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2301</idno><idno type="nines">rce3572</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47888 .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 69–72.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2301" type="letter"><head>2301. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <date when="1813-09-16">16 September
                        1813</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To Mrs Southey,/ Keswick,/ Cumberland./
                        Single<lb/>Postmark: SE/ 16/ 1813<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47888 <lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 69–72.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1813-09-16">Thursday morning. Sept. 16. 1813</date></dateline><salute>My dear Edith</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> This is the first moment in which it has been possible for me to write, &amp; I scarcely know with what to begin.
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> will certainly set out for <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> in two or three weeks, as soon as he has settled <ref target="people.html#MorganJohnJames">Morgans</ref>
                    affairs as he hopes to recover for the women<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#MorganMary">Mary Morgan</ref> and her sister Charlotte Brent (dates unknown).</note> about 200£ a
                    year out of the wreck.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Edith Southey, 5–7 September 1813, Letter
                        2299.</note> They would not hear of going into Cumberland at first, but he says that they have since listened to the proposal
                    with less unwillingness, &amp; talked of boarding with Porters mother<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably the mother
                        of Joseph Porter (d. 1834), an Anglican clergyman in Bristol and later Rector of St Johns, Bristol. Porter was involved in
                        plans to help both the Morgans and Coleridge.</note> in Wasdale; so that it is likely enough they may go down with him. He is
                    thinking of another dramatic piece, &amp; you may tell <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">your sister</ref> that I have very
                    little doubt of his making a fair income in this way. – Of the Laureateship nothing more has been heard, and probably the next
                    intelligence about it may be in the Gazette. There can be no doubt that it will be mine, tho of course I shall not reckon upon it
                    till the appointment has been signed. Now my dear Edith, whenever this does take place, I have made up my mind to consider it as a
                    God-send the use of which I may very well forego &amp; therefore the best manner in which it can be applied will be to insure my
                    life as far as the salary will go; it will cover an insurance for 2500£, or perhaps 3000£. The paltry income <del>xxxxxxxx</del>
                    which is attached to the laurel becomes of real importance by enabling me to make this provision in addition to my former
                    insurance. <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> tells me that there can be no better way of investing money; for if at
                    any time I should find it either unnecessary or inconvenient to continue <del>xx</del> the insurance (either from being too rich
                    to need it, or too poor to afford it) the office will always purchase my life out, – that is they will repay all that has paid in
                    with a current interest upon it. And the advantage is always increasing, so much so that the one thousand for which I stand
                    insured would in case of my death at this time produce 1100, – a yearly interest of 2½ per cent accruing upon the sum insured. –
                    As soon as my appointment is gazetted I will give <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> a power of attorney to receive
                    the salary, &amp; apply it in this manner.</p><p rend="indent1"> My time has been dissipated as you may suppose. I went to Courtenays<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas
                        Peregrine Courtenay (1782–1841; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Totnes 1811–1832 and Secretary of the Board of Control 1812–1828.
                        He had previously been a civil servant at the Exchequer, where he probably encountered Grosvenor Bedford.</note> on Wednesday
                    in the last week – came here the next day &amp; worked hard that evening &amp; the whole of Friday. Saturday dined with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, being his birth day, where <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#NicholsJohn">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi>
                        Nicol</ref> dined with us, &amp; <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> &amp; Rosenhagen<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anthony Rosenhagen (1778–1854), financial expert and friend of Landor. He started life as a junior civil
                        servant, but rose swiftly to be Private Secretary to the Chancellor of the Exchequer, 1811–1815.</note> (<ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Percevals</ref> late, &amp; Vansittarts<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicholas
                        Vansittart, 1st Baron Bexley (1766–1851; <title>DNB</title>), Chancellor of the Exchequer 1812–1823.</note> present secretary)
                    came in the evening. Sunday morning I <del>xx</del> saw <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#AllstonWashington">Allstone</ref>, &amp; went to look at the latters great picture,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably a reference to Allston’s <title>Dead Man Revived by Touching the Bones of the Prophet
                            Elisha</title> (1811–1814).</note> which proves him to be as great a painter as <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> used to represent him. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; I then walked to Richmond. We found M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Walpole<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Sophia (d. 1829), widow of Robert Walpole (1736–1810), envoy to Portugal, 1771–1800.</note> staying at <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John Mays</ref>, &amp; Laurence the painter<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Thomas
                        Lawrence (1769–1830; <title>DNB</title>). He specialised in portraits and painted Southey in 1829.</note> dined there. Monday
                    to see Miss Dee at Mortlake<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Miss Dee may have been another old friend from Portugal, possibly one of the daughters of James Dee (d. 1767), the Vice-Consul in Lisbon.</note> from whence we returned by water.
                    Tuesday an hours walk to see <ref target="people.html#SetonBarbara">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Bannister</ref>, who by great good hap
                    is visiting her cousins Miss Berrys.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The author Mary Berry (1763–1852;
                        <title>DNB</title>) and her sister Agnes (1764–1852; <title>DNB</title>), confidantes of Horace Walpole, 4th Earl of Orford
                        (1717–1797; <title>DNB</title>).</note> I need not tell you of the thousand inquiries she made &amp; the thousand remembrances
                    she sent. She is thin &amp; looks much other than she did eleven years ago when we saw her last. Returned to Richmond to breakfast
                    by appointment at between one &amp; two with Madam Stael.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anne Louise Germaine de
                        Staël-Holstein (1766–1817), the writer and salonnière, who was much feted during her 1813 visit to England.</note> Let me
                    caution you here against that green eyed monster whose influence over you I have on other occasions had occasion to remark &amp;
                    regret. M. Stael is called ugly, – I did not find her so, for tho her complexion is exceedingly &lt;dark&gt; &amp; the cast of her
                    countenance more resembles that of a negro than of an European the whole expression of the face is good as well as animated &amp;
                    she has fine eyes &amp; eye brows. I expected a very clever woman, &amp; found what I had not expected a very sensible &amp; very
                    pleasing one. You will probably see her next year on her way to Edinburgh.</p><p rend="indent1"> At Richmond I called on Lord Bute<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Stuart, 1st Marquess of Bute
                        (1744–1814; <title>DNB</title>). He was Ambassador to Spain 1795–1796 and had a collection of Spanish books.</note> without
                    seeing him. past an evening <hi rend="ital">por meos peccados</hi><note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘for my sins’.</note>
                    at the Dowager Countess of Kingstons,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Caroline King (c. 1754–1823), widow of Robert King,
                        2nd Earl of Kingston (1754–1799).</note> &amp; saw the Hairs, Tonkins &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Burn.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> All acquaintances from Portugal. At one time, John May had been in love with Charlotte Hair.
                        Southey had been close to Anne Tonkin (b. 1773) on his first visit to Lisbon in 1796. By this time the Tonkins seem to have
                        re-located to Richmond. Mrs Burn was the wife of the merchant William Burn (fl. 1770s-1810s) of the British Factory.</note>
                    Yesterday morning <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; I went from Richmond by the passage boat to
                    Westminster Bridge, – after which I walked here – &amp; my letter to you would have been written last night if M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Davis had not dropt in with his nephew a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jones<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reynold
                        Davies (1752–1822), Curate of Streatham and a neighbour of Herbert Hill’s. He ran a school for small boys. His nephew is
                        unidentified, but had presumably received one of a number of Travelling Fellowships offered at Oxford and Cambridge
                        Universities</note>. who on a travelling fellowship is just going to Spain. – Proof sheets &amp; letters will occupy the whole
                    of this morning, &amp; <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> come here to dine &amp; to sleep. I expect a note from
                        Mackintosh<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The politician and writer Sir James Mackintosh (1765–1832;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> about meeting M. Stael again tomorrow, – but it is very likely that he may fail in discovering
                    where to address it. However I shall see her again for she is the reigning Lioness &amp; her praise would be more profitable than
                    that of any other person at this time. <hi rend="ital">puffez vous me</hi> you know is what we ought to say to our friends, – but
                    moreover I like well what I saw of her. – With all this locomotion &amp; round of visits you will conclude that I have not made
                    much progress in the business which brought me to <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was writing a pamphlet entitled <title>An Exposure of the Misrepresentations and Calumnies in Mr
                            Marsh’s Review of Sir George Barlow’s Administration at Madras. By the Relatives of Sir George Barlow</title> (1813). This
                        was a defence of Sir George Barlow’s (1763–1846; <title>DNB</title>) conduct as Governor of Madras in 1807–1813, especially
                        during the army mutiny of 1809. It was a direct reply to Charles Marsh (c. 1774–1835; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Review of
                            Some Important Passages in the Late Administration of Sir G. H. Barlow, Bart., at Madras</title> (1813).</note> I have
                    however got fairly into it, much to the satisfaction of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> B<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> William
                        Barlow (1759–1839) a merchant and neighbour of Herbert Hill’s in Streatham. Brother of Sir George Barlow.</note> &amp; shall
                    get fairly thro it by the end of the month, that is to say in a fortnight from this time. When it is done I shall let him take me
                    to visit his brother Sir Robert<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The naval officer Sir Robert Barlow (1757–1843;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> at Chatham for two, or at the utmost, three days, then move into town for about ten or twelve
                    days, – <del>for</del> I need not tell you how weary I am of this life &amp; how I long to be at home once more. Except this
                    feeling – I am as well &amp; as comfortable in all respects as you could desire.</p><p rend="indent1"> As for the thousand guineas,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The sum Murray had offered Southey for his
                            <title>History of the Peninsula War</title> (1823–1832).</note> you need not talk of economizing while I am getting it,
                    for my means are increasing every year, &amp; I am beginning to reap the fruits of a well earned reputation. We shall print 750
                    copies of Roderick<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> in quarto instead of 500 &amp; there is no doubt of their sale.
                    Espriella is going to press again, &amp; I shall follow the new edition with the additional volumes.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> A third edition of <title>Letters from England</title> appeared in 1814; no additional volumes were
                        published.</note> There will be plenty of money as there always has been, God be thanked, – &amp; when this additional
                    insurance makes my family worth 4000£ in this way alone, I am sure you will cease to have any anxieties upon that score. The
                    Quarterly will most likely be out next week – there will be about 30£ from it to send you. – <del>xx</del> The business of <ref target="people.html#MaloneCatherine">Miss Malones</ref> maid<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been
                        investing some money on behalf of Sarah Ansell (dates unknown), who was a servant in the household of one of the two sisters
                        of Southey’s friend <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLord">Richard Malone, Lord Sunderlin</ref>, Henrietta Malone (c.
                            1745–1824) or <ref target="people.html#MaloneCatherine">Catherine Malone</ref>.</note> was to be finished yesterday by<ref target="people.html#MayJohn"> John
                        May</ref>, tell me in your next if I shall send the paper from the Bank to Keswick, or to Ireland, &amp;– if they are gone
                    from Keswick, you must look in my desk for <ref target="people.html#MaloneCatherine">Miss Malones</ref> note with their Irish
                    direction, – which I forgot to take with me.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have letters from <ref target="people.html#AbellaManuel">Abella</ref>, who is putting all his means in motion
                    (&amp; they are great ones) to procure documents for my great work, about this things are so far settled that the appearance of
                    the book is to be as splendid as the subject. – </p><p rend="indent1"> Tell <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> that I am much pleased with her letter; <del>it is very
                        well</del> the writing is very good, &amp; I am not disposed to find fault with the spelling, tho there ought to be two r r s
                    in Aballiboozobanganorribo.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> A nonsense word much favoured by Southey; used as a ‘mystic word’ in ‘Interchapter II’ of <title>The
                            Doctor</title>, 7 vols (London, 1834–1847), I, pp. 91–94.</note> I shall write letters both to her &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">the Moon</ref> before I return.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Robert
                        Southey to Edith May Southey, 20 September 1813, Letter 2304; no letter to Herbert Southey appears to have survived.</note> My
                    seal &amp; yours will probably be finished when next I go to town. I like the laureateship so well since I have determined in what
                    matter to appropriate the salary, that I have more than half a mind to order you a seal with a lyre &amp; a laurel wreath &amp;
                    the motto <hi rend="ital">jam revirescat</hi> – “it will now grow green again.” </p><p rend="indent1"> There is no appearance of another cousin. I am a huge favourite with two of these young ones<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s first cousins, <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref>, <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Herbert</ref> and <ref target="people.html#HillErrol">Errol</ref>, the sons of
                        Herbert and Catherine Hill.</note> &amp; have raised all three to the peerage in honour of the parts they bear in <del>the
                        story of</del> &lt;by similitude&gt; their favourite story<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Southey’s rendition
                        of ‘The Three Bears’, which was first published in <title>The Doctor</title>, 7 vols (London, 1834–1847), IV, pp.
                        318–321.</note> by the name of Duke Bruin, Marquis Bruin, &amp; Earl Bruin, – so you may give <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> a kiss &amp; tell her that her Welsh Uncles are all Bruins as well as herself.
                    I have bought some Arabian Tales<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Arabian Tales</title>, translated into English in 1792 by Robert Heron (1764–1807; <title>DNB</title>).</note> for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> &amp; the Persian &amp; Turkish<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Probably a volume of the <title>Persian and Turkish Tales. From the French of M. Petis de la Croix</title> (1809), translated
                        by William King (1663–1712; <title>DNB</title>). There was, however, a problem with the book Southey had purchased; see
                        Southey to Thomas De Quincey, 19 January 1814, Letter 2366.</note> for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Lunus</ref>. –
                    The last letter which you forwarded was from <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref>, he is on his
                    way to Cumberland, but how long it may be before he gets there I know not. – <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>
                    has another daughter:<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors"> The name of Wynn’s daughter is not recorded, so presumably she died young. Wynn had three living daughters, but his only son, Watkin, had died young in 1811.</note> – he is out of luck. – I have not had time to see <ref target="people.html#LovellRobertJr">Robert</ref> &amp; no doubt many other persons are now accusing me of incivility for not
                    having called upon them. </p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> is just arrived—so I will only add love to all. Tell the <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhora</ref> that I will not forget to see Miss Linwoods<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Linwood (1755–1845; <title>DNB</title>), artist in needlework. Her exhibition of copies of Old Master
                        paintings was on display at Leicester Square.</note> pictures – &amp; tell her without loss of time to make a paper book,
                    &amp; begin immediately to put therein things for the Book of Books. </p><closer><salute rend="indent4"> God bless you </salute><signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>