<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2546</idno><idno type="nines">rce3817</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text is taken from Eustace R. Conder,
                            Josiah Conder: A Memoir (London, 1857).  Previously  published: Eustace R. Conder, Josiah Conder: A
                            Memoir (London, 1857), pp. 169–172 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2546" type="letter"><head>2546. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ConderJosiah">Josiah Conder</ref> [fragment], <date when="1815-01-28">28
                        January 1815</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Eustace R. Conder,
                            <title>Josiah Conder: A Memoir</title> (London, 1857)<lb/>Previously published: Eustace R. Conder, <title>Josiah Conder: A
                            Memoir</title> (London, 1857), pp. 169–172 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1815-01-28">January 28, 1815.</date></dateline><salute>My Dear Sir,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have dealt very uncivilly by you, and am heartily ashamed of it. Let this suffice for apology – and forgive
                    me.</p><p rend="indent1"> I thought ere this to have offered you an article for your <title>Review</title>, taking for its text some
                    pamphlets of Perring’s upon the state of our ships in the navy, and from thence examining, with all freedom and in the real spirit
                    of reform, the state of the men as well as of the timber.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Perring (c. 1767–1839),
                        Clerk of the Cheque at the Royal Dockyards in Plymouth. Perring was best-known for improving the design of anchors. His
                        pamphlet was <title>A Brief Inquiry into the Causes of Premature Decay in our Wooden Bulwarks, with an Examination of the
                            means best calculated to prolong their duration</title> (1812). Southey commended his plans for ‘laying up our ships in
                        ordinary’ (<title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (October 1814), 187). His proposed article for the <title>Eclectic
                            Review</title> was not written.</note> The delay has not been from idleness, but from over-occupation; and in some
                    respects it has been fortunate, for I understand Perring’s plans have now been so far adopted as to satisfy him, and a most
                    essential step has been taken towards improving the condition of the men, by setting them free after twenty-one years of service,
                    with a fair pension for life: a measure which I earnestly called for some years ago.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Admiralty had reformed the Royal Navy pension system, so that all sailors were entitled to a pension after 14 years service
                        and all could demand their discharge after 21 years service, with a pension of at least 1<hi rend="ital">s</hi>. per day.
                        These measures were announced publicly in January 1815. Southey had advocated similar ideas in the <title>Quarterly
                        Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 353–354 (in his article on ‘the Poor’, 319–356).</note> What I have to say therefore may be
                    said now with more grace, as there will be much to commend.</p><p rend="indent1"> The moral defects of <ref target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron’s</ref> poems are well pointed out in the
                        <title>Eclectic</title>, and due justice is done to the vigour of his style.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        review of <title>Lara, A Tale</title> (1814) in <title>Eclectic Review</title>, 2 (October 1814), 393–400; although praising
                        the portrayal of Medora, and finding the poem significantly less troubling than <title>The Corsair</title> (1814), the review
                        expressed: ‘regret that Lord Byron should not see the false taste to say nothing of the inexcusable impiety, of the almost
                        atheistical insinuations by which some of the finest passages in his poetry are disfigured … When ascribed to an ideal
                        personage, such as Childe Harold, the same language might be tolerated, as dreadfully appropriate to the character: but when
                        the poet in his own person adopts the same sentiments as expressive of his individual feelings or belief, we can no longer
                        conceal from ourselves that they betray a degree of irreligion, which, in a Christian country, can scarcely be referred to any
                        other origin than the most melancholy ignorance. Of all descriptions of cant, the cant of scepticism is the most offensive,
                        and the most nearly allied to absurdity’ (398).</note> But there is a radical and characteristic fault in most of his tales,
                    which has not been sufficiently exposed: the characters which he describes are impossible; no such ever have existed, or ever can
                    exist. It is perfectly absurd to suppose that anything like the strong, abiding, soul-rooted feeling of love can be found in a
                    buccaneer – setting all the other unaccountable parts of the story out of the question. His characters are made up of
                    contradictions; and because the parts are all powerfully drawn, common readers never pause to ask themselves whether they could
                    possibly cohere. Do not imagine that I blame him for portraying <hi rend="ital">mixed</hi> characters – there is alloy enough in
                    the best of us, God knows! – I condemn him for making an impossible mixture. The real cause of this monstrosity is sufficiently
                    obvious. Like <ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomery</ref>, he has been painting from the looking-glass; but he had
                    not so good an original, and, unlike <ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomery</ref>, his day-dreams have been of evil.
                    His fancy has brooded upon his own heart, and, cameleon-like, taken its colour from thence: unhappily, the colour is a dark one.
                    And being conscious that he is in many of his feelings, and most or all of his opinions (certainly in all that relates to the
                    highest and holiest subjects), a sort of outlaw in the world, he makes his heroes bid defiance to all positive law, and transfers
                    to them all his own unhappy principles. But men who act like his characters are men not of <hi rend="ital">bad</hi> principles,
                    but of <hi rend="ital">no</hi> principles; not of <hi rend="ital">diseased</hi> feelings, but of <hi rend="ital">callous</hi>
                    ones. <ref target="people.html#Byron">Lord B.</ref> has just married a woman who is said to be one of the loveliest and most
                    accomplished of her sex.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anne Isabella Milbanke (1792–1860; <title>DNB</title>) had
                        married Byron on 2 January 1815.</note> When he finds himself a happier man, he may perhaps become a better one. But the
                    experiment on her part is a perilous one; and I should tremble if she were my daughter.</p><p rend="indent1"> You have not, in my judgment, given <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldRobert">Bloomfield</ref> more praise than he
                        deserves.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Electic Review</title>, 2 (November 1814), 461- 462, had defended
                        Bloomfield against his critics and praised him as: ‘a man of modest unpretending merit, and of real genius, of whom it is
                        equally ungenerous and unjust to speak in the language of contempt. In spite of the ridiculous efforts of well-meaning patrons
                        who degraded him by comparisons which cannot be sustained, or by exhibiting him in the ludicrous character of a prodigy, and
                        in spite of the injustice of those who would try his compositions by a standard to which they have no reference, the author of
                        Rural Tales will neither be run down by the sarcasms nor sunk by the praises with which he is assailed … He was a poor man
                        whom, in spite of poverty, genius did not ruin and in spite of popularity and patronage, the world could not corrupt. When
                        these failed him, he sought refuge in the spirit of independence, and indemnified himself in the love and enjoyment of nature,
                        for the harsh and unfeeling decisions of the critics, reserving for himself an appeal to posterity’.</note> The sort of
                    popularity, indeed, which he obtained at one time could not, from its nature, be lasting; but he will hold his place. A very
                    interesting man, and a thoroughly estimable one, who never over-valued himself, but poured forth a sweet strain of his own.</p><p rend="indent1"> Of the many self-taught men who have appeared in this country, <ref target="people.html#HoggJamesEttrick">Hogg, the
                        Ettrick Shepherd</ref>, is one of the most remarkable. He spent a couple of days with me last summer, and left me as much
                    pleased with the unaffected plainness and simplicity of his conversation, as I was with the vigour and life that appear in his
                    writings. He is the rising star of Scotland. The Scotch, you know, have a public of their own. Edinburgh is a Scotchman’s London,
                    and I might almost say his kingdom come – for most of them seem to think that nothing greater or better can be found anywhere
                    else, here or hereafter.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have heard of <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey’s</ref> reviewal of the “Excursion,” not seen
                        it.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Jeffrey’s review of Wordsworth’s <title>The Excursion</title> (1814), see
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 24 (November 1814), [1]-30. It began: ‘This will never do’ ([1]).</note> But it is my
                    full intention to take this occasion of exposing <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey’s</ref> ignorance, malice, and
                    self-contradictions. Most likely it will be through the medium of a newspaper, as giving it the widest circulation.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s threat was not carried out.</note> I shall enter fully into the subject, and treat him
                    with all the severity that he so amply has deserved. There can be no difficulty in showing that a man who does not admire the
                    “Excursion” cannot possibly understand what he may pretend to admire in Milton.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poet
                        and polemicist John Milton (1608–1674; <title>DNB</title>).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I do not like the political aspects. The good which might have been done at the overthrow of Buonaparte has been
                    left undone; and even if exhaustion should produce a peace for some time to come, there are abundant seeds of war left to
                    germinate. Italy ought to have been formed into one great state. I would rather have seen it a federal republic than a kingdom;
                    for when we have to begin anew upon clear unencumbered ground, I cannot but believe a republic to be the best thing. But as
                    kingdoms, naturally enough, are most in fashion, I would gladly have seen it a kingdom, and given to anybody – who had not
                    actually deserved the gallows. Had Buonaparte been a wise man, he would, at the Peace of Amiens, have restored the Bourbons, and
                    taken Italy for himself; but he had already given himself over to evil.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Congress of
                        Vienna (September 1814-June 1815) was still engaged in drawing up the map of Europe, but it was clear that Italy would remain
                        divided. Southey suggests, rather improbably, that Napoleon should have restored the Bourbon dynasty in France after the
                        Treaty of Amiens (1802) temporarily halted the war with Britain, and retired to rule a united Italy.</note> I suppose you know
                    that a Frenchman who, in 1802, published a “History of the Egyptian Expedition,” has now published a second edition, and inserted
                    a full account of the massacre at Jaffa, to which he was himself eye-witness!<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacques
                        François Miot (1779–1858), <title>Mémoires pour servir à l’Histoire des Expéditions en Egypte et en Syrie</title>, first
                        published in Paris in 1804 (not 1802) and in a new edition in 1814. Miot gave a first-hand account of the rape and murder by
                        French troops of the population of Jaffa after the city fell on 3 March 1799 (1814 edn), pp. 140–148). Southey reviewed Miot
                        in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 1–55.</note></p></div></body></text></TEI>