<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2524</idno><idno type="nines">rce3795</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849–1850), IV, pp. 92–94 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2524" type="letter"><head>2524. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1814-12-22">22 December 1814</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9. Stafford Row/ Buckingham Gate/ London<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ 26 DE 26/
                        1814<lb/> Endorsement: 22. Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1814<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25<lb/>Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849–1850), IV, pp. 92–94 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1814-12-22">22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Dec. 1814.</date></dateline><salute>My dear G.</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have the half-note;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. half-banknote – a secure way of sending money in
                        the post, by tearing banknotes in half and sending the two halves separately.</note> – peradventure its conjugal part now
                    disjunct may arrive in the letter which I expect from you on Monday, upon the odeous subject.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Bedford’s response to the draft of Southey’s ‘Ode, Written in December 1814’; see Southey to Grosvenor
                        Charles Bedford, 21 December 1814, Letter 2523.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My opinion respecting a <hi rend="ital">publication</hi> of Barres Remains entirely coincides with yours. In its
                    private circulation all is well, so circulated a book passes for more than it is worth; whereas if it be made current it generally
                    passes for less.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Grosvenor Bedford had privately published <title>Letters and
                            Miscellaneous Papers … With a Memoir of His Life</title> (1814) of his cousin Barré Charles Roberts, who had died in 1810
                        aged 21. It was reviewed by Southey in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (January 1815), 509–519.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> By this time <del>I ha</del> you have received the MSS<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A MS of
                            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814); see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 11 December 1814, Letter
                        2513.</note> I forgot to send with it, two single-sheet books of smaller size which contain the memoranda for the conduct of
                    the story as they occurrd from time to time, &amp; which ought to go with it: this is another reason for preferring the case-book
                    (I must not say book-case.) I would have it a handsome old-fashiond back with broad bands &amp; dead tooling: &amp; for a thing of
                    this kind I do’nt care <del>much about expence</del> &lt;about&gt; – an odd ten or fifteen shillings more upon the price, to make
                    it a goodly heirloom.</p><p rend="indent1"> Somebody has favourd me with a good word in the Courier; the character of the poem is given with good judgement, –
                    the quotation very oddly chosen.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> See the <title>Courier</title> (20 December 1814), which
                        described <title>Roderick</title> as ‘distinguished … throughout by a style of the noblest kind, and enriched with passages of
                        the most glowing and eloquent description’. The account quoted <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 12,
                        lines 101–124 and Book 11, lines 43–53; neither extract dealt with the poem’s central themes or incidents.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> If <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray </ref><hi rend="ital"> were</hi> to offer me 500 £ for a Register<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Murray was proposing either
                        to take over or continue the failing <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> or to establish a new annual publication. He was
                        sounding out Southey, who had written for the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> from 1810–1813, as a possible lead
                        contributor. In the end, nothing came of the idea; see Southey to John Murray, 4 December 1814 (Letter 2510) and 12 December
                        1814 (Letter 2515).</note> I certainly should not for a moment hesitate. Indeed I know not whether I ought not gladly to catch
                    at the 400 £, circumstanced as I am. In that case I should advise him to begin with the peace,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. in 1814.</note> for many reasons. First because it would be so tremendous an undertaking to bring up the
                    lee way from the beginning of 1812, &amp; secondly because there is a great advantage in commencing with a new era in history. It
                    might be worth while at leisure (if I could possibly procure it) to write the volumes for 1812–13 for &lt;the sake of&gt;
                    connecting the former volumes with these – but this I should despair of – <del>because</del> my history of the peninsula<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> will
                        <del>contain</del> include what is to me the most interesting portion, &amp; the only portion which I can do thoroughly as it
                    ought to be done. And more than all, however I might spirit myself up to the undertaking, flesh &amp; blood is not equal to it. I
                    cannot get thro more than at present unless I give up sleep, or the little exercise which I take &amp; I walk to the crag before
                    breakfast: &amp; that hour excepted, &amp; my meals (barely the meals for I remain not one minute after them) – the pen or the
                    book is <del>xx</del> always in my hand.</p><p rend="indent1"> Had you not better wait for <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrays</ref> attack upon Roderick?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bedford was reviewing <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814) for the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>. Southey here suggests he waited until Francis Jeffrey’s appraisal appeared. This did not
                        happen. Bedford’s review was in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 83–113; Jeffrey’s in <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 25 (June 1815), [1]-86. The latter described <title>Roderick</title> as: ‘The best … and the most powerful
                        of all Mr Southey’s poems’, though ‘now and then a little absurd – and pretty frequently not a little affected … The author is
                        a poet undoubtedly; but not of the highest order’ ([1]).</note> I have a most curious letter upon this subject from <ref target="people.html#HoggJamesEttrick">Hogg the Ettrick shepherd</ref>, a worthy fellow, &amp; a man of very extraordinary
                    powers, whom I call the pet pig of the Muses. Living in Edinburgh he thinks <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref>
                    the greatest man in the world, – an intellectual Buonaparte whom nobody &amp; nothing can resist. But <ref target="people.html#HoggEdward">Hogg</ref> notwithstanding this has fallen in liking with me &amp; is a great admirer of
                    Roderick. And this letter is to request that I will not do any thing to <hi rend="ital">nettle</hi><ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> while he is deliberating concerning Roderick, – for he seems favourably
                    disposed toward me! <del>Xxxx xxx xxxxx it is</del> Morbleu! It is a rich letter! <ref target="people.html#HoggEdward">Hogg</ref>
                    requested that he himself might review it, &amp; gave me an extract from <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrays</ref>
                    answer refusing him. ‘I have as well as you <del>x</del> a great respect for Southey, he says – but he is a most provoking fellow
                    &amp; at least as conceited as his neighbour <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>”. – B[MS torn] shall be
                    happy to talk to <ref target="people.html#HoggEdward">Hogg</ref> upon this &amp; other <hi rend="ital">kindred</hi> subjects &amp;
                    he should be very glad to give me a <hi rend="ital">lavish allowance</hi> of praise if I would afford him occasion, &amp;c – but
                    he must do what he thinks his duty, &amp;c –. I laugh to think of the effect my reply will produce upon <ref target="people.html#HoggEdward">Hogg</ref>, – how it will make every bristle to stand on end like quirrels of the fretful
                    porcupine. The sum of it is that I despise <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrays</ref> commendation, &amp; defy his
                    enmity; that <hi rend="ital">nettling</hi> is too weak a word for what I have in store for him, – <del>that</del> for in due time
                    he shall be scorpioned &amp; rattlesnaked, – yea served up to the public like a Turkeys gizzard sliced, scored, peppered salted,
                    kiannd (how is that word spelt?) grilled &amp; properly bedevilled.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> These sentiments were
                        expressed in Southey’s reply; see Southey to James Hogg, 24 December 1811, Letter 2528.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> What can I call the Ode? Can you find any thing to stand with Carmen, – Annuum I will not use, nor will I call
                        it Ode for the New Year, – for I will do nothing that I can avoid toward perpetuating the custom. – How would Carmen
                        Hortatorium do if there be such a word.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s ‘Ode, Written in December 1814’. A
                            ‘Carmen Hortatorium’ would be an ‘Exhortatory Song’.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>