<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2623</idno><idno type="nines">rce3894</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42551 .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2623" type="letter"><head>2623. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1815-06-26">26 June 1815</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London
                        <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb/>Postmark: [partial] E<lb/>Watermark: J DICKINSON &amp; Co/ 1811<lb/>Endorsement: 1815 26 June/
                        Southey Rob<hi rend="sup">t</hi><lb/> MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42551<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1815-06-26">26 June. 1815</date></dateline><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have received your draft, &amp; thank you for it. I am glad that the article upon <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Wellington</ref> has not disappointed you, – but I perceive strong objections
                    to putting it forward in a different form.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not wish to expand his article on
                        George Elliott (dates unknown), <title>The Life of the Most Noble Arthur Duke of Wellington, from the Period of his first
                            Achievements in India, down to his Invasion of France, and the Peace of Paris in 1814</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 215–275, into a book, as Murray had suggested; see Southey to Herbert Hill, 27 June 1815,
                        Letter 2624.</note><hi rend="ital">Where</hi> it is, it is pretty much as it should be: – there was an <hi rend="ital">excuse</hi> for presenting an
                    abstract of the Dukes life, because a catchpenny volume had taken up the subject at length; &amp; there was a <hi rend="ital">cause</hi> for doing it, because it was right to show the country what grounds we had for engaging in the present contest
                    with hope &amp; confidence. But I should be very unwilling to put it forth as a life of <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Wellington</ref> which might be supposed to be intended as a companion for the
                    life of Nelson.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Life of Nelson</title> (1813); an expansion of Southey’s article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February
                        1810), 218–262.</note> The limits of a review (tho I trespassed somewhat beyond them) <del>xxx xx xx xx xxx</del> allowed me
                    to hurry over those parts of his latter campaigns, which, as far as I am yet provided with materials for them, (tho of the highest
                    importance) have none of those rich circumstances that they can be <hi rend="ital">twice</hi> told with effect. I was indeed
                    compelled to hurry over them, – but glad to do so, because of my history. This is one reason. Another <del>xxx</del> is that this
                    late victory<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Battle of Waterloo, 18 June 1815.</note> would come in with the
                    awkwardness of a postscript, – to which by the time it was printed there would probably be another postscript required, &amp;
                    still the story would be left incompleat. To me it might be injurious, &amp; I should certainly feel it discreditable, to be
                    accused of catching at temporary subjects, &amp; writing for the demand of the day. And ultimately it might be disadvantageous to
                    us both, – for this campaign may well be expected to furnish matter for a paper in your review, – &amp; to the enlargement of that
                    paper there may possibly be none of these objections, as it might form the groundwork for a History of the Campaign.</p><p rend="indent1"> I possess the Ethiopia Alta of Tellez,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Baltazar Tellez (1595–1675) abridged
                        and partially revised the Jesuit Manuel de Almeida’s (1580–1646), <title>Historia de Etiopia a Alta ou Abassia</title> (1660),
                        no. 3304 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> of which Salt says there are only three copies in England;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Henry Salt (1780–1827; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Voyage to Abyssinia</title>
                        (London, 1814), p. 481n†. Southey did not review it for the <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> &amp; I possess also the
                    original work of Francisco Alvares<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Álvares (c. 1465–1536/1541) was a member of
                        the Portuguese mission to Ethiopia in 1520–1526. Part of his account was published as <title>Verdadeira Informação das Terras
                            do Preste João</title> (1540), no. 3305 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> which is much more rare. If the
                    Portugueze book of which you speak be the work of <hi rend="ital">Bermudes</hi><note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joao
                        Bermudes (d. 1570), <title>Breve Relacao da Embaixada que o Patriacha D. Joao Bermudez, trouxe do Imperador de Etiopia chamado
                        vulgarmente Preste Joao</title> (1565).</note> I shall be very glad to see it. – but still more if it were the Ethiopia Oriental of
                    Joam dos Santos.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> João dos Santos (d. 1622), <title>Ethiopia Oriental</title> (1609) deals
                        with the Portuguese role in Mozambique at the end of the sixteenth century.</note> I am very rich in information upon this
                    country, &amp; expect to produce an interesting paper, containing what has never yet been given a fair account of the history of
                    the Jesuits in Abyssinia.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not write this article.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> You see I rightly supposed that Campbells Travels lay within M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Barrows <del>xxx</del> line of
                        demarcation.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had expressed interest in writing on John Campbell (1766–1840;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in South Africa, Undertaken at the Request of the Missionary Society</title> (1815);
                        see Southey to John Murray, 27 May 1815, Letter 2606. It was reviewed by John Barrow (1764–1848; <title>DNB</title>) in
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (July 1815), 309–340.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> When you send to me next, remember that I have not had the number which precedes this.</p><p rend="indent1"> Gregoires Sects will be my next long article, – a good subject &amp; much in my way.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henri Gregoire (1750–1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuses</title> (1810), reviewed by Southey in
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), 1–46.</note> – We talked once of Huntingdons Works, – fish of that
                    kind make an excellent dish when properly drest &amp; served up with the right sauce.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        William Huntington (1745–1813; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Works</title> (1811), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 24 (January 1821), 462–510.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey. </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>