<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2308</idno><idno type="nines">rce3579</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47888.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 73-76.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2308" type="letter"><head>2308. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <date when="1813-09-25">25 September
                        1813</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland
                        <lb/>Postmark: SE/ 25/ 1813<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47888<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 73-76.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1813-09-25">Saturday morning. Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 25. 1813. </date><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#QueenAnneSt"> Q Anne Street</ref></placeName></address></dateline><salute>My dear Edith</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> dined here yesterday, in good health &amp; spirits. It will be a
                    fortnight before he leaves town at least, for on Sunday Oct 3 we dine together with <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> &amp; on Saturday the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> following, with D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stanger.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The physician Christopher Stanger (1759–1834; <title>DNB</title>). He was a member of a family
                        that owned estates near Keswick.</note> It is possible that he may be detained longer, for as he was on the stairs going away
                    last night, he said some thing about presenting a piece at Covent Garden &amp; that if any alterations were recommended he might
                    tarry a few days for the sake of making them on the spot. I could not <del>xxx</del> ask him any questions because the servant was
                    before us lighting him to the door. Tomorrow morning I shall see him again. Of the <ref target="people.html#MorganJohnJames">Morgans</ref> I heard nothing yesterday of course, <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref> being here.</p><p rend="indent1"> My own business is going on well. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> B.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Barlow
                        (1759–1839) a merchant and neighbour of Herbert Hill’s in Streatham. Brother of Sir George Barlow (1763–1846;
                            <title>DNB</title>). Southey was writing a pamphlet entitled <title>An Exposure of the Misrepresentations and Calumnies in
                            Mr Marsh’s Review of Sir George Barlow’s Administration at Madras. By the Relatives of Sir George Barlow</title> (1813).
                        This was a defence of Sir George Barlow’s conduct as Governor of Madras in 1807–1813, especially during the army mutiny of
                        1809. It was a direct reply to Charles Marsh (c. 1774–1835; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Review of Some Important Passages in
                            the Late Administration of Sir G. H. Barlow, Bart., at Madras</title> (1813).</note> seems exceedingly well pleased, &amp;
                    took the first portion to the printer yesterday; – from seven to ten days more will finish it. that is so many days work. I expect
                    to have compleated it before I come in to dine with D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stanger: &amp; then by Gods blessing another fortnight
                    will set me free. About my Laureateship nothing more has been done. I apprehend however that nothing will be lost by the delay,
                    for that the salary will commence from the death of the last occupant. Should there be a levee when Parliament meets I must make
                    my appearance at &lt;it&gt; in bag sword &amp; ruffles!! with all which the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctor</ref> can rig me out, thus saving an expence of no less than thirty pounds.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am sorry you had any hesitation about the number of the Magazine,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Possibly the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>. Southey subscribed between 1796–1817; see no. 1989 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note> which <del>it</del> is always to be had upon sending for it. <ref target="people.html#MaloneCatherine">Miss
                        Malone</ref> is exceedingly welcome to it.</p><p rend="indent1"> Today I shall look for <ref target="people.html#LovellRobertJr">Robert</ref>. I have to call on Lord W Gordon<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lord William Gordon (1744–1823), son of Cosmo George Gordon, 3rd Duke of Gordon
                        (1720–1752). He owned the Waterend estate on the west side of Derwentwater.</note> who has been three times to look for me,
                    &amp; left word that he should be at home this morning, &amp; I have afterwards to see <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, &amp; endeavour to negociate the arrangement between him &amp; <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> about the Opus Magnum,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a reference to Southey’s proposed
                            <title>History of the Peninsula War</title> (1823–1832).</note> of which the latter wanted to have the whole to himself
                    &amp; not very willingly offers to yield a fourth share. He talks largely about the manner in which he will bring it forth so as
                    in point of views portraits &amp;c to make it the finest national work that has ever yet appeared. Of the Nelson<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Life of Nelson</title> (1813). The second edition appeared in 1814.</note> 3000 were printed, &amp; a second
                    edition is to be sent to press as soon as I have looked it over &amp; made such improvements as new matter may enable me to make.
                    It will now be compressed by the printer into one volume as originally intended: &amp; we may reckon upon the hundred guineas
                    about Christmas.</p><p rend="indent1"> The inclosed draft is for my Quarterly article, which having been printed for the present number, stands over for
                    the succeeding one. Of course I care nothing about this arrangement, but am glad to receive payment for the sake of thus remitting
                    a supply to you. I shall bring home with me plenty, or send it before me. – My seal is cut &amp; you shall have a sample of it
                    upon this letter: so also is a very pretty smaller one with the crest, which is intended to hang at your watch: &amp; I have
                    ordered another for you, which is a fit &amp; proper seal for my wife, <del>of which</del> but which will not please <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> quite so well as it will you.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman</ref> is in the country so that I have not seen her.
                        M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Turner<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary (bap. 1768, d. 1843), who had married Turner on 18
                        January 1795.</note> I have seen, &amp; need not say that she enquired <del>xxx xxx xxx xx xxx</del> particularly concerning
                    you both she &amp; <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">her husband</ref> speaking with great pleasure of the time we past with
                    them at Cheshunt. Yesterday I saw <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Sir Humphry</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#DavyJane">Lady Davy</ref> who had arrived in town the day before &amp; are going abroad in about a fortnight, with the special
                    permission of the French Government. <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> ought not to have asked it; – but he has
                    long been going wrong. His wife (who by the by tells all her female friends they cannot imagine how well <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Sir Humphry</ref> looks in his night-cap) seems to be full ten years his elder, &amp; never
                    can have been handsome. I called at Miss Berry’s.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The author Mary Berry (1763–1852;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and her sister Agnes (1764–1852; <title>DNB</title>), confidantes of Horace Walpole, 4th Earl of
                        Orford (1717–1797; <title>DNB</title>).</note><ref target="people.html#SetonBarbara">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Bannister</ref> leaves them tomorrow they &amp; their father<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Berry (d. 1817).</note> are not looking older than when you saw them.</p><p rend="indent1"> My dispute with <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> is ending well as far as the point in
                    dispute; &amp; I am making an attempt to recover the cost of my share.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had
                        invested – unwisely – in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> – Whether I shall be able to add any more to
                    this latter is very doubtful, – breakfast is now ready, – I will however leave it open till I come in from my morning rounds, –
                    &amp; so till then <del>xxx</del> farewell.</p><p rend="indent1"> Three o clock. – It is not a little amusing to discover when any thing friendly is to be done by men in power, how
                    many are desirous of having a share in it. You remember Toms promotion was a sort of joint concern between <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>, &amp; <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> &amp;
                    poor <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Perceval</ref>.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> See
                        Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 12 May 1811, Letter 1921; and Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 4 August [1811],
                        Letter 1943.</note> Today I saw Ld W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Gordon, &amp; was not a little surprized to learn that the whole
                    affair of the Laureateship was left to him! Lady W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> is sister to the Marchioness of Hertford,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frances Ingram-Shepherd (1761–1841), sister of Isabella Anne Ingram-Shepherd (1760–1834), second
                        wife of the Marquis of Hertford, who as Lord Chamberlain was a key figure in the appointment of the Poet Laureate.</note> –
                    the appointment is in the gift of the <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Marquis</ref> &amp; so as it was to be given to me
                    Lord W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> is to have the credit of giving it. All this is comical enough. However he is a very good natured man,
                    &amp; has taken the trouble of calling upon me three times to tell me this, &amp; it costs me nothing to say I am much obliged to
                    him, which is all he wants: &amp; when you see him which you will do before my return you may say the same.</p><p rend="indent1"> I saw <ref target="people.html#LovellRobertJr">Robert</ref> this morning, looking remarkably [MS torn]ll, but not
                    taller than <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> &amp; with almost [MS torn] much beard, tho of a
                    different colour. I gave him [MS torn] pounds for an immediate supply. <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> was not
                    at home. [MS torn] been unwell &amp; spends much of his time in the country for the change of air.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p>Love to all. My next will probably be directed to the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Moon</ref>.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> No letter to Herbert Southey from this period appears to have survived.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>