<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1813</idno><idno type="nines">rce3084</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Houghton Library, MS Hyde 10 (656).  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1813" type="letter"><head>1813. Robert Southey to [<ref target="people.html#ElliottEbenezer">Ebenezer Elliott</ref>], <date when="1810-10-07">7 October
                        1810</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Houghton Library, MS Hyde 10 (656)<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1810-10-07">Oct 7. 1810.</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> I do not happen to posses Jornandes,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jornandes (c. mid C6th), a Roman
                        bureaucrat who wrote two Latin histories: <title>De Getarum (Gothorum) Origine et Rebus Gestis</title> (c. 551) and <title>De
                            Regnorum ac Temporum Successione</title> (c. 551–552). Both were widely used by later historians. At this time the first
                        of these works had been translated into French, as <title>Histoire Generale des Goths</title> (1703), by Jean Baptiste Drouet
                        de Maupertuy (1650?–1730); and Swedish, as <title>Doctor Jordans, Biskopens i Ravenna, Beskrifning om Gothernas uhrsprung och
                            bedrifter</title> (1719), by Johan Frederik Peringskiold (1689–1725).</note> or I would have sent you a translation of the
                    immediate part concerning which you are anxious to obtain a full account. I suspect this author has never been translated, &amp;
                    that there are hardly any more particulars of so early an event in Gothic history to be found, than you have in Gibbon,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Gibbon (1737–1794; <title>DNB</title>), whose <title>History of the Decline and Fall of
                            the Roman Empire</title> (1776–1789) charted the origins and customs of the Goths and their relationship with Rome. He
                        made some use of Jornandes’s, <title>De Getarum</title> as a source.</note> – for on referring to what books I have at hand, I
                    could find nothing more. With the historical facts you may inweave whatever you think fit. for your mythology if you take that of
                    the Edda, you will find every thing you can want or wish for in Mallets Northern Antiquities.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Paul-Henri Mallet (1730–1803), <title>Northern Antiquities: or, a Description of the Manners, Customs,
                            Religion and Laws of the Ancient Danes, and Other Northern Nations</title> (1770). The Old Norse <title>Poetic
                            Edda</title> and <title>Prose Edda</title>, both written in Iceland in the thirteenth century, contain much that is known
                        of Viking mythology.</note> That mythology I believe is the invention of a later age, but you are justified in ascribing it to
                    the earlier Goths, – if for no other reason for the valid one that there is no known system to supply its place.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will of course avail yourself of the persecution under Decius,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Roman emperor Decius (c. 201–251; ruled 249–251). In 250 he issued an edict for the suppression of Christianity. Decius and
                        his son and co-emperor, Herennius Etruscas (c. 227–251), were killed in battle against the Goths in the Battle of Abrittus
                        (251). This may have been the setting for the drama proposed by Ebenezer Elliott.</note> there should be something to your
                    purpose in Foxes Martyrs,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Foxe’s (1516/17–1587; <title>DNB</title>) <title>Acts and
                            Monuments</title> (1563); widely known as Foxe’s <title>Book of Martyrs</title>. Southey owned an edition of 1684, no. 975
                        in the sale catalogue of his library. Foxe’s book included a chapter on ‘The Seventh Persecution Under Decius’.</note> – &amp;
                    an old translation of Eusebius’s Ecclesiastical History<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Eusebius of Caesarea (c. 263–339),
                        historian and Christian polemicist, who became Bishop of Caesarea c. 314. His <title>Historia Ecclesiastica</title> provided a
                        chronological account of the development of the early Christian church and was widely translated. Southey owned an edition of
                        1636, no. 960 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> in small folio, is a book frequent enough in catalogues at a low
                    price.</p><p rend="indent1"> Go on with the drama. It is the surest way to reputation, &amp; the only one in which reputation brings with it
                    remuneration in a tangible shape. Epic poems may bring credit to their author, – but they bring nothing else.</p><p rend="indent1"> I expect to send you Kehama<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> in November, – at least they tell me it will be published in that month, –
                    which it well may be, the last proofs having been corrected a fortnight ago. It cannot be compared with Madoc.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> the two poems are compleatly different in kind; – it bears a nearer relation to
                        Thalaba.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> but even Thalaba can give you no conception of its wildness. Its merit
                    consists in the construction of the story, &amp; in a certain moral character which I think is peculiar to it. A human being is
                    represented suffering to the very height of human endurance, &amp; even cut off from that hope of reward which makes the Martyr
                    exalt at the stake. Yet in the progress of the work you cease to regard him as an object of compassion, &amp; every other feeling
                    is lost in admiration for the strength of virtuous principle. – This I believe will be felt by those who are capable of relishing
                    in any degree a work <del>x</del> which carries them so utterly out of all common conceptions &amp; associations: – such readers
                    are necessarily very few, &amp; I anticipate not merely a cry, but even a <hi rend="ital">hoot</hi> of astonishment.</p><p rend="indent1"> Have you ever read <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor’s</ref> Gebir?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor’s <title>Gebir</title> (1798).</note> a poem scarcely heard of, – upon a bad story, &amp; very
                    obscurely told, yet containing more true poetry than has appeared in any narrative poem since the days of Milton. It is the only
                    modern work <del>from</del> &lt;by&gt; the study of which I felt myself sensibly benefitted &amp; improved.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent4"> R Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>