<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1946</idno><idno type="nines">rce3217</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Keswick
                        Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1946" type="letter"><head>1946. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1811-09-02">2 September
                        1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/
                        Surry<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ 6 SE 6/ 1811; 10o’Clock SP 6 1811 FN<hi rend="sup">n</hi><lb/>MS: Keswick
                        Museum and Art Gallery<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1811-09-02">Monday Sept. 2. 1811</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> I reached home this morning, having travelled in the mail from Liverpool to Kendal, all night. We found every thing
                    well, the children had not experienced the slightest ailment during our absence, – <del>xx</del> we ourselves during twelve weeks
                    had only had two days &lt;of&gt; wet weather, &amp; in the course of 800 miles which we travelled together, with another hundred
                    which I travelled alone we never met with either accident delay, or any disagreable incident. Here then I am once more, God be
                    thanked, in my own library &amp; by the fire side, more thoroughly weary of long indolence &amp; dissipation of mind than I ever
                    was of the closest application.</p><p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Withers<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A relative of Herbert Hill by marriage.
                        Probably Herbert Hill’s father-in-law, Lovelace Bigg-Wither (c. 1742–1813), or his son, Harris Bigg-Wither (1781–1833).</note>
                    books were ordered three weeks ago, &amp; no doubt both he &amp; you have ere this received your copies, for that the work<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title> (1811).</note> is published I know,
                    having seen it at <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref>. –</p><p rend="indent1"> At Taunton I learnt that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt</ref> has recovered property from 4 to 500£
                    value, consisting of tenements bought after the Will was made, &amp; therefore devolving to her in common, or more truly speaking
                    uncommon course of law, according to the custom of Taunton Dean.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The ‘uncommon course of
                        law’ in Taunton Deane was the local Manor’s custom of copyhold tenure. This allowed Mary Southey to inherit some of her
                        brother, Thomas Southey’s, copyhold property. Thomas Southey was also trustee of some of the property at Fitzhead of Cannon
                        Southey (d. 1768), a distant cousin, whose complex will led to much litigation.</note> She suspects foul play with the wills,
                    &amp; is determined to go herself to London &amp; inspect them, because she knows the handwriting. I cannot think there is any
                    chance of detecting any villainy, tho many circumstances seem to render it very probable that some has been practised. About my
                    own immediate concerns, I learn that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Mr. T.S.</ref> sold ten acres of land recovered
                    under Canon Southeys will, which it is believed he could have no right to sell, my claim to it being prior to his: – this I shall
                    write to <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> about tomorrow, &amp; leave the whole in his hands.</p><p rend="indent1"> I learnt the news of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> promotion first from <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, then by a very handsome note from Perceval himself, the import of which was that he
                    had obtained the promotion knowing that I was anxious it should be obtained.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See also
                        Southey to Herbert Hill, 12 May 1811 (Letter 1921) and 16 August 1811 (Letter 1944), and Southey to Charles Watkin Williams
                        Wynn, 4 August [1811] (Letter 1943).</note> I wrote without delay to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Helens, but the Captain <hi rend="ital">malgre lui</hi><note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘in spite of himself’.</note>(as he deserves to be called for the humour in which he
                    joined the Elephant)<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <title>Elephant</title> was a 74 gun, third-rate ship of the
                        line, launched in 1786. Between 1811–1814 it was stationed in the North Sea and the Baltic under the command of Captain
                        Francis William Austen (1774–1865; <title>DNB</title>), a brother of the novelist Jane Austen (1775–1817;
                        <title>DNB</title>).</note> made such haste that he outstript my letter<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> This has not
                        survived.</note> &amp; I suppose travelled by the same mail as his own, so that he carried the news himself.</p><p rend="indent1"> At <ref target="places.html#Teddesley">Teddesley</ref> I met with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stafford Smith<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Stafford Smith (1750–1836; DNB), musician, historian of music and organist at the Chapel
                        Royal, 1802–1836.</note> who desires particularly that I would remember him to you. – If you take the business out of
                        Lloyds<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly John Lloyd (dates unknown) of the Ludlow solicitors, Baxter and
                        Lloyd.</note> hands &amp; it be necessary to employ a man of that country, I suppose my friend <ref target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Brownes</ref> recommendation will decide your choice. I think the name
                    of the person whom he mentioned was Wellings,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s confusion is understandable.
                        Edward Wellings (dates unknown) was a Ludlow solicitor. Thomas Wellings (d. 1841), was a clergyman, Rector of Church Clench,
                        and later Vicar of Bromsgrove, and Lecturer of Ludlow 1791–1841.</note> but am not certain, for I may have confounded it with
                    that of a clergyman whom I saw frequently at his house. Lloyd assured me he would write to you immediately, – he is manifestly a
                    liar, &amp; the sooner you take the business out of his hands the better, after this second proof of falshood.</p><p rend="indent1"> I found in Montgomeryshire Sir James Foulis<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir James Foulis of Colinton,
                        6th Baronet (d. 1825).</note> who was in the Portugueze service from 1764/ – 78. – a pleasant &amp; intelligent old man, who
                    delighted to talk about the country &amp; his old comrades. He did not know you, having resided almost <del>exclusively</del>
                    entirely in garrison at Penamacor &amp; Almeida.</p><p rend="indent1"> The box which I packed at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> has not yet arrived, perhaps it was
                    not sent off till some time after I left you. The later packages from <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> found
                    their way here before me. I shall be glad to hear the delay of your chest (which is the more valuable one) accounted for.</p><p rend="indent1"> I saw M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Dyson at Liverpool, but missed her husband,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Possibly Thomas Fournice Dyson (1767–1843) of Everton. He had formerly lived in Lisbon and moved in the same circles there as
                        Southey in 1800–1801. His wife, Anne Baldwin Sealy (c. 1780–1857), was the sister of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey’s</ref> first wife, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary-Harriet</ref>.</note> tho he called on me twice &amp; displayed a sort of
                    attentive civility which I did not expect from him. <ref target="people.html#KosterHenry">Henry Koster </ref><del> told</del> &lt;gave&gt; me a good account of Pernambuco to which place he is returning, – he is a pleasant unaffected
                        <del>xxx</del> young man, very desirous of <del>informing</del> &lt;improving&gt; himself. I think of enquiring what MSS.
                    exist at Pernambuco, Bahia &amp; the Rio in the monasteries there, – a catalogue will enable me to know whether we possess copies
                    already, &amp; we may perhaps obtain transcripts of such as seem to <del>xx</del> justify the expence.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Our love to <del>xxx</del><ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref>.</salute><salute rend="indent4"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent7"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>