<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1848</idno><idno type="nines">rce3119</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 1–3.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1848" type="letter"><head>1848. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1811-01-01">1 January 1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Stafford Row/ Buckingham Gate/ London<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ 4 JA 4/ 1811<lb/>MS:
                        Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 1–3.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1811-01-01">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1. 1811.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> This is an unlucky interference of <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott’s</ref>, &amp; one of which I was
                    afraid, after the manner in which he reviewed the Cid.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott had reviewed <title>The
                            Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 134–153.</note> It is clear
                    from your account that in this, as well as in the former instance, he has not seen any thing that lies below the surface.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott had been commissioned by Gifford to review <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).
                        Bedford had also applied to review the poem and had been shown a pre-publication version of Scott’s article. Bedford was
                        concerned at its emphasis upon narrative, rather than morality, and was allowed to make additions to it along the lines
                        suggested in this letter. Bedford remained, however, unhappy with the overall tone. For the review as published see
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5 (February 1811), 40–61 (esp. 55–56, probably Bedford’s interpolation).</note> The best
                    thing that could be done (for as for setting any thing of his aside, – that is out of the question) would be to interpolate it
                    with one paragraph, written to point out the moral grandeur of the fable, <del>which then</del> &lt;&amp; how it&gt; becomes of
                    universal interest &amp; application, founded as it is upon a particular superstition, – &amp; also to show the value of works of
                    high imagination, in taking us out of ourselves, &amp; <del>busy</del> busying the mind about something which is not connected
                    with the ordinary passions &amp; pursuits of life. – <del>xx</del><ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon"> Sharon Turners</ref>
                    wife<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Turner, née Watts
                        (c. 1768–1843).</note> said of Kehama that she “felt it elevate her conceptions, &amp; occasion an excitement of mind which
                    made her feel superior to herself.” This is precisely what it ought to do. – Insert some thing to this purport &amp; rescue me
                    from the imputation of having written a poem of 5000 lines for the purpose of teaching Hindoo mythology. You will thus prevent his
                    reviewal from being detrimental, – &amp; your own will be serviceable wherever you can get it inserted, which I suppose you can do
                    in the B. Critic.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>British Critic</title> (founded 1793), was a conservative
                        quarterly review journal. Number 39 (March 1812), 272–282 favourably reviewed <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810). This
                        review may have been written by Bedford.</note> This I think <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> will have
                    no objection to do, any more than he had to render justice to that good horse Bavian.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e.
                        Gifford’s <title>The Baviad</title> (1791).</note> The rest must pass, &amp; I can with perfect sincerity take the will to
                    serve me for the deed in my friend <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>, who I verily believe would serve me to the
                    utmost of his power, &amp; who <del>I do not think has</del> &lt;has not&gt; one atom of envy in his nature.</p><p rend="indent1"> You ask me about the Bristol Alderman.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The ‘English Eclogue’ ‘The
                        Alderman’s Funeral’, published in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.2 (1810), [i]–iv.</note> – it is not
                    precisely a portrait tho written <del>in consequence</del> after I had accidentally fallen in with the funeral of a worthy of that
                    description. Take it as the representative of a whole class not as individual satire. The operation of cutting an
                        <del>artificial</del> artificial iris was performed upon Rushton,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poet and slavery
                        abolitionist Edward Rushton (1756–1814; <title>DNB</title>).</note> a bookseller &amp; poet at Liverpool, by a surgeon at
                    Manchester whose name I believe <del>was</del> is Gibson.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rushton had contracted opthalmia
                        in 1773, whilst on a slaver heading for Dominica. He lost the sight of his left eye and had only partial vision in his right.
                        He regained his sight in 1807 after an operation by Benjamin Gibson (1774–1812), Surgeon to the Manchester Infirmary and
                        Vice-President of the Literary and Philosophical Society of Manchester. He published on conditions relating to the eye: for
                        example, <title>Observations on the Formation of an Artificial Pupil in Several Deranged States of the Eye</title>
                        (1811).</note> Rushton had been blind about 20 years, &amp; had undergone three fruitless operations before he came under his
                    hands. It was done twice; the first time an inflammation came on &amp; the opening on the cornea <del>clo</del> was closed up. It
                    was repeated, &amp; he beheld for the first time the faces of his wife &amp; children. – The success was compleat, &amp; he reads
                    a large print with ease.</p><p rend="indent1"> If an occasion can be made of giving you a commission to <ref target="people.html#AbellaManuel">D Manuel
                        Abella</ref> I will lay hold on it. Do you I pray you bespeak for me an acquaintance with <ref target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco</ref>, who has a right to whitewash his name into its original English or Irish,
                    – his father or grandfather having been a British subject.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Blanco White’s grandfather,
                        William White (dates unknown), had emigrated from Waterford to Andalusia in the early eighteenth century.</note> I suppose his
                    animosity to the Supreme Junta has made him overlook the mischief which James Moore has done to the Spaniards,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Moore (1762–1860; <title>DNB</title>), surgeon and biographer of his brother, Sir John
                        Moore (1761–1809); <title>DNB</title>), in <title>A Narrative of the Campaign of the British Army in Spain</title> (1809),
                        which was full of criticisms of Spanish troops.</note> otherwise I confess that house is the last place in London where I
                    should expect to meet a Spanish patriot.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am sorry to hear of <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">your mothers</ref> sufferings. My excellent old
                    friend <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Danvers</ref> was tormented in a similar manner for some
                    years, by a complaint which was supposed to be pruritus anilis,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Irritation of the skin at
                        the exit of the rectum.</note> – but proved at last to be literally nothing but the itch. How it should have reached her was
                    utterly inexplicable, – it yielded of course to the first proper application, – but she suffered grievously from it before its
                    nature was suspected. It is well the mercurial disease is giving way. Weak you must needs be, but I hope the main evil in the side
                    has been subdued, &amp; then time will do the rest. I long to hear that the lime water is to give place to port wine, – which in
                    cases of debility I hold to be an especial corroborant, &amp; pleasant to boot.</p><p rend="indent1"> Should you see <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> tell him we wish to hear from him,
                    &amp; ask him when we may expect to see him again.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge had left for London on 18
                        October 1810.</note> – Concerning the chair &amp; the desk never let it be an occasion of trouble to you, – only bear them in
                    mind when an opportunity lies in your way of looking for them.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Grosvenor
                        Charles Bedford, 28 November 1810, Letter 1830.</note> Keep <del>your</del> &lt;up&gt; your spirits the best you can. You have
                    one bright point of view in your family prospect as far as relates to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref>, who <hi rend="ital">is</hi> in himself, &amp; I doubt not will be in his fortunes all you could wish him.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you my dear Grosvenor</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> The children are recovered thank God. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herberts</ref> proved a third
                        attack of the croup.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>