<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">GOOD TIDINGS (1804)</title>
        <title type="main">Collected Poems of Robert Bloomfield</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author><name>Bloomfield, Robert</name></author>
        <editor>Tim Fulford</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor,</resp>
          <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor,</resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado, Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only
            in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
            republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic Circles.
            Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
            <address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine><addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine><addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine></address></p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list></p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
            Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">editions.2019.bloomfield_poems.18GoodTidingsPt1</idno>
        <idno type="resource">bloomfield_poems</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">GOOD TIDINGS (1804)</title>
            <author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Bloomfield</surname></persName></author>
            <ptr target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_poems/editions.2019.bloomfield_poems.18GoodTidingsPt1.html"/>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Collected Poems of Robert Bloomfield</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2019-04-28">April 28, 2019</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
<tagsDecl>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent1">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent2">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent3">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent4">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent5">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent6">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent7">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent8">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent9">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent10">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="center">text-align: center;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="left">text-align: left;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="right">text-align: right;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="small">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="large">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="largest">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="smallest">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="titlem">font-style: italic;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="titlej">font-style: italic;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="figure">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="sup">vertical-align: super;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="sub">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>       </tagsDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
            http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2019-04-15" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list>
          <item>Initial transforms to HTML</item>
        </list></change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="essay">
        <head rend="noCount" rendition="#center">GOOD TIDINGS; OR, NEWS FROM THE FARM (1804)</head>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">Introduction</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Bloomfield’s third major publication, <title>Good Tidings; or, News from the Farm </title>(1804), was a poem on the new
          medical treatment—vaccination—promoted since 1798 by the country doctor <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#JennerEdward">Edward Jenner</ref>. If this was unexpected from the poet of <title>The Farmer’s Boy </title>and <title>Rural Tales</title>, its form and content turned
          out to be familiar. In iambic pentameter couplets, the poem focused on the effects of smallpox in a rural village, relying on Bloomfield’s
          personal knowledge. As he wrote in the Advertisement, ‘it indulges in domestic anecdote. The account given of my infancy and of my father’s
          burial is not only poetically, but strictly true, and with me it has its weight accordingly. I have witnessed the destruction described in
          my brother’s family’. The manner and matter that made <title>The Farmer’s Boy </title>so full of conviction and appeal were thus re-created:
          Bloomfield wrote of his own childhood in the couplets used for ‘Giles’. An epigraph from <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#ThomsonJames"
            >Thomson</ref> also placed the new work in the same tradition as his first success. </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">The poem germinated from the enthusiasm of Jenner, who was a formidable self-promoter and wished to have his discovery
          recommended by the most fashionable poet of the day. Bloomfield, genuine in his gratitude for such a life-saving medical breakthrough, was
          somewhat disconcerted by Jenner’s pushiness. On 21 July 1802, he wrote to his brother <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#BloomfieldGeorge"
            >George</ref>, </p>
        <quote>I have seen Dr Jenner, and his kindness allmost induced me to shew him the little progress I have made in pursuit of his subject; but I
          suddenly determined to the contrary, and doubted of the propriety of so doing . . . This moment a Letter from Dr Jenner invites me to tea
          this evening. what shall I do? leave 150 lines of an unfinished subject in his hands? I am bound to consult <ref type="m"
            target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> and the <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">Duke</ref> and to submit
          my pieces to their judgement; and never will do otherwise: and yet it is hard to say <hi rend="ital">no</hi> in such cases as this. I wish
          he would suspend his curiosity 6 months, and I would take my chance. He is a very amiable man, and perhaps rates my abilities too high. He
          is an enthusiast in his pursuit, and well he may; when it is taken up by every country in Europe and by the poor Cherokees of America. The
          blessing is surely immensely great!! (<ref target="https://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/letterEEd.25.90.html">Letter
            90</ref>)</quote>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Fearful of being supervised by yet another patron, and thus coming into conflict with his first patrons, Lofft and the Duke
          of Grafton, Bloomfield kept the unfinished draft to himself, and submitted it, when complete in April 1803, to Grafton for approval before
          letting Jenner see a copy. He did, however, compose and sing a song at the party held by the Royal Jennerian Society (Jenner’s campaigning
          organisation) celebrating Jenner’s birthday (17 May), thus becoming publicly associated with a man whose claim to be a benefactor of
          humanity was, while accepted by many, viewed by some as the self-advertisement of a mountebank.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rendition="#indent3">Come hither, mild Beauty, that dwell’st on the mountain, </l>
          <l rendition="#indent4">Sweet handmaid of Liberty, meet us to-day; </l>
          <l rendition="#indent3">Thy votaries philanthropy ask from thy fountain, </l>
          <l rendition="#indent4">A soul-cheering nectar wherewith to be gay.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rendition="#indent3">The cup may o’erflow, and new grapes still be growing; </l>
          <l rendition="#indent4">The eyes of the drinkers resplendently shine; </l>
          <l rendition="#indent3">But grant us, bright nymph, with thy gifts overflowing, </l>
          <l rendition="#indent4">To lighten our hearts, and to relish our wine.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rendition="#indent3">Is Beauty’s gay rosebud a prize worth ensuring?</l>
          <l rendition="#indent4">Its guardianship rests with the friends of our cause.</l>
          <l rendition="#indent3">Shall we mark unconcern’d, what the blind are enduring? </l>
          <l rendition="#indent4">No! mercy and peace are the first of our laws.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rendition="#indent3">Wave, streamers of victory; be bravery requited;</l>
          <l rendition="#indent4">Be sails, in all climes, still with honour unfurl’d;</l>
          <l rendition="#indent3">All lovers of man with our cause are delighted;</l>
          <l rendition="#indent4">’Tis to banish the fears, and the tears of the world.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rendition="#indent3">All nations shall feel, and all nations inherit </l>
          <l rendition="#indent4">The wonderful blessing we place in their view; </l>
          <l rendition="#indent3">And if in that blessing a mortal claims merit, </l>
          <l rendition="#indent4">Oh! Jenner—your country resigns it to you!</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rendition="#indent3">From the field, from the farm, comes the glorious treasure, </l>
          <l rendition="#indent4">May its life-saving impulse—all fresh as the morn</l>
          <l rendition="#indent3">Still spread round the earth without bounds, without measure, </l>
          <l rendition="#indent4">Till Time has forgot, when his Jenner was born.</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">This piece was published in <title>The Gentleman’s Magazine </title>for June, (vol. 93, p. 551); it also appeared in
            <title>The Lady’s Magazine Or Entertaining Companion for the Fair Sex </title>in July (vol. 34, p. 383). Jenner, however, wanted it to be
          followed by the larger poem. He wrote to Bloomfield in summer 1803 ‘enquiring my determination as to the poem on Vaccination’ (<ref
            target="https://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/letterEEd.25.113.html">Letter 113</ref>, 2 August 1803). Bloomfield,
          however, in the aftermath of the dispute caused by Lofft’s determination to supervise his publications, was wary of going to press. On 23
          December he wrote to Jenner’s neighbour, <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#LloydBakerMary">Mary Lloyd Baker</ref>:</p>
        <quote>I have some time ago busied my brain and workd up my feelings to a great pitch in poetically celebrating the great victory obtain’d
          over the desease that kill’d my Father; and in which your neighbour and my friend <hi rend="ital">Dr Jenner</hi> is so immediately
          concern’d. The piece is still in existence, and I have allmost offended some worthy members of the medical world by keeping it
            unpublish’d. (<ref target="https://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/letterEEd.25.119.html">Letter 119</ref>)</quote>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">It was not until May/June 1804 that the poem was published by <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#VernorThomas">Vernor</ref>
          and <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#HoodThomas">Hood</ref>, and <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#LongmanThomasN">Longman</ref> and
          Rees, and printed by Bloomfield’s friend <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#SwanJames">James Swan</ref>. An extract from the poem, ‘recited
          at the anniversary meeting of the Royal Jennerian Society’ (1804) was published as a pamphlet. </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Reviews were complimentary: discussing the description of the dying father and blinded child, the <title>Monthly
            Mirror</title> declared (17 (June 1804), 385–89 (p. 389)) ‘it is unnecessary to point out the several exquisite beauties of this passage.
          Those who feel them, need it not; and those who do not, could derive no advantage from it.—Give us the blind to instruct in colours, and the
          deaf in sounds, but let nothing be required of us, touching the man who is not sensible of the charms of these verses, except our pity’.
          Somewhat pointedly, it alluded to the disputes about the Preface to <title>The Farmer’s Boy </title>and notes to <title>Rural Tales</title>:
          ‘In this delightful labour of his Muse, Mr. <title>Bloomfield</title> has received no assistance from either his worthy and best friend Mr.
          Lofft or Dr. Jenner, but has depended entirely on himself for the notes subjoined’. The <title>British Critic</title>, (24 (1804), 314–15
          (p. 314)) endorsed this judgement that Bloomfield’s independent spirit was at full strength: the poem, it said, showed ‘new strong proof of
          his powers’.. ‘historical views of former ravages, and affecting narratives of private misfortune, all contribute to interest the reader in
          the great discovery’. It ‘contains beauties, which only a true genius for poetry could infuse’.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Jenner himself was delighted. On 21 October, he wrote expressing gratitude and offering a token of thanks: </p>
        <quote>I was in hopes long before this time to have been in town, and to have thank’d you in person for your very elegant &amp; pathetic poem
          on Vaccine Inoculation, which you have so handsomely dedicated to me and my Brethren of the Royal J. Society. It excited in me those
          emotions which all who read it must feel, that are not void of sensibility. I trust it will be as well received and gain as high
          commendation as the Farmers Boy—It need not obtain more.</quote>
        <quote>You must allow me to fix upon you some mark of my esteem &amp; friendship. Do me the favour then to accept a Silver Inkstand, into
          which the inclosed note may be soon converted, if you will call upon Messrs. Rundell &amp; Bridge, Silversmiths in Ludgate Hill, &amp; use
          my name. I should like the following plain Engraving upon it. Edward Jenner M.D. to Robert Bloomfield. (<ref
            target="https://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/letterEEd.25.143.html">Letter 143</ref>)</quote>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">The method of publication was different from Bloomfield’s earlier volumes. Vernor and Hood only distributed the work, having
          bought no part of Bloomfield’s copyright. This deal seems to have reflected the publication’s purpose as a one-off piece of promotion for
          the campaign to popularize vaccination, it being intended to collect the poem in Bloomfield’s next major volume. The deal had consequences
          on sales, as Bloomfield noted in a letter to his brother (<ref
            target="https://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/letterEEd.25.135.html">Letter 135</ref>) of 3 August 1804:</p>
        <quote>When you wonder that good tidings is not known or advertized, you have only to recolect that of the other works the Bookseler has <hi
            rend="ital">Half</hi>, and of this <hi rend="ital">nothing</hi>. The advertizing rests with myself, and I won’t do it, and Hood cannot be
          expected to push my work as he would his own, more particularly when he <hi rend="ital">knows</hi> that when in a vollumn he will have it
          partly his own property, when it will be worth his while to send it all over the empire? </quote>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">No second edition was called for, because from 1806 the poem was indeed incorporated in Bloomfield’s new collection,
            <title>Wild Flowers; or Pastoral and Local Poetry</title>, and was reissued in each edition of that volume. Here, the copytext is the
          first edition of 1804, collated with the 1806 text from <title>Wild Flowers </title>and with later editions of that publication and also
          with the 1809 stereotype <title>Poems of Robert Bloomfield </title>(and later editions thereof).</p>
       </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
