<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">NATURE’S MUSIC (1808)</title>
        <title type="main">Collected Poems of Robert Bloomfield</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author><name>Bloomfield, Robert</name></author>
        <editor>Tim Fulford</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor,</resp>
          <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor,</resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado, Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only
            in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
            republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic Circles.
            Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
            <address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine><addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine><addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine></address></p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list></p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
            Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">editions.2019.bloomfield_poems.26NaturesMusicPt2</idno>
        <idno type="resource">bloomfield_poems</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">NATURE’S MUSIC (1808)</title>
            <author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Bloomfield</surname></persName></author>
            <ptr target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_poems/editions.2019.bloomfield_poems.26NaturesMusicPt2.html"/>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">Collected Poems of Robert Bloomfield</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2019-04-28">April 28, 2019</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
<tagsDecl>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent1">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent2">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent3">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent4">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent5">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent6">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent7">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent8">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent9">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="indent10">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="center">text-align: center;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="left">text-align: left;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="right">text-align: right;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="small">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="large">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="largest">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="smallest">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="titlem">font-style: italic;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="titlej">font-style: italic;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="figure">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="sup">vertical-align: super;</rendition>         <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="sub">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>       </tagsDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
            http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#DR" when="2019-04-15" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list>
          <item>Initial transforms to HTML</item>
        </list></change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="essay">
        <head rend="noCount" rendition="#center">NATURE’S MUSIC.</head>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center"> <hi rend="smcaps">consisting of</hi></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center"><hi rend="ital">EXTRACTS FROM SEVERAL AUTHORS;</hi></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center"> <hi rend="smcaps">with</hi></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">PRACTICAL OBSERVATIONS,</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center"> <hi rend="smcaps">and</hi></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">POETICAL TESTIMONIES,</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center"> <hi rend="smcaps">in honour of</hi></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">THE HARP OF ÆOLUS.</p>
        <lb/><lb/>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0"> <hi rend="smcaps">The</hi> motives for printing this pamphlet will, I hope, be as obvious and simple as the instrument of which it treats. I wish
          for nothing but to show, that men, wiser and abler than myself, have deemed it not unworthy of their particular notice; and at the same
          time, to convey information to those who may never have turned their thoughts to the subject. I am no musician. I dictate nothing; but, on
          the contrary, should be much obliged by receiving additional information, or hints for improvement.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#right">ROBT. BLOOMFIELD.</p>
        <lb/><lb/>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">NATURE’S MUSIC.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0"> <hi rend="smcaps">If</hi> we look into Lempriere’s Classical Dictionary, we find that ‘Æolus, the King of Storms and Winds, was the son of
          Hippotas: he reigned over Æolia<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Bloomfield’s note:] This Æolia was either a country of Asia Minor,
            near the Ægean sea, or the seven islands lying between Sicily and Italy, now called the Lipari islands, which Virgil calls the kingdom of
            Æolus, the God of Storms and Winds.</note>; and because he was the inventor of sails, and a great astronomer, the poets have called him
          the God of the Wind. It is said that he confined in a bag, and gave Ulysses, all the winds that could blow against his vessel when he
          returned to Ithaca. The companions of Ulysses untied the bag, and gave the winds their liberty. Æolus was indebted to Juno for his royal
          dignity, according to Virgil.’ </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">I am not disposed to covet the powers of this poet-made god, except in one particular, that of confining the wind in a bag;
          which would be extremely convenient on a sultry summer’s day, when not a breath of air is in motion: for, in the confined situation in which
          I live, surrounded almost by buildings which have started <hi rend="ital">literally </hi>out of the earth they cover, I often feel regret
          that, when my friends call, none but Æolus himself can oblige them with the vibration of a single string. But let them take the instrument
          to their villas, far from the smoke of London, and, though some may be found who will exclaim—</p>
        <lg>
          <l rendition="#indent3">‘Most musical, most melancholy;’<note place="foot" resp="editors">Line 62 of John Milton’s <title>Il Penseroso</title> (1645), also quoted by Coleridge in ‘The Nightingale; a Conversational Poem’.</note></l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">I think there will be a far greater proportion who will conceive in its tones the spirit of an anthem, and all the genuine
          fervour of praise. Yet it is equally true, that I have been jocosely told that Eolian harps are only adapted to send lazy people to sleep,
          and to give the unguarded a crick in the neck.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">A satisfactory account of this instrument may be found in Sir John Hawkins’s ‘General History of the Science and Practice of
          Music,’ published in 1776, in five volumes, 4to.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">In a preliminary discourse I find the following information:</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">‘The Harp of Æolus, as it is called, on which so much has been lately said and wrote, was constructed by Kircher above a
          century ago, and is accurately described in his Musurgia Universalis.’<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Athanasius Kircher, Musurgia
            Universalis, 2 vols (Rome, 1650).]</note> And in vol. iv. p. 218, Sir John makes the following remark, together with a translated extract
          from Kircher’s work:</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">‘In book ix, in a chapter entitled <title>De Sympathia</title>, &amp;c. Kircher mentions a contrivance of his own, an
          instrument which a few years ago was obtruded upon the public as a new invention, and called the Harp of Æolus, of which he thus speaks: </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">As the following instrument is new, so also is it easy to construct, and pleasant; and is heard in my museum to the great
          admiration of every one. It is silent as long as the window in which it is placed remains shut, but, as soon as it is opened, behold an
          harmonious sound on the sudden arises, that astonishes the hearers: for they are not able to perceive from whence the sound proceeds, nor
          yet what kind of instrument it is, for it resembles neither the sound of a stringed, nor yet of a pneumatic instrument, but partakes of
          both. The instrument is made of pine wood; it is five palms long, two broad, and one deep; it may contain fifteen or more chords, all equal,
          and composed of the intestines of animals. </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">The method of tuning it now remains, which is not, as in other instruments, by thirds, fourths, fifths, or eighths; but all
          the chords are to be tuned to an unison, or in octaves. It is very wonderful, and nearly paradoxical, that chords thus tuned should
          constitute different harmony. As this musical phenomenon has not as yet been observed by any one that I know of, I shall describe the
          instrument very minutely, to the end that it may be searched into very narrowly, and the effects produced by it accounted for; but first I
          shall show the conditions of the instrument, and where it ought to be fixed.”</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">These conditions differ from modern usage; and it is worthy of remark that the length of Kircher’s harp (if he called it a
          harp, for the name seems to be more modern) was but five palms, or fifteen inches; which is not more than half the usual width of our common
          sashes. That a greater length of string gives a sonorous and organ-like tone to the instrument I know by experience, and therefore conclude
          that its power and compass are thereby proportionably increased. Perhaps it is not impossible, or unlikely, that improvements may still be
          made, and its powers called forth in a much higher degree. Kircher goes on to describe a method of conducting the air through the strings of
          his instrument by means of what he terms valves, or boards so placed as to concentrate the breeze. This method I think too cumbersome and
          difficult to be practised in a dwelling-house, except a window could be set apart on purpose: but perhaps would answer in a garden, or open
          situation. I have made no attempt hitherto to reduce it to practice: but as this is intended to be a book of extracts, I shall proceed to
          another pleasing and circumstantial account of the Eolian harp, to be found in Jones’ ‘Physiological Disquisitions,’ page 338.—1781.<note
            place="foot" resp="editors"> [William Jones (1726–1800), <title>Physiological Disquisitions: Or, Discourses on the Natural
              Philosophy of the Elements </title>(1781).]</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">‘It was observed above, that as action and reaction are equal, the effect is the same, whether the sonorous body strikes the
          air, or the air strikes the sonorous body. In the case of a musical pipe this is plain enough; but it was not so well known, nor could it be
          so familiarly proved, till of late years, that the air can begin of itself to produce the effect, and fetch music out of a string, as a
          string fetches music out of the air. We have now a curious illustration of this fact from the instrument called an Eolian harp. How far the
          ancients were masters of this experiment is uncertain; but it has long been known that the wind would bring musical sounds from the strings
          of an instrument. In the Jewish Talmud, where we should scarcely expect to find any thing valuable in philosophy, the wind is reported to
          have brought music out of the harp of David; which, as it is there said, “being every midnight constantly blown upon by the north wind,
          warbled of itself”.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Jones’s note:] Talmud in Berac, folio 6.</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">The same effect has been alluded to by some of the poets, particularly by our own English poet, Spenser, where, speaking of
          the visionary harp of Orpheus, he has the following lines:</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">“I saw an harp strung all with silver twine;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">At length out of the river it was rear’d,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">And borne about the clouds to be divin’d;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Whilst all the way most heavenly noise was heard</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Of the strings stirred with the warbling wind.”</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5"><hi rend="ital">Spenser’s Ruins of Time, III. 2</hi>.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund Spenser (1552–99), <title>The
            Ruines of Time</title> (1591).</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">The author of the Principles and Power of Harmony ascribes the invention of what we now call the Eolian harp to Father
          Kircher; and it may be found in his Phonurgia, p. 148.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> Athanasius Kircher, <title>Phonurgia Nova
            </title>(1673).</note> In Mersennus,<note place="foot" resp="editors"> Marin Mersennus (1588–1648), whose work <title>Harmonie
              Universelle </title>(1636) described the harmonics of vibrating strings.</note> who endeavoured to pick up every thing the world could
          afford him, I see nothing of it. To the best of my knowledge, it was not taken from either of these authors when it was revived of late
          years in England. When Mr. Pope was translating Homer,<note place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander Pope’s translations of <title>The
              Iliad </title>(1715–20) and <title>Odyssey </title>(1726).</note> he had frequent occasion to consult the Greek commentary of
          Eustathius; where he met with a passage, in which it was suggested that the blowing of the wind against musical strings would produce
          harmonious sounds.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> Eustathius of Thessalonica (c. 1115–9/6) mentioned the fact in his Commentary on
            Homer, first printed Rome, 1542–50.</note> This was communicated to Mr. Oswald,<note place="foot" resp="editors"> James Oswald
            (1711–69).</note> a master of the violoncello, from North Britain, and an ingenious composer in the Scotch style, who himself gave me the
          following account many years ago, when I was under him as a practitioner in music. When he had received the hint of Mr. Pope’s discovery in
          Eustathius, he determined to try whether he could reduce it to practice. Accordingly, he took an old lute, and put strings upon it; he
          exposed it to the wind in every manner he could think of; but all without effect. When he was about to give the matter up as a mystery or a
          fable, he received some encouragement to a farther trial from an accident which happened to a harper on the Thames; who, having his
          instrument with him in a house-boat, perceived that a favourable stroke of the wind brought some momentary sounds from the strings, as if
          they had been suddenly touched after that manner, which, from the genius of this instrument, is called <hi rend="ital">arpeggio</hi>. The
          man was alarmed with the accident, and made many trials to procure a repetition of the same sounds from a like turn of the wind, but could
          never succeed; the music was vanished like an apparition. Upon this ground, however, Mr. Oswald persevered; and it came at last into his
          mind, that perhaps the strings ought to be exposed to a more confined current of air. With this view he drew up the sash of his
          chamber-window, so as to let in a shallow stream of air, and exposed his lute to it. In the middle of the night the wind rose, and the
          instrument sounded; which being heard by the artist, he sprang out of bed to examine all the circumstances of its situation, and noted down
          every thing with the most scrupulous precision; after which, as the principle was now ascertained, he never failed of the effect.<note
            place="foot" resp="editors"> [Jones’s note:] That the effect of the Eolian harp must often have been heard by accident seems
            undeniable from what I was lately informed of by Mr. Stanley, composer to his Majesty [Charles John Stanley, 1712–86, Master of the King’s
            Musicians under George III]; that two wires, stretched across an area before a house at London, had been heard to make very fine music,
            equal to the best Eolian harp. </note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">The construction of an Eolian harp is very simple. Nothing more is necessary than a long and narrow box of deal, with a thin
          belly, and eight or ten strings of catgut lightly stretched over two bridges, placed near the extremities, and all tuned in unison. When it
          plays, the unison itself is plainly heard as the lowest tone, and the combinations of concords, though consisting chiefly of the <hi
            rend="ital">harmonic </hi>notes, are by no means confined to them, but change, as the wind is more or less intense, with a variety and
          sweetness which is past description. I know not how to account for the compass of its notes on the principles of the harmonics but by
          admitting a new species of sounds, which I call <hi rend="ital">harmonics of the harmonics</hi>; or, <hi rend="ital">secondary
            harmonics</hi>. The sharp seventh is very commonly heard, which, if deduced as an harmonic, must be of the second species, as the 17th of
          the 12th; as also the 9th, which is as frequently heard, may be taken for the 12th of the 12th; and thus perhaps we may account for all its
          varieties.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">If we consider the quality of its harmony, it very much resembles that of a chorus of voices at a distance, with all the
          expressions of the <hi rend="ital">forte</hi>, the <hi rend="ital">piano</hi>, and the <hi rend="ital">swell</hi>; in a word, its harmony is
          more like to what we might imagine the aërial sounds of magic and enchantment to be, than to artificial music. We may call it, without a
          metaphor, the music of inspiration.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">With respect to the peculiar nature and causes of this phenomenon, I dare not promise entire satisfaction from my own
          speculations, being well aware of the difficulty. The principles I shall offer for solving this wonderful effect are founded on the analogy
          between light and air.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">1. And first I lay it down, that music is in air as colours are in light. When any body inflects the rays of light, or
          refracts them, it does not give the colours that are seen, but it makes the light give them; so a sonorous body does not give musical
          sounds, but makes the air give them.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">2. That as colours are produced by inflections and refractions of the rays of light; so musical sounds are produced by
          similar refractions of the air. There is no reason to suppose that air is homogeneous in its parts any more than light; and if air consists
          of heterogeneous parts, they will be differently refrangible, according to their magnitudes, and excite different sounds, as they are
          accommodated to different vibrations, and capable of different velocities; as the parts of light which are differently refrangible give
          different colours. The parts of air most refrangible will excite the most acute sounds, and the smallest parts will be most
            refrangible.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Jones’s note:] This notion concerning the different degrees of subtilty in the
            parts of air occurred to Mr. Derham [William Derham (1657–1735)]; who argued, that as sound moves near 1200 feet in a second, and the most
            violent wind not more than sixty miles in an hour, which is at the rate of eighty-eight feet in a second, the particles of air which
            communicate sound must be more subtile than those which constitute the winds. See Hales’ Doctr. Son. p. 47. [William Hales (1747–1831),
              <title>Sonorum Doctrina Rationalis et Experimentalis</title> (1778)]. If wind acts by the grosser parts of air, and sound by the finer,
            this may be a reason why they do not interfere nor disturb one another’s motions.*<lb/><lb/> [Bloomfield’s note:] * The following is taken from
            an old book published before Sir Isaac Newton received the honour of knighthood.<lb/><lb/> Mr. Isaac Newton demonstrates (in prop. 43, book ii.
            of his Principles) that sounds, because they arise from the tremulous motion of bodies, are nothing else but the propagation of the pulse
            of the air, and this, he saith, is confirmed by those great tremors that strong and grave sounds excite in bodies round about; as the
            ringing of bells, noise of cannon, &amp;c.<lb/><lb/> And in another place he concludes, that sounds do not consist in the motion of any aether,
            or finer air, but in the agitation of the whole common air; because he found by experiments, that the motion of sounds depended on the
            density of the whole air.’—Harris’ Dictionary of Arts and Sciences, printed in 1704. R. B. [John Harris (1666–1719), <title>Lexicon
              Technicum, Or, An Universal English Dictionary of Arts and Sciences</title>]</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">3. That as light shows no particular colour but by means of some other intervening body to separate and modify its rays, so
          the air yields no particular musical tone without the assistance of some sonorous body to separate its parts, and put them into a vibratory
          motion.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">4. That as light is refracted into colours, not only on dioptric principles, by passing through a prism of glass, or some
          other refracting medium, but also by passing near the edge of some solid body which inflects it out of its course; so is the air subject to
          be refracted by a similar inflection. It would require much time and observation, more than I have had leisure to bestow, to expand this
          principle into a theory, and confirm it by proper experiments; but the fact seems clear, that sound is produced, and that air becomes <hi
            rend="ital">vocal</hi> on this principle of a <hi rend="ital">refraction</hi>. As the Eolian harp plays by an inflection of a current of
          air over the edge of an aperture, so the column of air in an organ-pipe becomes vocal by means of a shallow current which strikes against
          the edge of the aperture, and is thence inflected into the cavity of the pipe. In the German flute also, the breath gives the tone by
          passing over the edge of the aperture; and according to its intensity, it produces higher or lower tones as the wind does in the Eolian
          harp. It would be endless to pursue this effect under all the various shapes in which it appears to us. It is sufficient for our purpose,
          that we have many instances in which air becomes vocal and musical by suffering a kind of refraction against the edge of some solid bodies;
          for this is the case with the Eolian harp; the wind passes to the strings of the instrument by the edge of an aperture; whence it is
          inflected partly at a greater, partly at a lesser angle; and that portion of the current of air which makes a different angle with the plane
          in which the strings lie, excites a different tone.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">This hypothesis for the solution of Eolian sound, by a refraction of the air, is recommended by an experiment, which
          demonstrates that such a relation between air and light, as we have here supposed, is not imaginary. For as light when refracted affords us
          seven colours, and no more; so the air yields seven degrees of sound within the system of the octave; of which all successive sounds,
          however multiplied, are but repetitions. I met with this comparison in an ancient English author; but the sagacity of Newton hit upon it in
          his optical experiments, and he has carried it much further, by showing us that the analogy extends even to the respective intervals of
          each. The prismatic spectrum, under his accurate examination of it, was found to exhibit the same degrees with the series of tones and
          semitones in an octave; but they do not answer to the degrees of the octave either in a flat or sharp key, as these keys are commonly now
          used; because the third is minor and the sixth major. However, these degrees of the optical octave may be justified, and the old masters
          have composed according to them; of which we have an instance in the old creed of Tallis;<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Thomas
            Tallis (1505–85), the composer of choral music.]</note> and there are many others. The diatonic scale affords us two octaves with the
          minor third, which differ in their degrees; the one from A to A, with the minor third and minor sixth; the other from D to D, with the minor
          third and major sixth. This latter has the advantage in two respects: First, It is more simple and natural, because the two tetrachords
          which make up the octave are similar; that is, they both have the hemitone in the same place, as it happens in the two tetrachords of the
          major key. Second, It leads to a greater variety of modulation; and though the harmonies by some are accounted harsh, yet, in my opinion,
          they are more stately and pleasing than in the flat key with its two dissimilar tetrachords, as now managed by modern masters; who have
          entirely dropped the other form, though it has excellencies peculiar to itself, and therefore deserves to be retained.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">The analogy between sounds and colours is very strict, and may be carried very far. In the order of the seven colours, three
          of them are simple and primary, the <hi rend="ital">red</hi>, the <hi rend="ital">yellow</hi>, and the <hi rend="ital">blue</hi>; so in the
          seven degrees of the octave, there are three principal tones which constitute its harmony, the <hi rend="ital">unison</hi>, the <hi
            rend="ital">third</hi>, and the <hi rend="ital">fifth</hi>; and these have the same places in the series as the three simple colours have
          in the prismatic spectrum; <hi rend="ital">red </hi>is in the place of the <hi rend="ital">unison</hi>, <hi rend="ital">yellow </hi>in the
          place of the <hi rend="ital">third</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">blue </hi>in the place of the <hi rend="ital">fifth. </hi>All harmony, though
          the parts are ever so many, is made up of these three sounds, as all hues are composed of those three colours.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Upon the whole, the Eolian harp may be considered as an air-prism, for the physical separation of musical sounds. The form
          of it may be improved, so as to give a farther illustration to the principles I have adopted. Instead of fixing the strings to the outside,
          I dispose them upon a sounding board, or belly, within side a wooden case, and admit the wind to them through a horizontal aperture, so that
          the affinity of the instrument to an organ-pipe appears at first sight; and thus it becomes portable and useful any where in the open air,
          instead of being confined to the house; which is a great advantage; and it is probable this new form may lead hereafter to some new
          experiments.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">No person of a musical ear can listen to the Eolian harp without discovering that the sound varies with the <hi rend="ital"
            >intensity </hi>of the wind. The unison with a sudden gust will change immediately into the octave on the same string; which happens in
          other instruments: the common and German flutes give the octaves with a more intense blast of the breath. What seemed to me most
          inexplicable of all was this, that if the Eolian harp is exposed to the air with a single string, that string, without any change in its
          situation, will be heard to sound all the harmonic notes, which are seven or eight, besides the unison; and several of them will be heard at
          the same time. When many strings, which the wind meets at different angles, sound together, we have not only the harmonics of the unison
          variously produced, but harmonics of the harmonics, as above mentioned.’</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Mr. Jones has given plates to illustrate his subject, and mentions, in a note, that, of his portable harp, he sent a model,
          on a small scale, to Messrs. <ref type="m" target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#LongmanThomasN">Longman </ref> and Broderip, with orders for its being
          constructed for sale. Although I have never seen one of that construction, I readily perceive the advantages which he ascribes to them, and
          hope some day to prove it by experience.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">The harps I have hitherto made have been, though of greater length, on the same principle with those seen at the music
          shops; but, where circumstances would admit of it, I have endeavoured to divide the strings into separate octaves. I have however proved, at
          least to my own satisfaction, that the top, or covering board, is of little use, if any, and that the strings ought to catch the wind in an
          inclination more approaching to a perpendicular than to a horizontal level. For this reason, I suppose, I find the instrument, when placed
          with the strings towards the window, always performs better than in the usual position. </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Strings covered with silver wire I have tried in various ways, but am not prepared to say whether they perform their part.
          Perhaps the metallic covering is not adapted to the action of the breeze. Strings covered with oil will not sound. Silk strings will give a
          most delicate tone, but I never yet could make them stand to their tension. </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">I have tried catgut about the size, or larger than the third string of the violin, but being strained to only the width of a
          common sash, they appeared to want <hi rend="ital">length </hi>in proportion to their <hi rend="ital">diameter</hi>, and therefore I
          conclude, that could such strings be placed at the length of eight or ten feet, so as to catch a current of wind, the effect would be
          increased proportionably. But as I am no musician, I advance this conjecture with diffidence, remembering that I have been repeatedly
          disappointed in my expectations, and as often found results that have been beyond my comprehension. </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Dr. Smollet, in the heyday of his strange imagination, has given the following description of this instrument in his Count
          Fathom, vol. i.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Tobias Smollett (1721–71), <title>The Adventures of Ferdinand Count Fathom
            </title>(1753).]</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">‘Some years ago, a twelve-stringed instrument was contrived by a very ingenious musician, by whom it was aptly entitled the
          harp of Eolus;<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Bloomfield’s note:] Most probably he alludes to Mr. Oswald, a better account of
            whom we have just given, by Mr. Jones.</note> because, being properly applied to a stream of air, it produces a wild, irregular variety of
          harmonious sounds, that seem to be the effect of enchantment, and wonderfully dispose the mind for the most romantic situations. </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">The strings no sooner felt the impression of the balmy zephyr, than they began to pour forth a stream of melody more
          ravishingly delightful than the song of Philomel, the warbling brook, and all the concert of the wood. The soft and tender notes of peace
          and love were swelled up with the most delicate and insensible transition, into a loud hymn of triumph and exultation, joined by the
          deep-toned organ, and a full choir of voices, which gradually decayed upon the ear until it died away in distant sound, as if a flight of
          angels had raised the song in their ascent to heaven.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Yet the chords hardly ceased to vibrate after the expiration of this overture, which ushered in a composition in the same
          pathetic style; and this again was succeeded by a third, almost without pause or intermission, as if the artist’s hand had been
          indefatigable, and the theme never to be exhausted.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">His heart must be quite callous, and his ear lost to all distinction, who could hear such harmony without emotion.’</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">I question whether this music, which Smollet so truly describes, was ever, or ever will be used for the villanous purpose
          which he has recorded in his novel. It deserves much higher employment. It will be observed that Smollet deemed the thing <hi rend="ital">of
            modern invention</hi>, and as he died, I believe, in 1771, five years before the publication of Sir John Hawkins’s work,<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Hawkins (1719–89) was the author of <title>A General History of the Science and Practice of Music
            </title>(1776).]</note> the latter was right when he calls it ‘an instrument which has been obtruded on the public as a new invention,’
          &amp;c. and did justice to Kircher, the oldest claimant on the subject. </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">The following observations appeared a few years since in a periodical work, and are, I believe, from the pen of Charles
          Bucke, Esq.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Charles Bucke (1781–1846), ‘Aeolian Harp’, <title>Monthly Mirror</title>, 14 (1802),
            297–99. The quoted passage runs to the sonnet concluding ‘Lulls to repose each transitory pain.’]</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">‘As nothing can be deemed natural but what proceeds from the actual principles of nature, we may safely pronounce the Eolian
          lyre to be the only natural instrument of emitting harmony. Other instruments, sending forth sounds by the assistance of the fingers, or by
          some other mechanical means, may be consequently termed artificial. This affords another instance of the truth of the old-established adage,
          that Simplicity is the nearest relative of Beauty, since the Eolian harp is the “most musical, most melancholy,” and most bewitching of all
          melodies.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Of the antiquity of this instrument it is difficult to decide: it had slept about a hundred years when it was accidentally
          discovered by Mr. Oswald.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">It has been asserted (by Sir John Hawkins in his History of Music, v. iv. b. 2. c. b. p. 221, and by Mr. Jones in his
          Physiological Disquisitions, p. 338) that this instrument was invented by Father Kircher, and this statement has been generally adopted as
          true: it appears however that Kircher was not the inventor; neither does he himself assume that merit; but says, in express terms, that the
          reason he is so particular in enlarging upon it is, <hi rend="ital">because no one had given any description of it before </hi>(De
          Sympathiae et Antipathiae Sonorum ratione, b. ix.).—The knowledge of the operation of air upon strings is doubtless of very high antiquity;
          allusions are made to it in the Talmud and Eustathius, and an anecdote from Lucian will sufficiently illustrate the remark.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">“When the Thracian Bacchanals tore Orpheus piecemeal, report says, that his harp was thrown into the river Hebrus, with his
          bleeding head upon it. The harp, touched with the wind, breathed forth a solemn strain. Still swimming down the Egean sea, the mournful
          concert arrived at Lesbos, where the inhabitants, taking them up, buried the head where now stands the Temple of Bacchus, and suspended the
          lyre in the Temple of Apollo.”<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Bloomfield’s note:] To this incident Spenser alludes in a beautiful
            passage of his Ruins of Time. [Lucian of Samosata (c. 125–c. 180) relates the story in <title>Remarks Addressed to an Illiterate
              Book-Fancier. </title>Spenser alludes to it in <title>The Ruines of Time</title>, III, 2 (cited above).] </note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Descending to a later period, we find Ossian observing the same enchanting effect:</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">“The blast came rustling through the hall, and gently touched my harp;—the sound was mournful and low, like the song of the
          tomb.” <hi rend="ital">Darthula</hi>.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [The Poems of Ossian, tr. by J. Macpherson, 2 vols
            (Edinburgh, 1805), II, 33.]</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Again in <hi rend="ital">Berrathon.</hi></p> 
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">“My harp hangs on a blasted branch; the sound of its strings is mournful. Does the
          wind touch thee, oh harp! or is it some passing ghost?”<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Ibid. p. 93.]</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">It were impossible not to believe the romantic circumstance of the statue of Memnon, which</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">. . . . . . . at the quivering touch</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Of Titan’s ray, with each repulsive string</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Consenting, sounded through the trembling air</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Unbidden strains,<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Bloomfield’s note:] Akenside, b. i. [Mark Akenside (1721–70),
                <title>The Pleasures of Imagination</title>, I, 110–13.]</note></l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">when supported by such authorities as Pliny, Juvenal, Pausanius, and Strabo: the fact is too well authenticated to be
          doubted. </p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">The art by which it was managed still remains an enigma, notwithstanding many ingenious solutions. We are to consider, in
          the first place, that sounds were not emitted from the mouth of that statue in the morning only; authority states that they likewise
          proceeded at other times; the morning was, however, the more favourable, as the breezes which rise at the dawn of day from the Nile might
          catch certain strings artfully placed in the throat of the image, and cause them to send forth those plaintive melodies which the ancients
          so frequently mention.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Whatever be its age, it is a most enchanting instrument, and bringing out all the tones in full concert, sometimes sinking
          them to the softest murmurs, and feeling for every tone, by its gradations of strength, it solicits those gradations of sound which art has
          taken such various methods to produce.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Bucke’s note:] Acoustics, ch. i.</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">The influence of this instrument upon the heart is truly pleasing: it disposes the mind to solemn, tender, and pathetic
          emotion; and, winning upon the imagination, strikes the heart with its simplicity, and leaves it resting in all the pure delights of a
          pleasing melancholy.</p>
        
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">SONNET.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Music of nature! emblem of each sphere! </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">How sweetly tranquil does my pensive soul, </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">At dewy eve, thy warbling murmurs hear, </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">When sooth’d to tenderness thy measures roll; </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Sometimes more loud, and now yet louder still, </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Sometimes more distant, and again more near, </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Waking soft echoes, and, with magic skill, </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Swelling the eye with a luxurious tear. </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Delightful flutterings! hovering toward the sky, </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Ten thousand Sylphs, on lightest pinions borne, </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">To realms ethereal on your murmurs fly, </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And waked to melancholy feelings, mourn, </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Nature’s best music! since thy simple strain </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Lulls to repose each transitory pain.’<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Bucke, citing this poem, credits it only
              to ‘Anon.’]</note></l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">I subjoin an interesting extract from the French voyage undertaken in search of the unfortunate Pérouse, which, though it
          has nothing to do with the vibration of a string, is at the same time so strictly nature’s music, that it deserves a place where we are
          following the vagaries of Æolus. When at the Dutch island of Amboyna, in September, 1792, the author says,<note place="foot"
            resp="editors"> [Jacques-Julien Houtou de La Billardière, <title>Voyage in Search of La Pérouse: Performed by Order of the Constituent
              Assembly </title>(London, 1800), p. 217.]</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">‘Being upon the beach, I heard the sound of wind instruments, the harmony of which was sometimes very just, and blended with
          dissonances by no means displeasing. Those fine and harmonious sounds seemed to come from such a distance as to make me believe, for some
          time, that the natives were entertaining themselves with their music, on the other side of the road, and near five thousand toises from the
          place where I stood.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [A toise is a French unit of measurement equating to roughly 6 feet.]</note>
          My ear was much deceived as to the distance, for I was not fifty toises from the instrument. It was a bamboo, at least sixty feet in height,
          fixed in a vertical position, close to the sea. Between every joint was a hole near an inch and two-tenths long, and somewhat above half an
          inch broad. These holes formed so many mouths, which, by the action of the wind, emitted agreeable and varied sounds. As the joints of this
          long bamboo were very numerous, care had been taken to pierce it in different directions; so that, from whatever point the wind blew, it
          always meets with some holes. The sound of this instrument more nearly resembles that of the harmonica than any other to which I can compare
          it.’</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Can it be wondered at, that the harp of Æolus, affording music as wild and as ungovernable as imagination itself, should at
          all times have been a favourite with the poets? And if ten men are enamoured of the same thing, and describe it with a feeling mind and
          appropriate language, can it be wonderful that their verses should exhibit a similarity? For myself, I have always been drawn irresistibly
          to esteem that description the most true and most delightful, which Thomson has given in his ‘Castle of Indolence,’ which is therefore
          placed first of the poetical testimonies which I have been able to collect.</p>
       
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">A certain music, never known before,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Here lull’d the pensive melancholy mind,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Full easily obtain’d. Behoves no more</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Than sidelong, to the gently waving wind,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">To lay the well-tuned instrument reclined;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">From which, with airy, flying fingers light,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Beyond each mortal touch the most refined,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">The God of Winds drew sounds of deep delight:</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Whence with just cause the harp of Æolus it hight.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Ah me! what hand can touch the strings so fine?</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Who, up the lofty diapason roll</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Such sweet, such sad, such solemn airs divine;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Then let them down again into the soul?</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">Now rising love they fann’d; now pleasing dole</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">They breathed, in tender musings, through the heart;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">And now a graver, sacred strain they stole,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent3">As when seraphic bands an hymn impart,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Wild warbling nature all, above the reach of art.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [James Thomson, <title>The
                Castle of Indolence </title>(1748), stanzas 40–41.]</note></l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Thomson has likewise written the following lines on the same subject, and there is little doubt but he felt what he wrote. </p>
        
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">ODE ON ÆOLUS’S HARP.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4"><hi rend="smcaps">Ethereal</hi> race, inhabitants of air,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Who hymn your God amid the secret grove,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Ye unseen beings, to my harp repair,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">And raise majestic strains, or melt in love.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Those tender notes, how kindly they upbraid,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">With what soft woe they thrill the lover’s heart;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Sure from the hand of some unhappy maid</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Who died of love, these sweet complainings part. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">But hark! that strain was of a graver tone:</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">On the deep strings his hand some hermit throws;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Or he, the sacred Bard<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Bloomfield’s note:] Jeremiah.</note>, who sat alone</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">In the drear waste, and wept his people’s woes. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Such was the song which Zion’s children sung,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">When by Euphrates’ stream they made their plaint ;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And to such sadly-solemn notes are strung</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Angelic harps, to sooth a dying saint.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Methinks I hear the full celestial choir</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Through heaven’s high dome their awful anthem raise:</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Now chanting clear, and now they all conspire</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">To swell the lofty hymn from praise to praise.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Let me, ye wandering spirits of the wind,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Who, as wild fancy prompts you, touch the string,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Smit with your theme, be in your chorus join’d,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">For till you cease, my Muse forgets to sing.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Published 1748).]</note></l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">That very extraordinary young man, the late H. K. White of Nottingham, has left us the following sonnet:</p>
        
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">ON HEARING THE SOUND OF AN</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">EOLIAN HARP.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4"><hi rend="smcaps">So</hi> ravishingly soft upon the tide</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Of the infuriate gust it did career,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">It might have sooth’d his rugged charioteer,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And sunk him to a zephyr,—then it died,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Melting in melody,—and I descried,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Borne to some wizard stream, the form appear</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Of Druid sage, who on the far-off ear</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Pour’d his lone song, to which the surge replied:</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Or thought I heard the hapless pilgrim’s knell,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Lost in some wild enchanted forest’s bounds,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">By unseen beings sung; or are these sounds</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Such as, ’tis said, at night, are known to swell</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">By startled shepherd on the lonely heath,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Keeping his night-watch sad! portending death!<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Henry Kirke White (1785–1806).
              The poem was published posthumously in <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White of Nottingham ... with an Account of his Life by Robert
                Southey</title>, 2 vols (London, 1807), II, 59.]</note></l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Mr. Mason thought a harp, which appears to have been constructed by his own hands, worthy of an ode; and a note attached to
          the piece is worth remarking, as its statement of the question of its invention agrees with that given by Sir John Hawkins.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">ODE TO AN ÆOLUS’S HARP.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Mason’s note:] This instrument was first invented by
            Kircher about the year 1649. See his Musurgia Universalis, &amp;c. After having been neglected above a hundred years, it was again
            accidentally discovered by Mr. Oswald.</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center"><hi rend="smcaps">sent to miss shepherd.</hi></p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4"><hi rend="smcaps">Yes</hi>, magic lyres now all complete,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Thy slender frame responsive rings,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">While kindred notes, with undulations sweet,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Accordant wake from all thy vocal strings.</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Go then to her, whose soft request</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Bade my blest hands thy form prepare; </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Ah go, and sweetly sooth her tender breast</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">With many a warble wild and artless air. </l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">For know, full oft, while o’er the mead</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Bright June extends her fragrant reign,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">The slumbering fair shall place thee near her head,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">To court the gales that cool the sultry plain.</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Then shall the Sylphs and Sylphids bright,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Mild Genii all, to whose high care</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Her virgin charms are given, in circling flight</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Skim sportive round thee in the fields of air.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Some, fluttering through thy trembling strings,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Shall catch the rich melodious spoil,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And lightly brush thee with their purple wings,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">To aid the Zephyrs in their tuneful toil;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">While others check each ruder gale,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Expel rough Boreas from the sky,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Nor let a breeze its heaving breath exhale,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Save such as softly pant, and panting die.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Then, as thy swelling accents rise,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Fair Fancy, waking at the sound,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Shall paint bright visions on her raptured eyes,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">And waft her spirits to enchanted ground;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">To myrtle groves, Elysian greens,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">In which some favourite youth shall rove,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And meet and lead her through the glittering scenes,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">And all be music, ecstasy, and love.</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#right"><title>Mason’s Poems, fourth edition</title>, 1774.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> William Mason (1724–97),
              <title>Poems</title>, 4th edn (York, 1774), pp. 27–28.</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">______</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">‘<hi rend="smcaps">Most</hi> pleasant warble thy wild flying notes,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Sweet, simple instrument!—O, I could pause</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Beneath some thick-wove canopy of elms,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">To hear thy music e’en from morn, till night</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Should spread her thickest veil: ah! then ’tis sweet</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">To hear thy soft sighs melancholy breathe</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">As the mild zephyr flutters o’er thy strings</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">On silken pinions . . . . . . . .</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">. . . . . . . . Hark! now a pensive lay,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">That wakes the soul to sympathy and love,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Steals on my watchful ear! It dies away</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">In soft faint murmur . . . . now again ’tis high!</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And, swelling loud and louder, in bold notes</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Peals forth the anthem, or the choral song</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Of steel-clad heroes. Now so sweet the sound,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">That fancy thinks no mortal touch can make</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Such harmony divine—but deems they flow</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">From the full choir of celestial harps,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Attuned by seraphs in the realms of love,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">To praise their Maker! . . . . . . . .</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">. . . . . . . Ah! were it mine to dwell</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Far, far retired from the busy throng,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">In vine-clad cottage—or at noon or eve,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Thy murmurs mingling with the moss-fringed brook</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Should lull my soul to happiness and peace!’</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#right"><hi rend="ital">Goodwin</hi><title>.</title><note place="foot" resp="editors"> George Goodwin of Lynn, author of
              <title>Rising Castle, with Other Poems</title> (Lynn, 1798), pp. 101–2.</note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">Mr. Dibdin, amongst the multiplicity of his excellent songs, has one entitled ‘The Eolian Harp,’ the music to which is a
          fine imitation of the wild notes of the instrument: the first verse of the song runs thus:</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Amphion’s lute and Orpheus’ lyre</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Pleased amateurs of yore;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Loud harps our amateurs inspire,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">And those are heard no more.</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Harps that assist each female charm,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">The snowy hand, the rounded arm;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">That turn with more than mortal grace</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">The stately neck and lovely face,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">As rapidly the fingers trace</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Each natural, flat, and sharp.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">But, more the senses to ensnare,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Give me the soft melodious strain</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">That gently floats upon the air,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">That all can feel, but none explain,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Sounds that the ear so smoothly greet</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">From the celestial self-play’d sweet</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Eolian Harp.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Dibdin (1768–1833). The song was issued with sheet music as
                <title>The Aeolian Harp, Written &amp; Composed by Mr. Dibdin and Sung by Him in His New Entertainment Called Most Votes</title>
              (London, 1802).</note></l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">A lady of the present day, whose writings continue to interest and amend the heart, once turned her attention to the
          instrument of which we are treating, and has given us</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">STANZAS</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center"><hi rend="smcaps">written under aeolus’s harp.</hi></p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4"><hi rend="smcaps">Come</hi> ye whose hearts the tyrant sorrows wound;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Come ye whose breasts the tyrant passions tear,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And seek this harp,—in whose still-varying sound</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Each woe its own appropriate plaint may hear.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Solemn and slow yon murmuring cadence rolls,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Till on th’ attentive ear it dies away,—</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">To your fond griefs responsive ye, whose souls</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">O’er loved lost friends regret’s sad tribute pay.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">But hark! in regular progression move</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Yon silver sounds, and mingle as they fall;—</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Do they not wake thy trembling nerves, O Love,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And into warmer life thy feelings call?</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Again it speaks;—but shrill and swift, the tones</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">In wild disorder strike upon the ear:</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Pale Frenzy listens,—kindred wildness owns,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And starts appall’d the well known sounds to hear:</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Lo! E’en the gay, the giddy, and the vain,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">In deep delight, his vocal wires attend,—</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Silent and breathless watch the varying strain,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And pleased, the vacant toils of mirth suspend.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">So, when the lute on Memnon’s statue hung,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">At day’s first rising strains melodious pour’d,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Untouch’d by mortal hands, the gathering throng</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">In silent wonder listen’d and adored.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">But the wild cadence of these trembling strings</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">The enchantress Fancy with most rapture hears;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">At the sweet sound to grasp her wand she springs,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And lo! her band of airy shapes appears.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">She, rapt enthusiast, thinks the melting strains</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">A choir of angels breathe, in bright array,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Bearing on radiant clouds, to yon blue plains,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">A soul just parted from its silent clay.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And oft at eve her wild creative eye</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Sees to the gale their silken pinions stream,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">While in the quivering trees soft zephyrs sigh,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And through the leaves disclose the moon’s pale beam.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">O breathing instrument! be ever near</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">While to the pensive muse my vows I pay;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Thy softest call the inmost soul can hear,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Thy faintest breath can Fancy’s pinions play.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And when art’s labour’d strains my feelings tire,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">To seek thy simple music shall be mine;</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">I’ll strive to win its graces to my lyre,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And make my plaintive lays enchant like thine.</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent6"><hi rend="smcaps">Mrs. Opie</hi>.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> Amelia Opie (1769–1853). The poem, published in <title>The Cabinet
            </title>in 1795, was collected in Opie’s <title>Poems </title>(1802). In revised form it appeared in the third edition (London, 1804) at
            pp. 121–24. </note></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">After the foregoing descriptions, who could hope to illustrate poetically the properties of this instrument in a new
            way?<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Note by J. Weston, editor of <title>Remains</title>, referring to Bloomfield’s ‘Aeolus’ in
              <title>Poems from the Remains of Robert Bloomfield</title>:] See Poetical Fragments, page 62.</note> and yet I have seen other pieces,
          of uncommon merit, on the same subject; and one particularly from the pen of a lady,<note place="foot" resp="editors"> [Note by J.
            Weston, editor of <title>Remains</title>:] Mrs. Park, whose tributary poem may now be introduced without any other sensation than that of
            tender regret, since both the writer and receiver are now beyond the reach of human praise or blame:<p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">LINES ADDRESSED
              TO AN EOLIAN HARP,</p><p rend="noCount" rendition="#center"><hi rend="smcaps">constructed by the author of the</hi><lb/><hi rend="smcaps">farmer’s boy</hi>.</p>
         <lg type="stanza">
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4"><hi rend="smcaps">What</hi> magic sweetness charms my raptured ear,</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Like choirs of airy spirits heard on high?</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Now as some cherub voice each note is clear,</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Now swells into celestial harmony.</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">’Tis charmed zephyr wakes the varied sound,</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">As o’er each string he breathes a trembling kiss,</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">His viewless pinion wafts the music round,</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Whose chords are ecstasy, whose close is bliss!</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Oh, sweetly raise thy more than mortal tone</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">To him who gave thy frame melodious birth,</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">The Bard whom Nature greets as all her own,</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">And Virtue honours for his inborn worth:</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">For him, sweet harp! thy dulcet strains prolong,</l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Since pure and artless is, like thine, his song.<lb/></l>
           <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent6"><hi rend="smcaps">Maria Hester Park</hi>.</l><l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4"><hi rend="ital">Hampstead</hi>,</l><l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4"><hi rend="ital">March</hi>, 1806.</l>
            </lg>
            <p rend="noCount">[Maria Hester Park (1760–1813), a singer, pianist and composer, was the wife of Bloomfield’s friend <ref type="m"
                target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/bloomfield_letters/HTML/people.html#ParkThomas">Thomas Park</ref>.]</p>
            </note> which I omit with unfeigned regret. Its insertion <hi rend="ital">here
          </hi>would be the most unpardonable self-praise. Its omission will be excused by the party, and there are several others in the like
          predicament.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#indent0">I therefore know of nothing which would form so appropriate a close to this collection as the following verses, printed at
          the end of an edition of ‘Bruce’s Poems on several Occasions.’ Edinburgh, 1796.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">ON HEARING AN EOLIAN HARP</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">AT MIDNIGHT.</p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center"><hi rend="smcaps">by mr. c——, a young gentleman who died</hi></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center"><hi rend="smcaps">of a consumption a few days after</hi></p>
        <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center"><hi rend="smcaps">writing them.</hi></p>
     
        <lg type="stanza">
          <head rendition="#center">1.</head>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4"><hi rend="smcaps">Ye</hi> heavenly sounds! enchanting notes!</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">That swell the whispering breeze; </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Say, whence your soft complaining airs,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Your magic power to please!</l>
        </lg>
        
        <lg type="stanza">
          <head rendition="#center">2.</head>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Are ye some fairy, tiny voice,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">That by the glow-worm’s light,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">At lonely hours, your vigils keep,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Unmark’d by mortal sight?</l>
        </lg>
  
        <lg type="stanza">
          <head rendition="#center">3.</head>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Are ye some nymph of ancient time,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Like Echo’s hapless maid,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">In plaintive songs, that woo’d your love </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Till changed into a shade?</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <head rendition="#center">4.</head>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Or are ye Ossian’s passing ghost,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">That thus the midnight cheers,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And to the fair Malvina turns </l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">The tale of other years?</l>
        </lg>
  
        <lg type="stanza">
          <head rendition="#center">5.</head>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Sweet sounds! that melt the soul to love,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">My senses captive take,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Soft as the Cygnet’s dying voice</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">That’s wafted from the lake.</l>
        </lg>

        <lg type="stanza">
          <head rendition="#center">6.</head>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">Oh! cease not to my list’ning ear,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">Still tune your heavenly lay,</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent4">And by your strains my raptured soul</l>
          <l rend="noCount" rendition="#indent5">To paradise convey.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> Michael Bruce (1746–67), <title>Poems on Several Occasions
              </title>(Edinburgh, 1796), p. 174.</note></l>
        </lg>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
