<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">The sound of the gaze in Ann Radcliffe’s <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian
                    Romance</title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>David Sigler</name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-05-14</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2023.sound.sigler</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">praxis</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">The sound of the gaze in Ann Radcliffe’s <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian
                            Romance
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>David</forename>
                                <surname>Sigler</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="praxis/sound/praxis.2023.sound.sigler"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Sound Studies: Recording Romantic Relationality </title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-02-21">May 14, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>05.14.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
            <head>The sound of the gaze in Ann Radcliffe’s <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian
                    Romance</hi></head>
                
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>David Sigler</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>University of Calgary</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
                <div type="section"></div>
                
            <p rend="center">David Sigler</p>
            <p> The terrifying mystery in Ann Radcliffe’s second novel,<hi rend="italic">A Sicilian
                    </hi><hi rend="italic">Romance</hi> (1790), is a sound.<note xml:id="ftn1"
                    place="end" n="1"> This research was supported by the Social Sciences and
                    Humanities Research Council of Canada, Insight Grant #435-2017-0037. I thank
                    Michele Speitz and Shoshannah Bryn Jones Square for reading drafts of this essay
                    so perceptively.</note> Julia Mazzini hears a distinct knock coming through the
                wall of a supposedly vacant part of Castle Mazzini, and spends the novel trying to
                understand how something like that could arise with no one to produce it. The knock,
                predecessor to terrifying sounds encountered in later texts by Thomas de Quincey and
                Charlotte Brontë, seems to be what psychoanalysts would call an “object voice,” a
                sound “fully unfastened from phonemization,” which marks a void in the castle
                architecture through its menacing excess to signification.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="2"> Slavoj Žižek, “‘I Hear You with My Eyes’; or, the Invisible
                    Master,” in <hi rend="italic">Gaze and Voice as Love Objects</hi>, ed. Renata
                    Salecl and Slavoj Žižek, SIC 1 (Durham: Duke University Press, 1996), 90–91;
                    Jacques Lacan, <hi rend="italic">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book X: Anxiety,
                        1962–63</hi>, ed. Jacques-Alain Miller, trans. A.R. Price (Cambridge:
                    Polity, 2015), 230–31, 249.</note> Though indeterminate, it soon becomes what
                Mladen Dolar would call “a grain of desire, a small provocation which triggers off
                massive consequences.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="3"> Mladen Dolar, <hi
                        rend="italic">A Voice and Nothing More</hi>, Short Circuits (Cambridge, MA:
                    The MIT Press, 2006), 131.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To the extent that the sound in this novel asks for anything, it asks to be seen.<hi
                    rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>Julia and her comrades, in concerted acts of
                synesthesia, frequently look around for sounds and listen for sights. The characters
                constantly attempt to keep a lookout for the sound: “For the remainder of this night
                they resolved to watch.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="4"> Ann Radcliffe, <hi
                        rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi>, ed. Alison Milbank (Oxford: Oxford
                    University Press, 2008), 35.</note> The mystery of the knock (as buttressed by
                other associated sounds, like footsteps or a groan) first manifests as a visual
                sign, a light in the tower seen and then “seen no more,” with all of the narrator’s
                emphasis placed on “what she [in this case, Madame de Menon] had seen.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="5"> Radcliffe, 8.</note>
                <hi rend="color(#000000)">Radcliffe consistently presents sound as an excessive
                    aspect of vision, and visuality as something lacking in sound, and thus
                </hi>repeatedly encourages the reader to contemplate the relationship between sound
                and vision, just as David Bowie recommends. Julia’s brother Ferdinand, the narrator
                assures us, “<hi rend="color(#000000)">had himself witnessed the sounds.”</hi><hi
                    rend="color(#000000)"><note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="6"> Radcliffe,
                        49.</note></hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"> Certainly, it is possible to
                    witness something auditorily, but the term, in 1790 as now, especially pertains
                    to visual phenomena.</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"><note xml:id="ftn120"
                        place="end" n="7"> “Witness, v.,” in <hi rend="italic">OED Online</hi>
                        (Oxford University Press), sec. 4, accessed January 9, 2020,
                        http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/229714.The <hi rend="italic">OED </hi>moves
                        between acts of seeing and hearing in its relevant entry for “witness, v.,”
                        but with especial emphasis on the former: <hi rend="color(#000000)"
                            >“</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)">To be a witness, spectator, or auditor
                            of (something of interest, importance, or special concern); to
                            experience by personal (esp. ocular) observation; to be present as an
                            observer at; to see with one’s own eyes. In early use said mainly of the
                            eyes or the ears. (In loose writing often used merely as a synonym of
                            ‘see’.)</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)">”</hi></note></hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="color(#000000)">Inspired by this strange synesthesia, this essay</hi> will
                resort to theories of the gaze in an attempt to think through the novel’s
                frightening maternal sound. First, I consider Michel Foucault’s comments in “The Eye
                of Power,” an interview in which he considers the ways that Radcliffe’s castle
                spaces seek illumination, to better herald the arrival of a gaze exercised
                pervasively. I suggest that sound in <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi>
                complicates that model, given how, on the one hand, both the ruins of the castle (in
                the narrative frame) and the castle itself (in the main narrative) remain inundated
                by sounds and silences that interfere with the operation of power, and how, on the
                other hand, the sound through the wall tends to disperse and diffuse the patriarchal
                authority of Castle Mazzini with a maternal counterpoint. Second, I connect this
                mechanism to a little-discussed aspect of Jacques Lacan’s commentary of the gaze in
                    <hi rend="italic">The Four </hi><hi rend="italic">Fundamental Concepts of
                    Psychoanalysis</hi>: as Lacan engages with and attempts to challenge Jean-Paul
                Sartre’s theory of the gaze, he notes that the gaze has to do with sound rather than
                sight directly. This sonic facet of the gaze will help us understand the role sound
                plays in Julia’s protestations of love for Hippolitus. Third, I consider Sigmund
                Freud’s discussion of alarm clock dreams in <hi rend="italic">The Interpretation of
                    Dreams</hi>, in which he contemplates how the same stimulus, and the same
                dreamer, can produce a diversity of dream images. Freud’s consideration of F. W.
                Hildebrandt’s alarm clock dreams complicates any attempt to understand the “meaning”
                of the knocking sound in Radcliffe’s novel or confine it to its seemingly obvious
                Oedipal resonances. Sending sound beyond any patent relation to signification, the
                bells of Castle Mazzini, like the knocks that emanate from within, position Julia as
                their true agent, as if the plot were bent on undoing her subjectivity rather than,
                as it may at first appear, asserting her right to make her own sexual decisions.</p>
            <p>In thinking about sound through epistemologies of vision, Radcliffe could respond to
                contemporary debates about gender, class, and privilege. It has often been noted
                that vision was increasingly presumed, over the eighteenth century, to be the basis
                of all knowledge and the instrument of subjectivity.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="8"> David Levin, <hi rend="italic">The Opening of Vision:
                        Nihilism and the Postmodern Situation</hi> (London: Routledge, 1988), 97–98;
                    Volker Langbehn, “The Lacanian Gaze and the Role of the Eye in Early German
                    Romanticism,” <hi rend="italic">European Romantic Review</hi> 16, no. 5 (2005):
                    614–15, https://doi.org/10.1080/10509580500420506.</note> Landed male poets
                would climb hills to “assume a position of superior knowledge drawn from personal
                experience,” while women writers would oftener adopt points of view within, rather
                than above, the field of vision.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="9"> Walt
                    Hunter, “The No-Prospect Poem: Lyric Finality in Prynne, Awoonor, and
                    Trethewey,” <hi rend="italic">The Minnesota Review</hi> 2015, no. 85 (2015):
                    145, https://doi.org/10.1215/00265667-3144702; Jacqueline M. Labbe, <hi
                        rend="italic">Romantic Visualities: Landscape, Gender, and Romanticism</hi>
                    (Houndmills: Palgrave Macmillan, 1998), xii–xiii.</note> The priority of vision
                within Enlightenment epistemology has helped to sustain several important analyses
                of Radcliffe’s work.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="10"> George Dekker, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Fictions of Romantic Tourism: Radcliffe, Scott, and Mary
                        Shelley</hi> (Stanford University Press, 2005), 58; Benjamin A. Brabon,
                    “Gothic Geography, 1760–1830,” in <hi rend="italic">The Gothic World</hi>, ed.
                    Glennis Byron and Dale Townshend, Routledge Worlds (London: Routledge, 2014),
                    102–4.</note> “What is new in Radcliffe’s fiction,” explains Alison Milbank, “is
                located in her way of seeing,” and <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi>
                particularly brims with “pictorial effects.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="11"
                    > Alison Milbank, “Ways of Seeing in Ann Radcliffe’s Early Fiction: <hi
                        rend="italic">The Castles of Aithlin and Dunbayne</hi> (1789) and <hi
                        rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi> (1790),” in <hi rend="italic">Ann
                        Radcliffe, Romanticism, and the Gothic</hi>, ed. Dale Townshend and Angela
                    Wright (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2014), 86, 88.</note> Even today,
                as Kandice Chuh has argued, the visual regime continues to reify neoliberal
                hierarchies of race and gender inherited from the Enlightenment.<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="12"> Kandice Chuh, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Difference Aesthetics Makes: On the Humanities “After Man”</hi> (Durham:
                    Duke University Press, 2019), 60–62.</note></p>
            <p>Critics remain in dispute over the function of sound in Radcliffe’s work, with Frits
                Noske arguing that “the sounds in her novels appear for their own sake,” and Angela
                M. Archambault arguing that Radcliffe uses sound, and especially the voice, to
                create terror and chaos in her novels, generally starting with quiet, peaceful sound
                effects which become more jarring as the novels progress.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="13"> Frits Noske, “Sound and Sentiment: The Function of Music in
                    the Gothic Novel,” <hi rend="italic">Music &amp; Letters</hi> 62, no. 2 (1981):
                    165; Angela M. Archambault, “The Function of Sound in the Gothic Novels of Ann
                    Radcliffe, Matthew Lewis and Charles Maturin,” <hi rend="italic">Études
                        Épistémè. Revue de Littérature et de Civilisation (XVIe – XVIIIe
                        Siècles)</hi>, no. 29 (June 21, 2016): paras. 4–6,
                    https://doi.org/10.4000/episteme.965.</note> Thinkers like Samuel Taylor
                Coleridge would, during the early nineteenth century, frequently associate sound
                with the sublime, arguing both that sound is intrinsically indeterminate and that we
                are relatively defenseless against it.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="14"> Tim
                    Fulford, “The Politics of the Sublime: Coleridge and Wordsworth in Germany,” <hi
                        rend="italic">The Modern Language Review</hi> 91, no. 4 (1996): 820,
                    https://doi.org/10.2307/3733510.</note> Noske maintains that “it was Ann
                Radcliffe who first used sonorous means as a structural factor in fiction.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="15"> Noske, “Sound and Sentiment,” 165.</note> In
                implicit opposition to Milbank’s conclusions, Matt Foley, from a Lacanian
                perspective, traces “the acoustics of the Gothic romance,” and finds, in <hi
                    rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi>, that voice conveys tyrannical
                    authority.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="16"> Matt Foley, “Tyranny as
                    Demand: Lacan Reading the Dreams of the Gothic Romance,” in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lacan and Romanticism</hi>, ed. Daniela Garofalo and David Sigler (Albany:
                    SUNY Press, 2019), 141, 149–50.</note> Throughout these debates, critics do tend
                implicitly to accept Noske’s now-classic assessment that Radcliffe uses music as a
                “connecting factor” between characters and as an “indicator of moral values.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="17"> Noske, “Sound and Sentiment,” 166–68;
                    Archambault, “The Function of Sound,” para. 4; Jeremy Chow, “Mellifluent
                    Sexuality: Female Intimacy in Ann Radcliffe’s The Romance of the Forest,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Eighteenth-Century Fiction</hi> 30, no. 2 (2017): 194.</note>
                Yet this essay will suggest that sound, at least in <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian
                    Romance</hi>, connects characters only by cutting relations between them in ways
                that defy moral classification. Sound (including music, noise, and silence) had an
                important visual component in eighteenth-century English culture, especially for the
                construction of gender,<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="18"> Richard Leppert,
                        <hi rend="italic">The Sight of Sound: Music, Representation, and the History
                        of the Body</hi> (University of California Press, 1993), 63–90.</note> and
                yet existing criticism on Radcliffe has seldom considered sight and sound at once.
                Milbank finds sight and sound to be dichotomous in Radcliffe’s early fiction, with
                tyrants exercising a visual dominance and “virtuous characters . . . particularly
                influenced by sound.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="19"> Milbank, “Ways of
                    Seeing,” 94.</note> This essay challenges that dichotomy by showing vision to be
                an aspect of sound in <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi>, and tracing the
                psychic consequences of that sensory entanglement. As <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian
                    Romance</hi> crosses and co-implicates vision and sound, pinning each as an
                impossible point within the other field, the relatively tidy taxonomies established
                by Milbank, Noske, and Archambault tend to break down. I am interested in exploring
                these points of intersection without intersection. </p>
            <p>1. The Sound of the Gaze Beyond Panopticism</p>
            <p>“Enchanting sounds!,” Hippolitus says, when he is told by Ferdinand that Julia
                secretly loves him: “I could listen till I forgot I had a wish beyond them.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="20"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>,
                    50–51.</note> Sounds, in this formulation, serve to obliterate one’s desire,
                even while one’s ability to listen is understood to be an effect of that desire.
                This arrangement may seem to facilitate an Oedipal plot, for which one would have to
                learn to forget one’s own wishes. Yet the visual structure of supervision in this
                scene expands that paradigm by constructing a whole series of triangulated relations
                around the “enchanting sounds” to give them multiple and competing points of
                reference. Hippolitus asks Ferdinand for some proof of Julia’s love, leading
                Ferdinand to report that he “saw her ineffectual struggles to conceal” her
                    feelings.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="21"> Radcliffe, 51.</note> In this
                model, the “enchanting sounds” of Ferdinand’s report are guaranteed by Julia’s
                feelings, which, although they cannot themselves be seen, become apparent in the
                attempt to camouflage what is already invisible. Julia has gone into hiding,
                Ferdinand says, not wanting to be seen in such a lovelorn state. She is invisible
                but audible: “I have often heard her singing in some lonely spot,” Ferdinand says to
                Hippolitus, noting that “your return produced a visible and instantaneous
                alteration” in her voice.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="22"> Radcliffe,
                    51.</note> In sum, Ferdinand reports having watched Julia not being seen by
                hearing her singing, which has made a spectacle of her invisible feelings. Although
                she is hidden from view—even he does not seem to know where she is, as to him it is
                merely “some lonely spot” or another—he could plainly see the change in her song
                once Hippolitus returned.</p>
            <p>This explanation raises a series of questions that are important throughout the
                novel: how is it possible to locate something “visible” in a voice emanating from a
                hidden place? And in what sense would the voyeur’s report of that discovery
                constitute a “sound,” per se, rather than mere information? It is as if the
                jouissance of Julia’s attachment to Hippolitus, something in excess of any possible
                sexual relationship between them, crosses narrative levels. It first conveys itself
                into a song about her love, which renders the love visible to auditors. It next
                becomes the excessive part of Ferdinand’s report of that song. The excess jouissance
                then gets transmitted back to Hippolitus, its original inspiration, in what he takes
                for simply “sounds.” Finally, it gets subsumed within the novel’s narrativizing
                structures, through which it gets ultimately and indirectly reported to the frame
                narrator and reader. It is as if anything attached to Julia’s desire overspills the
                capacity in language for communication, such that even reports of her desire
                necessarily carry with them this excessive quality, turning information into sound.
                Throughout the novel, Julia tends to convert incidental sounds (such as the rowing
                of oars in the water nearby the castle) into songs (or what she calls “hymns”), so
                as to produce “holy enthusiasm” and a stolen “sigh of exstacy.”<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="23"> Radcliffe, 58.</note> This is perhaps part of her general
                tendency—also a tendency of Radcliffe’s—to “transform the utilitarian into the
                    aesthetic.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="24"> Adam Miller, “Ann
                    Radcliffe’s Scientific Romance,” <hi rend="italic">Eighteenth-Century
                        Fiction</hi> 28, no. 3 (April 1, 2016): 535, https://doi.org/10.31
                    38/ecf.28.3.527.</note> The central question for the other characters then
                becomes: how can one look at this play of sound? Which is also to ask: how can we
                see someone hide from view, except insofar as they do so “ineffectually,” and thus
                    <hi rend="italic">not </hi>hide from view? Ferdinand’s method is to watch by
                listening.</p>
            <p>Ferdinand’s report of sonic voyeurism folds back on itself because, all the while,
                Julia is eavesdropping from a closet near the gallery, that quintessential parlor of
                Romantic visuality. She crouches there, where she cannot be seen, because she is
                afraid of being overheard: “She hardly dared to breathe, much less to move, . . .
                lest the sound of her step should betray her.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end"
                    n="25"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>, 50.</note> Fearful of being
                seen, she “moved softly,” but “the sound of her step alarmed the count.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="26"> Radcliffe, 51.</note> Hearing the gentle
                footsteps, Hippolitus bursts into the closet to discover her; mortified, she “hid
                her face in her robe.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="27"> Radcliffe,
                    51.</note> Ostrich-like, Julia signals her refusal to gaze rather than be seen:
                she is content to be looked at but not, any longer, to inhabit a hidden point of
                auditory oversight. Hippolitus responds with “expressive silence,” an oxymoronic
                state that suffices until he can “recover[ ] … his voice.”<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="28"> Radcliffe, 51.</note> Throughout this complicated and
                multi-layered tableau, sight cannot be disentangled from sound, and nor is either,
                as Milbank holds, particularly the domain of patriarchal tyrants.<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="29"> Milbank, “Ways of Seeing,” 89.</note></p>
            <p>Julia, like her brother, is hiding so as not to be heard and is ashamed when her
                footsteps are seen. To borrow from Slavoj Žižek, we might say that:</p>
            <p>voice does not simply persist at a different level with regard to what we see, it
                rather points toward a gap in the field of the visible, toward the dimension of what
                eludes our gaze. In other words, their relationship is mediated by an impossibility:
                    <hi rend="italic">ultimately, we hear things because we cannot see
                    everything</hi>.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="30"> Žižek, “I Hear You,”
                    93.</note></p>
            <p>Voice, with its capacity to present the disquieting excess found in lack, thus
                becomes a marker of the impossible. These effects, most importantly, continue to
                cross levels of narration: Julia is twice hidden from view here, first in “some
                lonely spot” and then in the gallery, where she overhears the tale of her own
                hiddenness; her body, hidden from tales of its own hiddenness, seems to emit sounds,
                constantly at both levels, which render her visible. Here, as in Yael Shapira’s
                analysis of <hi rend="italic">The Italian</hi>, “the ideology of the polite body and
                the challenges it presents to women are woven into the very fabric of [Radcliffe’s]
                    writing.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="31"> Yael Shapira, “Where the
                    Bodies Are Hidden: Ann Radcliffe’s ‘Delicate’ Gothic,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Eighteenth Century Fiction</hi> 18, no. 4 (September 28, 2006): 454,
                    https://doi.org/10.1353/ecf.2006.0068.</note> There is something in these
                sounds, occurring simultaneously across the two levels of narration, that speaks to
                Julia’s presence and yet seems far in excess of her status as a subject. The
                mysterious capacities of sound, always disclosing more than Julia intends,
                repeatedly interfere with her ability to remain hidden. Yet, it is Julia’s
                continuing visibility, as she buries herself in her cloak in response to being
                unhidden, that silences the man who has seen her.</p>
            <p>Such synesthetic situations characterize the first half of the novel. Julia, for
                instance, spends a lot of time looking for sound, as when “their steps ran in
                whispering echoes through the gallery, and often did Julia cast a fearful glance
                    around.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="32"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sicilian</hi>, 40.</note> When Ferdinand sees stairs, he oddly listens to
                them: “whence rose a winding stair-case, which led up to the south tower of the
                castle. Ferdinand paused to listen.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="33">
                    Radcliffe, 40.</note> Ferdinand, shortly after, finds that sound and vision work
                at cross-purposes but simultaneously:<hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>“A faint sound
                died away along the passage, the windings of which prevented his seeing the figure
                he pursued.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="34"> Radcliffe, 45.</note> The
                prepositional phrase “of which” retains a certain ambiguity here, as its syntax
                could pertain equally to the passage or the sound; because of this ambiguity, the
                passage inadvertently suggests that the windings of a sound are preventing Ferdinand
                from seeing. Yet, although we are told that the sound “died away” as the sightline
                vanishes, these are not presented as parallel effects—it’s not, for instance, <hi
                    rend="italic">the shape of the passage blocked both the sightline and
                sound</hi>—but as independent experiences each ending in sensory failure. When sight
                and sound are presented in parallel, the link between them is defined (as in the
                previous passage) by lack, absence, and exceptionality: “<hi rend="italic">Nothing
                    met the eye</hi> but beauty and romantic splendor;<hi rend="italic"> the ear
                    received no sounds</hi> but those of mirth and melody,” the narrator says of a
                Mazzini family festival, as if an overabundance of joyful sounds and sights would
                best be represented through figures of lack failing.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="35"> Radcliffe, 18.</note> Even when sight and sound are
                presented in parallel, and kept separate by, for instance, a semicolon, the subjects
                of these clauses—i.e., “nothing” and “the ear”—are unexpectedly not parallel. It is
                as if the ear is the equivalent instrument to the nothing that meets the eye. Is
                this not also what Hippolitus discovers in the gallery closet? These are the
                “strange contingenc[ies]” of lack in sound that characterize the gaze throughout
                Radcliffe’s second novel.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="36"> Jacques Lacan,
                        <hi rend="italic">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book XI: The Four
                        Fundamental Concepts of Psychoanalysis</hi>, ed. Jacques-Alain Miller,
                    trans. Alan Sheridan (New York: Norton, 1978), 72.</note></p>
            <p>This “nothing” discovered at the juncture of sight and sound radically complicates
                any attempt to theorize the novel’s visual field. I am thinking especially of Michel
                Foucault’s commentary on Radcliffe, which remains influential within studies of the
                Gothic. Foucault characterizes the latter half of the eighteenth century as a
                campaign against dark spaces; “the new political and moral order could not be
                established until those places were eradicated.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end"
                    n="37"> Michel Foucault, Jean-Pierre Barou, and Michelle Perrot, “The Eye of
                    Power,” in <hi rend="italic">Power/Knowledge: Selected Interviews and Other
                        Writings, 1972–1977</hi>, ed. and trans. Colin Gordon (New York: Pantheon
                    Books, 1980), 153.</note> To illustrate this thesis, Foucault suggests that “the
                landscapes of Ann Radcliffe’s novels are composed of . . . imaginary spaces [that]
                are like the negative of the transparency and visibility which it is aimed to
                    establish.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="38"> Foucault, Barou, and
                    Perrot, 154.</note> Radcliffe’s world, Foucault asserts, is one ruled by
                “opinion,” in which, for things to operate justly and efficiently, secrets must be
                laid bare and people thoroughly seen. It is a world organized by “an inspecting
                gaze” in search of “exact legibility,” in which everything seeks to be controlled by
                a pervasive ideological machine.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="39"> Foucault,
                    Barou, and Perrot, 154–57.</note> This thesis has influenced Foucauldian studies
                of Radcliffe’s fiction<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="40"> Cannon Schmitt,
                    “Techniques of Terror, Technologies of Nationality: Ann Radcliffe’s <hi
                        rend="italic">The Italian</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">ELH</hi> 61, no. 4
                    (1994): 863–67; George E. Haggerty, <hi rend="italic">Queer Gothic</hi> (Urbana:
                    University of Illinois Press, 2006), 30–36.</note> and also invited a measure of
                criticism by scholars of the Gothic.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="41">
                    Patrick R. O’Malley, <hi rend="italic">Catholicism, Sexual Deviance, and
                        Victorian Gothic Culture</hi> (Cambridge University Press, 2006), 214;
                    Shapira, “Where the Bodies Are Hidden,” 460 n.23.</note> Dale Townshend
                considers <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi> to be the quintessential
                illustration of Foucault’s claim, given what Townshend sees as the novel’s powerful
                investment in light and concerted attempts to make everything visible.<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="42"> Dale Townshend, <hi rend="italic">The Orders
                        of Gothic: Foucault, Lacan, and the Subject of Gothic Writing,
                        1764-1820</hi> (New York: AMS Press, 2007), 260.</note> For Townshend, <hi
                    rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi> depicts a crisis in “alliance” as a system
                of paternal authority, a point echoed elsewhere by Foley.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="43"> Townshend, 103–4; Foley, “Tyranny,” 150.</note></p>
            <p> The novel does explore the relationship between panopticism and authority, for
                instance when the evil Marquis tries to assure his retinue that the tower is “not
                haunted” by swearing that “you shall see the whole of these buildings,” or when it
                insists that Julia and Emilia “had never passed the boundaries of their father’s
                    domains.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="44"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sicilian</hi>, 79, 6.</note> Radcliffe sometimes plays with multiple and
                divergent meanings of Foucauldian words like “observe,” as in the sentence: “She
                observed that the marchioness pursued her with steady and constant
                    observation.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="45"> Radcliffe, 45.</note>
                Yet, as David Collings rightly notes, “the Gothic makes possible a direct refutation
                of disciplinary strategy in a way it cannot anticipate.”<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="46"> David Collings, <hi rend="italic">Monstrous Society:
                        Reciprocity, Discipline, and the Political Uncanny, c. 1780–1848</hi>
                    (Lewisburg: Bucknell University Press, 2009), 16.</note> In a crucial
                metafictional passage, Madame de Menon advises Julia and her sister Emilia that we
                believe in ghosts because we believe in God—which means that if ghosts do sometimes
                appear, it’s because God has authorized it: “be assured that there are no beings who
                act unseen by him.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="47"> Radcliffe, <hi
                        rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>, 36.</note> This would seem to be a
                quintessential example of Radcliffe’s enthusiasm for panoptic regimes. Yet the
                narrator—another form of all-seeing entity—immediately offers that “no further
                sounds disturbed them for that time.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="48">
                    Radcliffe, 36.</note> The implication is that God sees everything because we
                hear nothing. But Ferdinand reverses that logic in the next paragraph, when he
                suggests that the absence of sound must mean that we cannot be seen! “He very
                readily consented to watch with his sisters in Julia’s apartment; . . . there would
                be some difficulty in passing unobserved to her’s [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>]. It
                was agreed, however, that when all was hushed, he should make the attempt.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="49"> Radcliffe, 37.</note> One can enjoy
                invisibly, it seems, when it is quiet. So the troupe commits to the task of watching
                for sounds: “The greater part of several succeeding nights were spent in watching,
                but no sounds disturbed their silence.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="50">
                    Radcliffe, 37.</note></p>
            <p>In a similar vein, the novel opens with our frame narrator seeing voices, a device
                which quickly gets embedded into the general fiction through which the story of <hi
                    rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance </hi>is told. In the narrative frame, the ruins
                of the castle are specifically something “to be seen.”<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="51"> Radcliffe, 1.</note> Yet the frame narrator insists that he
                or she hears it: they fantasize about bygone times</p>
            <p><hi rend="color(#000000) background-color(#ffffff)">when the halls . . . resounded
                    with the voices of those whom death had long since swept from the earth. ‘Thus,’
                    said I, ‘shall the present generation—he who now sinks in misery—and he who now
                    swims in pleasure, alike pass away and be forgotten.’ My heart swelled with the
                    reflection; and, as I turned from the scene with a sigh, I fixed my eyes upon a
                    friar, whose venerable figure, gently bending towards the earth, formed no
                    uninteresting object in the picture.</hi><hi
                    rend="color(#000000) background-color(#ffffff)"><note xml:id="ftn120"
                        place="end" n="52"> Radcliffe, 1.</note></hi></p>
            <p>This is an intensely ironic passage, and not only because the narrator describes
                imagined “voices” as a “picture” capable of “reflection.” The frame narrator,
                hearing a visual spectacle, concludes that previous generations will be forgotten,
                despite seeming to hear “voices” that would testify to exactly the opposite. In
                another twist, the voices are not “real” but a mental extrapolation from the visual
                scene. The entire story to follow would lead someone to precisely the opposite
                conclusion: the previous generation may be repressed, but only incompletely; one’s
                ancestors remain very much present and audible, even if out of view for a long time.
                Immediately the frame narrator gets caught between written and oral histories, as
                the friar tries to convince the frame narrator that further information is to be
                acquired in a manuscript “of which I could, perhaps, procure you a sight.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="53"> Radcliffe, 1.</note> Yet the friar
                introduces the frame narrator to his boss, the abate, who for unknown reasons
                recounts the history of the castle to our frame narrator orally. From there, it gets
                assembled into “abstracts” for the reader’s view, which give body to the “voices”
                that had been initially imagined.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="54">
                    Radcliffe, 2.</note> The unstable movement back and forth between print media,
                oral storytelling, history, and fantasy is something that Garrett Stewart has called
                the “phonemanography of response to the silent babel of text,” according to which
                “voice is no sooner subsumed to the formal genres of print poetics than it
                resurfaces there.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="55"> Garrett Stewart,
                    “Phonemanography: Romantic to Victorian,” in <hi rend="italic">“Soundings of
                        Things Done”: The Poetry and Poetics of Sound in the Romantic Ear and
                        Era</hi>, ed. Susan J. Wolfson, Romantic Circles Praxis Series (Romantic
                    Circles, 2008), para. 69,
                    https://romantic-circles.org/praxis/soundings/stewart/stewart.html.</note> The
                narrative structure of <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi>, then, demands that
                voice is implicit as an active agent within any visual or textual experience of
                history.</p>
            <p> Although, throughout the novel and its narrative structure, voice refuses to be
                subsumed into visual ways of knowing and, by extension, print media, a moment in the
                main narrative turns this structure on its head. In a reversal of what will befall
                the frame narrator, Julia and Madame de Menon find that they are seen as they look
                upon the same ruined castle, and find themselves explaining their history to the
                abate’s predecessor. They, too, find that voices—this time of Julia’s father’s
                spies—interfere with their visual experience of the space: “As Julia gave a last
                look to the scene, she perceived two men leaning upon a part of the ruin at some
                distance, in earnest conversation. As they spoke, their looks were so attentively
                bent on her.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="56"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sicilian</hi>, 126.</note> She watches the people who are watching her look
                at the scene. Yet how does one “look” at a conversation, especially one in which she
                finds herself the object of the discussants’ own looks? This is what Nina Sun
                Eidsheim would call a “sonic reduction”: that is, the use of figural language to
                place a sound, in all of its unlimited multidimensionality, within a meaningful
                    register.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="57"> Nina Sun Eidsheim, <hi
                        rend="italic">Sensing Sound: Singing and Listening as Vibrational
                        Practice</hi> (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015), 2.</note> Sound,
                Eidsheim argues, bears haptic, tactile dimensions, and even visual and olfactory
                ones, so our tendency to treat it only auditorily amounts to a sustained, collective
                act of figuration. Radcliffe, though, is experimenting here with a different sort of
                sonic reduction, one that uses visual tropes to report on sound, and works through
                negation and interruption: rightly fearful, the two women “walked swiftly through
                the woods, … [and] were surprized to observe the distance to which they had strayed
                from the monastery, whose dark towers were now obscurely seen rising among the trees
                that closed the perspective.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="58"> Radcliffe,
                        <hi rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>, 126.</note> Seeing towers that, we are
                assured, could not be seen from their vantage, they “observed” their <hi
                    rend="italic">distance</hi> from the towers rather than the towers directly. Yet
                they report having seen, however “obscurely,” something that was “closed” from their
                perspective. They see the men pursuing them but conclude, strangely, that it does
                not look like a pursuit: “On looking back, they perceived the same men slowly
                advancing, without any appearance of pursuit, but clearly as if observing the place
                of their retreat.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="59"> Radcliffe, 126.</note>
                Once again, Julia is looked at from within a space that cannot be seen and is caught
                looking at other people’s voices. Lack becomes the extimate point that governs the
                visual scene as it gets, here and there, converted into sonic reduction.</p>
            <p>2. The Sound of the Gaze Beyond Sartre’s Keyhole</p>
            <p>Excerpts like these lead us to reexamine Foucault’s panopticon thesis. Certainly, as
                Foucault suggests, this is a novel filled with secret passageways and dark forests
                that could be improved through better lighting. But the anchor of the visual
                field—indeed, across the novel, a substantial number of different visual
                fields—seems to be a spot that cannot be synthesized into it, from which Julia,
                Ferdinand, or the frame narrator can gaze. They frequently see things that are
                specifically closed to her view—not by opening new avenues for sight, but precisely
                by remaining in the place where visibility fails. Voice and sound seem to be the
                mechanisms by which this impossible point can be sutured within the visual field—it
                is as if the entire visual field is constructed around the excessive lack in the
                object voice. Because of this, we will need to seek a theoretical model better
                equipped to think about the holes in the scene that cannot be seen. Although the
                novel arguably displays a desire for total and full illumination and disclosure, it
                positions its viewers somewhere that cannot be synthesized into that panoptic
                fantasy. They can only “radically disidentify” with their environs and foster
                “uncommon, illiberal sensibilities” expressed through silence.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="60"> Chuh, <hi rend="italic">The Difference</hi>, xii.</note>
                Sound (including silence) is the cut in this visual field that, to everyone’s shame
                and horror, authorizes subjectivity only as “a rupture at the core of
                    self-presence.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="61"> Dolar, <hi
                        rend="italic">A Voice</hi>, 42.</note></p>
            <p>Thus, it is significant that the secret passageways of Castle Mazzini are
                investigated auditorily—which is far from saying that the experience is not visual.
                For instance:</p>
            <p><hi rend="color(#000000)">Ferdinand carefully sounded the wall which communicated
                    with the southern buildings. From one part of it a sound was returned, which
                    convinced him there was something less solid than stone. He removed </hi><hi
                    rend="color(#000000)">the tapestry, and behind it appeared, to his inexpressible
                    satisfaction, a small door.</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"><note xml:id="ftn120"
                        place="end" n="62"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>,
                    39.</note></hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="color(#000000)">This passage suggests a satisfying reciprocity of sound:
                    one discovers the secrets of Castle Mazzini by hearing one’s own sound
                    “returned” by the castle itself: it is as if Ferdinand’s desire is the desire of
                    the Other, and so only through the “returned” sound can Ferdinand recognize
                    himself and feel “satisfaction.”</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"><note
                        xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="63"> Lacan, <hi rend="italic">Seminar
                        XI</hi>, 235.</note></hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"> Hence “sounding” is both
                    the name of Ferdinand’s action and the object of that action. Lifting the
                    tapestry, he confirms by sight the thing that he has heard. His satisfaction in
                    the discovery, though, remains “inexpressible”: it is the part that cannot be
                    articulated or mapped even at the point of the door’s discovery. What had seemed
                    to be a satisfyingly reciprocal call from the other side soon becomes excessive
                    and autonomous: as Ferdinand “stood gazing on the door, and inwardly lamenting,
                    . . . a low hollow sound was heard from beneath. Emilia and Julia seized his
                    arm; and almost sinking with apprehension, listened in profound silence. A
                    footstep was distinctly heard.”</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"><note
                        xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="64"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sicilian</hi>, 39.</note></hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"> Here again,
                    Ferdinand finds himself looking at a sound, and “uncertain sounds of strange and
                    fearful import” to boot.</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"><note xml:id="ftn120"
                        place="end" n="65"> Radcliffe, 46.</note></hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"> The
                    sounds are a figure of lack (associated with something “hollow” situated
                    “beneath,” and promoting silence); yet it is the lack of that lack that causes
                    the most anxiety of all: “though the night passed without further disturbance,
                    their fears were very little abated.”</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"><note
                        xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="66"> Radcliffe, 39.</note></hi><hi
                    rend="color(#000000)"> Ferdinand begins to fear the sound of his own footsteps,
                    as if the haunting supernatural sound were actually a figure for the mysterious
                    invisible excess in the investigating </hi><hi rend="color(#000000)">party.
                    Coleridge would be amazed at the sublime indeterminacy in sound, but Radcliffe
                    finds that even concrete sounds point to an excessive, inassimilable lack in the
                    auditor. Julia and Emilia endure Ferdinand’s efforts to open the secret door “in
                    fearful silence, but no sound disturbed the stillness of night”; they bravely
                    “followed in silence” once the door is pried open, presenting this new silence
                    as the interruption of the previous silence, which had been caused by a dread of
                    more silence.</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"><note xml:id="ftn120" place="end"
                        n="67"> Radcliffe, 40.</note></hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"> Silence is a
                    condition of the house and is not in any way separate from or opposite to
                    groans, which are characterized repeatedly by their hollowness.</hi></p>
            <p>Ed Pluth and Cindy Zeiher have called attention to Lacan’s early theorization of
                silences that are “not empty.” They point us toward Lacan’s little-known commentary
                on the 1929 murders committed by Christine and Lea Papin, commentary which came
                three years prior to his first iteration of the mirror stage. Pluth and Zeiher adopt
                this early Lacan text as a way to think about imaginary relations through sound and
                silence, rather than, as we might normally expect from Lacan, through sight and
                    mirroring.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="68"> Ed Pluth and Cindy Zeiher,
                        <hi rend="italic">On Silence: Holding the Voice Hostage</hi>, The Palgrave
                    Lacan Series (Cham, Switzerland: Palgrave Macmillan, 2019), 26–28.</note> The
                Papin sisters’ silence following their crime was, Pluth and Zeiher suggest, neither
                “meaningful” nor, as Lacan stresses, “empty”; rather, their violent act—killing
                their employers by gauging out their eyes before bludgeoning and stabbing them to
                death, and then retiring to bed together—was a way of interrupting a structural,
                enforced silence that had pervaded their workplace, the victims’ home. As Pluth and
                Zeiher indicate, this spectacular violence was an act of self-punishment at the
                level of the imaginary, as the sisters, being their victims’ domestic maids, had
                come to feel like doubles of their employers within the house. By gauging out their
                employers’ eyes and then remaining silent in court and to the press, the Papin
                sisters attacked the very mechanism through which the identification had happened,
                offering their own silence as a cut in what had been a visual circuit.<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="69"> Pluth and Zeiher, 27–28.</note><hi
                    rend="color(#000000)"> Radcliffe’s silences, I will suggest, are similarly “not
                    empty,” and constitute attempts to sever manifold structural crises fundamental
                    to the patriarchy.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="color(#000000)">As with the case of the Papin sisters, narrative meaning in
                    </hi><hi rend="color(#000000)italic">A Sicilian Romance </hi><hi
                    rend="color(#000000)">is cut by interruptions (both of silence and of sound)
                    that, though mysterious, are not empty, and that indicate the oppressive
                    patriarchal structure governing Castle Mazzini. </hi>Madame de Menon, for
                instance, in first telling Julia about her mother, fuses surveillance and sound in
                telling Julia that Louisa “would steal to her harpsichord” “when she thought herself
                    unobserved.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="70"> Radcliffe, <hi
                        rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>, 30.</note> Yet her tale of maternal
                musicianship is “interrupted” by “the horn … [that] sounded the signal for dinner”—a
                semi-musical sound that interrupts, as with a Lacanian short session, a tale of
                amateur musicianship.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="71"> Radcliffe, 31.</note>
                We have, then, a tale of sound interrupting the silence that was interrupted by
                another sound. What interests me is that there is no formal reason for the novel to
                include this horn; it doesn’t delay the exposition by any more than four sentences.
                Madame and Julia simply have dinner and then go right back to the story within in
                the same paragraph, like nothing had happened. The reader is left with a bizarre
                narrative interruption, bizarre because it doesn’t actually interrupt anything. The
                interruption, rather, is registered at the level of narrative but felt at the level
                of the story, as the sound makes conspicuous its own construction <hi rend="italic"
                    >après coup</hi>. The narrator’s emphasis in telling us the story of Julia being
                told a story is on Julia’s hearing<hi rend="italic"> </hi>of it, not the content, as
                if the story of the mother were itself an aural interruption into Julia’s own
                routine of playing the lute.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="72"> Radcliffe,
                    34.</note> That is, one’s mother’s harpsichord “interrupts” her own routine of
                musicianship: Julia is not like Louisa in the sense that both play musical
                instruments in defiance of patriarchal supervision, but rather they are linked by
                the way that this bond actually severs that relation. We have found, here, a way to
                traverse “the strange loop, the tie between inner and outer, the short circuit
                between the external contingency and the intimate, the curious match of the click
                [or in this case, musical sound, which has become a hollow knock] and the inner
                sexual arousal.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="73"> Dolar, <hi rend="italic">A
                        Voice</hi>, 132.</note> The situation thus finds a new iteration immediately
                to follow, when “<hi rend="color(#000000)">madame, who was then speaking, was
                    interrupted by a low hollow sound, which arose from beneath the apartment, and
                    seemed like the closing of a door.”</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"><note
                        xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="74"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sicilian</hi>, 35.</note></hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"> The story is
                    now interrupted, not by the horns of official castle timekeeping, but by the
                    subject of the story itself, as if the story’s content had managed to interrupt
                    its own narration, to ask for help in being discovered. The novel’s main plot is
                    thus made possible by the interruption of its backstory</hi>.<hi
                    rend="color(#000000)"> Only through this interruption can Julia be reunited with
                    her mother, whose voice, Dolar reminds us, </hi>is often “the first problematic
                connection to the other, the immaterial tie that comes to replace the umbilical
                    cord.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="75"> Dolar, <hi rend="italic">A
                        Voice</hi>, 39.</note> That voice is actually quite like a narrative
                umbilical cord, in the sense that Julia only gains a mother once the story of that
                motherhood is cut.</p>
            <p><hi rend="color(#000000)">These sounds are disruptive in their absence as much as in
                    their presence. Radcliffe, writes Anna Shajirat, chronicles the
                </hi>“irrevocable disruption” stemming from the “mundane realities” of
                eighteenth-century women’s lives, and thereby theorizes “the trauma of the ordinary
                for women.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="76"> Anna Shajirat, “‘Bending Her
                    Gentle Head to Swift Decay’: Horror, Loss, and Fantasy in the Female Gothic of
                    Ann Radcliffe and Regina Maria Roche,” <hi rend="italic">Studies in
                        Romanticism</hi> 58, no. 3 (2019): 383, 385,
                    https://doi.org/10.1353/srm.2019.0023.</note> This is why her novels are
                organized around the “double horror” of “an unimaginable void at the center of a
                void,” according to which the patriarchal legal frameworks and unchecked domestic
                violence prove, in the end, more horrifying than any ghost.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="77"> Shajirat, 385–87.</note> If read in this way, Castle
                Mazzini, for all of its musical performances and unaccountable footsteps, seems
                largely defined by the absence of sound: “a melancholy stillness reigned through the
                halls, and the silence of the courts . . . was for many hours together
                    undisturbed.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="78"> Radcliffe, <hi
                        rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>, 5.</note> Silence reigns at Castle Mazzini
                because the silence is structural rather than incidental; the silence is then
                interrupted by tales of silence, which are interrupted by further routinized
                silences. This is perhaps why, as Madame de Manon implies, the ghosts are an effect
                of silence and an aspect of the master’s gaze, and why the Real becomes, as Lacan
                warns, in Julia “to a very great degree the accomplice of the drive.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="79"> Lacan, <hi rend="italic">Seminar XI</hi>,
                    69.</note></p>
            <p> In<hi rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi>, the “void at the center of a void” is
                the gaze itself. Here, I am prone to consider the gaze in a Lacanian way, and thus
                contribute to a recent revival of Lacanian interest in Radcliffe.<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="80"> Townshend, <hi rend="italic">The
                    Orders</hi>; Andrew Warren, “Designing and Undrawing Veils: Anxiety and
                    Authorship in Radcliffe’s <hi rend="italic">The Italian</hi>,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Eighteenth Century</hi> 54, no. 4 (November 21, 2013): 521–44,
                    https://doi.org/10.1353/ecy.2013.0039; Foley, “Tyranny”; Shajirat,
                    “Bending.”</note> In this, I hope also to build on Volker Langbehn’s work, which
                was an “attempt to trace the philosophical precursors of Lacan’s theory of the gaze”
                in the Romantic period, all while heeding the warning that “Lacan’s theory of the
                gaze suffers under a certain degree of compartmentalization and manipulation” when
                adapted for literary analysis.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="81"> Langbehn,
                    “The Lacanian Gaze,” 613.</note> Very much unlike Foucault, Lacan rigorously
                distinguishes between the look and the gaze: one looks at things, but is beheld by
                the gaze, and the relation between these levels is vastly asymmetrical. The gaze
                happens, for instance, when Ferdinand and Julia, hiding in a cave worthy of Plato,
                detect shadows disappearing behind a rock: they feel themselves being seen from a
                point that they cannot see.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="82"> Radcliffe, <hi
                        rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>, 150.</note> The gaze, in Lacan’s analysis, is
                not, then, merely the depersonalized exercise of supervisory power; it is a
                traumatic point in a visual field that cannot be incorporated or claimed but that
                cuts open the subject. Lacan developed his theory of the gaze as a rejoinder to
                Jean-Paul Sartre, who had discussed the gaze in <hi rend="italic">Being and
                    Nothingness</hi>. Explains Lacan:</p>
            <p>If you turn to Sartre’s own text, you will see that, far from speaking of the
                emergence of this gaze as of something that concerns the organ of sight, he refers
                to the sound of rustling leaves, suddenly heard while out hunting, to a footstep
                heard in a corridor. And when are these sounds heard? At the moment when he has
                presented himself in the action of looking through a keyhole. A gaze surprises him
                in the function of voyeur, disturbs him, overwhelms him and reduces him to a feeling
                of shame. The gaze in question is certainly the presence of others as such. But does
                this mean that originally it is in the relation of subject to subject, in the
                function of the existence of others as looking at me, that we apprehend what the
                gaze really is?<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="83"> Lacan, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Seminar XI</hi>, 84.</note></p>
            <p>The rhetorical question that Lacan finally poses, with its implied answer of an
                ambiguous “no,” has clear implications for <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian
                Romance</hi>. We have seen how, for Ferdinand, silence guarantees a certain
                invisibility, and how, further, a sound is “satisfying” to the extent that one’s
                “soundings” are returned proportionately by the Other. We have also seen that, for
                Louisa in the narrative of Madame de Menon, sound provides a cut in the structural
                conditions of Castle Mazzini. In each case, the gaze sustains desire; it is not a
                map of the symbolic space that the Marquis gets to monitor. Part of the operation of
                that gaze is how Julia’s desire gains its form through a sonic interruption, rather
                than being contained by her father’s supervisory apparatuses. The relation at work
                is not, as Lacan hints, “subject to subject,” but rather in the asymmetrical
                experience of finding oneself in the invisible hiding place of the Other, seeing
                oneself being seen from that impossible vantage.</p>
            <p> As Lacan suggests, Sartre’s “own text” is indeed very interesting in this regard,
                for the insistent way that it crosses the registers of sound with sight. Sartre’s
                first test case for the gaze focuses on the voice, when: “this voice which I hear is
                that of a man and not a song on a phonograph.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end"
                    n="84"> Jean-Paul Sartre, <hi rend="italic">Being and Nothingness: An Essay on
                        Phenomenological Ontology</hi>, trans. Hazel E. Barnes (London: Meuthen,
                    1957), 253.</note> He then stresses the asymmetrical nature of being subjected
                to another’s look, noting how “I,” with my enduring subjectivity, cannot so easily
                become a pure object like, say, the grass, because, as he explains, “‘Being
                seen-by-the-Other’ is the truth of ‘seeing-the-Other’” <note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="85"> Sartre, 257.</note>. Yet passersby, he argues, are
                thoroughly objects for “me.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="86"> Sartre,
                    252–53.</note> Faced with this incongruity, he proposes the thought experiment
                that would catch Lacan’s interest: “Let us imagine that moved by jealousy,
                curiosity, or vice I have just glued my ear to the door and looked through a
                    keyhole.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="87"> Sartre, 259.</note> It is
                important for our purposes to note that Sartre, here, presents voyeurism as
                something anatomically impossible: how can someone look through a keyhole with their
                ear to the door? Behind that door, argues Sartre—and I picture a small door hidden
                behind a tapestry, as in <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi>—“a spectacle is
                presented as ‘to be seen,’ a conversation as ‘to be heard’”; it is “a sight” and “a
                spectacle” given meaning by my jealousy.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="88">
                    Sartre, 259.</note> Sartre is very clear that eavesdropping is an aspect of the
                gaze. He imagines the scene, then, interrupted: “But all of a sudden I hear
                footsteps in the hall. Someone is looking at me! What does this mean?”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="89"> Sartre, 260.</note> In Sartre’s vignette,
                then, one hears oneself being looked at when one is looking and listening illicitly,
                and in the act of being thus interrupted one comes into being within a triangulated
                structure of relations mediated by the semi-permeable door. He begins to reckon with
                the shame of being seen at the keyhole.</p>
            <p>Lacan emphasizes, with regard to the passage in Sartre, that the gaze is exercised
                through sound rather than sight. The gaze is never one’s own activity, and it is not
                as simple as one’s being-looked-at; rather, it is specifically the sound of one’s
                being looked at. This is, I would say, a capable interpretation of the passage from
                Sartre—an element of Sartre’s text that is present but not adequately factored into
                his thinking. When sound becomes an element of one’s perverse enjoyment, attesting
                to “the presence of others as such,” one experiences the gaze—which is always, it
                seems, a humiliating ordeal. The gaze is the experience of hearing oneself being
                watched while we are watching and listening. Lacan’s point is that the desiring
                subject is created, even sustained, through such triangulation.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="90"> Lacan, <hi rend="italic">Seminar XI</hi>, 85.</note></p>
            <p> The knock resonating through Castle Mazzini is just such an event. It is a pure part
                object, causing anxiety given its proximity to the partial drive. It is effectively
                a voice (testifying to a human presence) but with no content—it actively<hi
                    rend="italic">says nothing</hi> rather than merely being unclear. Yet the knock
                is noteworthy, among the millions of small sounds that surely bombard Julia and
                Ferdinand every day, for seeming to carry a meaning: it seems to say something or at
                least request the opportunity to do so. Yet it also, like any voice, seems
                “strangely recalcitrant to” meaning; it is a “material element” of communication
                that “<hi rend="italic">does not contribute to making sense</hi>” (Dolar 15,
                emphasis in the original). The knock is an exemplary case of “a voice and nothing
                more,” as Dolar would say. It is</p>
            <p>the grain of an inexplicable noise, a mysterious sound, which can appear even with
                the tiniest click. At the origin of fantasy there is a traumatic kernel materialized
                by the voice, the noise—we should allow full latitude here to a sonority not
                pertaining to language.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="91"> Dolar, <hi
                        rend="italic">A Voice</hi>, 133.</note></p>
            <p>The knock, in its function as a part object that calls into being the point of the
                gaze, arrives from a place in the castle yet outside the castle, or even beyond the
                castle. It is in this sense that Julia, like Sartre’s voyeur, is being gazed at by a
                sound. It is repeated at intervals in the story, and the intervals come and go in
                intervals of their own: <hi rend="color(#000000)">“The sounds were repeated, at
                    intervals, for near an hour, when silence returned . . . [for] the rest of the
                    night.”</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"><note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="92">
                        Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>, 99.</note></hi> The so-called
                “explained Gothic” of Radcliffe’s formula is never really explained, because it
                depends upon “a spectral presence in the real,” which remains ever an “unknowable
                and uncontainable excess.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="93"> Shajirat,
                    “Bending,” 385.</note></p>
            <p>Much as Shajirat stresses with regard to <hi rend="italic">Udolpho</hi>, <hi
                    rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi> challenges our most familiar paradigms for
                understanding Gothic topoi. The plot would seem to epitomize both the “unspeakable”
                and “live burial” topoi, which Eve Kosofsky Sedgwick argues are foundational to the
                genre. Much as Sedgwick affirms, these topoi take on multiple resonances throughout
                the text, repeatedly connecting Julia to her mother through a set of structural
                    redundancies.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="94"> Eve Kosofsky Sedgwick,
                        <hi rend="italic">The Coherence of Gothic Conventions</hi> (New York:
                    Meuthen, 1986), 4–5.</note> Yet, in a stark departure from Sedgwick’s model, <hi
                    rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi> refuses to let “everything mean[]
                something else” in a display of its signifying processes.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="95"> Sedgwick, 53.</note> Rather, the knock presents obstacles to
                signification. Sound, across this novel, comically creates cases of mistaken
                identity: the fourth terrifying knock on the door is actually just Ferdinand; Julia
                loves the song “Sonnet” but doesn’t know who sang it; Ferdinand, having heard the
                sound through the hidden door, is afraid of his own footsteps.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="96"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>, 37, 25,
                    46.</note> If the knock solicits a connection between Julia and her mother, it
                is only through their shared refusal to find meaning in these object voices. Julia,
                after all, plays the lute in a manner “<hi rend="color(#000000)">which seem[s] to
                    breathe a soul through the sound, and which take[s] captive the heart of the
                    hearer.”</hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"><note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="97">
                        Radcliffe, 4–5.</note></hi><hi rend="color(#000000)"> Julia, in this
                    metaphor, becomes both her mother and her father, insofar as the lute, in her
                    hands, is both the agent of imprisonment and the barely-audible breath attesting
                    to a life imprisoned. It is as if the novel’s metaphorical proxies for its own
                    metaphors of imprisonment turn on themselves and become complicit in that
                    imprisonment. In effect, Radcliffe here achieves at the figural level the same
                    sort of twisted Moebius pattern that she had achieved at the narratological
                    level, just a few pages earlier, in the narrative frame. Yet it is a figure not
                    of connection but of a cut. Although Julia, Louisa, and probably Hippolitus each
                    play the lute, what they have in common is not some sort of shared musicianship
                    but the way that each relates, through the musical note, to the surplus
                    enjoyment causing them anxiety. What they have in common is how this signifier,
                    now barred from any signification, </hi>“compresses the enigma of the Other
                while being simultaneously the telltale sign of the excess in the subject.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="98"> Dolar, <hi rend="italic">A Voice</hi>,
                    135.</note> Instead of establishing a circuit of displaced meaning, as Sedgwick
                would have it, it moves only through the shared experience of interruption. Lack,
                treated as a positive property, is what the characters have in common.</p>
            <p>Dolar, analyzing one of Freud’s cases, notes that a small sound can be “a structural
                moment when something which upsets and interrupts the course of desire toward its
                fulfillment actually defines and drives the desire itself.”<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="99"> Dolar, 132.</note> The two generations discover themselves
                in the other through their mutual experience of interruption rather than alliance.
                Indeed, as Ruth Beinstock Anolik argues in a semi-Lacanian key, “the absence of the
                mother [is] a requirement for the narratable deviance necessary for narrative to
                    occur.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="100"> Ruth Beinstock Anolik, “The
                    Missing Mother: The Meanings of Maternal Absence in the Gothic Mode,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Modern Language Studies</hi> 33, no. 1–2 (2003): 28.</note> As
                we have seen, Louisa’s absence must be accounted for through frequent acts of inset
                narration as well, and these stories, too, must be interrupted if Julia is to find
                her way through the secret passages that sustain her as a desiring subject. She is,
                as Lacan would say, “pouring [herself], as it were, along the veins through which
                the domain of vision has been integrated into the field of desire,” that is,
                    acoustically.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="101"> Lacan, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Seminar XI</hi>, 85.</note>
            </p>
            <p>3. The Sound of the Gaze Beyond Signification</p>
            <p>Early in <hi rend="italic">The Interpretation of Dreams</hi>, Freud considers a
                problem encountered by his predecessor in dream-theorization, F. W. Hildebrandt.
                Hildebrandt had, in the late nineteenth century, analyzed three very different
                dreams of his own, each punctuated by a sharp sound which, it turns out, was really
                him registering the sound of his alarm clock and attempting to incorporate the
                interruption into the dream. Hildebrandt dreamed, in one case, of a church bell; in
                another, of the jingle of a horse’s sleigh-bell; and in a third, of a kitchen-maid
                loudly dropping a tall stack of dishes, in dread of the very same alarm clock. In
                each case, the dreaming Hildebrandt responded to the jarring alarm clock with an
                attempt to continue sleeping by incorporating the interruption into the narrative of
                his dream.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="102"> Sigmund Freud, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works of
                        Sigmund Freud</hi>, trans. James Strachey (London: Hogarth Press, 1964), 4:
                    27-28.</note> Freud asks: why would the mind make “the arbitrary decision” to
                assign the sound to something else, when it knows an alarm clock lies in wait? Would
                not the dreamer’s attempt to continue sleeping be more effective if he were to dream
                of an alarm clock directly? Freud compares the situation to seeing a cow in a
                distant field and convincing oneself, through the inadequacy of one’s vantage, that
                it is a horse.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="103"> Freud, 4:29.</note>
                Breaking with Hildebrandt, Freud urges us to go beyond objective stimuli to
                understand this phenomenon.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="104"> Freud,
                    4:30.</note> Despite the external stimulus causing the dream, he says, we should
                be “engaged in looking for sources of dreams inside the organism instead of outside
                    it.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="105"> Freud, 4:34.</note> I take from
                this that even symbols, such as alarm clocks, with relatively stable and confined
                meanings stop having stable meanings once they have been introjected. The cut is
                interior to the subject now, even while, as a fragment of the real, it remains
                something forever excluded. “Where am I in relation to my desire?” is a more
                relevant question in these cases than “what is that sound?”</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance </hi>is, by the standards of an
                eighteenth-century novel, unexpectedly replete with alarm clocks. Early in the
                novel, for instance, as Julia lies awake late at night reading, she “was roused from
                her forgetfulness, by the sound of the castle clock, which struck one.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="106"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>,
                    9.</note> The sound startles her because it comes so late: why, she wonders,
                would the clock chime at 1:00 at night? She is jarred by its failure to interpellate
                her, which she takes as a possible temporal misalignment between herself and her
                environs: not being asleep, she cannot recognize herself as the proper subject of
                its rousing chime, which is ironically why it rouses her into an important
                discovery. The sound leads her to the window, where she sees for the first time, in
                the form of an inexplicable light, the central mystery of the South tower. As she
                continues to watch, she finds herself “survey[ing] the scene” as it “echoed the
                sounds of gaiety and gladness” at the marchioness’s return.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="107"> Radcliffe, 15.</note> Seeing the sound rather than either
                hearing it or seeing a visual phenomenon is, in this passage, reassuring for Julia.
                But repetition will render its effects uncanny.</p>
            <p>The scenario recurs later in the novel, in a twist that will force the meaning of the
                bell inward, into Julia, rather than into any external signifying system. This time,
                inappropriately-timed sounds seem to beget further sounds, rather than sights, which
                Julia finds disquieting:</p>
            <p>Julia was awakened by the bell of the monastery. She knew it was not the hour
                customary for prayer, and she listened to the sounds, which rolled through the deep
                silence of the fabric, with strong surprise and terror. Presently she heard the
                doors of several cells creak on their hinges, and the sound of quick footsteps in
                the passages.<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="108"> Radcliffe, 135.</note></p>
            <p>Archambault, interpreting the castle <hi
                    rend="color(#000000) background-color(#ffffff)">“bells as instruments of
                    behavior control,” suggests that their ringing at the wrong time signals the
                    breakdown of social order.</hi><hi
                    rend="color(#000000) background-color(#ffffff)"><note xml:id="ftn120"
                        place="end" n="109"> Archambault, “The Function of Sound,” para.
                    37.</note></hi><hi rend="color(#000000) background-color(#ffffff)"> Yet the
                    bells frighten Julia even when they ring as scheduled:</hi></p>
            <p>The castle clock struck twelve. The sound seemed to shake the pile. Julia felt it
                thrill upon her heart. “I hear you,” sighed she, “for the last time.” The stillness
                of death succeeded. She continued to listen; but no sound met her ear.<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="110"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>,
                    66.</note></p>
            <p>This version of the “alarm clock” disturbs Julia because it seems to mark the
                subjective time of her lifespan rather than any objective, chrononormative time in
                the world, which is to say that she seems to have traversed another Moebius strip of
                sorts: whereas once she had feared that the clocks had slipped out of time, she now
                fears that <hi rend="italic">she herself </hi>is slipping out of their regulatory
                mechanisms. Its ring now produces a “thrill” for Julia, who is anxious about eloping
                with Hippolitus while “the silence of the place remained undisturbed.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="111"> Radcliffe, 67.</note> If, for Coleridge,
                sound is powerful because of its intrinsic ambiguity, for Radcliffe sound is
                powerful because it can interrupt a state of uncertainty, and anchor meaning through
                its very capacity for polysemy and repetition. Julia, who is on the verge of a
                perilous attempt to escape from her prison-like existence with her illicit lover,
                the attempt at which will, sadly, immediately cost him his life, comes to associate,
                even in advance, the object-voice with life and its cessation with death. It is as
                if she has internalized the sound of the clock and made it part of her own
                unconscious aspiration toward stillness. In this sense, she embodies Freud’s
                analysis of Hildebrandt’s alarm clock dreams: the important thing is no longer the
                external stimulus of the alarm clock—when will it ring, and how will Julia
                react?—but in her own introjection of its chime. As Žižek explains in another
                context: “Far more horrifying than to see with our ears—to hear the vibrating life
                substance beyond visual representations, this blind spot in the field of the
                visible—is to hear with our eyes, that is, to see the absolute silence that marks
                the suspension of life.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="112"> Žižek, “I Hear
                    You,” 94.</note> What Julia hears, having traversed her fantasy of failed
                interpellation, is the sound of her own jouissance returning to her as an object
                voice.</p>
            <p>Having traversed that loop across the first half of the novel, we can compare its
                structure to a passage in Chapter 2, in which Julia is roused by a lovely song being
                played outside her window. This is the night of the Mazzini family ball, after
                which, we are told, she “retired to her apartment, but not to sleep”; as she
                fantasizes about Hippolitus in a “state of entranced delight, she was awakened by
                the sound of music immediately under her window.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end"
                    n="113"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>, 23.</note> This is an
                interesting passage because Julia is awakened from a state of already being awake,
                much as the bell in the previous chapter had done. She supposes, because it is sung
                by “a voice of more than magic expression” accompanied by “a lute touched by a
                masterly hand,” that Hippolitus must be courting her. This musical evidence, despite
                her not knowing if Hippolitus can even sing or play the lute, “confirms” what had
                previously been her mere belief that “she was loved by Hippolitus.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="114"> Radcliffe, 24.</note> The eight-line song
                rhyming <hi rend="italic">abab cdcd</hi>, she somehow knows, is titled “Sonnet,”
                despite her being Italian and its not being a sonnet. She takes it as a sign of
                love, despite the elegiac energies implied by the stanza form. One wonders: where
                and why did it get this title? Did Hippolitus announce the title before playing it,
                or did Julia, with apparently limited knowledge of verse forms, conclude that the
                title was appropriate? Or is it the work of the frame narrator working from oral
                “abstracts”? Would a late-sixteenth-century Italian like Julia recognize this rhyme
                scheme as the beginning of an English sonnet, even without the final six lines? The
                song itself, in a cruel irony, proposes that “not a lonely sound / Steals through
                the silence of this dreary hour.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="115">
                    Radcliffe, 23.</note> Neither Julia nor the narrator seems to note that she has
                been “awakened” from “not . . . sleep” by a non-sonnet called “Sonnet” that recounts
                how the absence of sound can pass through the silence. The scene in many ways
                presages the scene immediately following—and already discussed above—in which Madame
                de Menon’s story about musical sounds is interrupted by a musical sound. It is as if
                the novel must explore the topic first with regard to interrupted silence before
                presenting an analogous case involving interrupted tales of sound. While many
                people, myself included, would be irritated to be awakened by someone singing about
                silence, Julia savors the return of her lost jouissance in this impossible
                utterance: “she then perceived that love may produce other sensations than those of
                    delight.”<note xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="116"> Radcliffe, 24.</note></p>
            <p>The voice in this case functions as an autonomous part object, a gap in the visual
                field that constructs and sustains Julia’s desire. It “belongs” to Hippolitus only
                in her fantasy, and links the lovers through the cut it enacts.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="117"> Little wonder that Hippolitus is a “near and much-valued
                    relation” to the Marquis de Lomelli, whose name is so reminiscent of Lacan’s
                    mythological lamella, that organ of the drive.Radcliffe, 48; Lacan, <hi
                        rend="italic">Seminar XI</hi>, 205–6.</note> That cut, we might say, is
                their only real sexual relation. Repeatedly, we find that “the object voice emerges
                in counterpoint with the visible and the visual, it cannot be disentangled from the
                gaze which offers its framework, so that both the gaze and the voice appear as
                objects in the gaps as a result of which they never quite match.”<note
                    xml:id="ftn120" place="end" n="118"> Dolar, <hi rend="italic">A Voice</hi>,
                    67.</note> Yet they, like Julia and Hippolitus, are made inseparable by this
                mismatch. The <hi rend="color(#000000)">“strange and alarming sounds” </hi>of <hi
                    rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi> impinge upon and contain traces of the
                visual register precisely because they are the points excluded from that register,
                and around which that register has been constructed.<note xml:id="ftn120"
                    place="end" n="119"> Radcliffe, <hi rend="italic">Sicilian</hi>, 45.</note> We
                cannot easily speak of either its visual or sonic field as having a meaning apart
                from the “nothing” that Julia, Hippolitus, or Ferdinand have, with a measure of
                shame, introjected.</p>
            <p>4. Conclusion</p>
            <p>Radcliffe hears lack as a positive presence in its own right, consistently crossing
                the visual and sonic registers to highlight a multisensory ambiguity. The text
                attempts recourse to sonic reduction, but can figure this ambiguity only as a lack
                in the listener. This lack, appearing as a disquieting excess of sound-in-vision and
                vision-in-sound, interferes even with the figural, formal, and narratological
                processes of the text. Radcliffe subjects her characters to a sonic voyeurism that
                exceeds Foucauldian and Sartrean models of the gaze. By staging silences that are
                not empty within gazes that are not silent, and by allowing even the absence of
                sound to interrupt both the characters and the narration, Radcliffe challenges
                emergent visual epistemologies of the eighteenth century and reorganizes prevailing
                patterns of Enlightenment subjectivity. Lack, in her account, is not something
                missing but something present and resonant.</p>
            <pb/>
            <p rend="center">References</p>
            <p>Anolik, Ruth Beinstock. “The Missing Mother: The Meanings of Maternal Absence in the
                Gothic Mode.” <hi rend="italic">Modern Language Studies</hi> 33, no. 1–2 (2003):
                25–43.</p>
            <p>Archambault, Angela M. “The Function of Sound in the Gothic Novels of Ann Radcliffe,
                Matthew Lewis and Charles Maturin.” <hi rend="italic">Études Épistémè. Revue de
                    Littérature et de Civilisation (XVIe – XVIIIe Siècles)</hi>, no. 29 (June 21,
                2016). https://doi.org/10.4000/episteme.965.</p>
            <p>Brabon, Benjamin A. “Gothic Geography, 1760–1830.” In <hi rend="italic">The Gothic
                    World</hi>, edited by Glennis Byron and Dale Townshend, 98–110. Routledge
                Worlds. London: Routledge, 2014.</p>
            <p>Chow, Jeremy. “Mellifluent Sexuality: Female Intimacy in Ann Radcliffe’s The Romance
                of the Forest.” <hi rend="italic">Eighteenth-Century Fiction</hi> 30, no. 2 (2017):
                195–221.</p>
            <p>Chuh, Kandice. <hi rend="italic">The Difference Aesthetics Makes: On the Humanities
                    “After Man.”</hi> Durham: Duke University Press, 2019.</p>
            <p>Collings, David. <hi rend="italic">Monstrous Society: Reciprocity, Discipline, and
                    the Political Uncanny, c. 1780–1848</hi>. Lewisburg: Bucknell University Press,
                2009.</p>
            <p>Dekker, George. <hi rend="italic">The Fictions of Romantic Tourism: Radcliffe, Scott,
                    and Mary Shelley</hi>. Stanford University Press, 2005.</p>
            <p>Dolar, Mladen. <hi rend="italic">A Voice and Nothing More</hi>. Short Circuits.
                Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2006.</p>
            <p>Eidsheim, Nina Sun. <hi rend="italic">Sensing Sound: Singing and Listening as
                    Vibrational Practice</hi>. Durham: Duke University Press, 2015.</p>
            <p>Foley, Matt. “Tyranny as Demand: Lacan Reading the Dreams of the Gothic Romance.” In
                    <hi rend="italic">Lacan and Romanticism</hi>, edited by Daniela Garofalo and
                David Sigler, 141–56. Albany: SUNY Press, 2019.</p>
            <p>Foucault, Michel, Jean-Pierre Barou, and Michelle Perrot. “The Eye of Power.” In <hi
                    rend="italic">Power/Knowledge: Selected Interviews and Other Writings,
                    1972–1977</hi>, edited and translated by Colin Gordon, 146–65. New York:
                Pantheon Books, 1980.</p>
            <p>Freud, Sigmund. <hi rend="italic">The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological
                    Works of Sigmund Freud</hi>. Translated by James Strachey. 24 vols. London:
                Hogarth Press, 1964.</p>
            <p>Fulford, Tim. “The Politics of the Sublime: Coleridge and Wordsworth in Germany.” <hi
                    rend="italic">The Modern Language Review</hi> 91, no. 4 (1996): 817–32.
                https://doi.org/10.2307/3733510.</p>
            <p>Haggerty, George E. <hi rend="italic">Queer Gothic</hi>. Urbana: University of
                Illinois Press, 2006.</p>
            <p>Hunter, Walt. “The No-Prospect Poem: Lyric Finality in Prynne, Awoonor, and
                Trethewey.” <hi rend="italic">The Minnesota Review</hi> 2015, no. 85 (2015): 144–52.
                https://doi.org/10.1215/00265667-3144702.</p>
            <p>Labbe, Jacqueline M. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Visualities: Landscape, Gender, and
                    Romanticism</hi>. Houndmills: Palgrave Macmillan, 1998.</p>
            <p>Lacan, Jacques. <hi rend="italic">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book X: Anxiety,
                    1962–63</hi>. Edited by Jacques-Alain Miller. Translated by A.R. Price.
                Cambridge: Polity, 2015.</p>
            <p>———. <hi rend="italic">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book XI: The Four Fundamental
                    Concepts of Psychoanalysis</hi>. Edited by Jacques-Alain Miller. Translated by
                Alan Sheridan. New York: Norton, 1978.</p>
            <p>Langbehn, Volker. “The Lacanian Gaze and the Role of the Eye in Early German
                Romanticism.” <hi rend="italic">European Romantic Review</hi> 16, no. 5 (2005):
                613–26. https://doi.org/10.1080/10509580500420506.</p>
            <p>Leppert, Richard. <hi rend="italic">The Sight of Sound: Music, Representation, and
                    the History of the Body</hi>. University of California Press, 1993.</p>
            <p>Levin, David. <hi rend="italic">The Opening of Vision: Nihilism and the Postmodern
                    Situation</hi>. London: Routledge, 1988.</p>
            <p>Milbank, Alison. “Ways of Seeing in Ann Radcliffe’s Early Fiction: <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Castles of Aithlin and Dunbayne</hi> (1789) and <hi rend="italic">A
                    Sicilian Romance</hi> (1790).” In <hi rend="italic">Ann Radcliffe, Romanticism,
                    and the Gothic</hi>, edited by Dale Townshend and Angela Wright, 85–99.
                Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2014.</p>
            <p>Miller, Adam. “Ann Radcliffe’s Scientific Romance.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Eighteenth-Century Fiction</hi> 28, no. 3 (April 1, 2016): 527–45.
                https://doi.org/10.31 38/ecf.28.3.527.</p>
            <p>Noske, Frits. “Sound and Sentiment: The Function of Music in the Gothic Novel.” <hi
                    rend="italic">Music &amp; Letters</hi> 62, no. 2 (1981): 162–75.</p>
            <p>O’Malley, Patrick R. <hi rend="italic">Catholicism, Sexual Deviance, and Victorian
                    Gothic Culture</hi>. Cambridge University Press, 2006.</p>
            <p>Pluth, Ed, and Cindy Zeiher. <hi rend="italic">On Silence: Holding the Voice
                    Hostage</hi>. The Palgrave Lacan Series. Cham, Switzerland: Palgrave Macmillan,
                2019.</p>
            <p>Radcliffe, Ann. <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance</hi>. Edited by Alison Milbank.
                Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2008.</p>
            <p>Sartre, Jean-Paul. <hi rend="italic">Being and Nothingness: An Essay on
                    Phenomenological Ontology</hi>. Translated by Hazel E. Barnes. London: Meuthen,
                1957.</p>
            <p>Schmitt, Cannon. “Techniques of Terror, Technologies of Nationality: Ann Radcliffe’s
                    <hi rend="italic">The Italian</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">ELH</hi> 61, no. 4
                (1994): 853–76.</p>
            <p>Sedgwick, Eve Kosofsky. <hi rend="italic">The Coherence of Gothic Conventions</hi>.
                New York: Meuthen, 1986.</p>
            <p>Shajirat, Anna. “‘Bending Her Gentle Head to Swift Decay’: Horror, Loss, and Fantasy
                in the Female Gothic of Ann Radcliffe and Regina Maria Roche.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Studies in Romanticism</hi> 58, no. 3 (2019): 383–412.
                https://doi.org/10.1353/srm.2019.0023.</p>
            <p>Shapira, Yael. “Where the Bodies Are Hidden: Ann Radcliffe’s ‘Delicate’ Gothic.” <hi
                    rend="italic">Eighteenth Century Fiction</hi> 18, no. 4 (September 28, 2006):
                453–76. https://doi.org/10.1353/ecf.2006.0068.</p>
            <p>Stewart, Garrett. “Phonemanography: Romantic to Victorian.” In <hi rend="italic"
                    >“Soundings of Things Done”: The Poetry and Poetics of Sound in the Romantic Ear
                    and Era</hi>, edited by Susan J. Wolfson. Romantic Circles Praxis Series.
                Romantic Circles, 2008.
                https://romantic-circles.org/praxis/soundings/stewart/stewart.html.</p>
            <p>Townshend, Dale. <hi rend="italic">The Orders of Gothic: Foucault, Lacan, and the
                    Subject of Gothic Writing, 1764-1820</hi>. New York: AMS Press, 2007.</p>
            <p>Warren, Andrew. “Designing and Undrawing Veils: Anxiety and Authorship in Radcliffe’s
                    <hi rend="italic">The Italian</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">The Eighteenth
                    Century</hi> 54, no. 4 (November 21, 2013): 521–44.
                https://doi.org/10.1353/ecy.2013.0039.</p>
            <p>“Witness, v.” In <hi rend="italic">OED Online</hi>. Oxford University Press. Accessed
                January 9, 2020. http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/229714.</p>
            <p>Žižek, Slavoj. “‘I Hear You with My Eyes’; or, the Invisible Master.” In <hi
                    rend="italic">Gaze and Voice as Love Objects</hi>, edited by Renata Salecl and
                Slavoj Žižek, 90–126. SIC 1. Durham: Duke University Press, 1996.</p>
            <p>Notes</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
