<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Lyric Listening</title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Mina Gorji</name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-05-14</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2023.sound.gorji</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">praxis</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Lyric Listening
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Mina</forename>
                                <surname>Gorji</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="praxis/sound/praxis.2023.sound.gorgi"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Sound Studies: Recording Romantic Relationality </title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-02-21">May 14, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>05.14.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>  
        <front>
                <div type="abstract">
                    <p>This essay examines representations of quiet in Coleridge’s “Frost
                        at Midnight” to ask broader questions about the ways Romantic lyric can register
                        and express volume and sound dynamics. It offers historical contexts for
                        understanding the poem including the development of musical and rhetorical
                        notation for volume as well as accounts of shifting reading practices in the
                        period. It demonstrates how “Frost at Midnight” offers a rich nexus for thinking
                        about the experience and the representation of volume, and of silence, in
                        Romantic lyric. The poem invites further thinking about the semiotics of sound
                        and silence through a playful interplay between eye and ear. Coleridge was
                        fascinated by visual codes for sound and the ways in which patterns of sound can
                        be seen as well as heard, and his poems are full of accounts of different kinds
                        of sound, which complicate the distinction between silent and vocalised
                        reading. Coleridge provides an especially interesting
                            case study not only because he was writing on what has been described as the
                            cusp between reading aloud and silent reading, and during an era of scientific
                            discovery and innovation in the realm of acoustics, but also because he was
                            deeply interested in musical forms and in the science and semiotics of
                            acoustics. The essay demonstrates how shifts in volume can be expressed and
                            experienced in a poem’s own acoustic, rhythmic and verbal textures and suggests
                            that the representation of sound and quiet in “Frost at Midnight” challenges and
                            extends what is understood by ‘silent’ reading. More broadly, it proposes that
                            volume, a term which acquired its current acoustic sense in the Romantic period,
                            is a significant figure in Lyric studies which has gone unacknowledged. It
                            proposes that volume was not only important to Romantic poets such as Coleridge,
                            who, as this essay shows, found subtle ways of modulating and expressing shifts
                            in volume in his poetry, but also that, more broadly, volume should be
                            understood as part of a critical discourse about genre. The essay explores the
                            ways in which volume is figured and expressed in Coleridge’s writing, and
                            especially in “Frost at Midnight,” and considers the critical language we might
                            use to describe volume and dynamics more generally. Arguing that Coleridge’s
                            lyric poetry has its own playful modes and codes for communicating degrees of
                            sound, the essay proposes that volume is a neglected but significant figure in
                            Lyric studies.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </front>
            
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head>Lyric Listening</head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Mina Gorji</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>University of Cambridge, Pembroke</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
                <div type="section">
                 
            <head>Unheard melodies.</head>
           
            <p>“When I put my ear to the page, I hear nothing but the sound of my hair against the
                surface. If I erase the letters, no “sound” remains. Sound is not <hi rend="italic"
                    >on</hi> the page, even if a graphic transmission allows for its properties to
                be noted for reproduction’” (Johanna Drucker, in Marjorie Perloff and Craig Dworkin,
                eds.
                <hi rend="italic">The Sound of Poetry/The Poetry of Sound, </hi>2009,
                239) [my emphasis]</p>
                    
            <p>“Sound is what happens <hi rend="italic">in</hi> Lyric” (Jonathan Culler, <hi
                    rend="italic">Theory of the Lyric</hi>, Harvard, 2015) [my emphasis]</p>
                    
            <p>What does it mean for sound to happen in Lyric? Culler’s claim invites questions
                about how we define Lyric, but also about the phenomenology of sound, its medium,
                and the relation between sound, print and poem. How is sound experienced by the
                reader – by the eye, the ear, the mind’s ear, when it is read aloud and read in
                silence, <hi rend="italic">in </hi>Lyric? The preposition “in”
                suggests that Lyric is a container for sound, a vessel, perhaps, an urn: 
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    
            <l>Heard melodies are sweet, but those unheard</l>
            <l>Are sweeter; therefore, ye soft pipes, play on;</l>
            <l>Not to the sensual ear, but, more endear’d,</l>
            <l>Pipe to the spirit ditties of no tone: </l>
            <l>(John Keats, “Ode on a Grecian Urn”)</l>
                </lg>
                
            Where is sound happening in Keats’ lines? On the page? In our ears? “through the
                air”? in our mind’s ears? Is there a difference between the way it “happens” in our
                ears, when read out loud, and in the mind’s ear, during silent reading? And what of
                the sounds that are seen but not heard? Like the playful eye-rhyme suggested by
                “unheard” and “endear’d:” both words contain the word “ear,” but we only hear it
                sounded in “endear’d.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> As Susan Wolfson notes, in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Cambridge Companion to Keats,</hi> Glossary, xx. For a detailed
                            discussion of Keats’ “unheard melodies,” see Garrett Stewart, <hi
                                rend="italic">Reading Voices: Literature and the Phonotext</hi>
                            (Berkeley, U. of California Press, 1996), 155-160. See also Marshall
                            Brown, “Unheard Melodies: The Force of Form”,
                            <hi rend="italic">PMLA. Publications of the Modern Language Association of America; </hi>May
                            1992; 465-481. </note> And what of the poem’s other silences?
                The gaps and pauses? The moments of no sound and “no tone”? the quiet? The silence
                at the end of a line after “unheard,” the white space, the line break? or, somewhere
                else, as a boy “hangs/ waiting for the owls to answer”? What of these silences? Are
                they heard or “unheard”? What of the many silences contained in and articulated by
                Lyric? The silence of the urn, this “silent form”? Are they ‘happening’ in the same
                way as sound ‘happens’? And what of those eye rhymes we see and don’t hear, between
                “heard” and “endear’d”? Both contain the word “ear,” but it is not sounded in
                “heard,” seen not heard, silent. And what is <hi rend="italic">soft</hi> sound? In
                these lines, <hi rend="italic">soft</hi>, in the phrase “soft pipes”, suggests a
                quality of sound - timbre and volume. But do we experience different qualities of
                sound, and degrees of softness and loudness, when we read these lines silently? How
                does quietness “happen” in a poem? </p>
                    
            <p> The word “volume” acquired an acoustic register in the late eighteenth-century,
                according to <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>, a musical sense first recorded in Busby’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Complete dictionary of music</hi> (1786) referring to the tone
                and power of a human voice: “<hi rend="italic">Volume</hi>, a word applied to the
                compass of a voice from grave to acute: also to its tone, or power: as when we say,
                ‘such a performer possesses an extensive or rich volume of voice’.” (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>, 9a). The first recorded usage of the word volume as “Quantity, strength or power, combined mass, of sound”
                    (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>, 9b) occurs a little later, in 1822, and is attributed to Lord Byron in <hi rend="italic">Werner, </hi> (v.i. 134 I heard…, Distinct and keener far upon my ear Than the late cannon's 333) volume, this word—‘Werner!’). This new sense of the word registers a larger cultural and scientific curiosity about the nature and experience of sound in the period, a curiosity which also finds shape in poetry of the period. </p>
                    
            <p>The contemporary poet Alice Oswald is also interested in the expression of volume,
                and plays with different ways of suggesting quiet and silence through and around
                words, using space, measuring lines and fading ink to create a graphic code for
                calibrating sound and silence. In the last lines of her poem ‘Tithonus’
                (<hi rend="italic">Falling Awake, </hi>2016, 45-81), for
                example, there’s a moment of graphic quietening. The final letters of the poem fade
                into whiteness, so that the poem’s concluding word, “appearing” is almost invisible,
                printed in the very lightest shade of type, as dawn, and light, appear.<note place="foot" resp="author"> For a discussion of Oswald’ playfulness in this passage, see Angela Leighton,
                            <hi rend="italic">Hearing Things.  The Work of Sound in Literature </hi>(Harvard, Harvard University Press, 2018), 249.</note> The fading font
                produces an aural effect, the suggestion of diminuendo, in the way that <hi
                    rend="bold">bold</hi> or CAPITAL LETTERS, larger font size or <hi rend="italic"
                    >italics</hi> can suggest a louder volume. But, as we shall see, a poem can
                sound or produce the effect of quiet in other ways. </p>
                    
            <p>Coleridge, too, was intensely curious about the nature and experience of sound in the
                ear and in print. “Frost at Midnight”, written in Somerset in the winter of 1798,
                does not use the word “volume”, but records a playful exploration of dynamics and of
                the various ways (graphic, rhythmic, linguistic and as an effect of tempo) in which
                sound and quiet could be represented to both eye and ear in a poem. Like other
                Romantic poets, Coleridge was fascinated by visual codes and patterns for sound and
                marking emphasis. Julia S. Carlson has shown how Wordsworth drew on developments in
                cartography and rhetoric in his own shapings in and of sound on the page (Julia S.
                Carlson, <hi rend="italic">Romantic Marks and Measures: Wordsworth’s Poetry in
                    Fields of Print</hi>, 2016). Taking this yet further, I suggest that Coleridge
                was also preoccupied with how to represent sounds and especially volume, and that
                his imaginative interest in acoustics and in musical forms and notation informed the
                way he shaped sound into both aural patterns and visual language in his poetry.</p>
                </div>
                
            <div type="section">
            <head>ii. <hi rend="italic">pp</hi></head>    
            
            
            <p>Many of our critical terms for discussing lyric poetry are, of course, borrowed from
                music; for example, as Susan Stewart has explained: “we speak of such features as
                counterpoint, harmony, syncopation, stress, duration, and timbre” as some of the
                “ways in which sound is measured as if music and lyric were analogous” (<hi
                    rend="italic">Stewart</hi>, 2002: 68). In music, however, there is a system of
                notation for marking dynamics on a musical score, differences in volume and also in
                the quality of the sound, <hi rend="italic">pp, f, piu p, poco a poco dim., molto
                    piano</hi> and <hi rend="italic">quasi niente</hi>, for example. The Romantic
                period witnessed the expansion of the range of musical notation marks for dynamics;
                for example, it was during the last decade of the eighteenth century, “that the
                convention of indicating a gradual increase or decrease of volume by terms such as
                ‘cresc’ or ‘dim.’, or by ‘hairpins’, became commonplace” (Clive
                Brown<hi rend="italic">, </hi> 1999: 62). </p>
                
            <p> The expressive possibilities of volume became increasingly important to composers
                and performers in this period. In part, this was enabled by developments and
                innovations in musical instruments themselves: the <hi rend="italic"
                >pianoforte</hi>, invented in the eighteenth-century, allowed a much wider dynamic
                range than had been available to the harpsichord, for instance, and it was during
                the period 1750-1850 that various adjustments were made to stringed instruments
                which increased the range of volume they could express. Changes in the way sheet
                music was produced in the period may also have contributed to this interest in
                dynamics and its expression on the page as well as in performance: there was an
                increase in the publication of sheet music in the later eighteenth-century which
                meant, Brown argues, that the performance of music was no longer always in the
                direct acoustic control of the composer, since in the later period composers were no
                longer physically present to instruct performers how to alter dynamics. This is
                perhaps one reason why composers increasingly marked their scores to indicate these
                dynamic shifts. Moreover, “Many composers … came increasingly to regard accentuation
                and dynamic nuance as integral to the individuality of their conceptions and were
                unwilling to entrust this merely to the performer’s instinct” (Clive Brown, 1999,
                62). For this reason, he suggests, during the nineteenth century there was “a
                proliferation of markings, designed to show finer grades or types of accents and
                dynamic effects, and performance instructions of all kinds were used ever more
                freely” (Clive Brown, 1999, 62). It is likely that it was a combination of factors
                to do with the production and performance of music as well as technological
                innovation in the dynamic range of instruments that led to the development and
                proliferation of dynamic notation in the period, and that this also registered a
                wider cultural interest in sound and its expression.</p>
            </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>iii. Voicing and Volume.</head>
                
            <p>A range of new terms emerged for indicating the dynamics of performance in music but
                also in the fields of literary performance and rhetoric. It was not only on musical
                scores that dynamic markers appeared: a number of eighteenth-century literary
                critics also annotated reading texts to indicate volume and dynamics, the levels or
                the qualities of quiet or loudness for performance; some adopted musical notation,
                others used different terms. Discussing reading aloud, late eighteenth-century
                critics of rhetoric such as James Beattie associated different volumes with
                different emotional states and intensities of feeling and indicated in their
                annotations how readers might vary the volume and intensity of their voices to best
                express the affective range and qualities of a piece of writing. Varying the
                dynamics of reading, reciting or speaking, he explains, could also engage the
                listener and be more persuasive. In <hi rend="italic">Dissertations Moral and
                    Critical</hi> (1783), Beattie argues that:
                
           <quote>In describing what is great, poets often employ sonorous language. This is suitable
                to the nature of human speech: for while we give utterance to that which elevates
                our imagination, we are apt to speak louder, and with greater solemnity, than at
                other times.” (Beattie, 1783: I, 629) </quote>
                
            The word “sonorous” here conveys a sense of volume as well as suggesting a particular
                style, meaning, “Of spoken or written style: using imposing language; having a full,
                rich sound; imposing, grand; harmonious” (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>, 3a). The first
                recorded instance of the word to describe language is recorded in 1650, and derives
                from an earlier usage of the word to mean, more generally, “That makes a loud or
                resonant sound; capable of producing a loud sound, esp. of a deep or ringing
                character” (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>, 1a). The concept of linguistic volume
                Beattie’s comment suggests invites further investigation: certain words might be
                considered “sonorous”, others quiet depending, perhaps, on semantic associations,
                others because of onomatopoeia. The possibility that writers of the period <hi rend="italic">volume</hi> of words when selecting and composing
                a poem, for example, and that readers were attuned to the possibility of linguistic
                dynamics opens up another dimension for literary critics.</p>
                
            <p>The concept of volume also shaped how Beattie understood the rhythm of a poem or
                piece of dramatic writing. Readers should, he points out, attend closely to the
                rhythm of the writing, and this, he explains, could be understood in terms of
                loudness as well as duration, “The rhythm of sounds may be marked by the distinction
                of loud and soft, as well as that of long and short” (Beattie<hi rend="italic"
                    >,</hi> 1783: I, 283). It’s clear from Beattie’s account that volume was part of
                a critical vocabulary for understanding rhythm and conversely, as we shall see, in
                poetry, rhythm can express sound dynamics and volume.
                    <note place="foot" resp="author"> Beattie’s account of “loud and soft”
                            is contributing to a longer rhetorical tradition for describing vocal
                            performance, and especially the linguistic (and metrical) roles of
                            syllabic length and accent; but when Beattie uses the terms “loud and
                            soft” to describe rhythm, he is doing something slightly different,
                            referring to affective as well as rhythmical expression.
                  </note>
            </p>
                
            <p>Beattie was also concerned with the dynamics of performance, that is to say with how
                passages should best be read aloud to convey their mood and affective dynamics, and
                volume was an important aspect of this. He explains, for instance, that “Words of
                indignation pronounced with a soft voice and a smile… would be ridiculous”
                    (Beattie<hi rend="italic">,</hi>1783: I, 241). When reading aloud, choosing the
                appropriate volume and modulating between degrees of loud and soft was considered
                essential to the successful performance of a poem<note place="foot" resp="author"> It’s interesting to note that whereas Cicero discusses the importance of
                            tone in his <hi rend="italic">Institutio Oratoria</hi>, he does not
                            discuss volume at any length or often, in the way that 18<hi
                                rend="sup">th</hi> century rhetoricians do. This invites
                            further investigation. </note> In his <hi rend="italic">Art of
                    Speaking</hi>, for instance, James Burgh explained how a speaker’s <hi rend="italic">success</hi> with his audience” depends
                much upon his “<hi rend="italic">setting out</hi> in a proper key, and at a due
                pitch of <hi rend="italic">loudness</hi>. If he begins in too <hi rend="italic"
                    >high</hi> a tone, or sets out too
                <hi rend="italic">loud, </hi>how is he afterwards to rise to a
                    <hi rend="italic">higher note</hi>, or swell his voice <hi rend="italic"
                    >louder</hi>, as the more
                    <hi rend="italic">pathetic</hi> strains may require?” (emphasis original
                (Burgh, 1761: 12)). Burgh turns to terms such as “proper key,” “due pitch,” “tone”
                and “note” here; these terms are firmly part of musical as well as rhetorical
                discourse. He draws on them again when describing how the different emotional states
                require different modes of expression in both facial features and gestures, but also
                in terms of the dynamics of voice. “Despair” for instance requires the “tone of the voice” to be
                “<hi rend="italic">loud </hi>and <hi rend="italic"
                >furious</hi>” (Burgh, 1761: 17).
                Whereas “Shame” requires a voice that is “<hi rend="italic">weak</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">trembling</hi>” as well as short sentences and drawn down eyebrows
                to convey its full expression (Burgh, 1761: 17). He marks a number of speeches and
                texts with symbols to indicate the quality of delivery, which includes volume, for
                example in a speech on “Horrors of War,” an extract from Pope’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Homer</hi>. Certain lines, he indicates, are “to be spoken quick and loud,”
                others “to be spoken faintly, and with pity” or “to be spoken with a quivering
                voice” (Burgh<hi rend="italic">, </hi>1761<hi rend="italic"
                    >:</hi> 16, 17). Recognising and performing the appropriate volume for
                particular literary passages when reading them aloud was key to their rhetorical
                expressiveness, and Burgh offered readers help in doing this by using descriptive
                language to indicate the appropriate dynamics. Other kinds of notation were also
                available. </p>
                
            <p>In his <hi rend="italic">Lectures on Elocution</hi> (1762), Thomas Sheridan uses
                musical terms to distinguish between loud and soft, and high and low: “Loud and soft
                in speaking, is like the <hi rend="italic">forte</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >piano</hi> in music, it only refers to the different degrees of force used in
                the same key whereas high and low imply a change of key” (Sheridan, 1762: 83).
                Joshua Steele’s <hi rend="italic">Prosodia rationalis: or, An essay towards
                    establishing the melody and measure of speech, to be expressed and perpetuated
                    by peculiar symbols</hi> (1779) stresses the importance of modulating the voice,
                and sets out symbols for accent and emphasis, loud and soft (Steele, 1782: 24),
                which he applies to a number of literary examples, including a speech from <hi
                    rend="italic">Hamlet</hi> (Steele, 1762: 40).</p>
                
            <p> Gilbert Austin, writing in <hi rend="italic">Chiromania, or a Treatise on Rhetorical
                    Delivery</hi> (1806), also uses symbols, including some musical notation such as
                the hairpin to indicate shifts in loudness as well as a number of other symbols,
                such as the zigzag line to indicate uniform loudness or forte, explained in “Symbols for Noting the Force and
                Rapidity or Interruption of the Voice in Delivery” (Austin, 1806: 367). He advises
                readers and performers that these symbols were “to be marked in the margin near the
                commencement of the passage which they are to influence” (Austin, 1806: 367).</p>
                 
            <figure>
                <p><hi rend="italic bold"
                    >Fig.1 Symbols for Noting the Force and Rapidity or Interruption of the Voice, Austin, Chiromania (1806).</hi></p>
            </figure>
                
            
            <p>It is important to note that this kind of notation was not usually deployed by poets
                themselves; it was added later to mark up a text for performance, to encourage
                emphasis for dramatic and rhetorical effect. There were perhaps stylistic cues in
                the writing itself which these notations and marginal indications were responding to
                and amplifying. It was not necessarily only the subject matter or emotional tone of
                a piece of writing that suggested a particular volume; it could also be an effect
                suggested in the rhythmic and linguistic texture of the poem itself. Lyric poetry has its own language and codes for
                communicating volume and dynamics, and these effects do not depend on performance or
                vocalisation, on the timbre and grain and pitch of a reader’s voice, but can be
                experienced even when we read a poem in silence.
                There are other ways that a poem might register and express shifts in volume, not
                just in performance, but also during silent reading. If onomatopoeia denotes a
                shared code or language to represent certain sounds, like a cat purring or a dog
                barking, what are the linguistic, formal and rhythmic codes and cues of quiet? <hi
                    rend="italic">Shhhh, hush, </hi>ellipses . . . what else? </p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
                  <head>iv. Silent reading.</head>
        
            <p>Coleridge was well known for reading his own poems aloud, and of course when a poem
                is voiced, the reader can vary the volume as well as the pitch and tone, but usually
                there is no direct <hi rend="italic">verbal</hi> cue or instruction for this in the
                poem itself (as there sometimes is, say, in a play script, which often gives the
                actor or reader performance and stage directions). When he read his own poems aloud,
                Coleridge could of course vary the volume as he thought fitting. But how could he
                communicate the appropriate dynamics to his readers? And might they experience these
                shifts in volume during silent reading? Although, as Lucy Newlyn has shown, “the
                practice of ‘reading aloud’” was “a
                thriving one at the end of the eighteenth century” (Newlyn, 2003: 355), so too was silent reading. Laura Mandell
                points out that Romantic poets expected
                their poems to be read in silence, and that despite Wordsworth’s “love of
                reading-and-writing aloud and performing his poetry, nonetheless Wordsworth knew
                that most would encounter it as silent and graphic. Blake, too, could not mistake
                the essential noiselessness of his prints” (Mandell, 2007: 220). She goes on to
                argue that “their poems thematised their own soundlessness while offering
                compensatory images”(Mandell, 2007: 220). And yet the poems, read in silence, are not, perhaps, entirely
                soundless.</p>
                    
            <p>Effects or impressions of sound and volume can be experienced when a poem is read in
                silence. There is also the possibility of an imagined listening. Lyric poems can
                have their own inscripted codes and cues for volume and dynamics, ways of suggesting
                and registering shifts between loud and soft, sound effects which we experience even
                when we read in silence. And these differences in volume are expressed or suggested
                in various ways, in and through rhythm, vocabulary and lineation. The question of
                what volume means in relation to a poem is worth exploring further. If, according to
                the Anthony Ashley Cooper, third Earl of Shaftesbury, certain colours were
                    “quiet” (Shaftesbury, 1711: vol. 3, 313), perhaps a poet could also produce effects of quiet or loudness in words, rhythms, and spatial patterns on the printed
                    page. And this experience of sound puts pressure on the very idea of ‘silent reading’ itself.</p>
                    
            <p>The expansion of print, according to Walter Ong’s well-known thesis, produced a shift
                from oral reading aloud to quiet and then silent reading. Print, he claimed, was one
                factor in the creation of privacy in modern society, and, he argues, the production
                of books that were “smaller and more portable than those common in manuscript
                culture” set the stage “psychologically for solo reading in a quiet corner, and
                eventually for completely silent reading” (Walter Ong, 1982:131). It should be noted
                that silent reading in the West long precedes the invention of print, and is
                recorded by 400 CE, in Augustine’s famous comments on Ambrose, archbishop of Milan,
                in <hi rend="italic">Confessions</hi> 6.3.3. And that Ong’s description of print as
                a kind of silencing medium does not account for the various kinds of sound which
                print can embody. Perhaps, as Steven Connor suggests, “the move from sounded to
                silent reading” was not:
                
            <quote>simply a move from noise to quiet. Rather, perhaps, it is a move from one kind of
                sound to another … The increasing commonness of silent reading is to be regarded
                therefore, not as the simple turning down of sound, but as the creation of a more
                complex space of inner resounding. (Steven Connor, 2014: 106, 109) </quote>
                
            To push this further we might ask whether these “spaces of inner resounding” might
                vary according to genre. Perhaps Lyric enables and produces distinct kinds of aural
                and acoustic “spaces”, distinct possibilities for inner resounding. We might ask
                whether Romantic lyric is quieter than other genres or sub-genres, than declamatory
                neoclassical lyric, say, or than epic or satire. Perhaps the intimate occasion of
                certain lyric poems itself implies a dynamic of performance, that it be read in a
                quieter voice than a poem in another genre. Lyric, I want to argue, invites a
                particular kind of listening, and in the Romantic period this listening was
                inflected by historical contingencies in musical notation, book publication, and
                reading practices. The way volume was heard, and indeed the volume of poetry was
                recognised and interpreted, changed in the Romantic period. And perhaps one reason
                for this was that during this period a historical juncture between oral and silent
                reading was especially significant and pronounced. </p>
                    
            <p>In <hi rend="italic">Discourse Networks 1800/1900</hi> (1990), Friedrich Kittler
                famously suggested that reading after 1800 was shaped, Steven Connor explains, by
                the “principle of what might be called oralized writing,” (Steven Connor, 2015: 128)
                what Connor calls a “consensual hallucination, namely the capacity for a kind of
                ‘earsight’ or ‘hearsight’ that allows one to mistake writing for voice, to imagine
                that writing is everywhere suffused with the most intimate and expressive accents of
                the voice” (Steven Connor, 2015: 129). But if print could express, silently, the
                <hi rend="italic">accents </hi>of voice, it could also register
                the <hi rend="italic">dynamics</hi> of voice, and descriptions of sound in the poem
                itself. Dynamics are a feature of accent, but accent is not the only way dynamics
                are expressed. A printed poem can also convey shifts between loud and soft on the
                page, for example, such as a gradual quietening. And such shifts are not only
                descriptive but can also be mimetic of what is described. They can register effects
                of intimacy and musical and rhetorical patterns of expression. The question of how a
                poem might register these shifts and gradations in and of sound took particular
                inflection and emphasis in the Romantic period not only because of shifting reading
                practices but also because of a growing curiosity about the developing science and
                technologies of sound transmission, such as the stethoscope and microphone, and,
                later in the nineteenth century the phonograph, telephone and telegraph, as well as a fascination with the ways in which
                sound was codified in music, writing and in other visual forms, such as Chladni
                figures, the Phonautograph and the Eidophone, all part of what Coleridge was to call
                the “embryo Science of Acoustics<anchor type="commentRangeStart" n="23"/>”
                (Coleridge, 2003: 197).<note place="foot" resp="author"> For a
                            discussion of the scientific and technological developments in acoustics
                            in the late 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and early 19<hi
                                rend="sup">th</hi> centuries, see: Benjamin Walton and David
                            Trippett, eds., <hi rend="italic">Nineteenth-Century Opera and the
                                Scientific Imagination</hi> (Cambridge, Cambridge University Press,
                            2019); James Q. Davies and Ellen Lockhart
                            (eds.),<hi rend="italic"> Sound Knowledge: Music and Science in London, 1789-1851,</hi>
                            Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 2016; Richard Menke <hi
                                rend="italic">Literature, Print Culture, and Media Technologies,
                                1880–1900: Many Inventions,</hi> Cambridge, Cambridge University
                            Press, 2019; Thomas Hankins &amp; Robert
                            Silverman,<hi rend="italic"> Instruments and the Imagination</hi>,
                            (Princeton, Princeton University Press,1995).</note>
            </p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head>v. <hi rend="bold">Listening to Quiet</hi></head>
                    
           
            <p>Coleridge was a great talker, musical, oracular, entrancing, and his eloquence has
                been rightly celebrated. At times, his talking could be challenging; he was not as
                sensitive perhaps as he might have been to his own listeners: Wordsworth could not understand “one syllable”
                of his friend’s oration despite listening attentively for two hours, according to
                Samuel Rogers’ report (David Vallins, 2009: 308). There are
                many accounts of people listening to Coleridge, fewer of Coleridge himself as
                listener. And yet although he didn’t always attend enough to his listeners when he
                spoke, he was himself an acute and sensitive listener: his poems, as well as his
                notebooks, are full of great moments of listening. </p>
                    
            <p>Throughout Coleridge’s writing we find traces of this sensitivity in his “records of
                attentive listening,” as John Hollander has termed them. And often the sounds which
                drew his ear were quiet sounds. In these lines from a notebook entry, for
                instance:
                
            <quote>I hear only the Ticking of my Watch, in the Pen-place of my Writing Desk, &amp; the
                far lower note of the noise of the Fire— perpetual, yet seeming uncertain/it is the
                low voice of silent quiet change, of Destruction doing its work by little &amp;
                    little.<note place="foot" resp="author"> To
                            William Sotheby’, July 13, 1802, in L. Griggs (ed.), <hi rend="italic"
                                >Collected Letters of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</hi>, vol ii, ed. Earl
                            Leslie Griggs (Oxford, 1956), 808-813, 810.</note>
            </quote>
                
           This is a subtle pitch of listening: to distinguish between the clock and the <hi
                    rend="italic">lower note</hi> of the fire. ” Coleridge is drawing on a musical
                language, “low note”, to describe and distinguish between the sounds he hears. And
                he was curious about how these subtle variations of pitch and dynamics might be
                expressed in the texture of a poem.</p>
                    
            <p>Coleridge was writing on the cusp between reading aloud and silent reading. This is
                perhaps one reason that he was interested in the space between thought and address:
                in “Frost at Midnight,” for instance, he is addressing his babe, but in silence.
                This intimate occasion might also account for the poem’s interest in quiet sounds
                and sounding quiet. The volume of a poem perhaps depends on occasion as well as on
                genre, so that the intimate occasions of certain kinds of Romantic lyric poem might
                be productive of quiet, or at least be quieter than more declamatory or public
                modes. Like other Romantic poets Coleridge was thoughtful about the sound of poetry,
                and about shaping sound and silences—especially because he was writing in an age
                when poems were very often read in silence.</p>
                    
            <p>Writing in <hi rend="italic">Victorian Studies</hi>, Laura Mandell offers a specific
                technological explanation for a shift in reading practices, arguing that “Eighteenth-century changes in printing
                practices facilitated silent, rather than vocalized, reading of poetry.” (Mandell,
                2007: 220)<note place="foot" resp="author">Celeste Langan and N. McClane have shown that the material medium of transmission is crucially important to interpretation (“The medium of romantic poetry”, in James Chandler and Maureen N. McClane (Cambridge, 2008), 239-262).</note>. She suggests that the typographical
                shift from the long "f"-like "s" to the “s”, for example, accompanied a shift from
                reading aloud to silent reading (the “f”-like “s” being associated with reading
                aloud). It’s interesting to note, as Mandell does, that in the 1798 edition of
                Wordsworth and Coleridge’s <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads</hi>, both forms of “s”
                are used, and this, she suggests, “would have complicated silent reading” (Mandell, 2007: 220). Coleridge’s <hi rend="italic">Rime of the Ancient
                    Mariner</hi>, for instance, uses the “f” like “s,” and so calls for reading
                aloud. Mandell explains that this is because of different processes of reading
                associated with silent reading and reading aloud. You need to pronounce a word which
                contains an “f” like “s” to know whether it is an “f” or an “s,” she explains. But
                when an “s” form is used, you recognise it in a different way, which does not
                require pronouncing it or sounding it out. And yet, I would argue, this account of
                silent reading as a kind of visual decoding, a reading without sound, belies the
                complexity of the way sound operates and exists in the medium of print and in a
                poem.</p>
                    
            <p> Mandell’s notion of sound focusses on the idea of the voice and voicing; but poems
                offer other kinds of sounding and other patterns and articulations of sound.
                Coleridge understood poems to be musical forms, and his poems are full of accounts
                of other kinds of sound, which further complicate this distinction between silent or
                vocalised reading. Indeed, his poems seem to invite a play between eye and ear, not
                just by varying the typographic forms of letters such as the “s.” They invite us to
                think about the relation between seeing and hearing not only in terms of voice but
                also in terms of music and pattern. </p>
                    
            <p>Notwithstanding the need for further exploration of Mandell’s claim about the
                cognitive processes involved in reading aloud and reading silently, it is clear that
                poets writing in this period were keenly aware that reading practices were shifting,
                as Mandell and Newlyn have shown. It is also worth considering whether, and how,
                these and other cultural, technological and scientific changes might have shaped and
                influenced the representation of sound and dynamics in their poetry. Their poems
                invite further thinking about the semiotics of sound and of volume through a playful
                and dynamic interplay between eye and ear.</p>
                    
            <p>Writing elsewhere, Mandell examines Laurence Sterne’s play with visual and aural
                codes registered in his use of a sequence of four asterisks (****) to denote words
                which might offend readers in
                    <hi rend="italic">Tristram Shandy </hi>(1759). The **** are difficult to voice, she explains, but the words they
                represent and obscure present a different challenge to those reading aloud to an
                audience; his use of **** thus engages with a shift in reading practices in a
                playful way, mindful that some would read the novel aloud, others in silence.<note place="foot" resp="author"><hi rend="italic">New Literary History</hi>, Vol. 38, No. 4, Autumn,
                            2007, pp. 755-776</note> Coleridge’s engagement with the
                relation between sounds heard and seen or codified on a page, while not usually
                overtly humorous in this way, was often, as we shall see, no less witty. </p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head>vi. "O that I had the language of Music!" (Coleridge, <hi rend="italic">Notebooks</hi> II: 2035)</head>
                    
           
            <p>Writing in his notebooks Coleridge expressed his frustration that he did not “have
                the language of music” (Coleridge, <hi rend="italic">Notebooks</hi> II: 2035). This
                could mean that he was unable to read a musical score, or that he did not feel he
                fully understood musical language. And yet perhaps he was being overly modest; he
                does, after all, analyse the prosody of <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi> in
                terms of a pattern of “fifteen breves”, which suggests some knowledge of musical
                terms (<hi rend="italic">Marginalia, </hi>ed. Jackson, iv.
                603-4). And although there are no musical scores to be found in his notebooks, they
                do contain quite a few comments about his wide-ranging musical listening, to
                instruments such as the Eolian harp and Glass Harmonica as well as to a range of
                polite and popular musical forms; he notes, for instance, the superior song of the
                Ramsgate Muffin Man but also talks about enjoying Beethoven, Weber, Mozart and
                Cimarosa. In an essay in <hi rend="italic">The Friend</hi> he identifies a sense of
                ‘recognition’ in listening to music: 
                
            <quote>If we listen to a Symphony of Cimarosa, the present strain still seems not only to
                recall, but almost to renew, some past movement, another and yet the same! Each
                present movement bringing back, as it were, and embodying the spirit of some melody
                that had gone before, anticipates and seems trying to overtake something that is to
                come (<hi rend="italic">The Notebooks of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</hi>, ed. Kathleen
                Coburn (5 vols, London, 1957–2002), ii. 2356).</quote>
                
           This sensitivity to the effects of musical repetition informs Coleridge’s own poetic
                composition and points to the importance of musical thinking to his own
                understanding of sound and its forms and effects in poetry. <note place="foot" resp="author"> For a discussion of this passage and
                            an account of Coleridge’s rhyme and musical thinking see Olivia Reilly,
                            ‘[A]nother and yet the same’: Rhyme’s Music in <hi rend="italic">Kubla
                                Khan</hi>’,
                            <hi rend="italic">Romanticism, </hi>23, 2, 2017,
                            pp. 149-154.</note></p>
            
            <p> Coleridge was keenly aware that poets did not use the “language of music” itself,
                and that included musical notation, to indicate the dynamics of a poem. And yet, as
                he instinctively understood, somehow certain poems or lines in poems can suggest
                different dynamic qualities, with some moments seeming louder or quieter than
                others. Coleridge’s poems are especially rich in dynamic effects. It is striking how
                many of his lyric ‘Conversation poems’ not only meditate on sounds heard, but
                themselves describe and also communicate changes in volume. Consider the following
                    shifts: from the owlet’s cry which
                comes “loud” (l.3) to the quieter sound of the fluttering soot on the grate (l.15)
                in “Frost at Midnight;” from the silence of the stream (l.6) to the happy song of
                nightingales in “The Nightingale: A Conversation Poem;” from “green and silent spot”
                (l.1) and “small and silent dell” (l.2) to the crescendo in Invasion’s “thunder and
                the shout,/ And all the crash” (l.36-37) in “Fears in Solitude;” from “the stilly
                murmur of the distant Sea,” that “Tells us of Silence” (ll.11-12), to the music of
                the breeze as it plays over the lute strings in “The Eolian Harp” (l.15). Coleridge offers a descriptive
                vocabulary to describe a range of dynamics, a shifting scale of volume from loud to
                quiet to silence. But his poems not only name and describe these dynamics but also
                perform these shifts in their verbal, acoustic and rhythmic textures. </p>
                    
            <p>The late critic Thomas Macfarland was attuned to dynamic shifts across Coleridge’s
                poetry. The opening lines of “The Nightingale: A Conversation Poem,” he suggests,
                have, “a quietness that is
                in stark contrast to the frenetic
                notes of the hysterical sublime” we hear in some of Coleridge’s earlier work
                (Macfarland, 1981: 246). The word “quieter” suggests intimate, less declamatory; but
                his choice of word also conveys a sense of volume. I want to push this yet further
                and think about how this sound, this quiet is expressed:
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    
            <l>Distinguishes the West, no long thin slip</l>
            <l>Of sullen light, no obscure trembling hues. </l>
            <l>Come, we will rest on this old, mossy bridge! </l>
            <l>You see the glimmer of the stream beneath, </l>
            <l>But hear no murmuring: it flows silently</l>
            <l>O’er its soft bed of verdure. All is still,</l>
            <l>A balmy night! And tho’ the stars be dim,</l>
            <l>Yet let us think upon the vernal showers</l>
            <l>That gladden the green earth, and we shall find</l>
            <l>A pleasure in the dimness of the stars. </l>
            <l>(<hi rend="italic">CW, Poetical Works I, </hi>ed. J.C.C. Mays,
                Princeton University Press, 2001, ll.1ff)</l>
                </lg>
                
            How is a sense of quietness achieved in these lines? The language seems to be visual
                rather than aural here; the description begins by calling up to the eye what is <hi
                    rend="italic">not</hi> seen, clouds, a slip of light, trembling hues. The
                repetition of “no” emphasises, by contrast, the solidity of the deictic “this” in
                the phrase “this mossy bridge”, and the simple affirmation “You see” in the next
                line, emphasising what the eye can see. This visual language is soundless in one
                sense, anticipating the soundlessness described when we reach ‘no murmuring’ and
                ‘silently’. But the language takes on a more complex sensory register when we reach “dim”, a word used in these lines to describe a visual phenomena, faintness of
                light (<hi rend="italic">OED </hi>1 a), but which also had
                currency as an acoustic term in this period, meaning “Of sound, and esp. of the
                voice: Indistinct, faint” (<hi rend="italic">OED,</hi> 5; curiously, the last
                citation in <hi rend="italic">OED </hi>for this sense of the
                word is in the Romantic period, in Shelley’s 1817 poem “Marianne’s dream”). The lines create an effect of <hi rend="italic">diminuendo</hi>
                in terms of visual description and also in sound, so that effects of eye and ear
                confirm and amplify one another. What else in the opening lines suggests quiet? That
                word “still” is important; it offers one way in to thinking about how a sense of
                quiet is expressed in these lines. The predominant meaning of “still” here is
                “motionless” (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>, 1). But for Coleridge’s first readers the
                word also had a sense relating to volume, “Of a voice, sounds, utterances: Subdued,
                soft, not loud (<hi rend="italic">OED,</hi> 2a). This sense of “Still”, according to
                    <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> is no longer current. I think that this correspondence
                between movement and volume offers one way to think about how poetry expresses sound
                dynamics in and through shifts in movement, tempo or pace. It is,
                after all, moving or vibration of matter, as Coleridge understood, that creates
                sound in the first place as in the strings of a lute or an Eolian harp. That word
                “trembling”, in the phrase “trembling hues”, amplifies the sense I’m referring to
                here: overtly it’s referring to a visual phenomenon but it calls a sense of gentle
                movement to mind, the gentle movement of a stringed instrument playing very quietly
                (trembling suggests a faint movement).<note place="foot" resp="author"> Thinking about the lute string vibrating into
                            sound as a metaphor for animated matter trembling into thought,
                            Coleridge had used the word “tremble” in his poem “Eolian Harp”, first
                            published 2 years
                            (<hi rend="italic">CW, Poetical Works I, </hi>ed.
                            J. C.C. Mays, ll.46).</note> There is something suggestive
                about using Coleridge’s use of the word “trembling” to describe <hi rend="italic"
                    >colour</hi>, something synaesthetic perhaps, which calls to mind a kind of
                quiet sound by association. But which also alerts us to the sound texture of these
                lines and the way in which they move: the repetition suggests a kind of trembling
                and also a kind of quietening. In the opening of “The Nightingale. A Conversation
                Poem, April 1798”, the thick texture of repetition of the word “no” (ll.1, 2, 3, 6) which is drawn out by the
                <hi rend="italic">o </hi>sound in “flows” (l.6) and “O’er”
                (l.7) creates a slowing effect, so that the sound is not modulating as freely as we
                might expect, not moving not progressing, and this slowing suggests a
                    quietening.</p>
                    
            <p> Coleridge was interested in how gradations of sound were experienced by the listener
                and also by the reader, and he was thoughtful about how that might be represented on
                the page and in a poem. His poems are often intensely musical and sensitive to
                acoustic shiftings. Changes in linguistic register, tense, shifts in metre, pauses,
                punctuation marks, and the sonic texture of a line, the distribution of phonemes,
                all contribute to how a poem shifts dynamics between loud and soft. Pitch and tempo,
                genre, pacing and tonal register can contribute to a poem’s dynamics and Coleridge
                takes full and subtle advantage of all those means. Here in these lines from the
                1796 version of “The Eolian Harp,” for instance Coleridge creates a quietening
                effect rhythmically, by slowing the pace of the poem: 
                
                <lg type="stanza">
            <l> … How exquisite the scents </l>
            <l>Snatched from yon bean-field! and the world <hi rend="italic">so</hi> hushed! </l>
            <l>The stilly murmur of the distant Sea </l>
            <l>Tells us of silence. (ll.9-12)</l>
                </lg>
                    
            That italicized word <hi rend="italic">so</hi> stands out, typographically more
                emphatic, but not, somehow, <hi rend="italic">louder</hi>, than surrounding words.
                The word “so” (l.9) was italicized in the 1796 version of the poem (which appeared
                with the title “EFFUSION XXXV. COMPOSED <hi rend="italic">AUGUST</hi> 20<hi
                    rend="italic">th</hi>, 1795, AT CLEVEDON, SOMERSETSHIRE”) and the word was also
                italicised in the version of the poem published in <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>
                (1803), entitled “Composed at Clevedon
                Somersetshire." We know that this emphasis was intended by
                Coleridge because he underlined the word (“<hi rend="underline">so</hi>”) in the
                manuscript version of the poem he sent to Cottle for publication in 1796 (Rugby MS).
                However, the version of the poem published <hi rend="italic">Sibylline Leaves</hi>
                in 1817 does not have the word “so”
                italicised. </p>
                    
            <p>The italicisation (or its omission) is significant in terms of how we hear the line,
                and also in how the line represents volume. The use of <hi rend="italic"
                    >italics</hi> can create shifts of vocal tone but it can also contribute to
                shifts of pace and rhythm, which in turn suggests a dynamic effect, in this case, a
                quietening. Here, the italicization alters the rhythm of the line so that instead of
                the iambic pattern of “the WORLD so HUSHED,” that word “so” gains a stress, to the
                WORLD SO HUSHED. These three stresses in a row slow us down and the change of pace
                creates a feeling of intimacy—drawing us in, as it slows us down: together these
                contribute to the effect of <hi rend="italic">diminuendo</hi>. There is a sense of
                quieting as we reach the word “hushed,” a slowing down which puts emphasis on the
                quiet it denotes, a quiet which fades to the silence of the white space at the end
                of the end-stopped line. The word “hushed” conveys the sense, still current, of
                “Reduced to silence; silenced, stilled, quieted” (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>): in
                slowing the pace of the line by emphasizing the word “<hi rend="italic">so,”</hi>
                Coleridge creates a stilling effect rhythmically, and this contributes to the
                quietening of volume described and enacted. </p>
                    
            <p>The rhythmic shift in the next line, sounded in the phrase “the stilly murmur,” with
                its return to an iambic pattern, contributes to a steadying which suggests a
                quietening effect. The rhythm of the line shifts in the phrase “of the distant sea,”
                so that the word “distant” is emphasized after two unstressed syllables (“of the”);
                this shift in perspective is also suggested semantically as we shift from the
                proximity suggested by “murmur,” suggesting the “low continuous sound of water” (<hi
                    rend="italic">OED</hi>, 2) but also a quiet speaking voice, “A word or sentence
                spoken softly or indistinctly; faint or barely audible speech” (<hi rend="italic"
                    >OED,</hi> 4).<note place="foot" resp="author"> For a detailed exploration of sound and semiotics of
                            the murmur in Wordsworth and Romantic poetry, see Michele Speitz, ‘The
                            Wordsworthian Acoustic Imagination, Sonic Recursions, and ‘that dying
                                murmur”<hi rend="italic">’, SEL,</hi>
                        1500-1900, 55(3):621-646.</note> This “murmur” is a quiet voice we
                can hear only if we are close to the sound; a shift from this suggestion of
                proximity to “distant” produces a fading effect, a kind of diminuendo. Once again, a
                shift in pace and rhythm contributes to a quietening effect. There is a slowing of
                pace, suggested by the thickening acoustic texture of the lines with their
                alliterative clustering of <hi rend="italic">s </hi>sounds that
                concentrate in, and emphasise, the final word of the sentence, “silence”: “the <hi
                    rend="italic">s</hi>tilly murmur of the di<hi rend="italic">s</hi>tant <hi
                    rend="italic">s</hi>ea/ Tells u<hi rend="italic">s </hi>of
                    <hi rend="italic">silence.</hi>” This is an example of the kind of interplay
                between sound and semantic meaning which T.S. Eliot understood was key to the
                auditory imagination, that “feeling for syllable and rhythm, penetrating far below
                the conscious levels of thought and feeling, invigorating every word” (T.S. Eliot,
                ‘Matthew Arnold’, in
                <hi rend="italic">T. S. Eliot, The Use of Poetry and the Use of Criticism </hi>(London
                1933) p. 119). Coleridge creates acoustic shifts in and through rhythmic and verbal
                textures and contextures in many different ways, including the use of emphatic
                markings such as underlining or italicisation as well as through shifts of rhythm
                and pace, as he does in these lines.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                           He returns to the idea of a sound telling of silence in a notebook
                            entry for December 1803: “the waterfall at the
                            head of the vale…. The noise of waters everywhere/ something distant,
                            something near…Tis far off, &amp; yet very where/ and the pillar of
                            smoke/ the smooth winter fields- the <hi rend="italic">indistinct</hi>
                            <hi rend="underline">Shadows in the Lake</hi> [<hi rend="underline">are
                                all] eloquent of Silence]”</hi></note>
            </p>
                    
            <p>The change in register in the line “the stilly murmur of the distant sea” also
                contributes to a sense of historical distance, and to a related sense of acoustic
                distancing or quietening, diminuendo. The line, “the stilly murmur of the distant
                sea,” sounds archaic with its balanced pairs of adjective and noun- <hi
                    rend="italic">stilly</hi> murmur, <hi rend="italic">distant</hi> sea- in which
                the <hi rend="italic">st</hi> sounds chime with <hi rend="italic">stilly</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">distant</hi>. The word
                <hi rend="italic">stilly, </hi>in itself archaic, denotes not
                moving- and so the slowing down effect of the previous line,
                <hi rend="italic">the world so hushed, </hi>leads to this
                articulation of stilly-ness. A still sea, is, of course, a silent sea, and, as we
                might expect, another sense of the adverb “stilly”, recorded in <hi rend="italic"
                    >OED,</hi> bears this out; “In a still manner; silently, quietly; in a low
                voice; †secretly.” The sea is very quiet and therefore tells us of silence. It is an
                odd thing to say, that it tells us <hi rend="italic">of</hi> silence. That
                <hi rend="italic">of </hi>is intriguing. It’s not that the sea
                is silent, it tells us of – about - silence, a story of silence, perhaps. This is a
                playfully indirect- and perhaps we could say a <hi rend="italic">quieter</hi>
                way of telling us that the sea is silent, a syntactic distance opens up into a
                deeper silence.</p>
                
            <p>In “The Nightingale: A Conversation Poem,” the play with sound and semiotics takes
                another form: the invitation to listen at the heart of the poem is not voiced, but
                silent, signed rather than said:
                
                <lg type="stanza">
            <l>My dear babe,</l>
            <l>Who, capable of no articulate sound,</l>
            <l>Mars all things with his imitative lisp</l>
            <l>How he would place his hand beside his ear,<lb/>His little hand, the small forefinger
                up,<lb/>And bid us listen! (ll.91-6)</l>
                </lg>
                
            Here in these lines Coleridge is offering us the sign language of a pre-verbal baby,
                and inviting us to think about the silence of signs on the page. It is interesting
                to note that it was in the Romantic period that a new codified form of sign language
                for the deaf was developed in France (Jacobus: 2012, 84-88). Coleridge’s baby’s
                gesture can be better understood when placed in relation to some recent examples of
                sign language in the work of deaf poets Raymond Antrobus and Ilya Kaminsky as part
                of their own enquiries into the forms, dynamics and politics of signs and
                    silence.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            See Kaminsky’s <hi rend="italic">Deaf Republic</hi> (2019) and Antrobus’
                                <hi rend="italic">The Perseverence</hi> (2018).</note>
                Antrobus’ poem “Two Guns in the Sky for Daniel Harris”, for example,
                commemorates the deaf man Daniel Harris killed after police officers, who had been
                chasing him for speeding, misinterpreted his use of sign language and shot him. The
                poem interrogates the difficulties of interpreting sign language; Antrobus was
                trained in British Sign language, which is different from American Sign. But a
                failure to understand sign can, as Antrobus points out in the poem, have tragic
                consequences. He examines the cruel irony that the ASL sign for <hi rend="italic"
                    >alive</hi> looks like two guns pointing up to the sky:
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    
            <l>Now what could we sign or say out loud</l>
            <l>when the last word I learned in ASL was <hi rend="italic">alive</hi>?</l>
            <l><hi rend="italic">Alive</hi> — both thumbs pointing at your
                lower abdominal,</l>
                    
            <l>index fingers pointing up like two guns in the sky.</l>
                    <l>(Antrobus, 2018: 23)</l>
                </lg>
                    
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1002" width="15.920861111111112cm" height="6.840361111111111cm"
                    url="media/image2.jpeg" rend="inline">
                    <desc>A picture containing text, map, linedrawing Description automatically
                        generated</desc>
                </graphic>
            </figure>
                    
           
            Coleridge’s hand sign is not ambiguous and its clarity is part of its own expressive
                poignancy.</p>
                
            <p> In “Frost at Midnight,” composed and published in the same year as “The Nightingale:
                A Conversation”, this interest in signs and sounds and their correspondences is
                richly played out, from the very opening lines:
                
                <lg type="stanza">
            <l>The Frost performs its secret ministry, </l>
            <l>Unhelped by any wind. The owlet’s cry </l>
            <l>Came loud—and hark, again! loud as before. </l>
            <l>The inmates of my cottage, all at rest, </l>
            <l>Have left me to that solitude, which suits </l>
            <l>Abstruser musings: save that at my side </l>
            <l>My cradled infant slumbers peacefully. </l>
            <l>'Tis calm indeed! so calm, that it disturbs </l>
            <l>And vexes meditation with its strange </l>
            <l>And extreme silentness. Sea, hill, and wood, </l>
            <l>This populous village! Sea, and hill, and wood, </l>
            <l>With all the numberless goings on of life, </l>
            <l>Inaudible as dreams! the thin blue flame </l>
            <l>Lies on my low burnt fire, and quivers not; </l>
            <l>Only that film, which fluttered on the grate, </l>
            <l>Still flutters there, the sole unquiet thing. </l>
            <l>Methinks, its motion in this hush of nature </l>
            <l>Gives it dim sympathies with me who live, </l>
            <l>Making it a companionable form, </l>
            <l>Whose puny flaps and freaks the idling Spirit </l>
            <l>By its own moods interprets, every where </l>
            <l>Echo or mirror seeking of itself, </l>
            <l>And makes a toy of Thought.</l>
            <l> (<hi rend="italic">CW, Poetical Works I, </hi>ll. 1-23)</l>
                </lg>
                
            The poem’s very first lines signal an interest in the relation between eye and ear in
                a visual rhyme, or ‘eye rhyme’ between “ministry” and “cry.” This silent eye rhyme
                is part of the poem’s play with the way sound is codified or represented in visual
                form, in the semiotics of sound in print. The sound of that “cry” is picked up later
                in the half-rhyme with “side” and later “life.” Perhaps it’s too much of a stretch
                to suggest that t the long <hi rend="italic">I</hi> sound, or “eye” rhyme, is
                registered to the eye but not to the ear in “live.” Nonetheless, in these lines
                Coleridge invites us, in different ways, to move in and out between eye and ear,
                between rhyme seen and rhyme heard. Throughout the poem eye and ear work together
                and askance in unexpected ways. </p>
                    
            <p>Another striking feature of these opening lines is the dramatic dynamic shift from
                the “loud” cry of the owlet outdoors to the quiet of the indoor scene, a shift which
                produces a sense of intimacy and interiority and the accompanying illusion of <hi
                    rend="italic">diminuendo</hi>. That word “loud” primes our listening ears for a
                certain pitch of sound—which emphasizes in contrast the subsequent lines’ account of
                quiet. The poem’s shifts in dynamics depend on and produce shifts in intimacy as it
                records a shift from outside to inside, from loud noise to quiet. The word “secret”
                in the very first line suggests both quiet and intimacy, since “secret” carries the
                suggestion, now obsolete, but current when Coleridge was writing, of reticence, or
                quiet: “Of a person: †Reserved or reticent in conduct or conversation (obsolete);
                not given to indiscreet talking or the revelation of secrets; silent as to any
                matter, uncommunicative, close.” (<hi rend="italic">OED,</hi> 2 a). By giving the
                frost a curious sense of human agency, it “performs a secret ministry,” Coleridge
                draws out association of “secret” with quiet and closeness</p>
                    
            <p>The poem creates this sense of closeness dramatically, too, so that the reader feels
                as though we are standing with the poet, listening with him. That is expressed in
                the shift from the past tense “came loud” to the present tense “hark again!,” from
                the temporal distance of the past tense to the sense of immediacy suggested by HARK
                which instructs the reader, <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, give ear, listen! The reader
                imaginatively is listening but also aware of being a reader, something of which the
                poem deliberately reminds us. </p>
                    
            <p> Since M.H. Abrams’s classic and influential account of the poem as one of the Great
                Romantic Lyrics, it has been understood in terms of vocal utterance, a Conversation
                poem (Abrams, 1965). Coleridge’s “Conversation Poems” play with the dynamics of
                sound and its representation in curious ways. Much has been made of the vocal
                quality of these poems; critics have
                focussed on their various forms of address and the cadences of familiar
                    conversation <note place="foot" resp="author"> See, for example, Fred Burwick, “Coleridge’s Conversation Poems: Thinking the Thinker”, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Romanticism</hi>, 14.2 (2008), 168-182; Susan Eilenberg, <hi
                                rend="italic">Strang Powers of Speech. Wordsworth, Coleridge and
                                Literary Possession</hi> (Oxford, Oxford University Press, 1992),
                            esp. pp. 22-23; Ann Matheson, “The Influence of Cowper’s <hi
                                rend="italic">The Task</hi> on Coleridge’s Conversation Poems, in
                                <hi rend="italic">New Approaches to Coleridge: Biographical and
                                Critical Essays</hi> ed. Donald Sultana, London, Vision Press, 1981,
                            137-50; Peter Larkin, “Coleridge Conversing: Between Soliloquy and
                                Invocation<hi rend="italic">, The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, Summer,
                            2007, vol. 38, 3, 2006 (Summer, 2007), 113-117; G.S. Morris, “Sound,
                            Silence, and Voice in Meditation: Coleridge, Berkeley, and the
                            Conversation Poems”, <hi rend="italic">Christianity and Literature</hi>,
                            55.1, 2005, 51-57.</note>. And yet the poem itself places much
                emphasis on non-human sounds, sounds that are increasingly abstract and hard to
                imagine. The owl, the crackling fire, the fluttering speck, the dream (inaudible to
                another), the quiet shining of the quiet moon. Indeed, the model Coleridge chose to
                describe the poem was musical rather than vocal or dramatic: he conceived of the
                poem in musical terms, as a Rondo, a form which was extremely popular in the late
                eighteenth century. In an earlier draft, the poem ended with six lines which
                describe the baby’s response to the icicles. Explaining why he cut these lines,
                Coleridge wrote: ‘The last six lines I omit because they destroy the rondo, and
                return upon itself of the Poem. Poems of this kind &amp; length ought to lie coiled
                with its ‘tail round its’ head.” (<hi rend="italic">CC</hi>, 16.1.1, p.456n.).
                Coleridge had taken Charles Burney’s <hi rend="italic">General History of Music</hi>
                out of Bristol library a few months before he composed “Frost at Midnight” (in
                November 1797), and may well have read the account of the rondo in its pages
                (Burney: 1775, 155). His interest in Burney’s book around the time he wrote “Frost
                at Midnight” suggests a rich and suggestive musical context for interpreting the
                poem’s sounds and silences.</p>
                    
            <p> Understood as a musical form rather than overheard speech, the poem invites a
                different kind of listening.<note place="foot" resp="author"> For a rich perspective on Romantic poetry and music, see Adam Potkay’s essay on Wordsworth’s Poems on Music, <ref
                                target="https://romantic-circles.org/praxis/soundings/potkay/potkay.html"
                                >Romantic Circles</ref>
                            This essay is developed in Potkay’s 2012 JHUP book, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Wordsworth’s Ethics</hi>, Chapter 6, “Captivation and Liberty in
                            Poems on Music” (108-120); see also Chapter 5, “Music versus Conscience”
                            (90-107).</note> One which creates effects of volume and marks
                its shifts between loud and soft in playful ways. New possibilities for
                interpretation open up if we think of it not in terms of its orality, as a
                Conversation poem, to use Abram’s term, but in terms of aurality, as a
                listening poem. A poem which meditates on the experience of listening not just to the sound of a
                voice, but to the sounds of the non-human, the owls, the fire, the quiet itself. And
                it creates the effects of quiet through particular codes and patterns of sound and
                meaning.</p>
                    
            <p>If we put pressure on the poem’s acoustic language, its imaginings and figurings of
                sound, and think not only of the vocal cadences but also other forms and shapes of
                sound, abstracted from a notion of voice, pattern takes on a new significance.
                According to Marjorie Levinson, attending to visual pattern is a neglected key to
                understanding the poem. In a recent study she “seeks to shift the sensory register
                of criticism of the poem from its traditional emphasis on the acoustic to a new
                appreciation of the visible” (Levinson, 2018: Abstract,
                “Parsing the Frost”, online version). She emphasizes the poems’ visuality, rather than the acoustic qualities and
                expression. I would push this further and argue that Coleridge is deeply interested
                in the <hi rend="italic">relation</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">dynamics</hi>
                between the visual and the acoustic but also between the visual and the aural.
                Patterns can be heard as well as seen. Throughout the poem, Coleridge plays with the
                way visual and acoustic dimensions are intimately related. This is in part because
                the poem is written with a sense of its own mode of reception in mind: that is to
                say, Coleridge was keenly aware that it might be read in silence, and so was
                especially thoughtful about how sound might be represented in print patterns, on the
                page. </p>
                    
            <p>There is a curious play between eye and ear, for instance, in the poem’s concluding
                lines:
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    
            <l>[…] whether the eave-drops fall </l>
            <l>Heard only in the trances of the blast, </l>
            <l>Or if the secret ministry of frost </l>
            <l>Shall hang them up in silent icicles, </l>
            <l>Quietly shining to the quiet Moon. (ll. 70-74)</l>
                </lg>
                    
            The beautiful and strange description of a moon shining quietly prompts a question,
                an imagining, of what a loud shining might sound like. On the one hand, the idea of
                a “quiet moon” is a folk idiom to describe a new moon, and indeed the poem was
                written at the time of the new moon. And yet the image is so much more suggestive.
                It is “quietly shining to the quiet moon”: that <hi rend="italic">quiet</hi>
                repeated in <hi rend="italic">quietly</hi>, emphatically. An icicle can be silent by
                imagined contrast: its silence remembers the sound of dripping water before it has
                frozen into an icicle, or after it thaws. </p>
                    
            <p>Another example of Coleridge’s interests in the play between eye and ear is the
                visual analogy to musical form described by Levinson: the fluttering soot on the
                grate, she argues, and suggests visually (in her <hi rend="italic">fig</hi>. 7,
                reproduced below), can be read as a visual representation of a stave with a musical
                note. And to take this further, it is the semiotics of music, the semiotics of
                sound, that interest Coleridge here. </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1003" width="13.39616111111111cm" height="15.546730555555555cm"
                    url="media/image3.jpg" rend="inline">
                    <desc> <hi rend="italic bold">Fig. 3, 18th-c fire grate, journal page, musical staff, window frost, Aeolian Harp. <hi rend="italic">fig.
                            7</hi> in Levinson, 2018.</hi></desc>
                </graphic>
            </figure>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
            <head>vii. “the embryo science of acoustics”.</head>
                    
            <p>“Frost at Midnight” is a poem which explores the edges of silence. Coleridge has, as
                Susan Wolfson notes, an “ear for such limits, of sound suspended” (Wolfson, 2008:
                para. 3). There is an intriguing richness and, at times, an opacity to the poem’s
                acoustic language which rewards attention, and which, in turn, invites new readings
                and imaginings of the poem itself, and new possibilities for thinking about the
                quietudes of Romantic Lyric<hi rend="italic">.</hi> The poem generates thinking
                about what it might it mean to shine “quietly”. And about how we might listen to the
                moon. And about the audibility and inaudibility of dreams. Setting the poem’s sonic
                and aural language in the context of Coleridge’s wider thinking about sound dynamics
                and acoustics and its imaginative possibilities, gives us some hints. </p>
                    
            <p>In 1827, Coleridge read Sir Charles Wheatstone’s “Experiments on Audition” and was
                struck by his account of the microphone, an instrument which, he explained,
                “rendered audible the weakest sounds” (Wheatstone, 1827: 70). Coleridge describes,
                in <hi rend="italic">Marginalia</hi>, how it sparked a recognition of a “fond and
                earnest dream project of mine own …with sundry other imaginations in what might be
                effected in the only embryo Science of Acoustics” (Coleridge, 2003: 197). The
                science of Acoustics, that “branch of physics concerned with the properties and
                phenomena of sound, sometimes esp. in relation to hearing or speech.” (<hi
                    rend="italic">OED</hi>,1), was just over 100 years old when Coleridge scribbled
                these words. As his marginal gloss suggests, <hi rend="italic">Coleridge’s</hi>
                fascination with acoustics was apparent years before he read of Wheatstone’s
                invention: we find an interest in the properties and phenomena of sound registered
                in numerous notebook entries and poems.</p>
                    
            <p>We know, for instance, that he was fascinated by the sound experiments of the
                musician and scientist Ernst Chladni (who was to publish the first textbook on
                acoustics in 1802), which seemed to show sound itself making shapes in iron
                    filings.<note place="foot" resp="author">On Chladni’s
                            contribution to acoustics see Viktoria Tkaczyk, “The Making of Acoustics
                            around 1800, or How to Do Science with Words”, in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Performing Knowledge, 1750-1850</hi> (2015) <ref
                                target="https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110421064-003"
                                >Performing Knowledge</ref></note>
                Chladni drew a bow across the edge of a metal plate covered in sand before
                exclaiming, as legend has it: ‘The sound is painting!’ (quoted in Cox, 2002, p. 14).
                The significance of this experiment cannot be overstated: not only did it seem to
                reveal the material form of sound, but doing so Chladni proved that sound could
                travel through solid substances and could no longer “be subsumed under the ‘the
                science of air’ and could be considered a branch of physics in its own right”
                (Viktoria Tkaczyk, 2015: 27-56, 27). Chladni first published his acoustical figures
                in German in 1787, and gave a copy to the Royal Society in November of the same
                year. Coleridge may have read about the experiment in the
                <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Magazine </hi>(3, May 1799,
                389-96) in which a translation of the Jena physics professor Johann Heinrich Voigt’s
                1796 account of it (“Beytrag in den Versuchen über die Klangfiguren schwingender
                Flächen”, <hi rend="italic">Neues Journal der Physik</hi> vol. 3, part 4 (1796),
                391-399) was published as “Observations and experiments in regard to the figures
                formed by sand &amp;c on vibrating surfaces” (<hi rend="italic">Philosophical
                    Magazine</hi>, 3 (May 1799), 389-96, with illustrations). He may also have read
                of the experiment in <hi rend="italic">The Analytic Review</hi>, volume 1 (July
                1788, 371-2). Chladni toured Europe conducting performances of the experiment to
                enraptured audiences (including Napoleon, in the Tuilerries Palace); Coleridge may
                also have learned of the sound painting during his visit to Gottingen<note place="foot" resp="author"> Kathleen Koburn, note in <hi rend="italic">CW, </hi>14,
                            2019, pp. 284-5.</note>, where he studied in 1799, a few years
                after Chladni had demonstrated the experiment (he had visited Gottingen between
                December 1792 and early 1793, https://monoskop.org/Ernst Chladni ). The experiment
                was to be popularised in London in 1800 when Thomas Young repeated the demonstration
                to an enthralled audience at The Royal Society. The Chladni figures were part of a
                wider culture of acoustic spectacle in the early nineteenth century. Edward Gillen
                explains that in “London’s fashionable West End … sonorous displays, especially
                those of a musical nature, combined with philosophical inquiry, provided mystifying
                and wondrous entertainment” (Gillen: 2021, chapter 1, p. 1, forthcoming). He argues
                that “Chladni’s acoustic plates provided a rich example of how specialist and
                non-specialist audiences alike could engage with new scientific ideas from the
                Continent” (ibid.). While I am not suggesting that Coleridge’s poems of the 1790s
                were influenced directly by Chladni’s experiments, I want to propose that they too
                register a curiosity about what he was to describe as “the Embryo science of
                acoustics”, which was itself part of a culture of curiosity about sound in the
                Romantic period.<note place="foot" resp="author">For discussions
                            of the culture of scientific spectacle see, for instance, Melissa
                            Dickson, “Charles Wheatstone’s Enchanted Lyre and the spectacle of
                            sound”, in James Q. Davies and Ellen Lockhart (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                                >Sound Knowledge: music and science in London, 1789-1851</hi>,
                            (University of Chicago Press: Chicago, 2016), pp. 125-44 and Edward J.
                            Gillin (forthcoming), “<hi rend="italic">Sound Authorities: Scientific
                                and Musical Knowledge in Nineteenth-Century Britain,</hi> (Chicago: Chicago University Press, 2021).</note></p>
                    
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1004" width="15.920861111111112cm" height="10.31875cm"
                    url="media/image4.jpeg" rend="inline">
                    <desc><hi rend="italic bold"
                        >Fig. 4, Illustration of Chladni patterns in Ernst Chladni, <hi rend="italic">Die
                            Akustik</hi> (1802)</hi></desc>
                </graphic>
            </figure>
            
            <p> Coleridge’s own interest in the semiotics of sound and its representation is figured
                in the Conversation poems and based on his wider interest in science during his stay
                in Somerset the 1790s. As Tim Fulford has explained, the Conversation poems were
                influenced by and part of a wider culture of scientific enquiry (Fulford, 2018).
                Pushing Fulford’s argument yet further, we might understand Coleridge’s Conversation
                poems as articulations of a growing interest in and curiosity not only about the
                nature of air, but also about a relate field of enquiry, the science of acoustics,
                and in particular, the movement and materiality of sound. In “Frost at Midnight”
                this interest was perhaps modulated by his sense of the poems’ expected mode of
                reception: he knew that it was likely to be read in silence, heard only in the
                mind’s ear. But it is also framed by its occasion, spoken to a sleeping baby who
                cannot hear him, at least not consciously. </p>
                    
            <p> The poem’s concluding lines meditate on the sounds and silences of water drops and
                icicles in a way that puts pressure on the language of listening:
                <lg type="stanza">
                    
            <l>[…] whether the eve-drops fall </l>
            <l>Heard only in the trances of the blast, </l>
            <l>Or if the secret ministry of frost </l>
            <l>Shall hang them up in silent icicles, </l>
            <l>Quietly shining to the quiet Moon. (ll.70-74)</l>
                </lg>
                
            The word “silent” invites our listening. Here, in these lines, or perhaps I should
                say through these lines, our ears become subtly tuned to the sounds of <hi
                    rend="italic">silence</hi> which shifts gently into <hi rend="italic"
                >quiet</hi>. The line “<hi rend="italic">quietly shining to the quiet moon,</hi>”
                picks up and resounds the <hi rend="italic">i</hi> of
                <hi rend="italic">silent icicles, </hi>recalling the sound of
                that <hi rend="italic">silence</hi> even as it suggests a different sound. It’s
                worth noting here that the phrase is not, as it might have been,
                <hi rend="italic">silently </hi>shining to
                the<hi rend="italic"> silent </hi>moon – but <hi rend="italic"
                    >quietly</hi> shining to the <hi rend="italic">quiet</hi> moon<hi rend="italic"
                    >,</hi> and this difference suggests a thawing of <hi rend="italic"
                    >silence,</hi> since <hi rend="italic">quiet</hi> can, but does not always or
                only, mean silent. Quiet can suggest a low or subdued sound (<hi rend="italic"
                    >OED</hi> 1A, a, <hi rend="italic">adj</hi>, “making little sound”; 2a, “making
                little or no noise”). That repeated word <hi rend="italic">quietly</hi> dims into a
                shorter <hi rend="italic">quiet</hi>, drawing the ear to listen in, to the
                possibility of the moon’s quiet sound<hi rend="italic">.</hi> And the line has only
                4 stresses instead of the 5 stress iambic baseline of the poem, so we are left both
                with a sense of lack- and anticipation - listening out for the last stress. </p>
                    
            <p>There’s a sense of diminishing and <hi rend="italic">diminuendo</hi>, but also a
                feeling of completion as “quietly” turns to “quiet,” and as we move from “icicles”
                to the monosyllabic “moon”. This drawing in suggests both sonic diminuendo and
                intimacy, despite the great distance of the moon. The icicles are quiet because,
                unlike the water dropping from the eaves, they no longer splash and make a sound.
                There is a strange shift of scale and of distance here – one which prompts us to
                question how a moon might be quiet. That repeated word “quiet” suggests a kind of
                proximity —even, that it might be possible to hear the moon, that its sound might be
                quiet, even as are the nearby icicles. The quiet shining of the icicles <hi
                    rend="italic">to</hi> the moon is imagined as a form of address, to the
                listening moon. These icicles are silent but eloquent: and yet their silence is not
                eloquent of the self in the way Salome Voegelin proposes. (Voegelin, 2010: 83).
                Rather, it speaks of the presence of something greater. As Paul Magnuson puts it,
                “at the quietest moments of the year when the icicles are frozen in silence, there
                is a force in the world shining through the icicles.” <note place="foot" resp="author"> Coleridge may well have known that Robert Burns uses
                            the term “silent moon” (“While the silent moon shine clearly”) in the
                            last wooing and intimate verse of his Song <hi rend="italic">Westlin
                                Winds.</hi></note>
                       These silences speak of intimacy and also of something far
                more greatly interfused- a force in the world.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                <head>viii. Conclusion</head>
                    
            <p>For Coleridge, the ability to listen was fundamental to being a poet. A great poet,
                he suggests, writing in July 1802 to his friend William Sotheby, should be able to
                listen with “the ear of a wild Arab list’ning in the silent Desart” (Coleridge, <hi
                    rend="italic">Letters</hi>: ii, 810). We know that the Arab is listening, in
                silence – but we do not know what it is he listens to or for. The state of
                listening, hearkening, for something is the poetic state. But silence also seems
                important: Coleridge’s test for the poet combines forms of privation – that
                emptiness, which shares the root ‘desert’: the dryness of deserts, the solitude of
                the deserted, and the soundlessness of silence. The wild Arab is alert for the
                slightest sound- listening FOR sound in silence. Coleridge’s words invite the reader
                too to listen - that word “listening” alerts us to the sound patterns instinct in
                the lines that follow. The poet, Coleridge goes on, should also be possessed of “the
                eye of a North American Indian tracing the footsteps of an Enemy upon the leaves
                that strew the forest, the <hi rend="italic">Touch</hi> of a blind man feeling the
                face of a darling Child” (ibid., 810) Primed to listen, the reader might pick up a
                suggestion of sound in the word <hi rend="italic">footsteps</hi> (they are footsteps
                he is tracing, rather than the <hi rend="italic">footprints</hi> we might have
                expected) and the sound of these footsteps resounds in the <hi rend="italic">st</hi>
                sounds of <hi rend="italic">strew</hi> and <hi rend="italic">forest</hi>. It alerts
                us to the gentle pathos of that word
                <hi rend="italic">touch </hi>touching in <hi rend="italic"
                    >sound</hi> the <hi rend="italic">child</hi> as the blind man touches its face. </p>
                    
            <p> Thinking about different kinds of listening in a notebook entry a few months later,
                in September 1802, Coleridge returns to the blind man and the wild Arab as figures
                for sensory acuity. His choice of an Arab and a North American Indian as examples
                are striking and suggest, perhaps, a primitivist notion that such peoples had more
                acute senses than Europeans. Choosing these geographically remote listeners
                introduces a poignant distance between himself and the figure of the ideal listener,
                which in turn intensifies the dynamics of listening described. Here, the blind man
                and the Arab come together in the figure of “a <hi rend="italic">blind Arab</hi>
                list’ning in the wilderness” (Coleridge, <hi rend="italic">Notebooks</hi>, i. 1244):
                now the blindness of the listener intensifies his listening once again. And instead
                of the blind man feeling the face of the darling child we have, more painful, a
                different kind of listening, a listening which can never be satisfied, a “Mother
                listening for the <hi rend="italic">sound</hi> of a still-born child” (ibid.)
                Silence here comes to represent an extreme form of loss and absence – Coleridge’s
                examples move through degrees of privation- from the blind Arab in the desart to the
                poignant expectancy of the mother listening for a sound that she will never hear.<note place="foot" resp="author">To William Sotheby’, July 13, 1802, in L. Griggs
                            (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Collected Letters of Samuel Taylor
                                Coleridge</hi>, vol ii, ed. Earl Leslie Griggs (Oxford, 1956),
                            808-813, 810.</note>
            </p>
                    
            <p>To think about the representation and account of sound in these poems in relation to
                contemporary scientific instruments and innovations in acoustics, and also, as I
                have indicated, to a wider culture of curiosity about how sound could be represented
                and embodied on the page in music and in print opens up fresh thinking about the
                significance of silence and quiet in Coleridge’s poems, and in Romantic lyric more
                widely. What is needed is a new kind of listening, which includes attention to the
                dynamics of apostrophe, the cryptographic reading described by John Shoptaw, that,
                “listening for what familiar words and phrases the line echoes or calls to mind,” as
                well as the phonemic analysis described by James Lynch,<note place="foot" resp="author"> John Shoptaw, “Lyric
                            Cryptography,” <hi rend="italic">Poetics Today,</hi>
                            <ref target="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/27810/pdf">MUSE</ref> Volume 21, Number 1, Spring 2000, pp. 221-262) ; James Lynch, “The Tonality of Lyric Poetry:
                            An Experiment in Method,” 1953,
                            <ref target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/00437956.1953.11659470">tandfonline</ref>;WORD,
                            9:3, 211-224, DOI: 10.1080/00437956.1953.11659470)</note> a
                composite kind of imaginative auditory attention, one which is attuned not only to
                the ghosts and echoes of words, and their phonetic clustering, but also to the
                shifting patterns and dynamics in and of sound, to the way a poem creates effects of
                volume. It is time that Lyric Studies expanded the range and frequencies of its
                listening.</p>
                </div>
            
        <div type="citation">
            
        <head>Works Cited</head>
          
            <bibl>Abrams, M.H., “Studies and Style in the Greater Romantic Lyric”, <hi rend="italic"
                    >From Sensibility to Romanticism: Essays Presented to Frederick A. Pottle</hi>.
                Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 1965, 527-560.</bibl>
            
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">The Analytic Review</hi>, volume 1, July 1788.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Antrobus, Raymond, <hi rend="italic">The Perseverance</hi>.
                London: Penned in the Margins, 2018.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Austin, Gilbert, <hi rend="italic">Chiromania, or a Treatise on Rhetorical
                    Delivery</hi>. London, 1806.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Barry, Kevin, <hi rend="italic">Language, Music, and the Sign: A
                    Study in Aesthetics, Poetics and Poetic Practice.</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge
                University Press, 1987. </bibl>
            
            <bibl>Beattie, James, <hi rend="italic">Dissertations Moral and
                    Critical</hi>. London and Edinburgh, 1783.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Brown<hi rend="italic">, </hi>Clive, <hi rend="italic">Classical
                    and Romantic Performing Practice, 1750-1900</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University
                Press, 1999. </bibl>
            
            <bibl>Brown, Marshall, “Unheard Melodies: The Force of Form”. <hi
                    rend="italic">PMLA. Publications of the Modern Language Association of
                    America,</hi> May 1992, 465-481.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Burgh, James,
                <hi rend="italic">The Art of Speaking. </hi>London, 1762.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Burney, Charles, <hi rend="italic">General History of Music,</hi> II. London,
                1775.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Burwick, Fred, “Coleridge’s Conversation Poems: Thinking the Thinker”. <hi
                    rend="italic">Romanticism</hi>, 14.2 (2008), 168-182.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor, <hi rend="italic">Collected Letters of Samuel Taylor
                    Coleridge,</hi> ed. Earl Leslie Griggs (6 vols). Oxford: Oxford University
                Press, 1956.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor,
                <hi rend="italic">The Notebooks of Samuel Taylor Coleridge, </hi>ed.
                Kathleen Coburn. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1957-</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor,
                <hi rend="italic">Poetical Works I, </hi>ed. J. C.C. Mays.
                Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2002.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor,
                <hi rend="italic">A Book I Value.  Selected </hi>Marginalia,
                ed. H.J. Jackson. Princeton University Press: Princeton and Oxford, 2003.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Connor, Steven, “<hi rend="italic">Scilicet</hi>: Kittler, Media and Madness”, <hi
                    rend="italic">Kittler Now. Current Perspectives in Kittler Studies</hi>, ed.
                Stephen Sale and Laura Salisbury. Polity Press: Cambridge, 2015, 115-131. </bibl>
            
            <bibl>Connor, Steven, <hi rend="italic">Beckett, Modernism and the Material
                    Imagination</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2014.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Cooper, Anthony Ashley, Lord Shaftesbery,
                <hi rend="italic">Characteristics. Of Men, Manners, Opinions, Times.  </hi>London,
                1711.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Cox, C., “From synapse to signal: Carsten Nicolai’s ‘Telefunken’”, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Autopilot</hi>, ed. C Nicolai, Berlin: Die Gestalten Verlag (J. Gaines,
                Transl.), 2002.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Culler, Jonathan, <hi rend="italic">Theory of the Lyric</hi>. Harvard: Harvard
                University Press, 2015.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Davies, James Q. and Lockhart, Ellen (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sound Knowledge: Music
                    and Science in London, 1789-1851.</hi> Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
                2016.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Dickson, Melissa, “Charles Wheatstone’s Enchanted Lyre and the spectacle of sound”,
                in James Q. Davies and Ellen Lockhart (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sound Knowledge:
                    Music and Science in London, 1789-1851</hi>. University of Chicago Press:
                Chicago, 2016, pp. 125-44. </bibl>
            
            <bibl>Drucker, Johanna, “Not Sound”, in Perloff, Marjorie and Dworkin, Craig, eds.
                <hi rend="italic">The Sound of Poetry/The Poetry of Sound. </hi>Chicago:
                University of Chicago Press, 2009, 237-48. </bibl>
            
            <bibl>Eilenberg, Susan, <hi rend="italic">Strange Powers of Speech. Wordsworth, Coleridge
                    and Literary Possession</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1992.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Fulford, Tim, “Science and Poetry in 1790s Somerset: the Self-Experiment Narrative,
                the Aeriform Effusion and the Greater Romantic Lyric”. <hi rend="italic">ELH</hi>,
                Johns Hopkins University Press, Volume 85, Number 1, Spring 2018, pp. 85-117,
                10.1353/elh.2018.0003</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Gillin, Edward J. (forthcoming),
                “<hi rend="italic">Sound Authorities: Scientific and Musical Knowledge in Nineteenth-Century Britain. </hi>Chicago:
                Chicago University Press, 2021.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Hankins, Thomas &amp; Silverman, Robert,
                <hi rend="italic">Instruments and the Imagination. Princeton: Princeton University Press, </hi>1995.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Jacobus, Mary, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Romantic Things. A Tree, a Rock, a Cloud. University of
                    Chicago Press: Chicago, 2012.</hi></bibl>
            
            <bibl>Kaminsky, Ilya, <hi rend="italic">Deaf Republic</hi>. London:
                Faber and Faber, 2019.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Kittler, Friedrich, <hi rend="italic">Discourse Networks 1800/</hi>1900 (trans.
                Michael Metteer and Chris Cullens). Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1990.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Langan, Celeste and McClane, Maureen N., “The medium of Romantic
                poetry”, in Chandler, James and McClane, Maureen N.
                <hi rend="italic">The Cambridge Companion to Romantic Poetry. </hi>
                Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2008, 239-262.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Larkin, Peter, “Coleridge Conversing: Between Soliloquy and Invocation<hi
                    rend="italic">, The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, Summer, 2007, vol. 38, 3, 2006
                (Summer, 2007), 113-117.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Leighton, Angela, <hi rend="italic">Hearing Things. The Work of
                    Sound in Literature</hi>. Harvard: Harvard University Press, 2018.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Levinson, Marjorie, <hi rend="italic">Thinking Through Poetry: Field Reports on
                    Romantic Lyric</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018.</bibl>
            
            <bibl> Lynch, James, “The Tonality of Lyric Poetry: An Experiment in
                Method,” 1953,
               <ref target="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/00437956.1953.11659470">tandfonline</ref>WORD, 9:3,
                211-224, DOI: 10.1080/00437956.1953.11659470</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Macfarland, Thomas, <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and the Forms of Ruin: Wordsworth,
                    Coleridge and the Modalities of Fragmentation</hi>. Princeton: Princeton
                University Press, 1981.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Mandell, Laura, “Imaging Interiority: Photography, Psychology, and Lyric Poetry”. <hi
                    rend="italic">Victorian Studies,</hi> Indiana University Press, Volume 49, no.
                2, winter 2007, 218-227. </bibl>
            
            <bibl>Mandell, Laura, “What Is the Matter? Or, What Literary Theory
                Neither Hears nor Sees”<hi rend="italic">New Literary History</hi>, Vol. 38, No. 4, Autumn, 2007, pp.
                755-776.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Matheson, Ann, “The Influence of Cowper’s <hi rend="italic">The Task</hi> on
                Coleridge’s Conversation Poems. <hi rend="italic">New Approaches to Coleridge:
                    Biographical and Critical Essays,</hi> ed. Donald Sultana. London: Vision Press,
                1981, 137-50.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Menke, Richard,
                <hi rend="italic">Literature, Print Culture, and Media Technologies, 1880–1900: Many Inventions. </hi>Cambridge:
                Cambridge University Press, 2019.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Morris, G.S., “Sound, Silence, and Voice in Meditation: Coleridge, Berkeley, and the
                Conversation Poems”, <hi rend="italic">Christianity and Literature</hi>, 55.1, 2005,
                51-57.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Ong, Walter, <hi rend="italic">Orality and Literacy: The
                    Technologizing of the Word</hi>. London: Methuen, 1982.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Oswald, Alice <hi rend="italic"
                >Falling</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> Awake</hi>. Jonathan Cape:
                London, 2016.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Potkay, Adam, “Captivation and Liberty in Wordsworth's Poems on
                Music”, “‘Soundings of Things Done’: The Poetry and Poetics of Sound in the Romantic
                Ear and Era”, A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition, ed. Wolfson, Susan. 2008, <ref
                    target="https://romantic-circles.org/praxis/soundings/potkay/potkay.html"
                    >Romantic Circles</ref> This
                essay is developed in Potkay’s 2012 JHUP book, <hi rend="italic">Wordsworth’s
                    Ethics</hi>, Chapter 6, “Captivation and Liberty in Poems on Music” (108-120);
                see also Chapter 5, “Music versus Conscience” (90-107).</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Reilly, Olivia, ‘[A]nother and yet the same’: Rhyme’s Music in
                    <hi rend="italic">Kubla Khan</hi>’,
                <hi rend="italic">Romanticism, </hi>23, 2, 2017, pp.
                149-154.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Shoptaw, John, “Lyric Cryptography” <hi rend="italic"
                    >PoeticsToday,</hi><ref target="https://muse.jhu.edu/article/27810/pdf">MUSE</ref>Volume 21,
                Number 1, Spring 2000, pp. 221-262) </bibl>
            
            <bibl>Sheridan, Thomas, <hi rend="italic">Lectures on Elocution</hi>. London, 1762.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Speitz, Michele, ‘The Wordsworthian Acoustic Imagination, Sonic
                Recursions, and ‘that dying murmur”<hi rend="italic">’, SEL,</hi>
                1500-1900, 55(3):621-646.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Steele, Joshua,
                <hi rend="italic">Prosodia rationalis: or, An essay towards establishing the melody and measure of speech, to be expressed and perpetuated by peculiar symbols. </hi>London,
                1779.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Stewart, Garrett, <hi rend="italic">Reading Voices: Literature
                    and the Phonotext</hi>. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1996. </bibl>
            
            <bibl>Susan Stewart,
                <hi rend="italic">Poetry and the Fate of the Senses. </hi>Chicago
                and London: Chicago University Press, 2002.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Vallins, David, “Coleridge as Talker: Sage of Highgate, <hi rend="italic">Table
                    Talk</hi>”,
                <hi rend="italic">The Oxford Handbook of Samuel Taylor Coleridge, </hi>ed.
                Burwick, Frederick. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2009, 308-322. </bibl>
            
            <bibl>Tkaczyk, Viktoria, “The Making of Acoustics around 1800, or How to Do Science with
                Words”, in <hi rend="italic">Performing Knowledge. 1750-1850</hi>. Berlin: De
                Gruyter, 2015, 27-56, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110421064-003"
                    >DOI</ref></bibl>
            
            <bibl>Voigt, Johann Heinrich, “Observations and experiments in regard to the figures formed
                by sand &amp;c on vibrating surfaces”. <hi rend="italic">Philosophical
                Magazine</hi>, 3, May 1799, 389-96.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Voegelin, Salome, <hi rend="italic">Listening to Noise and Silence: Towards a
                    Philosophy of Sound Art</hi>. London: Bloomsbury, 2010.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Walton, Benjamin and Trippett, David, eds., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nineteenth-Century Opera and the Scientific Imagination</hi>. Cambridge,
                Cambridge University Press, 2019.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Wheatstone, Charles, “Experiments on Audition”,
                <hi rend="italic">The Quarterly Journal of Science, Literature and Art, </hi>24
                (July-December, 1827), 67-72.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Wolfson, Susan, “Sounding Romantic: The Sound of Sound”, “‘Soundings of Things Done’:
                The Poetry and Poetics of Sound in the Romantic Ear and Era”, A Romantic Circles
                Electronic Edition, ed. Wolfson, Susan, 2008, <ref target=" https://romantic"
                    >https://romantic</ref>
                    circles.org/praxis/soundings/wolfson/wolfson.html).</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Wolfson, Susan, Glossary,
                <hi rend="italic">Cambridge Companion to Keats. </hi>Cambridge:
                Cambridge University Press, 2001.</bibl>
        </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
