<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce608</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.599</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Bodleian Library,
                        Eng. Lett. c. 23.  Previously  published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence
                            of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849-1850), II, pp. 157-160 [in part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="599" type="letter">
<head>599. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor
                        Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1801-08-19">19 August
                        1801</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ Grosvenor Charles Bedford
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / Exchequer/ Westminster/
                        Single<lb/>Postmark: B/ AUG 21/ 1801<lb/>Endorsements:
                        19 August 1801; 19 August 1801<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library,
                        Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb/>Previously published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence
                            of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849-1850), II, pp. 157-160 [in part].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> The tone &amp; temper of your letter left me
                    in an uncomfortable mood. certainly I deserved it – but as
                    far as negligence deserves reproof so harsh – but indeed
                    Grosvenor you have been somewhat like the Scotch judge who
                    included all rape robbery <del rend="strikethrough">x</del>
                    murder &amp; horsestealing under the head of sedition<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Robert
                        Macqueen, Lord Braxfield (1722-1799;
                        <title>DNB</title>), who in 1793-1794 presided over the
                        trials and sentencing, in Edinburgh, of radical
                        activists, including Thomas Muir (1765-1799;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Maurice Margarot (1745-1815;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Joseph Gerrald (1763-1796;
                            <title>DNB</title>). Southey may have misunderstood
                        the fine details of Scottish law, under which rape,
                        robbery, murder and arson were all crimes that had to be
                        tried in the highest court.</note> – so have you
                    suspected negligence of cloaking a cold &amp; fickle &amp;
                    insincere heart. dear dear Grosvenor if by any magic of ear
                    you could hear how often your name passes my lips – or could
                    you see how often I see your figure in my walks – the
                    recollections – &amp; the wishes – but what are these? – an
                    hundred times should I have begun a letter if these had been
                    enough to fill it – if I could have sent you the exquisite
                    laugh when I again saw S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Augustine
                    &amp; his load<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably an in-joke dating back to Southey’s and
                        Bedford’s schooldays. ‘St Augustine’ could refer to a
                        fellow ex-pupil at Westminster School (whose nickname
                        drew on either St Augustine of Hippo (354-430) or St
                        Augustine of Canterbury (d. 604)) or to an object
                        (possibly a painting) Southey and Bedford both
                        knew.</note> – or the smile when I read Leanders<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Leander’s’ identity
                        is uncertain. He could be the musician Thomas Leander
                        (d. 1801), whose death at the age of 99 was reported in
                        the London newspapers; see, for example, the
                            <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 20 May 1801.
                        Alternatively, he may have been someone Southey and
                        Bedford had known at Westminster School. If so, the
                        nickname suggests he was a keen swimmer, like the
                        Leander of Greek legend who nightly swam the Hellespont
                        in order to visit his lover. The joke would have had
                        extra resonance as Bedford’s translation of Musæus (fl.
                        c. early 6th century), <title>The Loves of Hero and
                            Leander</title>, had appeared in 1797.</note> death
                    in the newspaper – but these are unwriteable things – the
                    gossip &amp; the playfulness &amp; the boyness &amp; the
                    happiness – I was about to write however – in conscience
                    &amp; truth I was – &amp; for an odd reason. I heard a
                    gentleman imitate Henderson<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly John Henderson (c. 1747-1785;
                            <title>DNB</title>), a famous actor who had spent
                        his early career in Bath.</note> – &amp; there was in
                    that imitation a decisiveness of pronunciation – a rolling
                    every syllable over the tongue, a force &amp; pressure of
                    lip &amp; of palate – that had my eyes been shut I could
                    have half believed you had been reading Shakespeare to me –
                    &amp; I was about to tell you so, because the impression was
                    so strong – </p>
<p rend="indent1"> With Drummond<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The proposal by Wynn that Southey should
                        become Secretary to Sir William Drummond (c. 1770-1828;
                            <title>DNB</title>), classical scholar, poet and
                        diplomat; Charge d’Affaires in Denmark 1800-1801,
                        Minister-Plenipotentiary in Naples 1801-1803 and
                        1807-1808, and Ambassador to the Ottoman Empire in
                        1803.</note> it seems I go not but he &amp; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> design to
                    get for me or try to get a better birth – that of Secretary
                    to some Italian Legation – which is permanent – &amp; not
                    personally attached to the Minister. Amen – I love the
                    South, &amp; the possibility highly pleases me &amp; the
                    prospect of advancing fortunes. To England I have no strong
                    tie – the friends whom I love live so wide that I never see
                    two in a place – &amp; for acquaintance they are to be found
                    every where. thus much for the future, for the present I am
                    about to move to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, who is at the Lakes – &amp; I am
                    labouring somewhat blindly indeed, but all to some purpose –
                    about my ways &amp; means – for the foreign expedition that
                    has restored my health has at the same time picked my pocket
                    – &amp; if I had not good spirits &amp; chearful industry I
                    should be somewhat surly &amp; sad. So I am – I hope most
                    truly &amp; ardently for the last time – pen &amp; inking
                    for supplies &amp; not from pure inclination – I am rather
                    heaping brick &amp; mortar than building – hesitating
                    between this plan &amp; that plan &amp; preparing for both –
                    I rather think it will end in a Romance, in metre Thalaban,
                    in mythology Hindoo – by name the Curse of Kehāma,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">For Southey’s plan for
                        the <title>Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), see
                            <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood
                        Warter, 4 series (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 12-15.
                        This is Southey’s first mention of the switch of title
                        from ‘The Curse of Keradou’. He seems to have made this
                        change in a new draft of Book 1, begun ‘Aug. 15. 1801’,
                        Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and
                        Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of
                        Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727.</note> on which
                    name you may speculate – &amp; if you have any curiosity to
                    see a crude outline – the undeveloped life-germ of the egg –
                    say so – &amp; you shall &lt;see&gt; the story as it is
                    &amp; the poem as it is to be written piecemeal.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Thus then is my time employed – or thus it
                    ought to be – for how much is dissipated by going here &amp;
                    there – dinnering &amp; tea-taking – &amp; suppering traying
                    or eveninging take which phrase of fashion pleases you – you
                    may guess. – you asked me about Thalaba – owing to my
                    absence the printer dirtily enough did not print any large
                    paper copies – whenever a second be printed you shall have
                    one. I stipulated for twelve copies of the poem – of which
                    you of course had one – you will therefore either write
                    “from his schoolfellow &amp; friend” after your own name in
                    it – or wait till I can write it myself. – did you get a
                    second Anthology?<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Annual Anthology</title> (1800).</note> –
                    &amp; moreover now I am on this subject my first Poems<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Poems</title>
                        (1797). Second and third editions had followed in 1797
                        and 1799 and a fourth in 1801.</note> – instead of being
                    sent into the fire – or the bog as they ought, are now a
                    fourth time sent to press – &amp; now large paper copies are
                    manufacturing to suit the second volume – the which of
                    course shall be forwarded to you – </p>
<p rend="indent1"> Grosvenor I perceive no change in myself –
                    nor any symptoms of change – I suffer only in years from
                    what I was – &amp; years make less difference in me than in
                    most men. – all<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> things
                    considered I feel myself a fortunate &amp; happy man – the
                    future wears a better face that it ever has done – &amp; I
                    have no reason to regret that indifference to fortune which
                    has marked the past – By the by it is unfortunate that you
                    cannot come to the sacrifice of one Law Book – my whole
                    proper stock – whom I design to take up to the top of Mount
                    Etna – for the express purpose of throwing him down,
                    straight to the Devil. Huzza Grosvenor – I was once afraid
                    that I should have a deadly deal of Law to forget whenever I
                    had done with it but my brains – God bless them – never
                    received any – <del rend="strikethrough">they</del>
                    &lt;it&gt; purged off as it went in – ran thro like water
                    gruel after jalap<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                        common cathartic drug.</note> – or <del rend="strikethrough">the Sows</del> Doctor Halfpenny
                    Greens Sows julep<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is recalling an event from 1793. For the saga
                        of the Bedfords’ pig and Dr Halfpenny (first name and
                        dates unknown), see Robert Southey and Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford to Nicholas Lightfoot, 27-30 September 1793,
                            <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part
                            1</title>, Letter 59.</note> – &amp; I am as
                    ignorant as heart could wish. the tares would not grow – </p>
<p rend="indent1"> You will direct to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> Cumberland –
                    I set off on Saturday next – &amp; shall be there about
                    Tuesday – &amp; if you could contrive to steal time for a
                    visit to the Lakes you would find me a rare guide. </p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is about
                    leaving London, (where he has been labouring at the
                    Population act<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Census Act of 1800 authorised the first census of
                        1801.</note> – which is <hi rend="ital">his</hi> scheme)
                    – to go as Secretary with Abbot<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Abbot, Lord Colchester
                        (1757-1829; <title>DNB</title>), Chief Secretary for
                        Ireland 1801-1802, The Speaker 1802-1817.</note> to
                    Ireland. he is an excellent fellow &amp; will be a great
                    man. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is off
                    Ireland – scarred I fear sadly in the Copenhagen
                        business,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                        British fleet had destroyed the Danish fleet at
                        Copenhagen on 2 April 1801. Tom Southey had served as a
                        Lieutenant on the <hi rend="ital">Beltona</hi> in this
                        action, and was listed as wounded, e.g. in <title>Bell’s
                            Weekly Messenger</title>, 19 April 1801.</note>
                    which had nearly cost him his life – or his eyes.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> How &amp; where is <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref>?
                    remember me also to <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">your father &amp; mother</ref> as one not unmindful of
                    many happy hours passed under their roof.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have tried to read Pyes Alfred<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry James Pye (1745-1813;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Alfred</title>
                        (1801).</note> – which is insomuch worse than Alfred the
                        Pious<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph
                        Cottle, <title>Alfred, an Epic Poem, in Twenty-Four
                            Books</title> (1800).</note> as it is not bad enough
                    to be ridiculous. If you have not seen the second volume of
                        <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> Lyrical Ballads I counsel you to buy
                    them, &amp; read <hi rend="ital">aloud</hi> the Poems
                    entitled The Brothers, &amp; Michael<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">William Wordsworth,
                            <title>Lyrical Ballads</title>, 2 vols (London,
                        1800), II, pp. 19-45, 199-225.</note> – which especially
                    the first – are to my taste excellent. I have never been so
                    much affected &amp; so well as by some passages there. – I
                    should have liked some opinion of Thalaba from you – some
                    fault-finding – to know if enough interest was excited – or
                    if miracles like pantomime-tricks were so rapid as to weary
                    &amp; satiate.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref>
                        remembrance –</salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs as ever.</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
<lb/>
<date when="1801-08-19">Wednesday. 19 Aug. 1801.</date>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>Yours reached me but yesterday &amp; too late for
                        reply.</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
