<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce499</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.490</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Harry
                        Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas,
                        Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849-1850), II, pp.
                        49–43 [in part]; Adolfo Cabral (ed.), Robert
                            Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal
                            1800–1801 and a Visit to France 1838
                        (Oxford, 1960), pp. 64–65 [in part]; Charles Ramos,
                            The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                            1797–1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp.
                        50–53.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="490" type="letter">
<head>490. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1800-02-18">18 February
                        1800</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond Green/ Surry/
                        Single<lb/>Postmarks: BRISTOL/ FEB 18 1800; B/ FEB 19/
                        1800; [traces of 2 partial, illegible
                        postmarks]<lb/>Watermark: crown and anchor/
                        1796<lb/>Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 49 1800/
                        Robert Southey/ No place 18 February/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 19 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 8 March/ Portugal<lb/>MS: Harry
                        Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas,
                        Austin<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849-1850), II, pp.
                        49–43 [in part]; Adolfo Cabral (ed.), <title>Robert
                            Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal
                            1800–1801 and a Visit to France 1838</title>
                        (Oxford, 1960), pp. 64–65 [in part]; Charles Ramos,
                            <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                            1797–1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp.
                        50–53.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear friend</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> Your last letter entered into an interesting
                    subject. a young man entering the world is exposed to hourly
                    danger − &amp; what more important than to discover the best
                    preservative? to have a friend, dear enough &amp;
                    respectable enough to hold the place of a Confessor, would
                    assuredly be the best, − &amp; if the station of Confessor
                    could always be well filled, I would give up half the
                    Reformation to restore it. In my moments of reverie I have
                    sometimes imagined myself such a character, <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxxx can be more</del> the
                    obscure instrument in promoting virtue &amp; happiness. But
                    it is obvious that more evil than good results from this
                    power being, like all other power, in improper hands. − I
                    have wandered from the subject. it is not likely that I
                    shall ever gain the confidence of my brothers<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
<ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward
                            Southey</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry
                            Herbert Southey</ref>.</note> to the desired extent.
                    whatever affection they may feel for me, a sort of fear is
                    mixed with it – I am more the object of their esteem than
                    love. there has been no equality between us – we have rarely
                    domesticated together, &amp; when that has been the case,
                    they have been accustomed, if they were faulty, to
                    understand my silent disapprobation. No – <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>
                    will never entrust his feelings to me −. &amp; for precepts
                    of warning – indeed I doubt their propriety – I doubt lest
                    from the strange perverting powers of the mind, they should
                    me made minister to temptation. indirect admonition –
                    example – are not these better means? − Feelings almost
                    romantically refined were my preservation − &amp; with these
                    I amalgamated afterwards a Stoical morality. I perceive the
                    seeds of neither in <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> My health fluctuates − &amp; the necessity of
                    changing climate is sadly &amp; sufficiently obvious, lest,
                    tho my disease should prove of no serious danger, the worst
                    habits of hypochondriasm fasten upon me &amp; palsy all
                    intellectual power. I look with anxiety for <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref>
                    letter, &amp; think so much of Lisbon, that to abandon the
                    thoughts would be a considerable disappointment. it would
                    greatly gratify me to see <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>,
                    &amp; I have associations with Lisbon<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> that give me a friendship
                    for the place – recollected feelings &amp; hopes – pleasures
                    &amp; anxieties – all now mellowed into remembrances that
                    endear the associated scenes. But that <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>
                    should approve this is perhaps little probable. a few weeks
                    will decide, &amp; if I do not go to Portugal – I have no
                    choice but Italy. for Madeira is a prison, &amp; the voyage
                    to the West Indies of a terrifying length. this detestable
                    war! if they would make peace upon motives as light as they
                    made war, <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> there would be
                    cause enough because I want to cross from Dover to Calais.
                    it would save me some sea-sickness − &amp; the wealth &amp;
                    blood of the nation in to the bargain.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have busied myself in idleness already on
                    the History of Portugal<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s uncompleted ‘History of
                        Portugal’. Southey proposed to visit: the battlefield of
                        Ourique, where Afonso I (1094–1185; King of Portugal
                        1139–1185) won a decisive victory over the Moors in
                        1139; the Mondego river, which flows through Coimbra;
                        the tomb of Inez de Castro (1325–1355), lover of Pedro I
                        (1320–1367; King of Portugal, 1357–1357), at the
                        Monastery of Alcobaca; and the library of the Oratorian
                        friars at the Convent of Necessidades.</note> &amp; the
                    interest with which this employment will make me visit the
                    field of Ourique, &amp; the banks of Mondego &amp; the grave
                    of Inez. the Indian transactions are too much for an episode
                    &amp; must be seperately related. the manners &amp;
                    literature of the country should accompany the chronological
                    order of events. I should disturb the spiders at the
                    Necessidades &amp; leave no convent library unransacked.
                    should Italy be my destination no definite object of
                    research presents itself. the literature of that country is
                    too vast a field to be harvested by one labourer. the
                    history split into fifty channels – the petty broils of
                    petty states – infinitely perplexed, infinitely
                    insignificant.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> You have heard me mention <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, as one
                    whose society was <del rend="strikethrough">the</del>
                    &lt;my&gt; great motive for taking the cottage at <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>. he is coming
                    to Bristol, to assist me in an undertaking which he proposed
                    &amp; pressed upon me. An essay upon the state of women in
                    society, &amp; its possible amelioration, by means, at
                    first, of institutions similar to the Flemish
                        Beguinages.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman had proposed a system of ‘beguinages’, modelled
                        on lay Catholic communities of women in the Low
                        Countries, in which poor single women could work and
                        live together.</note> you will feel an interest in this
                    subject. I shall be little more than mason in this business
                    under the master architect. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is a man
                    of uncommon talents &amp; knowledge, &amp; political economy
                    has been his favourite study. all calculations &amp; parts
                    requiring this knowledge he will execute – the part intended
                    to impress upon the reader the necessity of alleviating the
                    evil which he sees inforced, will be mine – for <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> would
                    write too strictly &amp; closely for the public taste. you
                    probably know the nature of the Beguinages, they were female
                        <hi rend="ital">fraternities</hi>, where the members
                    were engaged in some useful employment, &amp; bound by no
                    religious obligation. the object is to provide for the
                    numerous class of women who want employment, the means of
                    respectable independance, by restoring to them those
                    branches of business which the men have mischievously
                    usurped, or monopolized when they ought only to have shared.
                    – O what a country might this England become did its
                    governors but wisely direct the strength &amp; wealth &amp;
                    activity of the people! every [MS torn]fession, every trade,
                    is overstocked, there are more adventurers in each than
                    possibly can find employment. hence poverty &amp; crime. do
                    not misunderstand me as asserting this to be the sole cause
                    – but it is the most frequent one. a system of colonization
                    that should [MS torn] an outlet for the superfluous activity
                    of the country would convert this into a cause of general
                    good, &amp; the blessings of civilization might be extended
                    over the desarts, that to the <del rend="strikethrough">gre</del> disgrace of man, occupy so great a part of
                    the world! assuredly poverty &amp; the dread of poverty are
                    the great sources of guilt. want fills our streets with
                    prostitutes, &amp; the dangerous imprudence of early
                    marriage drives many young men to a worse danger. but the
                    country cannot be well regulated where marriage is an
                    imprudence, where children are a burthen &amp; a
                    misfortune.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> A very – very small portion of this evil our
                    plan if established will remove. but of great magnitude
                    seperately considered. I am not very sanguine in my
                    expectations of success – but I will do my best in examining
                    the evil &amp; proposing the remedy. if the plan be not
                    encouraged now, it may hereafter.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I will send you a bundle of the Chatterton
                        proposals<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">For
                        Southey and Cottle’s <title>Works of Thomas
                            Chatterton</title> (1803).</note> when the
                        Anthology<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Annual Anthology</title> (1800).</note> is
                    finished which will be in a few weeks.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<date when="1800-02-18">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 18.
                            1800.</date>
</p>
<p>&lt;<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>
                        desires to be remembered.&gt;</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
