<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce418</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.409</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>British
                        Library, Add MS 47888.  Previously  published: Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 186–189.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="409" type="letter">
<head>409. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>,
                        <date when="1799-05-15">15 May 1799</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/
                            M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ with M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge/ Stowey/ near
                        Bridgewater,/ Somersetshire/ Single<lb/>MS: British
                        Library, Add MS 47888<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 186–189.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="left">
<date when="1799-05-15">Wednesday night. May 15.
                            99.</date>
<address>
<placeName>
<ref target="places.html#Brixton"> Brixton.</ref>
</placeName>
</address>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> Edith I begin to be uneasy at not hearing
                    from you. you know I always scold when you hurt yourself,
                    &amp; now I am angry because I am anxious. you have often
                    told me Edith, that when I am away from you, you fancy all
                    possible accidents &amp; alarm yourself; dear dear Edith if
                    I could but look at you now you should not &lt;think&gt; I
                    felt the least harshness – but indeed disappointment makes
                    me uneasy. perhaps tomorrow will bring me a letter.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> You know <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> is
                    coming to Bristol. now our arrangements are thus. he will be
                    fishing at Hungerford, for you know he likes to be at one
                    end of the stick &amp; string with a maggot at the other. I
                    shall come down by the day coach, pick him up there, &amp;
                    be with him at <ref target="places.html#Westbury">Westbury</ref> on Monday night 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                    of this month. I do not suppose he will stay more than three
                    days &amp; will not perhaps sleep at <ref target="places.html#Westbury">Westbury</ref> all the
                    time. the inconveniences of this are – coming home so late,
                    &amp; bringing him with me when I had rather be alone, but
                    then I shall be home on Monday night instead of Tuesday
                    noon. tell <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref>
<ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony"> Carlisle</ref> is
                    coming down. while <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> is with me he can bed at his sisters I
                    suppose – or perhaps <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> can
                    lodge him. he will be glad to see <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref>,
                    &amp; may talk to him with advantage of his physical views.
                    Edith I count the days like a school-boy. it is Monday week
                    – &amp; now the uncomfortable thought comes across me that
                    you have been so long silent – that perhaps you are ill – or
                    have met with some accident. write – if but a line that I
                    may think of you with pleasure, for think of you I must.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I called on Hamilton<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Critical Review</title>, for
                        which Southey was working, was owned 1793–1804 by the
                        brothers Archibald (fl. 1790s) and Samuel (fl.
                        1790s-1810s) Hamilton.</note> yesterday. there had been
                    an oversight about the 20 <hi rend="ital">£</hi> for which I
                    drew on him. he was not at home when it was presented for
                    payment, &amp; it was sent back to Bristol. <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> had it
                    immediately returned to town, wrote to me, &amp; Hamilton
                    promised it should be taken up immediately. it seems he has
                    now the whole review, having seperated from his brother. I
                    dine there on Tuesday to meet <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref>
                    &amp; Friend. I called on <ref target="people.html#HaysMary">Mary Hays</ref>. she appeared glad to see me, &amp; the
                    conversation of course turned upon <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref>. she told
                    me <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> had
                    behaved very ill to her. The circumstances were these. One
                    evening when her spirits were very much oppressed by some
                    grief, she went on a visit somewhere with <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> &amp;
                    Stephen Weever Browne:<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Stephen Weaver Browne (1769-1832).
                        Southey had met Browne in Norwich in 1798 (William
                        Taylor to Robert Southey, 23 December 1798, J.W.
                        Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings
                            of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2
                        vols (London, 1843), I, p. 236). He was a Norwich
                        clergyman who later became a Unitarian minister and
                        published <title>The Duties of a Christian
                            Minister</title> (1819).</note> a man who<del rend="strikethrough">m</del> you know talks most
                    mightily. from the effort which persons often make when they
                    are depressed, she had talked with a degree of gaiety, so as
                    to exhaust herself. they went home with her, Stephen Brownes
                    talking fatigued her still more, he left her first - &amp;
                    when she came into her lodgings &amp; sat down she burst
                    into tears. <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> was full of expressions &lt;of friendship
                    –&gt; – had she anything on her mind? &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;
                    the following day wrote her a letter full of professions
                    &amp; sentiment &amp; feelings. But <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> tells this
                    story in company with these alterations – that <ref target="people.html#HaysMary">Mary Hays</ref> was in
                    love with him – that she contrived to send away St. Browne
                    that she might be left alone with <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref>, &amp;
                    burst into tears because <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> would not
                    understand her. this was repeated to her, &amp; she wrote to
                        <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref>,
                    rather rallying him for his ridiculous vanity than
                    reproaching him, because it was so contemptible &amp;
                    because she did not fully understand the whole abuse till
                    his reply. he answered by confessing that he had traduced
                    her character – &amp; apologizing most humbly for it,
                    alledging that her principles were so very bad that he had
                    suspected her conduct – yet saying that no one who knew her
                    could doubt her excellence unless he were a fool or a
                    villain. of course she thinks him either the one or the
                    other, nor was it possible for me to justify him – as he
                    evidently has said that she would have prostituted herself
                    to him if he had pleased – &amp; now comes out with a
                    canting repentance. it has sadly sunk him in my opinion. She
                    told me these circumstances because she thought I might hear
                    something of them from him. she spoke with temper &amp;
                    great good sense. you know I like <ref target="people.html#HaysMary">Mary Hays</ref>. About his
                    marriage she blamed him for telling every body that he had
                    no affection for <ref target="people.html#PembertonSophia">Sophia</ref>.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Lloyd had married Sophia Pemberton on 24 April
                        1799.</note> Edith those persons who talk most about
                    their feelings do not feel the most.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I shall only tell <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> that I
                    have seen <ref target="people.html#HaysMary">Mary Hays</ref>
                    &amp; heard that they have disagreed. it is not my wish to
                    enter upon the subject. the intercourse between us, <hi rend="ital">he</hi> will probably drop if he takes
                    orders – &amp; I <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxxx xxxxxx
                        that</del> suspect that will be the end – in that case
                    my consistency will estrange him, &amp; his inconsistency,
                    to use a gentle word, must preclude all esteem on my
                    part.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> On Saturday I am going with <ref target="people.html#HaysMary">Mary Hays</ref> to see
                    Barrys Pictures<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        history painter James Barry (1741–1806;
                            <title>DNB</title>), who had been deprived of his
                        Professorship of Painting and expelled from the Royal
                        Academy in April 1799, shortly after the publication of
                        his controversial <title>A Letter to the Dilettanti
                            Society</title> (1799). Southey possibly went with
                            <ref target="people.html#HaysMary">Hays</ref> to see
                        Barry’s contributions to the Shakespeare Gallery, Pall
                        Mall, London, widely advertised in the London
                        press.</note> – which Taylor the Pagan<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The philosopher and
                        translator Thomas Taylor (1758–1835;
                        <title>DNB</title>).</note> is to show us. my life I
                    understand is likely to be stuck into Phillips’s dirty book
                    of Public Characters.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Phillips (1767–1840; DNB), publisher of
                            <title>Public Characters of 1799–1800</title>
                        (London, 1800), pp. 224–230.</note> for this there is no
                    help – he is a money making fellow who cares nothing for any
                    bodys feelings so he can <del rend="strikethrough">make
                        money</del> &lt;fill his pocket&gt;. however as this
                    must be one must make the best of it, &amp; as there is
                    something to be got by me it had better be got by a friend,
                    so the job will be <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos
                        Cottle’s</ref>, &amp; then there will be no lies, &amp;
                    I can object to any thing objectionable. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> Perhaps you will be amused to hear that there
                    is a man in Bond Street<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A fashionable and expensive area of
                        London, frequented by the wealthy, the aristocratic and
                        their hangers-on.</note> who teaches gentlemen for half
                    a guinea to tie their neckcloths!<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified; possibly someone influenced
                        by – and cashing in on – the dandyism espoused by George
                        ‘Beau’ Brummell (1778–1840; <title>DNB</title>) and his
                        followers.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> If I do not get a letter tomorrow Edith – but
                    my dear dear Edith write to me when you receive this &amp;
                    tell me if you will be at home on the Monday? I shall get
                    over the down by ten o clock I suppose. it is almost supper
                    time – the pleasantest part of the day because the day is
                    nearly over. God bless you. yr Robert Southey.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Remember me to your sister. I think of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Moses</ref>,
                    &amp; shall probably remember him when he has forgotten me.
                    perhaps one of these days. God bless you Edith – if I was
                    not as happy at home as any man can hope to be, I should not
                    &lt;look&gt; forward with such eagerness to my return.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#OpieAmelia">Mrs Opie</ref> &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#HaysMary">Mary Hays</ref>
                    inquired for you.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
