<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce449</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.440</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>University of
                        Kentucky Library.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 26–29 [in part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="440" type="letter">
<head>440. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel
                        Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1799-10-03">3 October 1799</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ S. T. Coleridge/
                        Stowey/ near/ Bridgewater/ Single<lb/>Stamped: EXETER<lb/>MS: University of
                        Kentucky Library<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 26–29 [in part].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<address>
<placeName>Exeter.</placeName>
</address>
<date when="1799-10-03">Thursday. Oct 3. 1799.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> Buonaparte<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon
                        Bonaparte (1769–1821; First Consul 1799–1804, Emperor of the French
                        1804–1814). He was educated at the Brienne military academy and the Ecole
                        Militaire in Paris, and a career officer in the artillery before his rise to
                        power.</note> was remarkably studious, &amp; mathematics his particular
                    study. he associated little or not at all with other officers, &amp; in company
                    was reserved &amp; silent. this is Mrs Keenans<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Mrs Keenan née MacKinnen, wife of John Keenan (fl. c.
                        1780–1819), Irish portrait painter, then living in Exeter. Keenan painted
                        two portraits of Southey.</note> account – to whom I lookd up with more
                    respect because the light of his countenance had shone upon her. Banfill<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Samuel Banfill (fl. 1790s–1830s),
                        partner in a woollen mill at Exwick, near Exeter.</note> tells me that the
                    &lt;mathematical&gt; tutor of Buonaparte is in Exeter, an Emigrant, he says that
                    he was an excellent mathematician – in the military branch chiefly – &amp; that
                    he was always the great man – always the first – always Buonaparte. God bless
                    him – but he disturbs my dreams now for I see no redemption possible!</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Jackson<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">William Jackson
                        (1730–1803; <title>DNB</title>), Exeter-based musician, composer, painter
                        and writer. Suspicions about his ‘loose morals’ were correct. In 1797 he
                        fathered an illegitimate son. Though he had no great opinion of his own
                        paintings, Jackson had exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1771. His
                            <title>Four Ages</title> (1798) was a collection of miscellaneous
                        essays.</note> has taste to a certain extent. he seems to be an old man of
                    loose morals – I hinted this to Kendal,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">William Kendall (dates unknown); author of <title>Poems</title>, published
                        in Exeter in 1793. He was the librettist for William Jackson’s <title>Fairy
                            Fantasies</title> op. 16 (c. 1790).</note> &amp; his reply was that tho
                    Jackson was ever friendly to him he had for some time avoided his society on
                    that account. his music I take for granted. his pictures are always well
                    conceived, the creations of a man of genius – but he cannot execute – his trees
                    are like the rustic work on a Porters Lodge – sea-weed landscapes –
                    cavern-drippings chiselled into ramifications, cold – cramp – stiff – stoney. I
                    thank him for his “Four Ages”, a man with a name may publish such a book – but
                    when a book is merely a lounging collection of scraps – the common place book
                    printed one wishes it to hold more than half an hours turning over. a little
                    turtle soup &amp; a little pine apple – but one wants a huge bason of broth
                    &amp; plenty of filberts. his daughter<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Jackson (c. 1760–1807). In 1806 she married the painter, John Downman
                        (1750–1824; <title>DNB</title>).</note> is <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> a perfect Succubus – Beelzebubina showing her face without a
                    mask. I soon talkd of Bampfylde,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The poet
                        John Codrington Warwick Bampfylde (1754–1796; <title>DNB</title>) spent the
                        last twenty years of his life in an asylum. William Jackson’s projected
                        edition of Bampfylde’s poetry never appeared. Southey published three of
                        Bampfylde’s sonnets and his ode ‘To the River Teign’ in <title>Specimens of
                            the Later English Poets</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), III, pp.
                        434–437.</note> &amp; Jackson rose in my esteem for he talkd of him till I
                    saw the tears. I have copied one ode in imitation of Grays Alcaic<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Gray (1716–1771; <title>DNB</title>),
                        whose alcaic ‘Written in the Album of the Grande Chartreuse’ (1741) provided
                        the inspiration for Bampfylde’s ode ‘To the River Teign’.</note> – &amp;
                    nineteen Sonnets. after I had done Jackson required a promise that I would
                    communicate no copy – as he was going <del rend="strikethrough">them</del> to
                    publish them – &amp; more, that I had not seen. he read me the Preface. it will
                    tell you what a miraculous Musician Bampfylde was – &amp; that he died insane –
                    but it will not tell you Bampfyldes history.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> His wish was to live in solitude &amp; write &amp; play. from his
                    farm-lodging near Chudleigh, often would he come to town in winter, before
                    Jackson was up, &amp; Jackson is an early riser – ungloved – open breasted –
                    with a pocket full of music, or poems, to know how he liked them. his <hi rend="ital">friends</hi> plague on the word – his relations I mean, thought
                    this was a sad life for a man of family, so they drove him to London. poor
                    fellow said Jackson – there did not live a purer creature – &amp; if they would
                    have let him alone he might &lt;have&gt; been alive now. in London his feelings
                    took a wrong course &amp; he paid the price of debauchery.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> His sixteen sonnets<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">John
                        Codrington Warwick Bampfylde, <title>Sixteen Sonnets</title> (1778).</note>
                    are dedicated to Miss Palmer,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary
                        Palmer (1750–1820) was the niece and heiress of the painter Sir Joshua
                        Reynolds (1723–1792; <title>DNB</title>). On inheriting Reynolds’s estate,
                        she married Murrough O’Brien, 5th Earl of Inchiquin and 1st Marquess of
                        Thomond (1726–1808), who quickly ran through her fortune.</note> now Lady
                    Inchiquin, a neice of Sir Joshua Reynolds. her he was madly in love with.
                    whether Sir J. opposed the match on account of Bampfyldes own irregularities in
                    London, or of the hereditary insanity I know not. but this was the commencement
                    of his madness. on being refused admittance at Sir Joshuas, he broke the windows
                    – &amp; was taken to Newgate! Some weeks after Jackson unknowing of what had
                    passed went to London, &amp; enquired for Bampfylde. Lady B. his mother<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Jane Bampfylde (1720–1789), wife of
                        Sir Richard Warwick Bampfylde, 4th Baronet (1722–1776).</note> – said she
                    knew little of him – she had got him out of Newgate – he was in some beggarly
                    place. where? in King Street Holborn she believed but did not know the number.
                    away went Jackson &amp; knockd at every door till he found the right. it was a
                    miserable place. the woman of the house was one of the worst class of women in
                    London. she knew B. had no money &amp; that he had been then three days without
                    food. Jackson found him with the levity of derangement. his shirt collar – black
                    &amp; ragged – his beard a two months growth. he said he was come to breakfast –
                    &amp; turnd to a harpsichord in the room literally he said to let B. gorge
                    himself without being noticed. he took him away – gave his mother a severe
                    lecture &amp; left him in decent lodgings &amp; with a decent allowance,
                    earnestly begging him to write. he never wrote. the next news was his
                    confinement &amp; Jackson <del rend="strikethrough">he</del> never <del rend="strikethrough">seen</del> &lt;saw&gt; him <del rend="strikethrough">seen</del> more. Almost the last time they <del rend="strikethrough">saw</del> met, he shewed him several poems, among others a ballad on the
                    murder of David Rizzio<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">David Rizzio
                        (1533–1566; <title>DNB</title>), an Italian courtier of Mary Stuart
                        (1542–1587; Queen of Scotland 1542–1567; <title>DNB</title>). He was stabbed
                        to death in the Queen’s presence at Holyroodhouse Palace, Edinburgh.</note>
                    – such a ballad! says J. he came to J. to dinner &amp; was asked for copies. I
                    burnt them was the reply. you did not seem to like them – &amp; I wrote them to
                    please you – so I burnt them. After twenty years confinement his senses
                    returned, but he was dying in a consumption. he was urged by his Apothecary to
                    leave the house in Sloane Street, where he was well treated – &amp; go into
                    Devonshire. your Devonshire friends will be very glad to see you. he immediately
                    hid his face – No Sir said he – they who knew me what I was, shall never see me
                    what I am.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Kendall improves on acquaintance. he is the best of translators –
                    I have seen some dozen sonnets from the Italian, &amp; in the regular
                        rhymes.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">William Kendall (dates
                        unknown). His <title>Poems</title> (Exeter, 1793), pp. 49–60 contained 12
                        sonnets using ‘<hi rend="ital">Italian</hi> rhythm’ (p. 4).</note> I
                    compared them line by line with the originals – there was no variation of
                    thought whatever – &amp; yet they read like originals. a passage of Tasso<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Torquato Tasso (1544–1595), Italian poet,
                        best known for his epic, <title>Jerusalem Delivered</title> (1580).</note>
                    bore the same test.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Yesterday we dined with <ref target="people.html#HucksJoseph">Hucks</ref>. today we dine with Banfill. of the Keenans I see much. I have
                    now lying on the table a book of her drawing the insects &amp; flowers &amp;
                    trees of the West Indies, with descriptions<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Mrs Keenan was a sister of Daniel MacKinnon (1767-1830),
                        whose <title>Tour through the British West Indies</title> was reviewed by
                        Southey in <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 50–56.</note> –
                    lent me for Madoc. she walks with her husband like <ref target="people.html#WordsworthDorothy">Miss Wordsworth</ref>. when they
                    visit the North of Devon I shall direct them to you. they are worth knowing –
                    &amp; I leave Exeter with some reluctance on their account. Keenan is a fine
                    painter, a man of genius who wants only to be known to stand high in his
                    profession.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">My Mother</ref> came last night – we
                    go on Monday. our direction is <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>
                    near Ringwood. Eliza<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably <ref target="people.html#Frickerfamily">Eliza Fricker</ref>.</note> is well –
                    &amp; I suspect you mistook the disorder. I will write to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>. our loves – &amp;
                    make <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Moses</ref> laugh again.
                    but for Gods sake keep him from the Madman!</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent2"> R.S. </signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
