<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce578</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.569</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849-1850), II, pp.
                        131-135; Adolfo Cabral (ed.), Robert Southey:
                            Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800-1801 and a
                            Visit to France 1838 (Oxford, 1960), pp.
                        149-150 [in part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="569" type="letter">
<head>569. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1801-02-21">21 February
                        1801</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M. P./ 5. Stone Buildings/
                        Lincolns Inn/ London<lb/>Stamped: LISBON<lb/>Postmark:
                        FOREIGN OFFICE/ MR/ 14<lb/>Endorsement: Feb 21/
                        1801<lb/>MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849-1850), II, pp.
                        131-135; Adolfo Cabral (ed.), <title>Robert Southey:
                            Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800-1801 and a
                            Visit to France 1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp.
                        149-150 [in part].</note>
</head>
<opener>My dear Wynn</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> Your letter gave me the first detail of the
                    great news.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William
                        Pitt (1759-1806, Prime Minister 1783-1801, 1804-1806;
                            <title>DNB</title>) resigned as Prime Minister on 16
                        February 1801, mainly over the refusal of George III to
                        agree to any measures to relieve the civil disabilities
                        on Roman Catholics. The fall of his ministry was also
                        expected to pave the way for peace with France.</note> a
                    passage of four days <del rend="strikethrough">xxxx</del>
                    made it as fresh as possible &amp; we are here cursing winds
                    &amp; water that we must wait a fortnight before another
                    mail can reach us.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> What will happen? the breach is made &amp;
                    this lath &amp; plaister cannot long keep out the weather.
                    Will the old administration be strong enough to force their
                    plans upon the crown? possible. equally so that the art of
                    alarming in which they were so proficient may now be turned
                    successfully against them. Yet on this point, the whole body
                    of opposition is with them, &amp; the whole intellect of the
                    country. I rather expect after more inefficient changes the
                    establishment of opposition – &amp; peace. the helm requires
                    a strong hand.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Decidedly as my own principles lead to
                    toleration I yet think in the sufferance of converts &amp;
                    proselytism it has been carried too far. you might as well
                    let a fire burn or a pestilence spread, as suffer the
                    propagation of popery. I hate &amp; abhor it from the bottom
                    of my soul. &amp; the only antidote is poison – Voltaire
                    &amp; such writers cut up the wheat with the tares. the
                    monastic establishments in England ought to be dissolved. as
                    for the Priests, they will for the most part find their way
                    into France. they who remain should not be suffered to
                    recruit &amp; would soon die away in peace. I half fear a
                    breach of the Union<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Union between Great Britain and Ireland, which came
                        into effect on 1 January 1801.</note> – perhaps an<del rend="strikethrough">xx</del>other rebellion in that
                    cursed country. alas – that earthquakes &amp; volcanos
                    cannot be inoculated!</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I do not purpose returning till the year of
                    my house-rent be compleat, &amp; shall then leave Lisbon
                    with regret. in spite of English house-comforts &amp; the
                    all-in-all happiness of living among old friends &amp;
                    familiar faces, <del rend="strikethrough">xxx xxx of</del>
                    this climate so compleatly changes my whole animal being
                    that I would exchange every thing for it. It is not Lisbon,
                    – Italy or the South of Spain or of France would perhaps
                    offer greater inducements if the possibility of a foreign
                    settlement existed.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> On my history<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s uncompleted ‘History of
                        Portugal’.</note> no labour shall be spared. now I only
                    heap marble <del rend="strikethrough">x xxxx</del> the
                    edifice must be erected in England – but I must return again
                    to the quarry. You will find my style plain &amp; short
                    &amp; of condensed meaning. plain as a Doric building<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Believed to be the
                        earliest and plainest style of Greek
                        architecture.</note> – &amp; I trust of eternal
                    durability. The notes will drain off all quaintness. I have
                    no doubt of making a work by which I shall be honourably
                    remembered. You shall see it, &amp; <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsly</ref> if he
                    will take the trouble, before publication. Of profit I must
                    not be sanguine, yet if it attain the reputation of
                    Robertson – than whom it will not be worse, or of Roscoe
                    &amp; Gibbon<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        well-known eighteenth-century historians William
                        Robertson (1721-1793; <title>DNB</title>), <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">William
                            Roscoe</ref> and Edward Gibbon (1737-1794;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> than whom it will
                    assuredly be better, it will procure me something more
                    substantial than fame. – My price for Thalaba was for 1000
                    copies – 115 pounds. twelve copies being allowed me. the
                    booksellers would have bargained for a quarto edition also,
                    but it would have been illjudged to have glutted the public,
                    &amp; they at least delayed correction. the money is gone to
                    settle my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref>
                    with a Surgeon<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Philip
                        Meadows Martineau (1752-1829), surgeon at the Norfolk
                        and Norwich Hospital and a member of the Martineau
                        family, prominent Unitarians in Norwich.</note> – &amp;
                    thus secure him a useful profession.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I expect in the ensuing winter to be ready
                    with my first volume. to hurry it would be injudicious,
                    &amp; historic labour will be relieved by employing myself
                    in correcting Madoc.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had written a version of <title>Madoc</title>
                        in 1797-1799. He revised it extensively in 1803-1804 and
                        published the poem in 1805.</note> my intention is
                    therefore to journey thro North Wales next summer to the
                    Lakes where <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is settled, &amp; to pass the autumn
                    (their summer) there – for a Welsh map of the roads &amp;
                    what-to-be-seen you must be my director. perhaps too you
                    might in another way assist Madoc, by pointing out what
                    manners or superstition of the Welsh would look well in
                    blank verse. much may have escaped me – &amp; some
                    necessarily must. Long as this poem (from the age of
                        14)<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had
                        completed a prose outline of <title>Madoc</title> as
                        early as 1789.</note> has been in my head, &amp; long as
                    its sketch has now lain by me, I now look on at no very
                    distant date to its publication, after an ample revision
                    &amp; recasting. you will see it &amp; scrutinize it when
                    corrected.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Leoline (the Welsh name is Llewellin &amp;
                    the Latinism is certainly non-descript) – &amp; the
                    Botch-Hayes Episode are gone down the bottomless pool,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Central features of
                        the early draft of Book 12 of <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title>; see Southey to Wynn, 30-[31]
                        December 1800, Letter 563. ‘Botch Hayes’ was Samuel
                        Hayes (d. c. 1795), a master at Westminster School
                        during Southey’s time there. He was renowned for being
                        lax on discipline, so much so that Southey later
                        recorded that pupils used to ‘stick his wig full of
                        paper darts’. Hayes was also a writer of poems and
                        sermons, and co-author of a tragedy,
                            <title>Eugenia</title> (1766).</note> &amp; Thalaba
                    is now a whole &amp; unembarrassed story. the introduction
                    of Laila is not an episode – it is so connected with the
                    murder of Hodeirah &amp; the after actions of Thalaba as to
                    be essentially part of the tale. Thalaba has certainly &amp;
                    inevitably the fault of Samson Agonistes<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Samson
                            Agonistes</title> (1671), a tragic closet drama by
                        John Milton (1608-1674; <title>DNB</title>).</note> –
                    its parts might change place. but in a Romance epic laws may
                    be dispensed with. its faults now are verbal, <del rend="strikethrough">but</del> such as it &lt;is&gt;, I
                    know no poem which can claim a place between it &amp;
                        Orlando.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Orlando Furioso</title> (1532), by the
                        Italian poet Ludovico Ariosto (1474-1533).</note> Let it
                    be weighed with the Oberon<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Christoph Wieland (1733-1813), German
                        poet and author of <title>Oberon</title> (1780).</note>
                    perhaps – were I to speak out – I should not dread a trial
                    with Ariosto. &lt;my&gt; <del rend="strikethrough">his</del>
                    proportion of ore to dross is greater. perhaps the Anti
                    Jacobine criticasters may spark Thalaba; it is so utterly
                    innocent of all good drift; it may pass by the world like
                    Richard Cromwell<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Cromwell (1626-1712, Lord Protector 1658-1659;
                            <title>DNB</title>) returned to England from exile
                        in the 1680s and lived undisturbed under an assumed
                        name.</note> notwithstanding the sweet savour of its [MS
                    obscured] name. Do you know that they have caricatured me
                    between Fox &amp; Norfolk worshipping Bonaparte?<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles James Fox
                        (1749-1806, Foreign Secretary 1782, 1783 and 1806;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Charles Howard, 11th Duke of
                        Norfolk (1746-1815; <title>DNB</title>) were leaders of
                        the opposition Whig group who wished to make peace with
                        France, led by Napoleon Bonaparte (1769-1821, First
                        Consul 1799-1804, Emperor of the French 1804-1814).
                        Southey appears to have been given the wrong
                        information: no such caricature appeared in the
                            <title>Anti-Jacobin</title>.</note> poor me – at
                    Lisbon – who have certainly molested nothing but Portugueze
                    spiders! Amen! I am only afraid my company will be ashamed
                    of me – one at least – he is too good for me – &amp; upon my
                    soul I think myself too good for the other.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The Spanish Ambassador<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Ambassador’s name is not
                        recorded in contemporary reports; he left because Spain
                        was about to declare war on Portugal.</note> truckled
                    off for Madrid this morning – he is a bad imitation of a
                    hogshead in make. All is alarm here – &amp; I sweat in
                    cursed cold weather for my books, creditors alas for many a
                    six-&amp;-thirty! We have two allies more faithful than
                    Austria (the honest [MS torn] Paul the Magnanimous.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Paul I (1754-1801,
                        Tsar of Russia 1796-1801).</note> Famine &amp; the
                    Yellow Fever but the American Gentleman is asleep till
                    summer, &amp; as for Famine she is as busy in England as
                    here. I rejoice in the eventual effects of scarcity – the
                    cultivation of the wastes. the population bill<del rend="strikethrough">s</del>
<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The Census Act became law on 31 December
                        1800 and authorised the first census of 1801.</note> you
                    probably know to be <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> – for which he has long been soliciting
                        Rose,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">George
                        Rose (1744-1818), MP Launceston 1784-1790, Christ Church
                        1790-1818, Clerk of the Parliaments 1788-1801.</note>
                    &amp; the management is his of course &amp; compliment. it
                    is of important utility.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Of the red wines I spoke in my last. Will you
                    have Bucellas as it can be got? it should be kept rather in
                    a garret than a cellar – a place dry &amp; warm. but ample
                    direction shall be sent with it. you may perhaps get <hi rend="ital">old</hi> now, when so just an alarm
                    prevails. <hi rend="ital">new</hi> is better than none –
                    because it will improve even in ideal value should Portugal
                    be closed to England. its price will little if at all differ
                    from Port or Lisbon – it is your vile taxes that make the
                    expence. &amp; by the by I must vent a monstrous curse
                    against the duty upon foreign books – <hi rend="ital">sixpence per pound weight</hi> if bound. it is
                    abominable.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> farewell &amp; God bless you. – I am going
                    next week on my journey – I have again drawn for 40 £. some
                    statement is due to you. My price for Thalaba is gone – I
                    had calculated on a surplus for myself – but there was a
                    deficiency. books have cost me more than would be
                    justifiable were they not a stock in trade &amp; responsible
                    debtors. my expences out run me – but the labour of a year
                    at home will overtake them.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> About Chatterton<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Cottle’s edition of the
                            <title>Works of Thomas Chatterton</title>
                        (1803).</note> – my first job will be to send the
                    edition to press as soon as the number of copies can be
                    ascertained. I hope it may reach 750. for <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Sir Herbert</ref> I
                    shall treat him with severe superiority, &amp; chastise him
                    with <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> unmerciful
                    calmness. About the red haired Xtian<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801), Book 9, lines 616-653, in
                        which a red-haired Christian boy is sacrificed so that
                        poison can be extracted from his dying body.</note> in
                    Thalaba – tis a Turk receipt for poison – but a Turk might
                    have done less certainly. sus-per-col<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">An abbreviation of
                        ‘suspendatur per colum’, Latin for ‘let him be hanged by
                        the neck’; the phrase was written in the calendar of
                        attainted criminals against the name of someone
                        convicted of a capital crime. The red-haired boy was
                        hanged upside down, so he was ‘sus – the other
                        way’.</note> is a blunder of yours he being sus – the
                    other way.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<lb/>
<postscript>
<p>
<date when="1801-02-21">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 21.
                            1801. </date> Lisbon</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
