<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce525</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.516</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Hispanic Society of America, New York.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 61–65 [in
                        part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="516" type="letter">
<head>516. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel
                        Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1800-05-01">[1] May [1800]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: [deletions and
                        readdress in another hand] To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coleridge/ &lt;at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pools&gt;/ <del rend="strikethrough">Stokes
                            Croft</del>/ &lt;Stowey&gt;/ <del rend="strikethrough">Bristol</del>/
                        &lt;Somersetshire&gt;/ Single<lb/>Stamped: LISBON<lb/>Postmark: BRISTOL/ MAY
                        17 1800<lb/>MS: Hispanic Society of America, New York<lb/>Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 61–65 [in
                        part].</note>
</head>
<p>
<date when="1800-05-01">May day. Thursday.</date> Lisbon. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> Here then we are thank God! alive &amp; recovering from dreadfull
                    sickness. I never suffered so much at sea, &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> was worse than I was. we
                    scarcely ate or slept at all. but the passage was very fine &amp; short. five
                    days &amp; a half brought us to our port; with light winds the whole of the way.
                    the way was not however without alarms. on Monday morning between five &amp; six
                    the Captain<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Bayntun Yescombe
                        (1765–1803), Captain of the Falmouth Packet.</note> was awakened with
                    tidings that a Cutter<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">HMS
                            <title>Endymion</title>, a British frigate.</note> was bearing down upon
                    us, with English colours indeed, but apparently a French vessel. we made a
                    signal which was not answered, we fired a gun, she did the same, &amp;
                    preparations were made for action. We had another Lisbon packet in company,
                    mounting six guns – our own force was ten, the Cutter was a match &amp; more for
                    both, but we did not expect to be taken. – you may imagine <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> terror, awakened on a sick
                    bed – disturbed, I should have said, with these tidings! the Captain advised me
                    to <del rend="strikethrough">cov</del> surround her with mattrasses in the
                    cabin, but she would not believe herself in safety there; <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> I lodged her in the cockpit &amp; took my
                    station on the quarter deck with a musket. – how I felt I can hardly tell – the
                    hurry of the scene – the sight of grape shot – bar shot &amp; the other
                    ingenious implements of this sort – the novelty of my fighting – made an
                    undistinguishable mixture of feelings. I was going to fight without any one
                    motive but that of taking my share in the business. my cloaths were of no
                    adequate value to the risk – &amp; they were insured; &amp; if I had had the
                        <del rend="strikethrough">power</del> choice I certainly should far rather
                    have entered Coruña as a prisoner than have proceeded to Lisbon – because four
                    hundred miles land travelling would have been infinitely pleasanter than the
                    continued voyage. the Cutter bore down between us – I saw the smoke from her
                    matches we<del rend="strikethrough">r</del> were so near – &amp; not a man on
                    board had the least idea but than an immediate action was to take place. We
                    hailed her – she answered in broken English &amp; passed on. “tis over! cried
                    somebody. not yet – said the Captain – &amp; we expected she was coming round us
                    or about to attack our comrade vessel. She was English however, manned chiefly
                    from Guernsey, &amp; this explained her frenchified language. you will easily
                    imagine that my sensations at thus ending the business were very definable – one
                    honest simple joy – that I was in a whole skin! I laid the musket in the chest
                    with considerably more pleasure than when I took it out. I am glad this took
                    place – it has shown me what it is to prepare for action.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Four years absence from Lisbon have given every thing the varnish
                    of novelty – &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">yet</del> this with the revival of
                    old associations makes me pleased with every thing. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> – poor Manuel<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Manuel Mambrino (dates unknown), a Spanish
                        servant from Oviedo who worked for Herbert Hill. Mambrino had accompanied
                        Southey on some of his travels in Spain and Portugal in 1795–1796.</note>
                    too is as happy as man <del rend="strikethrough">could</del> &lt;can&gt; be to
                    see me once more – here he stands at breakfast &amp; talks of his meeting us at
                    Villa Franca – &amp; what we saw at this place &amp; at that – &amp; hopes that
                    wherever I go in this country he may go with me. It even amused me to renew my
                    acquaintance with the fleas, who opened the campaign immediately on the arrival
                    of a foreigner. We landed yesterday, about ten in the morning, &amp; took
                    possession of our house the same night. our house is very small &amp; thoroughly
                    Portuguese, little rooms all doors &amp; windows, odd but well calculated for
                    coolness. from one window we have a most magnificent view over the river, Almada
                    Hill, &amp; the opposite shores of Alentejo, bounded by hills about the
                    half-mountain height of Malvern –. the bed room is of a good size. in this
                    climate seperate beds are necessary. I did not know this till I saw two
                    prepared. – to day is a busy day – we are arranging away our things – &amp;
                    seeing visitors. these visits must all be returned – then ends the ceremony –
                    &amp; then I may chuse retirement. I hurry over my letters for the sake of
                    feeling leisure to begin my employments. the voyage by depriving me of all rest
                    &amp; leaving me too giddy to sleep well, will with the help of the fleas break
                    me in well for early rising. the work before me is almost of terrifying labour.
                    folio after folio to be gutted – &amp; the immense mass of collateral knowledge
                    which is indispensable. but I have leisure, &amp; inclination – <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> who has been looking half her
                    time out of window, has just seen – “really a decent looking woman.” this will
                    show you what cattle the passers-by must be. she has found out that there are no
                    middle aged women here – &amp; it is true – like their climate it is only summer
                    &amp; winter. their heavy cloaks of thick woollen like horsemen coats in
                    England, amuse her in this weather – as much as her clear muslin would amuse
                    them in an English winter. but the most ridiculous thing is a substitute for a
                    close-stool up in the garret – it is so high that I am obliged to sit like a boy
                    just breeched with my feet resting upon the cross-bar between its legs. not a
                    drain or sink in the house! all <hi rend="ital">all</hi> goes into the street –
                    but especial care will I take to have it laid at my neighbours door. tis a
                    damned Portugueze trick &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> tis but their
                    due to give them the filth they oblige me to make.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Thalaba<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> will soon be finished. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is my plenipotentiary with
                    the booksellers for this. pray send me your plays<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably <title>The Piccolomini, or the First Part of
                            Wallenstein, a Drama in Five Acts. Translated from the German of
                            Frederick Schiller by S. T. Coleridge</title> (1800) and <title>The
                            Death of Wallenstein. A Tragedy in Five Acts. Translated from the German
                            of Frederick Schiller by S. T. Coleridge</title> (1800).</note> – direct
                    them to the <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                        Herbert Hill</ref>. Chaplain to the British forces. Lisbon. to the care of
                        Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Yescombe. Falmouth. Yescombe is very friendly &amp;
                    will bring them cost free. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncles</ref> name will carry them ashore unexamined. the inner paper may
                    bear my name. – I got your letter<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge’s letter of [10] April 1800, E.L. Griggs, <title>The Collected
                            Letters of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</title>, 6 vols (Oxford, 1956–1971),
                        I, pp. 585–586.</note> at Falmouth. your fleaing Croft<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge had offered to intervene in Southey’s
                        public argument with Herbert Croft over Thomas Chatterton (1752–1770;
                            <title>DNB</title>), by giving Croft ‘a scourging that shall flea him’
                        (E.L. Griggs, <title>The Collected Letters of Samuel Taylor
                            Coleridge</title>, 6 vols (Oxford, 1956–1971), I, p. 585); see Robert
                        Southey to Joseph Cottle, [c. 20 April 1800], Letter 514.</note> may do good
                    by preventing the matter from being forgotten. for the Anthology<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably the proposed, but unexecuted, third
                        volume of the <title>Annual Anthology</title>. Coleridge had contributed to
                        the second volume, published in 1800.</note> – I am willing to weigh all
                    your objections. here I shall have no time for trifles. Thalaba finished all my
                    poetry instead of being wasted in rivulets &amp; ditches shall flow into the
                    great Madoc-Missisippi river.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s
                        Welsh-American revisionist epic <title>Madoc</title> was not published until
                        1805.</note> I have with me your volume – Lyrical Ballads Burns &amp;
                        Gebir.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge,
                            <title>Poems</title> (1797); Coleridge and Wordsworth, <title>Lyrical
                            Ballads</title> (1798); an unidentified edition of Robert Burns
                        (1759–1796; <title>DNB</title>); and Walter Savage Landor,
                            <title>Gebir</title> (1798).</note> read Gebir again – he grows upon
                    me.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncles</ref> Library is admirably
                    stocked with foreign books. the collections he has of Portugueze chronicles
                    &amp; books connected with that single subject could not be purchased here for
                    less than forty pounds. my plan is this – immediately to go thro the chronicles
                    in order &amp; thus make a skeleton of the narrative. the timbers put together,
                    the house may be furnished at leisure. it will be a great work, &amp; worthy of
                    all labour.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey never completed his
                        planned ‘History of Portugal’.</note> – I am interrupted momently by
                    visitors – like the fleas, infesting a new comer! <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> spirits are mending – a
                    handfull of roses has just made her forgive the stink of Lisbon – &amp; the
                    green peas, the ranges &amp;c &amp;c <del rend="strikethrough">with</del> are
                    reconciling her to a country for which Nature has done so much. we are
                    transported into your Midsummer – your most luxuriant midsummer – plague upon
                    that heart-stop that has reminded me that this is a voyage of prescription as
                    well as of pleasure, but I will get well &amp; you must join us &amp; return
                    with us over the Pyrennes – &amp; a little of the Dream must be fullfilled! –
                    God bless you. write to me &amp; some long letters – &amp; send me your
                    Christobell &amp; your Three Graves, &amp; finish them on purpose to send
                        them.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge finished neither
                        ‘Christabel’ (published in 1816) nor ‘The Three Graves’ (published in
                        1809).</note>
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love – I reach a long arm
                    &amp; shake hands with you across the seas.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey. </signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
