<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce540</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.531</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>.  Not previously published.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="531" type="letter">
<head>531. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles
                        Danvers</ref>, <date when="1800-06-15">[15 June
                        1800]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Danvers/
                        9 – S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> James’s Place/ Kingsdown/
                        Bristol<lb/>Stamped: FALMOUTH<lb/>MS: British Library,
                        Add MS 30928<lb/>Published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        104–108 [dated ‘June 1800’]; Adolfo Cabral
                        (ed.), <title>Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in
                            Portugal 1800–1801 and a Visit to France
                            1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp. 99–100 [in part;
                        dated [c. 15] June 1800].<lb/>Dating note: The letter is
                        dated from Southey’s reference to finishing the tenth
                        book of <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>, which was
                        completed on 15 June 1800, see British Library, Add MS
                        47884.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> I have an especial Postman to Bristol,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Rundell (first name
                        and dates unknown) travelled to Portugal with Southey.
                        He was possibly a member of a prominent Bath family of
                        silversmiths, jewellers and surgeons.</note> &amp;
                    leisure only for one letter, to which you have most claim.
                    On Thursday last we saw the long looked for procession of
                    the Body of God – I give the English name that I may not
                    throw a Portugueze cloak over the naked nonsense of
                    blasphemy. The Pix is empty in all other processions, <del rend="strikethrough">it</del> in this it contains the
                    wafer – So it was the Real Presence. on the preceding night
                    the streets thro which it is to pass are cleaned &amp;
                    strewn with sand – the most miraculous thing I have ever yet
                    witnessed of the Host. the houses are hung with crimson
                    damask from top to bottom. they <del rend="strikethrough">houses</del> are high, very handsome &amp; perfectly
                    regular, &amp; the Street rather longer than Redclift
                    Street. The Soldiers lined the way, their new uniforms were
                    put on &amp; their appearance very respectable. every window
                    &amp; balcony was crowded, the Portugueze were all in full
                    dress, &amp; of the finery of Portugueze full dress you can
                    have but very inadequate ideas. not a jewel in Lisbon but
                    was displayed; rainbows &amp; peacocks are
                    Quaker-comparisons. The banners of the city &amp; its
                    various corporate trades led the way – I never saw banners
                    so clumsily carried. they were stuck out with rods instead
                    of being suffered to play freely, &amp; wave with the wind
                    &amp; roll out their beauties in light &amp; shade. sticks
                    were stuck at right angles in the poles to carry them by;
                    nothing could be more awkward or more laborious for the
                    bearers; they were obliged to walk <hi rend="ital">round</hi> the first, some backwards like lobsters,
                    others crabsideling along, &amp; all toiling with a waste of
                    exertion. Then came a champion in compleat armour, carrying
                    a flag. I pitied him, the armour was a heavy load, &amp; the
                    attitude painfull, both hands holding the flag, so that his
                    horse was led. I saw S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> George also, who
                    followed him. a wooden <hi rend="ital">Portugueze</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> George – his legs stiff striding like
                    the notch of a bootjack, a man walking on each side to hold
                    him on by the feet. He lives in the Castle, &amp; on his way
                    to this procession calls at the Duke of Cadavals,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Miguel Caetano Alvares
                        Pereira de Melo, 5th Duke of Cadaval (1765–1806).</note>
                    where they dress his hat with all the jewels of the family.
                    on his return he calls again &amp; leaves them. When the
                    late King<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Jose I
                        (1714–1777; King of Portugal 1750–1777).</note> was
                    dying he had S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> George put to bed to
                    him. he sent for all the Saints in Lisbon &amp; a palace
                    full there was, but the consultation produced no effect.
                    –</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Scarcely any part of the procession was more
                    beautiful than a number of fine led horses, their saddles
                    covered with rich emblazonments. the brotherhoods then
                    walked, an immense train, red cloaks &amp; grey cloaks out
                    of number, &amp; all the friars. some few of these indeed
                    were “more fat than friars beseemed,”<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly an adaption of
                        James Thomson (1700–1748; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Castle of Indolence</title>, Canto 1,
                        stanza 68, line 1, ‘A bard here dwelt, more fat than
                        bard beseems’.</note> but there were some that filled me
                    with respect &amp; pity. Old men, grey bearded, thin as
                    austerity could make old age, so pale – so hermit-like – of
                    such a bread &amp; water appearance, that of their sincerity
                    no doubt could be entertained. They quite made me melancholy
                    to see uprightness of intention &amp; energy so misapplied.
                    tho temperate for June the day was hot, &amp; I pitied the
                    shaven heads glistening under the fierce noon sun. their
                    breviaries – their hands – handkerchiefs &amp; cowls were
                    held up ineffectually, two years ago some of their people
                    are said to have died, struck by the sun, in this
                    procession. At that time an accident <del rend="strikethrough">prove</del> happened which gave the
                    Irish friars an opportunity to show they had not degenerated
                    in a foreign land. A stranger dropt with a <hi rend="ital">coup de soleil</hi>. he was dead to all appearance, the
                    Irish friars got him <del rend="strikethrough">at their
                        church</del> &amp; carried him off to be buried. the
                    coffin is always kept open during the service, &amp; before
                    it was finished the Man moved. What do you suppose the Wild
                    Hunies did? they could not bury him then they agreed – but
                    they locked him in the church instead of sending for
                    assistance. the next day the man was dead enough &amp; they
                    finished their job.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The concluding part was wonderfully fine. the
                    Knights of the various order, the Patriarchal Church,
                    dressed most superbly, the nobles &amp; the Ugly
                        Prince,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John VI
                        (1767–1826; King of Portugal 1816–1826), Prince Regent
                        1799–1816.</note> all following the Wafer. I never saw
                    ought finer than this – nor indeed to be compared with it.
                    the crowd close<del rend="strikethrough">d</del> behind –
                    the music – the blaze of the<del rend="strikethrough">x</del> dresses – the long street thronged – flooded
                    with people. Had this been well managed it would have been
                    one of the finest imaginable sights, but they moved so
                    irregularly &amp; with such gaps that it was a long
                    procession broken into a number of little pieces. it ought
                    also to be seen with Catholic eyes, not with the eyes of a
                    philosopher. I hate <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxx</del>
                    this idolatry as much as I despise it, for I know the bloody
                    &amp; brutalizing spirit of popery. Next day S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Anthony had a puppet-show. two Negro Saints
                    carried by Negroes formed the most striking feature. they
                    made me smile by reminding me of old Flavell,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Flavell (c. 1630–1691;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Whole Works of the
                            Rev. Mr. John Flavell</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1799), I, p. xx.</note> &amp; what black Angels they
                    must make. In the course of conversation upon these
                    procession I said to a Lady who remembered the Auto-da-fes,
                    how dreadful the day of one of those damnable sacrifices
                    must have been to the English residents. no, she said, not
                    at all. it was like these raree-shows expected as a fine
                    sight, &amp; the English by whose window the procession
                    passed, kept open house, as now &amp; gave entertainments.
                    the execution was at midnight indeed – but they ought to
                    have shut up their houses. no English eyes ought to have
                    seen any part of so cursed a spectacle. I never pass the
                    Inquisition, quiet as it is, without longing to join a mob
                    in as glorious a day as the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of
                        July.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Bastille was stormed on 14 July 1789, marking the
                        beginning of the French Revolution.</note> – What is it
                    that has put a stop to these barbarities? I cannot
                    satisfactorily discover. the court is as bigotted as madmen
                    &amp; folly can be – the mob as unenlightened as ever –
                    &amp; the circumstance of Pombal<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Sebastiao Jose de Carvalho e Melo,
                        Marquis of Pombal (1699–1782; Prime Minister of Portugal
                        1750–1777). He abolished public autos-da-fé and the
                        power of the Inquisition to inflict the death penalty in
                        1774.</note> having checked them, would after his
                    disgrace <del rend="strikethrough">xxxx</del> &lt;only&gt;
                    have been &lt;a&gt; motive for reviving them. I imagine that
                    it is the effect of Infidelity – that the cold water of
                    scepticism has put out their fires – God grant – for ever!
                    the higher Priests are – must be – infidels – so are the
                    nobles chiefly. perhaps Voltaire<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Francois-Marie Arouet (1694–1778),
                            <title>Candide, ou l’Optimisme</title> (1759),
                        Chapter 6, contained a famous account of an auto-da-fé
                        held after the Portuguese earthquake of 1755.</note> has
                    saved many a poor Jew from these Catholic bonfires.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Our Bristol man here has done his native
                    place no credit.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly William Stephens (dates unknown), a
                        warehouseman in Wine Street, Bristol, who was in Lisbon
                        at this time; see Robert Southey to Charles Danvers, 2
                        May 1800, Letter 518.</note> he received a leg of mutton
                    from Falmouth – it was very fine, &amp; by an effort of
                    generosity he gave it away – but at the same time sent a
                    message – that when they had done with it he should be
                    obliged to them to send him back what was left. – I pick up
                    a number of half-acquaintance here. here is a gentleman of
                        Cardiff<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified; but possibly a member of one of the
                        Bacon, Crawshay or Homfray families, who played crucial
                        roles in the iron industry in Merthyr Tydfil, South
                        Wales.</note> who knows <ref target="people.html#MaberGeorge">Maber</ref>, &amp;
                    whose brother has the great iron works at Merthyr. he knows
                    all the Welch acquaintance of my boyhood. &amp; I have found
                    the Liverpool man who gave me an invitation in the
                    Southampton stage this time twelvemonth.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified, but possibly
                            <ref target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">John
                            Theodore Koster</ref>, who had a home in
                        Liverpool.</note> &amp; here is a <del rend="strikethrough">Lady</del> girl here who knows
                    Charlotte Smith<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte Turner Smith (1749–1806; <title>DNB</title>),
                        poet and novelist.</note> &amp; has seen <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwin</ref> &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#HaysMary">Mary Hays</ref>
                    &amp;c &amp;c – a fine lively good natured girl with a head
                    brimfull of brains.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary
                            Barker</ref>.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> My spirits continue very good. otherwise I am
                    very little better – but this is a great point, &amp; must
                    wholly be owing to climate. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> has been
                    thrice in a great mob – commonly called <del rend="strikethrough">xx xxxx</del> a private assembly –
                    &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">x xxx some</del> she liked
                    them well enough to stay cruelly late. we speedily move to
                        <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref>. you will
                    continue to direct here – from my other friend I only hope
                    letters – from you I expect them with certainty. – today I
                    finished the tenth book of Thalaba. you shall have the four
                    last on their way to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> as soon as they are written – &amp; I mean
                    to go on galloping. our love to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> D. I
                    wish we could transport her here, our Sunday-window would
                    afford her ample amusement. When the Alfred<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Cottle,
                            <title>Alfred, An Epic Poem, in Twenty-Four
                            Books</title> (1800).</note> comes I wish <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> would
                    send me three or four quires of the paper on which the
                        Anthology<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Annual Anthology</title> (1800).</note> is
                    printed – the same as my copy of Thalaba is written on – I
                    have not quite enough to finish it – &amp; besides I may
                    perhaps bring home half another poem.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you –</salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs truly</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>We send <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> letter to you, not knowing where to
                        direct it. another Packet! &amp; a letter from <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>. I
                        have not yet heard from <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>. remember me to <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> – I will
                        soon write to him. but it is an expence of time &amp; I
                        am avaricious.</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
