<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce554</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.545</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos,
                            The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                            1797–1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp.
                        58–61.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="545" type="letter">
<head>545. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1800-09-01">1 September
                        1800</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond Green/ Surry/
                        Single<lb/>Postmarks: FOREIGN OFFICE POST/ SE/ 19/ 1800;
                        P.P./ 1800; [partial] 4 o’Clock/ SE/ 180<lb/>Watermark:
                        crown and anchor/ GR <lb/>Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 56/ 1800/ Robert Southey/ Cintra 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> September/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 19 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 30 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
<lb/>MS:
                        Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of
                        Texas, Austin<lb/>Previously published: Charles Ramos,
                            <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                            1797–1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp.
                        58–61.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear friend</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> The Watch &amp; the Books are landed &amp;
                    safe. your letter also has reached me. Our life at <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref> is such as you
                    may imagine – its unvarying employments allow nothing to
                    describe. I lay down my pen or my book, &amp; we walk. is
                    the evening tranquil? for we are living in hurricanes here
                    at present – out we go on burros. sometimes we drop in to
                    tea at <ref target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">Kosters</ref> – rather more often at the Metzeners<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The Metzeners were a
                        prominent family of merchants, long-resident in
                        Portugal, but originally from Germany.</note> – &amp;
                    about once a fortnight I – make up a casino party at the
                    Rooms. oftenest of all the English I visit – &amp;
                    infinitely – infinitely best of all do I like M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Mrs Gonne (dates unknown) was the wife of
                        William Gonne (d. before 1815), the packet agent in
                        Lisbon. Their daughter, Louisa (d. 1830), later became
                        Henry Herbert Southey’s first wife.</note> in the crowd
                    of a Lisbon party you know nobody – but here she has lain
                    in, &amp; we have frequently seen her by herself, nor did I
                    ever see a woman of quicker or better feelings. Chance made
                    me god-father to her child – Daniel Metzener<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Daniel Metzener (1770–fl.
                        1840s), member of the Metzener family of Lisbon.</note>
                    &amp; myself being the only Protestants in the place. A
                    young man of modest merit – Waterhouse<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Waterhouse (dates
                        unknown), English merchant in Lisbon.</note> by name has
                    been <del rend="strikethrough">my</del> the only man with
                    whom I have associated. Koster calls &amp; talks an hour
                    with me whenever he comes down. I thought him rude formerly,
                    he is not so at present – perhaps knowing that he can assert
                    no superiority with me. Of Charlotte Hair<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
<ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> had
                        wished to marry Charlotte Hair in 1797.</note> I see
                    less than ever – the house she inhabits is infested by
                    soldiers, &amp; all those fellows who talk nothing but
                    nonsense, &amp; talk that incessantly, buz about her like
                    flesh-flies. For society I am in a state of mental famine –
                    but Charlotte Hair, with an attention of which I am fully
                    sensible, has this morning sent me Spenser,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Edmund Spenser (1552–1599;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Faerie
                            Queene</title> (1590–1596).</note> &amp; I shall
                    live the next month in Faery Land.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> But first to business. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>
                    still supplies me with money &amp; I have yet had no
                    occasion to apply to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coppendale.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Coppendale (d.
                        1833), <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John
                            May’s</ref> uncle and business partner.</note> be
                    good enough to send ten pounds to <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Charles
                        Biddlecombe</ref> Esq. <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> near Ringwood. it is the years rent at
                        <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> due
                    Michaelmas next, with about surplus enough for an
                    apothecaries bill for my illness there which I could not get
                    in time before our departure. &amp; ten pounds also to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Danvers</ref>. 9. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                    James’s Place. <ref target="places.html#KingsdownParade">Kingsdown</ref> – Bristol. to purchase things for <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> at Bristol
                    of which due directions will be sent, in the parcel that
                    will soon carry <del rend="strikethrough">off</del> over
                        Thalaba.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Islamic romance <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>
                        (1801).</note> mention this as I have no time to write
                    him.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> And now I have a tale to relate which you
                    might doubt if it came from less authentic sources. for
                    thank God these instances of frantic passion are almost
                    unknown amongst Englishmen. A serjeant in the English
                    cavalry quartered at Belem was jealous of his wife,
                    suspecting her to be attached to one who held the same rank
                    in the same regiment. attached to the man she certainly was,
                    but I believe with no other criminality than this mental
                    preference. she was handsome &amp; a very well behaved
                    woman. the man remarkably decent – these are <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref>
                    words. The Husband on account of this jealousy beat his
                    wife. this made the other man so unhappy that he declared
                    his intention of destroying himself. accordingly on Monday
                    last, &amp; after the hour when the Soldiers are punishable
                    if out of quarters, in a taberna, he shot himself &amp; died
                    instantly. at the tidings the Woman came in, in a state of
                    frantic agony. she gathered from the ground the blood &amp;
                    the dust with which it had mingled &amp; swallowed all she
                    could collect. her husband attempted to force her away. she
                    called the Centinel charged him with her husband &amp;
                    threatened to report <hi rend="ital">him</hi> to the Colonel
                    unless he took him into custody. The Centinel foolishly did
                    his military duty – &amp; the Woman no longer prevented, ran
                    to a Well in the barrack yard &amp; leapt down. only
                    solitary confinement &amp; bread &amp; water have prevented
                        <del rend="strikethrough">him</del> &lt;the Husband&gt;
                    from consummating the tragedy by self-murder also. The
                    bodies were not brought to Lisbon for Xtian burial, neither
                    was the savage indecency of driving a stake thro them
                    perpetrated. a grave was dug in the sands at low water, one
                    grave, the Lover &amp; the Wife were laid in it – &amp; the
                    Tagus now flows over them. be sure I shall enquire the spot.
                    only the perversion of strong &amp; good feelings could have
                    occasioned this madness.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I wish to see Branstone<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">James Yorke Bramston
                        (1763–1836; <title>DNB</title>), English Catholic priest
                        in Lisbon 1796–1801; later, a prominent Catholic in
                        England and Vicar-Apostolic of London District
                        1827–1836.</note> – but I cannot. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> is
                    offended with him, &amp; reasonably, for, whether willingly,
                    or because he must join with his fraternity, he has aided
                    &amp; abetted in smuggling some of the dying Protestants. he
                    knows better – yet admit his principles – that error is
                    guilt, &amp; belief salvation – &amp; these are assuredly
                    the tenets of his church – &amp; this death-hunting must be
                    the consequence. tis a detestable superstition, &amp; from
                    the depths of my heart &amp; feelings &amp; understanding, I
                    loathe &amp; abominate it. you did not tell me that Nancy
                        Tonkin<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Ann
                        Tonkin (dates unknown), the daughter of members of the
                        English Factory, Lisbon. Southey had befriended her
                        during his first visit to Lisbon.</note> had embraced
                    it. Is it because she wishes to enter a convent? in that
                    case I think her wish should be indulged. poor gir[MS torn]
                    suffered to retire to a Bedlam of her own choice! – I plan
                    [MS torn] May, of which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Domingos<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">St Dominic (c.
                        1170–1221), born Domingo Guzman, in Castile. Founder of
                        the Dominican friars, he preached extensively against
                        the Albigensian heresy in southern France; the
                        Dominicans were later closely associated with the
                        Inquisition; see <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed.
                        John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849–1850), IV, p.
                        11.</note> shall be the personage, &amp; the Esta[MS
                    torn] the Inquisition the subject. it would delight me to
                    strike one heavy [MS torn] this hydra-headed monster.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> At <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref> we shall not remain much longer. I wait
                    the return of Waterhouse to visit Mafra,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Huge Baroque complex,
                        containing a palace, library, monastery and basilica,
                        built 1717–1735.</note> &amp; spend one day at the
                        Peninha,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                        mountain near Cintra, with a chapel at the
                        summit.</note> &amp; then shall go back to Lisbon that I
                    may get at the Libraries &amp; be warm. in another fortnight
                    I ship off Thalaba the Destroyer for publication. then my
                    head will be clear of all ideas that are not Portugueze. – I
                    have picked up much miscellaneous matter, as a man with open
                    eyes &amp; open ears must do.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have good accounts from my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> of
                    his progress, &amp; visible proofs of it by his improved
                    letter-writing. he begins also to feel some anxiety for the
                    future. on my return I hope to immediately settle – not in
                    London – that air would[MS torn] poison me! but within a
                    walk or a half-crown stage. Hampstead [MS torn] town, in
                    sight of a blade of grass. this will enable him to get on in
                    surgery &amp; have his home with me. the profession which he
                    has chosen as I wished, is the only one to which no
                    objection can be started, &amp; which is of unquestionable
                    utility. He will do well I trust, &amp; rise to that
                    station, for which he is qualified by intellectual rank.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> does not
                    improve in health by change of climate. perhaps in some
                    measure owing to the absence of every friend except her
                    husband. acquaintance enough we have. but I also want one
                    companion to whom every serious thought might be freely
                    communicated – who would see things a little as I see them –
                    feel as I feel, &amp; look upon the great theatre with the
                    same hopes. when I return certainly I shall live upon Bread
                    &amp; butter – sit by the fire all day, &amp; do nothing but
                    talk.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Your information in the last letter will make
                    me tremblingly anxious for [MS torn]hen it shall be time to
                    expect it. – <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> remembrance. </p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &amp; yours!</salute>
<signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<date when="1800-09-01">[MS torn]day Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1. 1800. </date>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
