<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce544</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.535</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Huntington Library, HM 4830
                        .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.),
                            A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late
                            William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London,
                        1843), I, pp. 348–353. [in part; dated 5 July
                        1800].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="535" type="letter">
<head>535. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>,
                        <date when="1800-07-05">5 July[– c. 4 August]
                        1800</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./
                        Surry Street/ Norwich./ Single<lb/>Stamped:
                        [illegible]<lb/>Postmark: A/ AUG 4/
                        1800<lb/>Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 5
                        October<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, HM 4830
                        <lb/>Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.),
                            <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late
                            William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London,
                        1843), I, pp. 348–353. [in part; dated 5 July
                        1800].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<address>
<placeName>
<ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref>.</placeName>
</address>
<date when="1800-07-05">July 5. 1800.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear friend</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> I know not why distance by water should
                    occasion neglect of letter-writing more than distance by
                    land. but my English correspondents have proved the fact to
                    me – &amp; I in my turn, have given you sufficient reason to
                    believe it. We were in Lisbon on May day, look at the date
                    above &amp; pardon &amp; absolve him that doth truly
                    repent.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> First of my health, the immediate object of
                    this emigration. The effect of climate has been what I
                    expected &amp; wished. night seizures I have none. the
                    irregularity of my heart is lessened, not removed, I eat
                    voraciously, &amp; above all enjoy an everlasting sunshine
                    of spirits. Something of this is assuredly owing to the
                    total change of scenery &amp; society, but the climate has
                    been the great cause. In England, summer &amp; winter, I sit
                    by the fire, − I have never seen a fire since our departure
                    from Falmouth. the society here is <del rend="strikethrough">not</del> rather such as would depress than elevate
                        <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> &lt;the&gt; spirits
                    of a man accustomed to freedom of speech &amp; intellectual
                    intercourse. literature here is none, &amp; I am too fond of
                    tranquillity ever to utter a political opinion where <del rend="strikethrough">every</del> a true Catholic
                    uniformity of sentiment prevails. I hunger &amp; thirst for
                    the intercourse of my friends, &amp; yet feel the climate so
                    sensibly, that if only inclination were to be consulted, I
                    should perhaps pitch my tent here, &amp; settle in a country
                    where the will of the sovereign is paramount &amp; the
                    Inquisition consummates the church establishment.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The political situation of Portugal is far
                    more critical than when I last visited it. a foolish treaty
                    with Russia has offended Spain,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Portugal and Russia signed a defensive
                        alliance in 1799 (aimed at France). This annoyed Spain,
                        which had severed ties with Russia after Paul I
                        (1754–1801; Tsar of Russia 1796–1801), though an
                        Orthodox Christian, assumed the title of Grand Master of
                        the Knights Hospitaller, a Catholic order, in
                        1798.</note> the only possible consequence of such a
                    treaty. If it be the intention of Bonaparte to shut us out
                    of the Mediterranean this port will not again be left for
                    the English fleet. we are inclined here to believe Lisbon
                    will be the point aimed at by the Brest fleet: it can make
                    no resistance. the forts are weak, soon silenced, or soon
                    past: the English force very trifling, the city without
                    fortifications. the Spanish forces alone, should the attack
                    be made by land, are equal to the conquest of the country.
                    they are only Spaniards you will say, but they would have
                    only Portugueze for their enemies, &amp; numbers would
                    decide the contest. But it is the fear of Spain for her own
                    tottering government that has preserved this. the
                    revolutionary torrent when let loose will not follow the
                    line of demarcation. The Spaniard is therefore carefull how
                    he sets fire<del rend="strikethrough">d</del> to his
                    nextdoor neighbours house. The folly of irritating Spain by
                    a treaty with Russia, after that Barbarian Paul<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Paul I. Russia did not
                        declare war on Spain, but diplomatic ties were
                        severed.</note> had so absurdly declared war against
                    Spain, was a fine specimen of Portugueze policy, more
                    especially as the Spanish minister who now directs every
                        thing,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Manuel de
                        Godoy y Alvarez de Faria (1767–1851), First Secretary of
                        State 1792–1798 and still the dominant influence on the
                        Spanish government. He was not a Jacobin, but was
                        associated with a pro-French alignment in Spanish
                        foreign policy.</note> is a violent Jacobine, of more
                    zeal than prudence. The solitary Merchantman at sea wishes
                    for the wind that suits his course, whether or no it thwarts
                    fleets &amp; expeditions. I confess that it would please me
                    a great deal better to read the Capture of Lisbon in England
                    than to witness it. &amp; I should carry home the news with
                    very different feelings <del rend="strikethrough">than</del>
                    &lt;from those which&gt; would be excited by an order
                    commanding all English subjects to evacuate Portugal. a long
                    passage in a crowded transport would be a sad <del rend="strikethrough">exchange</del> way of returning
                    after I have planned a journey over the Pyrenees &amp; a
                    visit to Paris.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Time will decide all these chances. perhaps
                    the Income Tax &amp; the campaign in Italy<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The British government had
                        announced the first income tax, to pay for the war with
                        France, in December 1798. France had just won a decisive
                        victory over Austrian forces in Italy at the Battle of
                        Marengo on 14 June 1800.</note> may plead for peace in
                    England. meantime I live as comfortably as if no earthquake
                    were brooding under my feet, literally &amp; metaphorically.
                    it is just a week since we removed here for the summer, − to
                    a spot the most delightfull I have ever known. I am daily
                    acquiring knowledge for the History of the Kingdom – my
                    materials for the Literary History of Both countries,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s uncompleted
                        ‘History of Portugal’ and literary history of Portugal
                        and Spain.</note> will, except the translations, be
                    compleat when I return, &amp; the miscellaneous information
                    which my eyes &amp; ears pick up will swell into a volume.
                    in autumn, when the weather will permit, I shall begin my
                    travels, &amp; visit the whole of the country. literary
                    habits &amp; employments make some amends for the want of
                    society, I go among the English no more than civility
                    demands, &amp; always return to my books with a better
                    appetite.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The strangest novelties here are a
                    mail-coach. &amp; paper money. the history of both
                    characteristic of the statesmen. <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxx</del> the mail coach is priced so highly, that a
                    single person may go to Porto (the road it runs) in a chaise
                    somewhat cheaper. time only therefore is saved, for it
                    actually travels an English mail pace, 8 miles an hour. but
                    this high price excludes the main body of travellers from
                    profiting by the speed, &amp; the little dealers must still
                    jog backward &amp; forward on their mules. this therefore
                    will not last long. no vehicle can run <hi rend="ital">profitably</hi>, faster than the usual posting pace of
                    the country. this is a royal undertaking. Immediately upon
                    issuing the paper money, they set the example of discounting
                    it: Only half the [MS obscured] you pay is a legal tender,
                    the consequences are <del rend="strikethrough">xxx
                        xxxxxxxx</del> a progressive depreciation, &amp; an
                    advance in price upon every article. they chose to pay the
                    Sailors in paper, &amp; when these fellows found out what
                    they lost by it, they rioted &amp; shouted Bonaparte<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte
                        (1769–1821; First Consul 1799–1804; Emperor of the
                        French 1804–1814).</note> for ever. a name now growing
                    more bug-bearish than ever. pasquinades are common here. the
                    “order-counter order &amp; disorder” caricature of Paul<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Tsar Paul I was
                        obsessed with military drill and issued a new
                            <title>Military Code Concerning the Field Service
                            for Infantry</title> (1796), which was much derided
                        and caricatured.</note> was applied to the Prince,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John VI (1767–1826;
                        King of Portugal 1816–1826), Prince Regent
                        1799–1816.</note> &amp; I saw the other day a Sonnet
                    which was affixed to the Opera house door, recommending
                    transportation for some of the Ministry, &amp; a madhouse
                    for others. a Friar who preached some months ago before the
                    Prince, chose to give him a political sermon, but not in the
                    English fashion. it was a lecture upon the wrong measures he
                    was pursuing. when it was over the Princess<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Princess Charlotte of Spain
                        (1775–1830), wife of John VI, Prince Regent of
                        Portugal.</note> waked her husband &amp; asked him if he
                    had heard what that fellow had been saying. the consequence
                    was an order to confine the Priest to his convent. these are
                    merely bubbles that rise to the stagnant surfac[MS torn]</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I am preparing Thalaba for the press,
                    designing to send it over for publication, &amp; travel home
                    upon its profits in the spring. you never gave me your
                    judgement of <title>Gebir</title>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>
                        (1801); Walter Savage Landor, <title>Gebir</title>
                        (1798).</note> I have [MS torn] me &amp; read it daily
                    with increased astonishment &amp; admiration. of bad poetry,
                    mo[MS torn] divertingly bad both Spain &amp; Portugal
                    furnish me with abundance. I have been much amused with a
                    metrical life of Vieyra the Portugueze painter,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Francisco Vieira
                        (1699–1783), <title>O Insigne Pintor e Leal Esposo
                            Vieira Lusitano</title> (1780).</note> written by
                    himself. the most original mixture of devotion, enthusiasm
                    &amp; vanity I ever met with. A quarto volume, published by
                    the Academy here in compliment to the victories of Maria
                        Theresa,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Idéa de hum Elogio Historico de Maria
                            Theresa Archiduqueza de Austria, Imperatriz Viuva,
                            Rainha Apostolica de Hungria, e de Bohemia, Princeza
                            Soberana dos Paizes Baixos. Escrita em Francez por
                            ***</title> (1781, republished c. 1800). This was a
                        Portuguese translation of Marie-Caroline Murray (fl.
                        1780s), <title>Essai d'un éloge Historique de
                            Marie-Thérese, Archiduchesse d'Autriche,
                            Impératrice-Douairiere, Reine Apostolique de Hongrie
                            &amp; de Bohême, Princesse Souveraine des Pys-Bas
                            par M. M. ***</title> (1781). The translator was
                        Teresa de Mello Breyner, Countess of Vimieiro
                        (1739-after 1798), a leading light in the foundation of
                        the Academy of Sciences of Lisbon in 1779. Teresa de
                        Mello Breyner was a great admirer of Maria Theresa
                        (1717–1780; ruler of Austria 1740–1780), and by
                        establishing parallels between her and Maria I
                        (1734-1816; Queen of Portugal 1777-1816) wished to
                        address the question of power exercised by women. The
                        editors are extremely grateful to Dr Maria Castanheira
                        for this information.</note> furnishes me some
                    incomparable specimens for a chapter upon the absurdities of
                    literature, which <del rend="strikethrough">will</del> make
                    &lt;no&gt; <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxxxxxx for the</del>
                    no inconsiderable part in an historical account of
                    Portugueze letters. it abounds with crosses &amp; wheels.
                    &amp; anonymous follies that are to be read across &amp;
                    athwart &amp; all ways from the middle.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Send me <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnetts</ref>
                    direction, &amp; give him mine that I may hear from him
                    sooner, for I much wish to hear from him. R S. with the <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Reverend Herbert
                        Hill</ref>, Lisbon. your letter should reach London on
                    Tuesday, or it loses the weeks mail &amp; the Packet. We
                    have French &amp; Italian news rather earlier than it
                    reaches England by way of Madrid. Berthiers<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis Alexandre Berthier
                        (1753–1815), French commander in the victory over
                        Austria at Marengo on 14 June 1800.</note> victory is
                    felt very heavily here – so much hope &amp; expectation was
                    excited that I hear every body complaining. let me hear from
                    you soon. the arrival of a Packet excites fifty fold more
                    hope &amp; fear than the daily Posts of England. </p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you –</salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<lb/>
<postscript>
<p>I must have some Poem in head when Thalaba is gone –
                        &amp; it will be probably my hexameter Mohammed.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge and
                            Southey’s plan for a jointly-written poem in
                            hexameters on Muhammad (570–632), the Prophet of
                            Islam, did not make much progress. A fragment by
                            Southey was published posthumously in <title>Oliver
                                Newman: a New-England Tale</title> (London,
                            1845), pp. 113–116; and 14 lines by Coleridge in
                                <title>The Poetical Works of S. T.
                                Coleridge</title>, 3 vols (London, 1834), II, p.
                            68. For Southey’s notes for, and early sketch of,
                            the poem see <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed.
                            John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849–1850), IV,
                            pp. 18–20.</note> The necessity of beginning the
                        line with a long syllable seems more hostile to our
                        language than any thing else in the metre. An Iambic
                        must be used there occasionally, or a redundant
                        syllable. I am afraid your Show Eclogue<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">William Taylor, ‘The
                            Show. An English Eclogue’, <title>Annual
                                Anthology</title> (Bristol, 1800), pp.
                            200–210.</note> will be abused for my sake. a
                        hostile hand is at work in the Monthly Review<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of
                            Southey’s <title>Poems</title> (1799) in the
                                <title>Monthly Review</title>, 31 (March 1800),
                            261–267.</note> against me, or the Old Woman of
                        Berkeley must have been more civilly treated. with
                        Thalaba I trust you will be satisfied. it satisfies
                        myself. </p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
