<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce811</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.802</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Huntington
                        Library, HM 4839 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 459-463 [in
                    part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="802" type="letter">
<head>802. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William
                        Taylor</ref>, <date when="1803-06-23">23 June 1803</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/
                        Norwich/ Single<lb/>Postmarks: BRISTOL/ JUN 24 1803; B/ JUN 25/
                        1803<lb/>Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 3 July<lb/>MS: Huntington
                        Library, HM 4839 <lb/>Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 459-463 [in
                    part].</note>
</head>
<p rend="indent1"> I have very long been silent – not because you were so – but
                    because I was bound to say something of reproof to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> in my letter – &amp;
                    that was an unpleasant task. by one phrase in yours, I guess that <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">his Uncle</ref> has enabled him to
                    discharge his debts. I believe it is useless ever to preach frugality to one who
                    has not the principle in his nature. but indeed if <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> involves himself he
                    will find that his relations however much they may wish to relieve him, have not
                    the power. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">his Uncle</ref> would be
                    able if he had no other calls. I work like a negro &amp; difficultly keep even
                    with the world – indeed not even that. his brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has not been fortunate as yet in
                    his profession. he is very generous – but has those sailor-like habits – that
                    let him get what fortune he will – he will never <del rend="strikethrough">be
                        rich</del> &lt;have to share.&gt; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> must be his own friend.
                    Enough he shall have, but if he will not abstain from pleasures – he must not
                    expect to draw upon his friends wants to pay for them. Now this is said too
                    harshly – &amp; do not you show it to him. To what you now say I scarcely know
                    how to answer.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Henry Herbert
                        Southey’s intention to enrol at Edinburgh University in November 1803 to
                        study medicine.</note> he is not yet too old for college graduation – but
                    there is an imprudence in the waste of an apprentice fee, &amp; an unsteadiness
                    in the change – &amp; moreover when he says he has no conscientious scruples –
                    that I take it – means he has no conscience at all about the matter. do not
                    misunderstand me. I who am a believer, &amp; that upon the Socinian – or low
                    Arian ground – were I now at three &amp; twenty with the opinions that I hold at
                    nine &amp; twenty – would chuse the church for my profession – but then I have a
                    deep &amp; silent &amp; poet-feeling. connected with these things, that grows
                        <del rend="strikethrough">&amp;</del> with me &amp; will grow. I do not
                    think <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> mind has any
                    similarity with mine. That he should change I should never have advised – but
                    now that he has written to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">his
                        Uncle</ref> I shall feel no sorrow for the change – tho in truth I believe
                        <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">his Uncle</ref> will advise him
                    to follow his first choice.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Dear <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>
                    – your theology does nothing but mischief.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In a letter to Southey, 21 June 1803 (J.W. Robberds (ed.),
                            <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 456-459), Taylor
                        described how his ‘Who wrote the Wisdom of Solomon?’ attributed authorship
                        to Jesus. The essay appeared in the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 16
                        (October 1803), 221-224.</note> it serves only to thin the miserable ranks
                    of Unitarianism. The regular troops of Infidelity do little harm – &amp; their
                    trumpeters such as Voltaire &amp; Paine,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Paine (1737-1809; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Age of Reason</title>
                        (1794-1795).</note> not much more – but it is such pioneers as
                        Middleton<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Conyers Middleton
                        (1683-1750; <title>DNB</title>), clergyman known for his unorthodox
                        opinions, including denying the historical accuracy of the Old Testament and
                        accounts of miracles by early Christian authors.</note> – &amp; you &amp;
                    your German friends, that work underground &amp; sap the very citadel. that
                    Monthly Magazine is read by all the Dissenters – I always call it the Dissenters
                    Obituary – &amp; here are you eternally mining, mining under the shallow faith
                    of their half-learned, half-witted – half-paid – half-starved pastors. We must
                    not give strong meats to weak stomachs. I have qualms of conscience about it
                    myself. there is poor <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> gone
                    stark foolish because he has been made the friend of the wise – diseased at once
                    with a plethora of vanity &amp; an inanition of knowledge – with all the
                    disposition to destroy himself – only that he cannot muster up courage – &amp;
                    that I suppose he will do at last – in the hope of being talkd of as an instance
                    of neglected genius. Oh that proverb about the pearls &amp; the swine has a
                    great deal more in it than I once imagined!<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Matthew</title> 7: 6.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> It is you then who have delayed the Annual Review?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Taylor had reviewed for <title>Annual Review for
                            1802</title>, 1 (1803).</note> my threshing was finished two months ago.
                    I go to London on Sunday next &amp; will ask Hamilton<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Hamilton (fl. 1790s-1810s), owner of the
                            <title>Critical Review</title> 1799-1804.</note> for that account of
                    Broomholme Priory,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Bromholm Priory, a
                        Cluniac priory near Bacton in Norfolk. Southey’s account did not appear in
                        the <title>Critical Review</title>.</note> which he has used me somewhat
                    uncivilly in not inserting. his application to you – twelve months after I
                    mentioned you to him – <del rend="strikethrough">is</del> almost six months
                    after he applied to me for your direction is very much in character. if he has
                    not lost the article I will turn it over to <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">A Aikin</ref>. it cannot want abridgement –
                    he <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> requested long articles from me because
                    he was short of matter.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Why refashion Drayton?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Michael Drayton (1563-1631; <title>DNB)</title>, poet, whose <title>The
                            Battle of Agincourt</title> (1627) Taylor was modernising.</note> in the
                    first place you could write a better poem than the old Michael. in the next
                    place – instead of making the poets of Elizabeths<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth I (1533-1603; reigned 1558-1603;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> day talk as they do now, you would do better
                    to make the poets under his most gracious Majesty George 3<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">George III (1738-1820, King of Great Britain
                        1760-1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> – talk as they did in Elizabeths day.
                    tis an article in my creed that from the days of John Milton English Poetry has
                    gone on from bad to worse – we have had froth &amp; flummery imposed upon us –
                    contortions of language that passed for poetry because they were not prose,
                    &amp; phrases that have been admired by faith, never being designed to be
                    understood. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>
                    &amp; I have often talked of making a great work upon English Literature – but
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> only lately
                    – &amp; poor fellow he will not do that long I fear – &amp; then I shall begin
                    in my turn <del rend="strikethrough">xxxx</del> &lt;to feel&gt; an old man – to
                    talk of the age of little men &amp; complain like old Ossian.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">James Macpherson (1736-1796;
                        <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of Ossian</title> (1765).</note> by
                    God it provokes me when I see a set of puppies yelping at him, &lt;upon&gt; whom
                    he – a great good-natured mastiff, if he came up to them, would just lift up his
                    leg &amp; pass on. &amp; it vexes &amp; grieves me to the heart that when he is
                    gone, as go he will nobody will believe what a mind goes with him, how
                    infinitely &amp; ten thousand thousand-fold – the mightiest of his
                    generation!</p>
<p rend="indent1"> My stay in London <del rend="strikethrough">I xxxx</del> will be
                    short. I do not mean to be absent from home above a fortnight – &amp; already
                    wish that time was past. if transmigration be the true faith, &amp; our
                    aptitudes determine our destiny, if I be not exalted into my own old owl-eyed
                        Simorgh<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The Simurgh was a fabulous
                        bird in Persian mythology and appeared in <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801), Book 11 as the hero’s guide.</note> – I shall
                    certainly make my appearance in the next post-deluvian world in the shape of a
                    Toad in a stone.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">In popular belief,
                        toads were thought to be able to live for prolonged periods encased in
                        stone.</note>
<ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">My little girl</ref> is so
                    fond of me that I am in a fair way of spoiling her, &amp; young as she is I am
                    sometimes showing her the pictures – when I ought to be reading the book.
                    however I get on. you will like my history<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s unfinished ‘History of Portugal’.</note> – &amp;
                    you will like my Madoc<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had
                        completed a version of <title>Madoc</title> in 1797-1799 and was revising it
                        for publication. It did not appear until 1805.</note> – &amp; if you were to
                    review them – why I should be half an edition the richer man. my poor books make
                    their own fortune but not mine – they get me reputation &amp; I want money – oh
                    if I could find some kind gentleman who has an ambition to be a poet! &amp;
                    would pay me well for writing him up above all the Darwins &amp; Rogers’s &amp;
                        Campbells<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Erasmus Darwin (1731-1802;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Samuel Rogers (1763-1855; <title>DNB</title>) and
                        Thomas Campbell (1777-1844; <title>DNB</title>) were all poets whose work
                        sold very well.</note> of the day!</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Among the odd revolutions of the world you may reckon this – that
                    my politics come nearer M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wyndhams<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">William Windham (1750-1810; <title>DNB</title>), Secretary at
                        War 1794-1801. He was against the Treaty of Amiens in 1802. Windham was MP
                        for Norwich 1784-1802 and Taylor was opposed to his influence in the
                        borough.</note> – than they do William Taylors! </p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you – </salute>
<signed rend="indent2"> R S.</signed>
<lb/>
<date when="1803-06-23">Thursday afternoon. June 23. 1803.</date>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
