<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce661</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.652</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Not previously published.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="652" type="letter">
<head>652. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles
                        Danvers</ref>, <date when="1802-01-26">26 January 1802</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb/>Unpublished.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> You would have heard sooner from me, if <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">my writer of franks</ref> had called
                    sooner. I have bought the tickets, &amp; will send them down by <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">Estlin</ref>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Tickets in the state lottery of 1802.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> We are on the point – indeed in the very act of removal to N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
<ref target="places.html#Strand">35. Strand</ref>. a place not noisier than our
                    present abode, &amp; of more convenience in apartments &amp; situation. we are
                    glad too to leave a house connected with unpleasant recollections. <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> is going to lodge in the
                    same house – a pleasant circumstance at any time – &amp; the more so in the
                    deplorable state of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> spirits.
                    she is exceedingly ill, far worse than I have ever known her, &amp; a<del rend="strikethrough">n</del> total depression of spirits is a part of her
                    disease. I know not what to do – the state of her stomach is so bad that it
                    turns at any prescribed diet or medicine – &amp; she can digest nothing without
                        aperients.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Edith Southey was pregnant
                        with her first child.</note> We have had a comfortless house. our
                        servant<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> has been
                    saved from a putrid fever by <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref>, but she has been confined to her bed or to the house ever
                    since <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mothers</ref> death, &amp; is
                    but just beginning to recover strength. without <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary</ref> I know not what we should have
                    done – &amp; she has had her troubles. <ref target="people.html#Lovellfamily">Old Lovell</ref> has written to me to say he will no longer allow her any
                    thing. an annuity of forty pounds was not much to his sons widow. I have replied
                    – to enquire what he will do for <ref target="people.html#LovellRobertJr">the
                        boy</ref>
<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had a struggle in
                        getting the Lovell family to do anything for Robert Lovell Jnr.</note> –
                    &amp; taken up the duty that he <del rend="strikethrough">does not chuse</del>
                    will not continue to perform. the worst part of the story is to come – I want to
                    be abroad again from a lamentable conviction that it impossible &lt;for me&gt;
                    to enjoy life in England. By day the healthy state of the mind keeps the body in
                    order, but the brother brute as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Francis<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">St Francis of Assisi (1181-1226), whose belief
                        that the human body was meant to carry burdens and to be beaten when
                        refractory, led him to refer to his own body as ‘Brother Ass’.</note> calls
                    him, gets the better by night.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> One of my remedies is change of circumstances – &amp; I shall go
                    for a week to Norwich. Of late I have been much out, uncomfortably &amp;
                    unavoidably. I met <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">Estlin</ref> at
                        Barbaulds.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The home of the writer
                            <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">Anna Letitia
                            Barbauld</ref> and her husband, the Revd Rochemont Barbauld (1749-1808),
                        in Hampstead.</note> it was quite a Presbyterian dinner – a synod.
                        Kentish<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The Unitarian minister John
                        Kentish (1768-1853; <title>DNB</title>).</note> – Joyce<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The Unitarian minister and writer Jeremiah Joyce
                        (1763-1816; <title>DNB</title>).</note> Jervis<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The Unitarian minister and author Thomas Jervis (1748-1833;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> – Belsham.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Unitarian minister Thomas Belsham (1750–1829;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> this led to a dinner with Belsham at Hackney
                    – a good natured man whom doubtless you know. I have a whole legion of
                    acquaintance. all the old acquaintanceships that had been dead &amp; buried
                    these ten years have risen again, &amp; new introductions unavoidably increase.
                    this makes sad havoc of my time, &amp; if I did not read full gallop, &amp; in
                    those quarters of hours &amp; ten &amp; five minutes that are usually idled
                    away, I should literally do nothing. – my newspaper speculation has ended in
                        smoke.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Southey’s plan to
                        write for the <title>Courier</title> and resume contributing poems to the
                            <title>Morning Post</title> (though only 3 of his poems were published
                        in the latter in late 1801).</note> my play is planned &amp; no more.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s projected drama set in the
                        reign of Mary I (1516-1558, Queen of England 1553-1558; <title>DNB</title>),
                        ‘The Days of Queen Mary’; see <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John
                        Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 190-192.</note> my novel
                    exists in idea like an uncreated world in the mind of Platos Deity.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s proposed novel ‘Oliver Elton’; see
                            <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series
                        (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 9-10. Plato (428/7-348/7 BC) believed the
                        physical world consisted of imperfect copies of ideas – the only true
                        reality.</note> Madoc grows slowly.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was revising the fifteen-book version completed in 1799;
                            <title>Madoc</title> was not published until 1805.</note> Kehama<del rend="strikethrough">x</del> stands still – wherefore I shrewdly suspect
                    that what is done is not very good.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had finished drafting Book 1 of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>
                        (1810) on 20 November 1801. He did not begin Book 2 until 4 June
                        1802.</note> if I liked the horse I think he would not stand so long in the
                    stable. meantime I read valiantly &amp; gut folio after folio for all imaginable
                    purposes, but with a main reference to my History.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s uncompleted ‘History of Portugal’.</note> the Red
                    Cross Library<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Dr Williams’s Library,
                        London, established by a bequest from the dissenting minister Daniel
                        Williams (c. 1643–1716; <title>DNB</title>).</note> is the mine from whence
                    I dig my ore. Belsham has given me a Catalogue – Barbauld signs the receipt for
                    the books. <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> also feeds me. I
                    am working at a Collection of old French History in 68 octavo volumes which he
                    lends me, full of good matter.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly
                            <title>Collection Universelle des Mémoires Particuliers Relatifs à
                            l’Histoire de France</title> (1785-1790), published in 67
                        volumes.</note> my own books accumulate. if we were but well these
                    employments would make me very happy.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> All <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes’s</ref>
                    friends are exceedingly mortified &amp; surprized at his astonishing folly in
                    that sneering dedication, &amp; his mad attack upon <ref target="people.html#MoreHannah">Hannah More</ref>.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Beddoes, <title>Hygeia: or Essays Moral and Medical,
                            on the Causes Affecting the Personal State of Our Middling and Affluent
                            Classes</title>, 3 vols (London, 1802-1803), I, ‘Essays on the Means of
                        Avoiding Habitual Sickliness and Premature Mortality’, ‘Essay Second’. The
                        essay began with a ‘Dedication to the Ministers of the Gospel of Every
                        Denomination’, which attacked them for failing to use their influence to
                        minster to the body (health) as well as the mind, and for failing to support
                        Beddoes’s scheme to popularise preventive medicine by distributing cheap
                        tracts of health advice to the poor. Beddoes continued by deriding the
                        influence of ‘holy persons’ such as More: ‘HOLY HANNAH! Cries Horace
                        Walpole. Unless the popes are belied, it is not the first instance of a ———
                        canonised by an infidel’ (p. 5 and n*).</note> booby! he has given pain to
                    none but his friends. his enemies have just cause to triumph. he has injured
                    himself beyond recovery. &amp; his book upon consumption<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Beddoes’s <title>Observations on the Medical and
                            Domestic Management of the Consumptive</title> (1801).</note> – was ever
                    such a pick-pocket type? –</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have something to tell you of <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> – the Methodist.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Cottle had published a pseudonymous satire,
                            <title>The Methodist</title> (1801). It was reviewed as ‘entirely of the
                        ironical kind, and is intended as a severe and biting satire against those
                        who are not Methodists, particularly of the Established Church, and, above
                        all, the Bishops. The author writes in the character of a zealous opposer of
                        Methodists’, <title>British Critic</title>, 20 (September 1802),
                        320-321.</note> you know how he neglected my large paper copies of the first
                    volume of Poems,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Poems</title>
                        (1797).</note> &amp; that he printed twelve just at the time of my return
                    from Portugal.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Grosvenor
                        Charles Bedford, 19 August, 1801, Letter 599.</note> these he has now sent
                    up &amp; with them a bill of £4 – 11 – for the paper &amp; the trouble of
                    striking off. that is 4 – 11 – 0 – for twelve copies of a book for the copy
                    right of which he paid me 30£. Of course I shall not pay him. besides one of the
                    sheets leave all the pages so misplaced as to render the whole good for nothing.
                    the man has taken to faith &amp; renounced good works in earnest.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I see a second volume of Collinss Botany Bay<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">David Collins (1756-1810; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>An Account of the English Colony in New South Wales</title>. The
                        first volume appeared in 1798 and the second in 1802.</note> advertised,
                    &amp; wish myself at <ref target="places.html#DanversKingsdown">Kingsdown</ref>
                    to read it. there however I hope in May to see it. no new books ever fall in my
                    way here. I heard <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davys</ref> introductory
                        lecture.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Davy’s introduction to his
                        ‘Course of Lectures on Chemistry’ had been delivered at the Royal
                        Institution, London, on 21 January 1802.</note> it was truly admirable. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is returned &amp;
                    with him <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Poole</ref>. I find a very useful
                    acquaintance in <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref>, whom I met
                    in Wales. the greatest of book collectors, &amp; the most liberal, for he lends
                    me bundle after bundle, unsolicited, hunting his library for what he thinks may
                    be useful to me. the <hi rend="ital">private</hi> success of Thalaba equals<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>
                        (1801). Southey was correct that the poem’s public success – and sales –
                        were not so great.</note> – or more than equals my own expectation &amp;
                    belief of its merit. I hear characters, &amp; see letters about it of even
                    exaggerated praise. it were well did the sale keep pace with the reputation. It
                    has done as much for the author of Joan of Arc<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s revisionist epic, first published in 1796, had
                        marked him out as an up-and-coming, and very controversial, poet.</note> –
                    as that poem did for a young &amp; unknown writer.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> From Belsham I heard an odd rumour. that the real cause of the
                    frequent adjournments of Parliament was, on a wish in the King to retire
                    altogether from public business – which of course <hi rend="ital">his
                        friends</hi> will not readily agree to. it explains Addingtons
                        language.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Addington
                        (1757-1844; <title>DNB</title>), The Speaker 1789-1801, Prime Minister
                        1801-1804, Home Secretary 1812-1822. Addington was fully supported by George
                        III, though the King was less visible in 1801 as he had suffered a
                        recurrence of the illness that had incapacitated him in
                    1788-1789.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">Corry</ref> &amp; I continue in the same
                    easy intercourse. I shall ask his assistance in getting a situation abroad. the
                    Secretaries of Legation receive 300£ a year. a small income – but I can make it
                    do – &amp; shall accept one – like a reprieve.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> It is doubted whether Governor Wall will be hung.<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">The former acting governor of Goree, Joseph Wall
                        (1737-1802; <title>DNB</title>), was tried on 20 January 1802 for the
                        murder, some two decades earlier, of Serjeant Benjamin Armstrong (d. 1782),
                        whom he had sentenced to 800 lashes for alleged mutiny. He was found guilty
                        and executed on 28 January. For Southey’s later analysis of the case see
                            <title>Letters From England</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), I, pp.
                        97-108.</note> but if he is not the justice of English law must be no more
                    mentioned. the people draw the fair inference &amp; say there is no justice for
                    the rich.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> your numbers are</p>
<lb/>
<p rend="indent2"> 15.177.
                                the
                    quarter</p>
<p rend="indent2"> 588.</p>
<p rend="indent2"> 14.008.
                                  8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> These I bought of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bish<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Bish (fl. 1790-1826), a well-known
                        lottery office-keeper at 4 Cornhill, London.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent4"> In hopes that you might have your wish.</p>
<lb/>
<p rend="indent2"> 2.772.
                                the
                    quarter</p>
<p rend="indent2"> 52.910</p>
<p rend="indent2"> 25.075
                               eights.
                    These of Mr Maddison<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">Mr Maddison (first
                        name and dates unknown), lottery office-keeper in London.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent4"> That his good news might glad ye soon.</p>
<lb/>
<p>The offices are at Charing Cross, next door to each other. the tickets are
                    registered in your name. the whole cost £17 – 6 – 0. the secret hath been duly
                    kept – &amp; so good luck <del rend="strikethrough">to</del> t’ye. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> Our love to <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">Mrs
                        Danvers</ref>. her cushion shall come down with us. remember me to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref>.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you – </salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
<lb/>
<date when="1802-01-26">Tuesday 26. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1802.</date>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
