<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce574</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.565</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Huntington Library, RS 11.  Previously 
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of
                            Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York,
                        1965), I, pp. 237-242.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="565" type="letter">
<head>565. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>,
                        <date when="1801-01-30">30 January–9 February
                        1801</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John
                        Rickman/ 33 Southampton Buildings/ Holburn/ London/
                        Single<lb/>Stamped: LISBON<lb/>Postmark: FOREIGN OFFICE/
                        FE/ 26/ 1801<lb/>Endorsement: Jan. 30 – 1801. –/ Feb. 9.
                        1801<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 11<lb/>Previously
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York,
                        1965), I, pp. 237-242.</note>
</head>
<p>
<date when="1801-01-30">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 30. 1801.
                    </date> Lisbon </p>
<p rend="indent1"> First I must thank you for your agency.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman had arranged
                        for <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801) to be
                        published by Longman and Rees.</note> all the
                    arrangements satisfy me. your overseeing eye would indeed
                    have detected many inaccuracies that escape my hasty one,
                    &amp; in point of correctness the work will suffer by its
                    Bristol printer. the <ref target="people.html#BiggsNathaniel">Conjurer</ref>
                    however will print better than a town craftsman, &amp;
                    slower – by which fault I have leisure to transmit a new
                    half book for the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> – which was
                    before a clumsy piece of patchwork. this business occupied
                    me or you would have heard my acknowledgements by the last
                    packet. As to the “<hi rend="ital">its</hi>” in the first
                    paragraph – you know I attribute no undue importance to
                    trifles – if it seemed wrong to any person – that was reason
                    enough for removing it. had it been a word of sedition I
                    might have fought for it –. And now I have made my
                    alteration, &amp; done with Thalaba, it remains only to
                    spend the money for which I have 115 ways<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was paid £115 by
                        Longman and Rees for <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> – &amp; live in
                    hope of a quick sale &amp; a second edition.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Your two letters arrived by one packet &amp;
                    I had at once the home-politics of a month. you were quite
                    right in preventing <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> quarto-scheme. Alfred ought to cure him
                    of quartos.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph
                        Cottle, <title>Alfred, An Epic Poem, in Twenty Four
                            Books</title> (1800).</note> moreover the short
                    lines of Thalaba in a quarto page would make much such an
                    appearance as I should in one of <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombes</ref> waistcoats. the poem is so utterly
                    innocent of all good principles or useful drift that it may
                    possibly pass quietly thro the world like Richard
                        Cromwell,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard
                        Cromwell (1626-1712, Lord Protector 1658-1659;
                            <title>DNB</title>), returned to England from exile
                        in the 1680s and lived undisturbed under an assumed
                        name.</note> notwithstanding the sweet savour of its
                    fathers name. yet whatever may kindle a young imagination or
                    correct a vicious taste is not altogether useless – &amp;
                    moreover Thalaba may pave the way for Madoc,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had written a
                        fifteen-book version of <title>Madoc</title> in
                        1797-1799, but a revised version was not published until
                        1805.</note> who will be as Jacobinical as heart can
                    wish. meantime my labours are of a species decidedly useful.
                    my literary materials accumulate – &amp; my history<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s unfinished
                        ‘History of Portugal’.</note> is in a state of
                    progression. the 115 pounds were not illy earned, &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> a large part of that sum
                    will be well spent in brick &amp; mortar for the historical
                    building. my plan extends to two quartos – the Indian
                    history forming a seperate third. The first will be ready
                    for publication in the ensuing winter – &amp; the literary
                    history will keep pace with it, the researches for both
                    assisting &amp; relieving each other.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The death of the Marquis Ponte de Lima<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The head of the
                        Portuguese Treasury and former Secretary of State (prime
                        minister) in 1786-1788, Tomas Xavier de Lima Teles da
                        Silva, Marquess of Ponte de Lima (1727-1800), had died
                        on 23 December 1800.</note> is regarded as a fortunate
                    event here. he was an old man, almost superannuated – &amp;
                    miserably negligent of public affairs. the new ministry is
                    hostile to the nobles &amp; fidalgos &amp; therefore
                    popular. they have also promised to remedy the evils of the
                    paper currency, by receiving half in payment – &amp; paying
                    half cash – whereas formerly they <hi rend="ital">took</hi>
                    all specie &amp; <hi rend="ital">gave</hi> all paper. the
                    discount which before was 22 has since fluctuated from 17 to
                    19. – it is singular that a circumstance very similar to
                    this currency existed <del rend="strikethrough">above</del>
                    250 years ago. there was such a want of small coins that the
                    Maltese (now the paper-changers) used to change the larger
                    pieces at a discount. this practice was prohibited – &amp; a
                    coinage gave effect to the prohibition. 1550 under John 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> – <note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John III (1502-1557, King of Portugal
                        1521-1557).</note> The merchants here still look
                    apprehensively towards France, in my judgement with
                    causeless fear, because it is the interest of Spain to
                    prevent the revolution of Portugal, they must not aid in
                    setting fire to the house of Ucalegon.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">In the
                        <title>Aeneid</title>, Book 2, lines 311-312, Aeneas
                        sees the house of Ucalegon, one of the elders of Troy,
                        set on fire by the invading Greeks; ‘Ucalegon’ became a
                        proverbial name for a neighbour’s house that was on
                        fire.</note> because it is not the interest of France,
                    who certainly receives subsidies for respite – the property
                    here lies so much in sterling gold that it is removeable at
                    an hours warning, &amp; of valuable merchandize so much
                    could be shipped as to leave little plunder. besides if a
                    French army were in possession of Lisbon, our fleet would
                    cut off their supplies of food &amp; starve the city. These
                    are strong reasons – but men more acquainted with what is
                    going on, &amp; with the state of the country than I am,
                    apprehend a treaty with France, that the threatened naval
                        league<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        League of the North, formed in 1800, was an alliance of
                        Denmark, Sweden, Russia and Prussia against the British
                        policy of searching neutral ships suspected of trading
                        with France.</note> may be pointed out as a safeguard
                    against our sea-despotism, that a French garrison may defend
                    the river forts against naval hostility, &amp; that English
                    property at Lisbon may go like English property at
                        Leghorn.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">When
                        the French Army occupied the Italian port of Leghorn
                        (Livorno) in June 1796 they sequestered a huge amount of
                        British merchants’ property.</note> certainly the
                    decisive moment is at hand, &amp; certainly so large a body
                    of troops was never before assembled at Perpignan to
                    influence negociation.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Feb<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 5. the Decree
                    respecting the Paper money was made public. it lies before
                    me &amp; you therefore may depend upon the accuracy of my
                    statement. they promise to pay faithfully the 6 per cent
                    interest. that all sums under 100 milreas (about 27 £ only)
                    they will pay half in paper half in cash, all sums above one
                    third cash. the Troops <del rend="strikethrough">xxxx
                        xxxxxx</del> all cash, the Officers two thirds
                    paper.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> crown lands to be sold to redeem the smaller
                    paper &amp; burn it. the rest of the Edict promises to
                    receive all payments half &amp; half, &amp; declares that no
                    favour from the Treasury shall be shown those who do not use
                    the same method. they hope soon to pay all sums half &amp;
                    half – &amp; look on to totally withdrawing the paper from
                    circulation. They have abandoned some stupid schemes of
                    doubling the nominal value of copper after calling it in –
                    of debasing the silver – &amp; also of a Bank – for which
                    there is no foundation in this tottering country. About 120
                    years or rather less under Pedro 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>
<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Pedro II
                        (1648-1706, King of Portugal 1683-1706).</note> a scheme
                    of similar knavery was acted by the crown – they raised the
                    value of money 20 per cent – &amp; paid their debts
                    according to the new reckoning. thus gaining the 1 in 5. the
                    coin still bears the old figures. the milrea exists not
                    &lt;now&gt; as a coin, but what was a milrea still bears the
                    figures 1000, &amp; passes for 1200 – or a quarter-moidore. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> The new Minister Dom (remember the Do<hi rend="ital">n</hi> is Spanish &amp; ignorantly applied
                    to Portugueze) Rodrigo de Sousa Coutinho,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Rodrigo Domingos de Sousa
                        Coutinho, Count of Linhares (1755-1812), had just been
                        appointed head of the Portuguese Treasury. He was also
                        briefly Secretary of State (prime minister), 21 May-23
                        July 1801. The new Secretary of State, appointed on 6
                        January 1801, was Joao Carlos de Braganca e Ligne de
                        Sousa Tavares Mascarenhas de Silva, Duke of Lafoes
                        (1719-1806). The Duke had been President of the Royal
                        Portuguese Academy of Sciences since its foundation in
                        1779. The Academy had proposed a new Portuguese
                        dictionary, but only the volume covering the letter ‘A’
                        had been published in 1793.</note> is said to be a man
                    of talents, &amp; ambitious of literary patronship. on the
                    old Duke de Lafoes’ death he looks on to the Presidentship
                    of the Academy, &amp; already they talk of continuing the
                    Dictionary. the Patriarchal church is rich &amp; ill
                    managed. it is in agitation to take the estates – &amp; pay
                    the church from the crown. it is only the Prince<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">John VI (1767-1826, Prince
                        Regent of Portugal 1799-1816, King of Portugal
                        1816-1826).</note> who saves the rich orders from a
                    similar guardianship, &amp; the poor ones from being limited
                    &amp; reduced &amp; rooted out.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> An introduction to some of the Portugueze has
                    been highly useful to me. I am known for a <hi rend="ital">curioso</hi>, a man busied upon their literature. The
                    Chief Librarian of the Public Library,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio Ribeiro dos Santos
                        (1745-1818), Professor at the University of Coimbra,
                        historian, poet and Director of the Real Publica Corte
                        since its foundation in 1796.</note> a man of rank &amp;
                    of learning has offered me his own very valuable collection
                    – &amp; also his papers. The Sub Librarian<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Agostinho Jose da Costa
                        Macedo (1745-1822), lexicographer and editor.</note>
                    admits me among the mss. I see the Censor reports upon what
                    books are published &amp; what suppressed – &amp; I am now
                    promised access to what public documents are preserved among
                    the archives. the young race of poets are ambitious of
                    showing me their works in hopes of a nich. I only regret my
                    short stay, of which the greater part will be employed in
                    travelling. but for the latter volumes of history another
                    visit to Portugal will be indispensable. We shall return in
                    May, &amp; if a merchant ship is ready, directly for
                    Bristol. The moving cannot be less than 30 guineas, &amp; it
                    can make little difference in what sort of a cabin we are to
                    be sick.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Little seems to be dreaded from the nearest
                    &amp; almost inevitable danger – the yellow fever. it still
                    exists, but these unthinking people fancy it is dead –
                    because it sleepeth. baffling medicine here as it has done
                    in America, it is a dreadful calamity from which Portugal
                    has no possibility of escaping. <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> possibly the rest of Europe may be infected. we
                        <del rend="strikethrough">have</del> shall suffer from
                    the northern league. the neutral ships were the
                    corn-carriers, &amp; our little loaves will be lessened –
                    but not their price. agriculture here never can improve till
                    the tenures be altered. It is so difficult – so almost
                    impossible to alienate lands, that whoever purchases an
                    estate purchases a dozen law-suits with it. the rich
                    merchants therefore never think of retiring &amp;
                    establishing their family upon the graves of poor gentility.
                    the sale of the crown-lands will have some effect in
                    offering them clear tiller. – they have thought &amp;
                    written upon agriculture, as <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> they have written upon many things &amp;
                    thought of more – without the power as yet of practising.
                    the average number of men of information is not perhaps much
                    inferior to what it would be found in England. but they are
                    crushed b[MS torn]sorial boards, &amp; the Inquisition. if
                    these were destroyed [MS torn] if the fiat lux<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">A Latin translation of ‘let
                        there be light’, <title>Genesis</title> 1: 3.</note>
                    were but pronounced – there would be light.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> There is a Frenchman here, the Abbé Du
                        Boys,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> employed upon a history of Brazil
                    for which he has procured important documents. perhaps
                    Manuscripts are no where so common as in Portugal. very many
                    of the adventurers to Asia – &amp; Africa – &amp; America
                    drew up their accounts – they disliked the scrutiny of a
                    Censor &amp; declined publication. libraries rarely descend
                    here – &amp; manuscripts &amp; books go indiscriminately to
                    the shops. if the work be of importance copies of it are to
                    be found. I have one of their most famous poem fairly
                    written – it is about 6000 lines – the Author a mongrel
                    Irish-Portugueze turned monk<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio da Fonseca Soares (1631-1682), a
                        soldier who became a Franciscan friar under the name
                        Antonio das Chagas. The manuscript is possibly
                            <title>Obra Heroica y Tragica</title>, listed as no.
                        3837 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note>
                    &amp; died in sanctity after a twelvemonths penance &amp;
                    discipline for writing this ungodly love story. therefore it
                    was never printed but for three shillings I bought the mss –
                    &amp; there were three other copies at the same price. Books
                    have cost me much – so much that I begin in prudence to
                    think of selling them when my work is done. My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref>
                    destination is no ways disagreable to me. his conscience may
                    digest more easily than mine, &amp; I am at least a saver by
                    the business.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> We wait my <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Uncles</ref>
                    return to commence our long planned ramble. &amp; if the
                    yellow fever do not advance nearer on our return, it is my
                    intention to traverse Algarve &amp; see Spain once more
                    across the Guadiana.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> poor <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos</ref>! – &amp; poor <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph</ref>! – &amp;
                    alas for Alfred the long<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Cottle’s <title>Alfred, An Epic
                            Poem, in Twenty Four Books</title> (1800).</note> –
                    &amp; his most inimitable original similes! I quake for <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> when the
                    reviews come at him – bunglers &amp; blockheads as they are.
                    these books I never see. the Monthly Magazine reaches me. it
                    contains an ill-spelt annunciation of Thalaba<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Monthly
                            Magazine</title>, 8 (November 1800), 807.</note>
                    which probably came from <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George Dyer</ref>. a
                    sort of magazine is just commenced here under the title of
                        Varieties.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> I have sent for it. there is also
                    a sort of periodical Joe Miller<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. a joke book, after John Mottley
                        (1692-1750; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Joe Miller’s
                            Jests, or, The Wit’s Vade Mecum</title> (1739),
                        which purported to be drawn from the sayings of the
                        comic actor Josias Miller (1683/4-1738;
                            <title>DNB</title>) but was actually a compilation
                        of material from earlier joke books. A ‘Joe Miller’
                        became slang for a hackneyed joke.</note> – so the title
                    bespeaks it, called The Convoy of Lies,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">José Daniel Rodrigues da
                        Costa (1757-1832), <title>Comboy de Mentiras, Vindo do
                            Reino Petista Com a Fragata Verdade Encoberta Por
                            Capitania</title> (1801).</note> &amp; it has
                    probably a profitable sale as the author made jokes by the
                    week for 3 years in another work of the same kind.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">José Daniel Rodrigues
                        da Costa, <title>Almocreve de Petas, Ou Moral
                            Disfarçada, para corecçao das Minderas da
                            Vida</title> (1798-1799).</note> reviews exist not
                    here, except the censorial books – which are hidden from
                    profane eyes. these I have seen behind the curtain, &amp;
                    laughed over. the merit or demerit of a book consists in
                    what it says of Portugal &amp; its Priests &amp; its Prince.
                    thus of Murphys book<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">James Cavanah Murphy (1760-1814; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Travels in Portugal</title> (London, 1795),
                        p. 296.</note> – the stupidest compilation that ever
                    blundering Irishman made – an account of a young Franciscan
                    overturning a broth kettle in whispering to a girl was
                    selected for censure – as the ignorance of a foreigner
                    seeing things in a wrong light but scattered compliments to
                    Portugal – &amp; above all the very respectful &amp; highly
                    proper dedication to his Royal Highness<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">John VI (1767-1826, Prince
                        Regent of Portugal 1799-1816, King of Portugal
                        1816-1826).</note> – oh it weighed heavier than all the
                    faults – &amp; made atonement for a quarto full of dullness
                    &amp; blunders.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Ediths remembrance. remember me to Lamb –
                    &amp; the <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">Cancellarius
                        Magnus</ref>.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs truly</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
<date when="1801-02-09">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 9.
                        1801</date>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
