<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce369</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.360</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                        University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published:
                        Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), I, pp. 350–352 [in part]; Charles
                        Ramos, The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                            1797–1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp.
                        40–41.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="360" type="letter">
<head>360. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1798-12-14">14 December
                        1798</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 4 Bedford Square/ London/
                        Single<lb/>Stamped: BRISTOL<lb/>Postmark:
                        DE/15/98<lb/>Watermark: [illegible]<lb/>Endorsement:
                        1798 N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 28/ Robert Southey/ No
                        place 14 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 15 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 5 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>
                        1799<lb/>MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                        University of Texas, Austin<lb/>Previously published:
                        Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), I, pp. 350–352 [in part]; Charles
                        Ramos, <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                            1797–1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp.
                        40–41.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<date when="1798-12-14">Dec. 14. 98.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear friend</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> I am about to send off a great coat to your
                    house for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> journey. he will have <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnetts</ref> to
                    town &amp; from thence must send it back. I should think we
                    may expect him here in the course of three or four days.
                    from <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> I have received no answer yet, which
                    somewhat surprizes me, but he may have left his situation,
                    or been absent from it &amp; so the letter may have followed
                    him or been waiting his return.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> We are enduring something like a Kamtschatkan
                    winter here, I am obliged to take my daily walk, &amp; tho I
                    go wrapped up in my great coat almost like a dancing bear in
                    hirsute appearance still the wind pierces me. we are very
                    deficient in having no face dress for such weather as
                    this.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I am busy upon the Grecian history, or rather
                    it is the employment of all my leisure. the escape of my
                        Pythoness<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Pythia was the title given to the priestess of Apollo at
                        Delphi, who was famous for her prophecies, uttered under
                        the influence of vapours rising from the earth. The
                        priestess was originally always a young virgin, but
                        Echecrates the Thessalian kidnapped and raped the
                        incumbent. After this event, the priestess was always
                        chosen from among old women.</note>
<del rend="strikethrough">mxxx</del> was in the early ages,
                    &amp; they I believe will suit me best. I must have the
                    Pythian games<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Held
                        every four years at Delphi in honour of Apollo.</note>
                    celebrated. for the story I have only invention to trust to.
                    the costume of Greece will be new to the English drama,
                    owing to the defects of our theatre. but I had rather get to
                    some country &amp; some people less known. among the many
                    thoughts that have passed over my mind upon this subject, I
                    have had the idea of grounding stories upon the oppressions
                    exercised at different periods of time upon particular
                    classes of people. the Helots<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">An unfree population tied to the land in
                        parts of Sparta.</note> for instance, the
                        Albigenses,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                        dualist religious movement in southern France in the
                        12th and 13th centuries. Suppressed by Catholic
                        crusades.</note> or the Jews. the idea of a tragedy upon
                    one of the early martyrs has for some years been among my
                    crude plans but it would not suit the stage because it would
                    not suit the times. there is something more noble in such a
                    character than I can conceive in any other, firm to the
                    defiance of death in avowing the truth, &amp; patient under
                    all oppression, without enthusiasm, supported by the calm
                    conviction that this is his duty.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Among the Helots something may be made of the
                    infernal Crypteia,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Spartan boys who had shown great promise in their
                        training were given the opportunity to prove their
                        fighting skills by being sent into the countryside
                        unarmed with instructions to kill any helot they met at
                        night and to take any food they needed.</note> but I am
                    afraid to meddle with a Spartan, there is neither feeling
                    thinking or speaking like one who has been educated
                    according to the laws of Lycurgus.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Lycurgus was the legendary law-giver of
                        Sparta. Among the practices he implemented was the
                        military training of all Spartan boys from the age of
                        seven.</note> Knowledge of human nature is not knowledge
                    of Lacedæmonian nature. the state of slavery among our own
                    countrymen in an early period is better, – the grievances of
                    wardship &amp; the situation of a neif or villain.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Wardship was the
                        medieval system under which feudal lords had rights over
                        their vassals, for example control of minors or the
                        ability to decide who widows or heiresses might marry.
                        ‘Neif’ and ‘villain’ are terms for female and male serfs
                        who were bound to the soil, <title>Common-Place
                            Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series
                        (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 18, 215.</note> dramatists
                    &amp; novelists have ransackd early history, &amp; we have
                    as many crusaders on the stage &amp; in the circulating
                    library as ever saild to Palestine – but they only pay
                    attention to the chronology &amp; not to the manners or mind
                    of the period.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> When do you leave London? &amp; how is your
                    brother Arthur?<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Arthur May, John May’s brother.</note> my letters are
                    very nearly finished.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A second, revised edition of Southey’s <title>Letters
                            Written During a Short Residence in Spain and
                            Portugal</title> was published in 1799.</note> they
                    will be out a fortnight earlier than my Poems<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s two volume
                        collection <title>Poems</title> appeared in 1799: volume
                        one was a third edition of the collection first
                        published in 1797; volume two consisted of poems
                        published previously (though not under Southey’s own
                        name) in the <title>Morning Post</title> and the
                            <title>Monthly Magazine</title> or published for the
                        first time.</note> – shall I send them to you, or keep
                    them till <del rend="strikethrough">you</del> I see you here
                    on your way to town again?</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> desires
                    to be remembered. I am myself not well, towards night my
                    indisposition affects me &amp; induces a very uncomfortable
                    state. </p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
