<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2011-08-15</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="nines">rce882</idno>
            <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.873</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                  1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                  only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                  redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                        Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                  that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                  additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                  all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Huntington Library, RS 48. Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
               (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 243-244 [in part].</p>
            <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
            <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript
               Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
               Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University
               Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
               Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University; the John Rylands Library,
               Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
               Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public
               Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
               Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne;
               the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
            <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the English Department of
               Nottingham Trent University.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Southey’s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
               <category xml:id="people">
                  <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
               <category xml:id="places">
                  <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
            <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
            <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
            <list>
               <item>corrections from proofing</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
            <list>
               <item>Part II added</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="873" type="letter">
            <head>873. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1803-12-23">23 December
                  1803</date>
               <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  <lb/> Endorsement: RS/ Dec 23:/ 1803<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 48. ALS; 4p.<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                  (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 243-244 [in part].</note>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline rend="right">
                  <date when="1803-12-23">Dec. 23. 1803</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Rickman</salute>
            </opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> Some translations from Camoens by a Lord Strangford<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Percy Clinton Sydney, 6th
                  Viscount Strangford (1780-1855; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poems from the Portuguese of Camoens, with Remarks and Notes</title>
                  (1803), reviewed in <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 569-577.</note> have reached me in the course of business,
               &amp; I shall be enabled to make a two guinea job of them if you will send me down by coach the originals in five duodecimo
                  volumes,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Luis Vaz de Cam&#245;es (1524-1580), <title>Obras</title> (1782), no. 3185 in the
                  sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> bound, without any ornament on the backs which is rather unusual for Portugueze books. I
               want this edition &amp; not an unbound one in three volumes<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> which is also
               in your house, because it has more matter &amp; some useful criticism &amp; notes. With them I should be glad also of Mickles
                  Luisad<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">William Julius Mickle, (1734/5-1788), <title>The Lusiad, or the Discovery of India, a
                     Poem</title> (1778), no. 440 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – a quarto in boards – but I am not certain
               whether or no it be in your possession or among the books still at <ref type="m" target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles"
                  >Biddlecombes</ref>, from whom I shall be glad when you have recovered them.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Now as this implies charge &amp; trouble of conveyance to the coach, &amp; as I shall ere long stand in need of another
               supply for better purposes, it may be as well if you have leisure to pack off a parcel per waggon at the same time. In this I would
               have the Chronica del Rey D Joaõ 3.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Francisco de Rades y Andrada (d. 1599), <title>Chronica do
                     Rey D. Joaom o III</title> (1796), no. 3260 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> in four small quartos well bound
               after their manner. Commentarios do Albuquerque<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Afonso de Albuquerque (1453-1515),
                     <title>Commentarios</title> (1774), no. 3165 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> 4 volumes common Spectator size –
               they were in the bookcase to the right of the fireplace. the volumes of that twenty-tomed Historia Genealogica which contain the Provas
               (documents) I forget whether four or six in number, but rather think four.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio Caetano de
                  Sousa (1674-1759), <title>Historia Genealogica de Casa Real Portugueza</title> (1735-1748), no. 3738 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey’s library. There were six volumes of Documents.</note> &amp; for Madoc<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had
                  completed a version of <title>Madoc</title> in 1797-1799 and was revising it for publication. It did not appear until 1805.</note>
               omnia opera<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as ‘all the works’.</note> Sharonica,<note n="10" place="foot"
                  resp="editors">Sharon Turner, <title>History of the Anglo-Saxons</title> (1799-1805) and <title>Vindication of the Genuineness of
                     the Ancient British Poems</title> (1803), no. 2776 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Saxon as well as Welsh,
               with my Pierce Ploughman,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">William Langland (c. 1325-c. 1390; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                     Vision of Pierce Plowman, Nowe the Second Time Imprinted</title> (1550), no. 1414 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                  library.</note> a book which will materially help me to delineate the moral history of Europe before the Maritime Discoveries
               changed every thing. And now that I am on the subject of my books let me mention the few at <ref target="places.html#Dublin"
                  >Dublin</ref> – I do not know Roes<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Richard Baillie Roe (1764/5-1853;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Irish stenographer and writer.</note> direction – <ref type="m" target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George
                  I</ref> can obtain it from <ref type="m" target="people.html#Cottlefamily">Robert Cottle</ref> who is at Hoares the banker<note
                  n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">C. Hoare &amp; Co., a private bank in Fleet St, London, founded in 1672.</note> – &amp; if you
               will write <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> cum potentia frankande<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as
                  ‘With the power of franking’, a jokey reference to Rickman’s privileges as The Speaker’s Secretary.</note> that will be the shortest
               way – &amp; have them sent to you – for I shall not want them here, &amp; my resting place at last must be within reach of some public
               library.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I am about a curious review of the Mission at Otaheite.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed London
                  Missionary Society, <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> (1803) for <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2
                  (1804), 189-201.</note>
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#BurneyJames">Capt Burney</ref> will find his friends rather roughly handled for I look upon them as
               the most degraded of the human species – they have convinced me that Moses went the right way to work with the Canaanites,<note n="16"
                  place="foot" resp="editors">
                  <title>Numbers</title> 21: 34-35; 31: 1-54; 33: 50-52, contains numerous examples of Moses urging the killing of all the
                  Canaanites.</note> &amp; induced me to think it probable that the Spaniards did less evil in Hispaniola<note n="17" place="foot"
                  resp="editors">The aboriginal population of Hispaniola was virtually wiped out by disease in the 16th century.</note> than we
               suppose. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> scheme to mend them is by extirpating the Bread
               Fruit from their island, &amp; making them live – by the sweat of their brows. It always grieves me when I think that you are no friend
               to colonization. my hopes fly farther than yours – I want English knowledge &amp; the English language diffused to the East &amp; the
               West &amp; the South.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Can you get for me the Evidence upon the Slave Trade as printed for the House of Commons?<note n="18" place="foot"
                  resp="editors">
                  <title>An Abstract of the Evidence Delivered Before a Select Committee of the House of Commons: in the Years 1790 and 1791; On the
                     Part of the Petitioners for the Abolition of the Slave Trade</title> (1791).</note> I want to collect all materials for
               speculating upon the negroes. that they are a fallen people is certain – because being savages they have among them the forms of
               civilization. It is remarkable that in all our discoveries we have never discovered any people in a state of progression except the
               Mexicans &amp; Peruvians. that the Otaheiteans are a degraded race is proved by their Mythology which is physical allegory – ergo the
               work of people who thought of physics. I am very desirous to know whether the Negro Priests or Jugglers be a cast – or if any man may
               enter the fraternity; &amp; if they have a sacred language. We must continue to grope in darkness about early history till some
               strong-headed man shall read the hieroglyphics<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Egyptian hieroglyphics were not deciphered until
                  1822.</note> for us. Much might yet be done by comparison of languages. some hundred words of the most common objects – sun moon
               &amp; stars – the parts of the body the personal pronouns – the auxiliary verbs &amp;c if these were collected as occasion could be
               found from every different tribe, such languages as have been [MS obscured]if fluent we should certainly be able to trace to their
               source. In New Holland<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Australia.</note> language is said to be confluent – every tribe – &amp;
               almost family – having its own. but that Island is an odd place – coral above water &amp; coal – new birds beasts &amp; plants, &amp;
               such a breed of savages! it looks like a new country, if one could tell where the animals came from. Do you know that the Dodo is
               actually extinct? having been beyond all doubt too stupid to take care of himself. the learned Shavius<note n="21" place="foot"
                  resp="editors">George Shaw (1751-1813; <term>DNB</term>), <title>The Naturalist’s Miscellany</title> (1793) illustrated a preserved
                  foot of a dodo. Shaw was assistant keeper of natural history at the British Museum.</note> found part of one in the Museum. There is
               no hope of recovering the species unless you could get <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">your friend the
                  bridge-maker</ref><note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman and Telford were at this time members of parliamentary commissions
                  on the Caledonian Canal and Highland Roads and Bridges.</note> to sit upon a ganders egg.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
               <signed rend="indent2"> R.S.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>The Brig<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">The brig-sloop HMS <hi rend="ital">Suffisante</hi>, on which Edward Southey had
                     briefly served.</note> has been so succesful since <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">my Whelp of a brother</ref>
                  left her that his share of prize money, only as a foremast man would have exceeded <hi rend="ital">300</hi> £. so <ref type="m"
                     target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> tells me – who is now first Lieutenant &amp; going out with convoy to the W Indies.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
