<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce561</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.552</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>British
                        Library, Add MS 30928.  Previously  published: Adolfo
                        Cabral (ed.), Robert Southey: Journals of a
                            Residence in Portugal 1800–1801 and a Visit to
                            France 1838 (Oxford, 1960), pp. 129–132
                        [where it is dated [27? October 1800]].Dating note:
                        Dated from internal evidence, especially Southey’s
                        reference to his intention to leave Sintra the following
                        day. The Southeys left Sintra on 28 October 1800.
                    </p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="552" type="letter">
<head>552. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles
                        Danvers</ref>, <date when="1800-10-27">[27 October
                        1800]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ Mr Danvers<lb/>Endorsement:
                        Book 9/ // note 14 –/ line 478/ The gnawing of his 100
                        poison mouths [Another hand adds marginal note: ‘From
                            <title>Thalaba</title>.’ Editors note: The note to
                            <title>Thalaba</title> (1801) described in the
                        endorsement refers to Muslim beliefs about the
                        punishment of the wicked after death. It is taken from
                        George Sale, <title>The Koran commonly called the
                            Alcoran of Mohammed, Translated into English
                            Immediately From the Original Arabic; with
                            Explanatory Notes, Taken From the Most Approved
                            Commentators. To which is Prefixed a Preliminary
                            Discourse</title> (1734), p. 76].<lb/>MS: British
                        Library, Add MS 30928<lb/>Previously published: Adolfo
                        Cabral (ed.), <title>Robert Southey: Journals of a
                            Residence in Portugal 1800–1801 and a Visit to
                            France 1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp. 129–132
                        [where it is dated [27? October 1800]].<lb/>Dating note:
                        Dated from internal evidence, especially Southey’s
                        reference to his intention to leave Sintra the following
                        day. The Southeys left Sintra on 28 October 1800.
                    </note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> I have written five Letters to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref>.
                    the last might not have arrived when you wrote – but four
                    she ought then to have received. I have not neglected her,
                    &amp; hope that both she &amp; you rather suspected the
                    fault to be in the post offices than in me. The circumstance
                    of your receiving a letter a fortnight later than those
                    which were written by the same packet is an instance of
                    their irregularity. moreover <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> is
                    fond of writing by private hands – &amp; as he usually
                    dispatches my letters from Lisbon, some may have miscarried
                    by this insecure conveyance.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The parcel has not reached me, but I believe
                    it is lying at Lisbon. I expect Alfred<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Cottle,
                            <title>Alfred, an Epic Poem, in Twenty-four
                            Books</title> (1800).</note> with that uneasiness
                    &amp; half self-shame that a man always feels at the errors
                    of a friend. a pamphlet – a common volume is launched
                    quietly, &amp; sinks into the pool of oblivion without
                    raising one bubble, or agitating the surface with one
                    circle. but when a quarto splashes in! – <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> has
                    written to me – &amp; tells me his brother <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos</ref> is in a
                    consumption – a disease which I fear will be fatal to the
                    family. A Chaplain of the Prince of Wales, by name Clarke,
                    has announced a history intitled The Progress of Naval
                        Discovery.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">James
                        Stanier Clarke (1765–1834; <title>DNB</title>),
                        clergyman, social climber, domestic chaplain to George
                        IV (1762–1830; Prince Regent 1810–1820; reigned
                        1820–1830) and author of <title>The Progress of Maritime
                            Discovery</title> (1803).</note> he writes a letter
                    to his booksellers <ref target="people.html#CadellThomas">Cadell</ref> &amp; Davies,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The London booksellers and publishers
                            <ref target="people.html#CadellThomas">Thomas Cadell
                            Jnr</ref> and William Davies (d. 1820).</note>
                    containing certain queries which he desires they will send
                    to any literary man whom they may know, at present in
                    Portugal – &amp; they have dispatched it to me with the mans
                    Prospectus. Now this is uncivilly done. If the Prince of
                    Wales’s chaplain wants me to rummage Lisbon for him, he
                    ought to have written himself, when his booksellers had
                    discovered that I was here. besides he is a palpable Puppy,
                    by his prospectus which is full of cant about patronage
                    &amp; his Maecenas<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Gaius Maecenas (70–8 BC), famous patron of the
                        arts.</note> – &amp; embellishments. &amp; the questions
                    he has sent about Portugal <del rend="strikethrough">are</del> betray a miserable ignorance, &amp; what are
                    not ignorant – are childish. however if he understands
                    navigation &amp; geography, that is what his work wants,
                    &amp; the book will be useful &amp; indeed necessary. I
                    shall therefore consider the work &amp; not the workman,
                    &amp; do every thing for him which is to be done.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> We leave <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref> tomorrow, &amp; the exceeding
                    inconvenience of having no books but what I send eighteen
                    miles for, makes me leave it without reluctance. Portugueze
                    scenery suffers less than our colder country by winter; the
                    Cork keeps thro the year its foliage – the olive also – the
                    firs, the orange &amp; lemon trees; the laurel of this
                    country, &amp; the arbutus are all evergreens, I know not
                    whether the mixture of grey boughs among the evergreen woods
                    be not rather a beauty than a winter-scene of nakedness.
                    besides the hills that are brown-burnt in the summer have
                    now a somewhat of grassiness to the eye – &amp; the great
                    aloe is of unchanging magnificence. we lose less than we
                    gain by having an endurable sun, &amp; weather for walking.
                    – Yesterday we went nine miles to see fishermen walk up
                    &amp; down an almost perpendicular rock. one false step
                    &amp; down they go to be shattered upon the rocks or drowned
                    – &amp; yet they scramble for who shall do it – &amp; we
                    went two hours ride for the sake of seeing them &amp;
                    finding ourselves in a most uncomfortable state of
                    apprehension. the rock is shelving &amp; rough – they went
                    bare footed, &amp; fast by the help of hands &amp; that part
                    which is usually of more use in rest than in motion –
                    Kangaroos indeed use their tails also in walking as you may
                    remember. near this place the rock is perforated I know not
                    how. but we lay down &amp; saw a monstrous pit into which
                    the rushing sea smoked up. it was a shuddering feeling – our
                    man called upon Jesu Maria – &amp; crossed himself.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The Indian corn is now drying by every house
                    in yellow &amp; sunshiny patches. the husks of the vintage
                    are also exposed, &amp; the women sifting it to lay by for
                    the porks in winter. they tread the corn by oxen here – on a
                    round pavement like that at Keynsham where the Woad is
                    crushed. – I am planning a ten days ramble northward, with a
                    young man whose sister is married to young Protheroe in Park
                        Row.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">An
                        unidentified member of the wealthy Protheroe family of
                        Bristol, bankers and West Indian merchants.</note> his
                    name Waterhouse.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Waterhouse (dates unknown), an English merchant
                        in Lisbon.</note> I wish he were a Jacobine but he is
                    intelligent, &amp; diffident, &amp; one whose manners I
                    should have liked any where, so that in Portugal he is a
                    very acceptable companion. but as he is lame &amp; I think
                    of trying <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>
                    this trip (where we &lt;shall&gt; rest almost every other
                    night in private houses) – I shall fancy myself quite a man
                    of war in this convoy. our object is to see Batalha &amp;
                    Alcobaca – the two finest monasteries in Portugal – both
                    historical ground. &amp; I have business with a M.SS. at
                        Thomar<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Tomar is
                        the location of a 12th-century castle which contains the
                        Convent of Christ.</note> – a collection of very early
                    Poems, collected by King Diniz.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Diniz (1261–1325; King of Portugal
                        1279–1325). Southey was unable to find the manuscript he
                        was seeking at Tomar.</note>
<del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> there is a Frenchman
                    resident in the town<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Timoteo Lecussan Verdier (1754–1831), Portuguese man of
                        letters and mill-owner, he was of French
                        parentage.</note> who is one of the cleverest men in
                    Portugal &amp; will probably be useful to me. &amp; I know
                    the language well enough to speak fluently upon any subject
                    whatever. grammatical accuracy I care little for – if a word
                    be not ready I make one, &amp; never fail to be
                    understood.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> There are two methods of avoiding military
                    service in this country – by marrying – or by turning Monk.
                    many motives contribute to fill the monasteries – the
                    service of God is easier than military duty, &amp; a fellow
                    boldly defies the World the Flesh &amp; the Devil – who
                    would be confoundedly afraid of the French &amp; Spaniards.
                    besides it is easier to pray than to work, &amp; the Friars
                    are always well fed. abolish these begging orders, the sink
                    of all the idle vagabonds in the kingdom, &amp; the landed
                    Communities will be less absurd &amp; more useful than our
                    Universities. they feed the poor, so as to prevent all
                    poor-rates: they are the only Landlords under whom a man can
                    venture to improve his estate, because not being embarrassed
                    they are not eternally racking their tenants like the
                    nobles. allow them the liberty of coming out &amp; marrying
                    – you have our colleges – with this advantage [MS torn]t the
                    youth of the kingdom is not sent there – to learn nothing.
                    Every convent dresses food daily for the beggars, &amp; all
                    at the same hour to prevent the same person from feeding at
                        <del rend="strikethrough">both</del> &lt;more than
                    one&gt;. but this precaution is ineffectual – they know the
                    difference of clocks to a minute &amp; eat full-gallop that
                    they [MS torn] arrive in time at a second course. These
                    landed orders are supplied from the aristocracy – younger
                    sons, who would in England be quartered upon the public in
                    the shape of placemen, <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del>
                    who would there strut in regimentals, <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> enter these convents.
                    with you they are mischievous – here they are only useless.
                    moreover they are now of the same use here that the
                    Monasteries were in England 300 years ago: they have the
                    only libraries, &amp; preserve books tho they do not use
                    them. – The Friars will not stand in the way of revolution
                    whenever the hour arrives. witness France. the secular
                    priests there have been troublesome in La Vendee,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Vendée area of
                        western France was a centre of anti-Revolutionary revolt
                        in 1793–1796.</note>
<del rend="strikethrough">&amp;</del> often &amp; the
                    greater part – have emigrated, but the Friars &amp; Nuns
                    fell quietly into the ranks of society. very very few
                    attempted to emigrate. a Portugueze of family had
                    &lt;professed&gt; in a nunnery in France. her brother on
                    hearing of the dissolution of the monasteries procured her a
                    situation here in a nunnery, &amp; wrote for her to come
                    immediately. she replied she was very much obliged to him –
                    but she was married.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> A dog said to be mad passed thro <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref> two days ago
                    &amp; bit almost every dog in the town. I told the Boy to
                    take care of ours – lest he should be bit. Sir, said he,
                    there is no danger now, the dogs have all been blest &amp;
                    burnt with the Iron of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Quiteria<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">St Quiteria:
                        5th-century virgin and martyr. In legend, she held two
                        rabid dogs at bay with the sanctity of her voice, so she
                        was invoked as a protector against rabies.</note> on the
                        <del rend="strikethrough">forehead</del> &lt;nose&gt;: a
                    precious security! holy water &amp; the iron of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Quiteria to save us from the
                    hydrophobia. – you will perhaps be amused at the name of our
                    dog – the servants heard me call him poor fellow, &amp; he
                    goes by that name – or rather as they pronounce it Boo
                    fellow. from a similar circumstance the dog of an Englishman
                    here got the name of “Come along.” – I forgot to add that if
                    a man is bit he must be burnt with this iron in the hand.
                    the original iron is in possession of a nobleman but
                    fac-similes that have been blest partake the virtue. – The
                    Yellow Fever has spent itself at Cadiz. of 63,000
                    Inhabitants (for 17,000 fled in time) 4,000 &lt;only&gt;
                    have escaped the contagion – 8000 have died, the rest have
                    recovered. It spreads in the province &amp; rages more
                    violently at Seville that it had ever done at Cadiz. the
                    gates of Cadiz are now shut to keep out the contagion. An
                    Englishman writes from Xeres that his wife &amp; children
                    &amp; all his servants are in the disease – he can get no
                    assistance whatever – no one will come near them – he
                    attends upon all – &amp; hourly expects to be attacked with
                    it himself. In Turkey you are never thus abandoned. their
                    fearless superstition palliates the evil that it spreads. </p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you – our love to <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Danvers</ref>
</salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
