<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Spatial Contingency: Digital Networks, James Hogg, and the Religious Politics of Space</title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Winter Jade Werner</name>
                </author>
                
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-07-9</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2024.contingent.werner</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">contingent</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND ref // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Romantic Contingency
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Winter Jade</forename>
                                <surname>Werner</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ref target="praxis/contingent/praxis.2024.contingent.werner"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/wellbeing/praxis.2024.wellbeing.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Contingency</title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-07-09">July 9, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>07.09.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p>Written in the first months of the Covid-19 pandemic, this essay probes the enthusiasm for virtual communication in higher education to consider the political ramifications of virtual versus physical spaces. Reading James Hogg’s The Private Memoirs and Confessions of a Justified Sinner in light of a resonant spatial politics, it argues that absent what the novel proposes are the moderating effects of shared space, religious fundamentalism becomes radically individualistic fanaticism. In demonstrating Hogg’s attention to the ways new technologies enabled new forms of “virtual” religious affiliation, the essay suggests that the novel proves a rumination on our current orderings of space, offering a prescient view of the problems that might accompany uncritical acceptance of a supposedly inevitable digitally networked future. 
                </p>
                </div>
            
            <div type="essay">
                <head>Spatial Contingency: Digital Networks, James Hogg, and the Religious Politics of Space</head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Winter Jade Wener</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>Wheaton College</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
            <p>In the first months of the pandemic, a smattering of voices across higher education
                tried to find the situation’s silver lining. Seeing economic, logistical, and social
                hardships facing colleges as an opportunity to disrupt what they took to be an
                unsustainable business model, these optimists suggested that the transition to
                remote learning and Zoom conferencing represented a chance to “innovate” and
                “unbundle” the college experience. <note place="foot" resp="author" > Michael D. Smith, “Are
                    Universities Going the Way of CDs and Cable TV?,”<hi rend="italic">The
                        Atlantic</hi>, June 22, 2020, <ref
                        target="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2020/06/university-like-cd-streaming-age/613291/"
                    >The Atlantic</ref></note>Thanks to improved digital technologies, so went this line of thinking,
                financially imperiled institutions could deliver education to more students without
                the inconveniences and costs that attend maintaining a physical infrastructure.
                What’s more, students, faculty and staff who otherwise might not possess the
                economic means to attend in-person courses and conferences could participate in
                digital alternatives at little to no expense to themselves (or their institutions). </p>
                
            <p>This movement toward higher education’s despatialization—defined by John B. Thompson
                in light of tele-communication as “detach[ment] from the spatial condition of common
                    locality”<note place="foot" resp="author" > John B. Thompson,<hi
                        rend="italic">The Media and Modernity: A Social Theory of the
                    Media</hi>(Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1995), 32.</note>—preceded the
                pandemic, of course. But the pandemic hastened what some called the inevitable trend
                toward networked models of assembling. Hence the spring and summer of 2020 witnessed
                calls to “embrace this moment strategically,” to use the words of Hans Taparia, a
                professor of business at New York University, as “online education could expand
                access exponentially and drop its costs by magnitudes.”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author" > Hans Taparia, “The Future of College is Online, and It’s
                        Cheaper,”<hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, May 25, 2020, <ref
                        target="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/05/25/opinion/online-college-coronavirus.html"
                    >New York Times</ref></note>
            </p>
                
            <p>On the one hand, it was easy to sympathize with these arguments. Before the pandemic,
                the privilege of possessing and accessing physical space was mostly relegated to
                academia’s elite. Adjuncts, for instance, were often denied physical offices on
                campus, let alone institutional “homes,” and contingent faculty (like my spouse)
                were overwhelmingly employed to teach online courses, while teaching in-person
                generally was the default position of tenured or tenure-track faculty. Moreover,
                because contingent faculty are granted little to no research funding, they had
                little ability to physically attend academic conferences. As Jessie Daniels and
                Polly Thistlethwaite note, “What happens inside a conference meeting room rarely
                exists for anyone except those few who can afford to be physically present.”<note
                     place="foot" > Jessie Daniels and Polly Thistlethwaite,<hi
                        rend="italic">Being a Scholar in the Digital Era: Transforming Scholarly
                        Practice for the Public Good </hi>(Policy Press, 2016), 13.</note> A similar
                dynamic applied to the student experience, as idyllic, residential campuses tend to
                attract a wealthier student body relative to online schools or commuter campuses. In
                these ways, physical space in higher education often has functioned as the<hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>dividing line separating the haves and have-nots, the
                privileged and everyone else. No wonder the push among some to diminish the
                centrality of academia’s physical spaces, to make them more contingent rather than
                central to the college experience.</p>
                
            <p>But despatialization also exacerbates the very divides that its proponents argue it
                would overcome. Taparia’s op-ed in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times </hi>is an
                interesting case in point. Even as he acknowledges that “no one doubts that the
                [online] student experience would not be as holistic” as the in-person one, he
                nevertheless reaches this ultimate takeaway: “But universities don’t need to abandon
                in-person teaching for students who see the value in it. They simply need to create
                ‘parallel’ online degrees for all their core degree programs.”<note 
                    place="foot" > Taparia, “The Future of College is Online.”</note> In short,
                Taparia inadvertently ends up advocating for the further entrenchment of the
                two-tiered system in academia, one that offers affluent students a more “holistic”
                face-to-face, campus-based education while providing less affluent students a
                supposedly “parallel” but, by his own admission, less “holistic” online
                education.</p>
                
            <p>Taparia’s argument illustrates one of the main claims of this essay: the role of
                higher education as an aspirationally-democratic enterprise partly hinges on its
                ability to maintain the existence, robustness, and accessibility of its <hi
                    rend="italic">physical</hi> shared spaces. No doubt the maintenance of such
                spaces with the threat of a pandemic resurgence is unprecedentedly complicated,
                expensive, and even, in some cases, impossible. Nevertheless, even as we improve
                digital communication, we must also keep front and center the importance of
                cultivating, investing in, and ensuring widespread access to academia’s shared
                physical spaces. </p>
                
            <p>Somewhat understandably, there is a presentism that attends descriptions of remote
                learning, online conferencing, or “unbundled” education: these are “unprecedented”
                endeavors in “uncharted waters” only recently opened by recent strides in computing
                technologies (see, for instance, Russell). But while it’s true Zoom has only been
                around since 2011, nevertheless there are past resources for thinking through the
                political ramifications of this shift. Thinkers ranging from Manuel Castells to
                Wendy Brown, for example, have considered the politics that arise from shared,
                concrete spaces versus technologically-enabled networks, bringing into focus how
                “network society” might come at the expense of the social weal. </p>
                
            <p>Romanticism, I believe, is also well poised to contribute to contemporary defenses of
                the political value of bounded, shared space. As Siobhan Carroll observes, “Scholars
                historicizing spatial concepts have, from Henri Lefebvre onward, tended to single
                out the Romantic era as a time in which urbanization, new technologies of
                measurement, and dramatic political revolutions collided to crystallize the modern
                construction of space.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Siobhan Carroll,<hi
                        rend="italic">An Empire of Air and Water: Uncolonizable Space in the British
                        Imagination, 1750-1850</hi>(Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press,
                    2015), 11.</note> As such, the early nineteenth century was forced to grapple
                with “imagined” versus concrete spaces in community formation.<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> See Benedict Anderson,<hi rend="italic">Imagined
                        Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of Nationalism</hi>(New
                    York: Verso Books, 1983); Zeynep Tufecki, <hi rend="italic">Twitter and Tear
                        Gas: The Power and Fragility of Networked Protest</hi>(New Haven: Yale
                    University Press, 2017), 5.</note> For instance, it witnessed the attempt to
                establish alternatives to face-to-face community via the medium of new print
                technologies, and confronted multiple efforts to develop “non-unified formulations
                of nationness” that strove to make coherent the idea of “Britain” and the British
                    Empire.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Esther Wohlgemut,<hi
                        rend="italic">Romantic Cosmopolitanism </hi>(New York: Palgrave MacMillan,
                    2009), 1. On establishing “imagined” communities via print culture, see Michael
                    Warner, <hi rend="italic">Publics and Counterpublics </hi>(Princeton: Zone
                    Books, 2005) and Joshua King, <hi rend="italic">Imagined Spiritual Communities
                        in Britain’s Age of Print </hi>(Columbus, OH: The Ohio State University
                    Press, 2015). For more on creating the imagined community of the nation at the
                    turn of the century, see Linda Colley, <hi rend="italic">Britons: Forging the
                        Nation 1707-1837</hi>(New Haven: Yale University Press, 1992).</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>Examining these historical developments, critics often have noted the enduringness
                and relative success of Romantic projects in substituting “imaginary” spaces and
                communities for more geographically bounded ones. Some of these scholars, influenced
                by the work of historians such as Marcus Rediker, have celebrated the relative
                boundlessness of the Romantic era as one that opened new opportunities for subject
                and community formation unhindered by national boundaries. But several critics also
                observe that the flipside of this success was an apprehension of the potential ill
                effects of such “unbounded” projects. As they point out, an acute sense of
                anomie often accompanied nineteenth-century endeavors to create imagined
                communities—an anomie that fed Romantic texts’ preoccupation with the perils of
                social atomization.<note place="foot" resp="author" >
                    <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein</hi>, for instance, is often read as a modern
                    parable on unchecked, dangerous individualism without the moderating effects of
                    society. For more on nineteenth-century anomie, see Christopher Herbert, <hi
                        rend="italic">Culture and Anomie: Ethnographic Imagination in the Nineteenth
                        Century</hi>(Chicago: Chicago University Press, 1991) and James Buzard, <hi
                        rend="italic">Disorienting Fiction: The Autoethnographic Work of
                        Nineteenth-Century British Novels </hi>(Princeton: Princeton University
                    Press, 2005).</note>
            </p>
            <p>To chart the relationship between such Romantic socio-political projects and
                contemporary discussions of higher education, I want to take these projects a step
                further than their authors perhaps wanted or imagined. As I understand it, part of
                the “purchase” of Romanticism “inside and outside academe” (in the words of this
                CFP) flows from one vein of thought in the period that interrogated the supposed
                social benefits of precisely what Brown terms “deterritorialized societies.” This
                channel of Romantic thinking questioned the supposed social good of such
                deterritorialized societies, as well as the “frenzied affirmation of individual
                freedom” that usually accompanied them.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    Wendy Brown,<hi rend="italic">In the Ruins of Neoliberalism: The Rise of
                        Antidemocratic Politics in the West</hi>(New York: Columbia University
                    Press, 2019), 168.</note> Furthermore, it dwelled on the potential political and
                social fallout that came of “imagined communities,” which were built on and
                valorized an ideal of imagined shared values, rather than norms of “reciprocity and
                accommodation” developed by repeated interaction and proximity. </p>
                
            <p>James Hogg—who was pushed out of the <hi rend="italic">Blackwood’s Magazine
                </hi>print community he had helped to establish in large part due to his
                working-class background and lack of formal education—was particularly attuned to
                the politics of “imagined communities.” As much as he subscribed to the promises of
                finding like-minded individuals via the networks of mass print culture (which had
                freed him from shepherding and put him on the path to literary success), he remained
                throughout his career fixated on the social, cultural, and political values
                generated by shared land and bounded space. His outsider status at <hi rend="italic"
                    >Blackwood’s</hi>, perhaps, made him attuned as much to what was lost, as well
                as gained, by the replacement of physical space by “imagined communities.” </p>
                
            <p>Hogg explored the politics of despatialization most prominently in his famous work,
                    <hi rend="italic">The Private Memoirs and Confessions of a Justified Sinner
                </hi>(1824). Robert Wringhim, of course, is a religious fanatic. But Wringhim’s
                religious fanaticism, I argue, must be understood in the context of space. Wringhim
                recognizes that the politics arising from a “common locality” threaten the exercise
                of his “boundless” individualism:<note place="foot" resp="author" > James
                        Hogg,<hi rend="italic">The Private Memoirs and Confessions of a Justified
                        Sinner, </hi>edited by Adrian Hunter<hi rend="italic"> </hi>(Toronto:
                    Broadview Press, 2001), 111.</note> he never recounts attending (the bounded
                community of) church, and he pledges fealty to (who he takes to be) a foreign
                monarch openly hostile to traditional boundaries. Absent what the novel proposes are
                the moderating effects of shared space, Wringhim’s religious fundamentalism becomes
                fanaticism. </p>
                
            <p>Hogg’s concern over despatialization, as represented by Wringhim, provides an
                unexpected resource as to why we should interrogate the rush to adopt permanently
                “digital” alternatives to academe’s lost spaces. In the modern academy, space is
                evermore at a premium, and it is tempting to view digital technologies as a means of
                providing virtual (and cheaper) replacements for the office, the classroom, the
                conference, or, even, the institution. Yet to heed Hogg is to see the very different
                politics that arise from bounded versus boundaryless spaces, to see the ways that
                concrete spaces perhaps are the irreplaceable foundation of an equitable,
                representative, and healthily pluralistic society. In the admittedly idiosyncratic
                way I bring together Hogg and today’s digitized society, then, I want to demonstrate
                that the novel is not simply about some distant, strife-ridden religious past. I
                suggest instead the novel explores the potential ill-effects of virtual “networks”
                on political subjectivity, perhaps cautioning us today to continue in the systematic
                investment and maintenance of our accessible, shared physical spaces. </p>
                
                <div type="section">
            <head>A Politics of Space in the Digital Era</head>
                    
            <p>Political theorists from John Dewey to Wendy Brown have long noted that although
                xenophobes and tribalists exhibit an obsession with policing the boundaries of their
                spaces, bounded, shared space is nevertheless the precondition of those values
                necessary to free society. Put differently, what such political theorists recognize
                is that even if boundaries promote radical forms of exclusion, this doesn’t<hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>necessarily mean that the condition of “boundarylessness”
                does the opposite. We might equate boundarylessness (such as that which commonly
                attends conceptions of digital spaces) with ultimate individual freedom, but this
                ideal of unhindered individual freedom is also at odds with the values necessary to
                free society.</p>
                    
            <p>Brown offers a compelling explanation as to why the politics arising from the
                precondition of concrete, shared space are anathema to neoliberal understandings of
                freedom. According to Brown, neoliberalism is a “moral-political project” aimed at
                “dismantling and disparaging the social state in the name of free, responsibilized
                    individuals.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Brown, <hi rend="italic"
                        >In the Ruins</hi>, 13, 29.</note> Pursuing an ideal of boundless individual
                freedom (supposedly) unfettered by “<hi rend="italic">any kind</hi> of deliberate
                and state-administered social policy, planning, and justice,” neoliberalism promotes
                ideologies, technologies, and economic systems that atomize individuals.<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Brown,<hi rend="italic">In the Ruins</hi>,
                    11.</note> This atomization, Brown continues, bolsters neoliberal logic as it
                erodes social consciousness of and support for conditions of “political equality”
                upon which the capacity for democratic power-sharing and self-rule depend.<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Brown,<hi rend="italic">In the
                        Ruins</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>11, 28.</note> Hence why the freedoms
                engendered by “digital space” has not been able to save us from profound feelings of
                isolation and alienation:<note place="foot" resp="author" > See, also,
                    Katherine Hobson, “Feeling Lonely? Too Much Time On Social Media May Be Why.”<hi
                        rend="italic">National Public Radio</hi>, March 6, 2017. <ref
                        target="https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2017/03/06/518362255/feeling-lonely-too-much-time-on-social-media-may-be-why"
                    >National Public Radio</ref>and Jason Linkins, “The Death of the Good Internet Was an Inside Job.” <hi
                        rend="italic">The New Republic</hi>, December 31, 2019. <ref
                        target="https://newrepublic.com/article/156096/death-good-internet-inside-job-decade-hell"
                    >New Republic</ref></note> “The rise of the digital,” Brown argues, “generates a novel, radically
                deterritorialized and dedemocratized sociality. This sociality features no clear
                protocols of power sharing, enfranchisement, or commitment to negotiating diverse
                views and needs, inclusion, or plurality. Whatever their merits, digitized
                ‘societies’ are detached from the challenge of sharing power equally in order to
                rule ourselves.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Brown,<hi rend="italic">In
                        the Ruins, </hi>183-84.</note> Such sentiments are differently expressed by
                political theorist Jennifer Forestal, who—drawing on John Dewey’s meditations on the
                “the role of space in facilitating democratic politics”—calls for the imposition of
                tangible “boundaries” on Internet communities “to foster reciprocity and
                accommodation through repeated interactions.”<note place="foot" resp="author"
                    > Jennifer Forestal, “The Architecture of Political Spaces: Trolls,
                    Digital Media, and Deweyan Democracy,”<hi rend="italic">American Political
                        Science Review</hi>111, no. 1 (2017), 151,154.</note>
            </p>
                    
            <p>Brown draws on Carl Schmitt in particular to illustrate how boundarylessness produces
                a certain type of subjectivity antagonistic to the social weal. Pondering the
                differences between “land” and “seafaring” peoples, Schmitt notes that the
                “boundarylessness” of seafaring populations oriented them toward “use and
                consumption, rather than ownership and cultivation.”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Qtd. in Brown,<hi rend="italic">In the Ruins</hi>,
                    185-66.</note> A key difference, then, between the move from an imaginary based
                on concrete, geographically-bounded space to one based on deterritorialized space
                was that the latter promoted a rapacious appetite to “extend sovereignty” without
                the moderating responsibilities that attend actual land—that is, the responsibility
                to make land more productive, to defend that land, or, most of all, to negotiate
                conditions of cohabitation. Applying such contexts to online discussion boards,
                Forestal looks to Dewey to argue that flexible but distinct “boundaries” on Internet
                communities foster “an openness to respond and adapt to new ideas and information”
                while discouraging trolls.<note place="foot" resp="author" > Forestal,
                    “Architecture,” 155.</note> What Dewey knew, she argues, is that “spaces are not
                value-neutral” but rather provide “cues as to how to behave … focus[ing] our
                attention on certain kinds of activities and organiz[ing] our relationships in
                certain ways.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Forestal, “Architecture,”
                    154.</note> For both thinkers, “boundarylessness” is linked to undemocratic
                tendencies. And for Brown in particular, concrete, shared space is the precondition
                of developing a social consciousness committed to “negotiating diverse views and
                needs, inclusion, or plurality.”</p>
                    
            <p>Yet because commonly conceived as the alternative to “hierarchical, vertically
                integrated structures located in fixed positions,” the rise of the modern “network
                society” has often been cast as flexible and horizontal in comparison.<note
                     place="foot" resp="author" > Yoon Sun Lee, “Charlotte Smith’s Network
                    Story,” in<hi rend="italic">Global Romanticism: Origins, Orientations, and
                        Engagements, 1760-1920</hi>, edited by Evan Gottlieb (Lewisburg, PA:
                    Bucknell University Press, 2015), 39.</note> Granting actors more “relative
                autonomy,” it yields a “more flexible and decentered [form] of organization,” as
                Yoon Sun Lee observes.<note place="foot" resp="author" > Lee, “Charlotte
                    Smith’s Network Story,” 39, 40.</note> But Castells reminds us that network
                society also reproduces—even ossifies—distinctions between privileged and
                unprivileged rather than “decentering” power. Networks depend on nodes, and the
                gatekeepers of such nodes are the new privileged class. And these gatekeepers gather
                in <hi rend="italic">geographic </hi>spaces, even as they look to <hi rend="italic"
                    >un</hi>space space and <hi rend="italic">un</hi>time time. Such spaces are
                exclusionary: Castells gives luxury hotels and airport VIP lounges as examples, but
                Silicon Valley, Ivy League colleges, and prohibitively-expensive “cosmopolitan”
                cities also come to mind.<note place="foot" resp="author" > Manuel
                        Castells,<hi rend="italic">The Rise of the Network Society</hi>(Cambridge,
                    MA: Blackwell Press, 1995), 415-17.</note> In this sense, Castells suggests that
                geographic space becomes all the more rarefied in the modern network society. As the
                rest of society is increasingly atomized—the centrality of the school, office, shop,
                and other public places rendered disposable thanks to the expansion of the digital
                domain—physical space increasingly is transmuted into a luxury conferred on the
                privileged. One can consider how access to or ownership of bounded (or gate-kept)
                geographic “nodes” have become an expected part of the “benefits” granted to
                academic, economic, and political elites—a benefit whose desirability increases in
                direct proportion to its increased <hi rend="italic">in</hi>accessibility to
                everyone else.<note place="foot" resp="author" > Covid-19 in some ways has
                    accelerated these trends. In a March 2020 blog post for the “The Philosophical
                    Salon,” Slavoj Žižek argues, “Who, today, will be able to afford shaking hands
                    and embracing? The privileged. … The financial elite will withdraw into secluded
                    zones and amuse themselves there telling stories in the<hi rend="italic"
                        >Decameron </hi>style. (The ultra-rich are already flocking with private
                    planes to exclusive small islands in the Caribbean).” See Slavoj Žižek, “Monitor
                    and Punish? Yes, Please!” <hi rend="italic">Los Angeles Review of Books</hi>,
                    March 16. 2020, <ref
                        target="https://thephilosophicalsalon.com/monitor-and-punish-yes-please/"
                    >The Philosophical Salon</ref></note></p>
                    
            <p>Luckily, the rest of us are told, there are alternatives. Consider the academic
                conference, for example. Because they are expensive and time-consuming, students,
                faculty, and independent scholars with limited funds and time often can’t attend
                them. Technology, however, renders geographic distance moot, and anyone with access
                to the Internet and a computer can (supposedly) take part in the lively exchange of
                ideas. In this vein, Daniels and Thistlethwaite note that “as an alternative to the
                expense (and environmental impact) of travel to conferences, some scholars are
                creating virtual conferences through digital video and web conferencing or following
                conferences from afar via Twitter hashtags.”<note place="foot" resp="author" 
                    > Daniels and Thistlethwaite,<hi rend="italic">Being a Scholar, </hi>13.</note>
                They continue, “Scholars present at conferences can also share their work with the
                public, those attending the meetings, through open access repositories at their
                institutions or on commercial platforms like SlideShare.”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Daniels and Thistlethwaite,<hi rend="italic">Being a
                        Scholar</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>13.</note> More relative autonomy is
                granted to each scholar thanks to digital technologies—those who can’t make it can
                participate anyway, and in-person attendees can share their work with those
                off-site. Obviated is the need to advocate for time off or dedicated funds in order
                physically to attend what is implied to be the perhaps obsolete academic
                conference.</p>
                    
            <p>There are clear environmental benefits that come with online and hybrid conferencing
                (though, as a recent study in <hi rend="italic">Nature Communications </hi>noted,
                the hub placement of the hybrid conference is critical to realize these benefits).
                    <note place="foot" resp="author" > Specifically, it cautions that without
                    proper attention to hub placement, hybrid conferences risked having “higher
                    carbon footprints than … even in-person scenarios.” Yanqiu Tao, Debbie Steckel,
                    Jiří Jaromír Klemeš, and Fengqi You, “Trend towards virtual and hybrid
                    conferences may be an effective climate change mitigation strategy,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Nature Communications</hi>, December 16, 2021, <ref
                        target="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-27251-2">Nature</ref></note> But it
                is precisely because the environmental considerations are so urgent that the
                political ramifications of online conferencing perhaps receive less attention. For
                instance, there is rarely discussion about academe’s reliance on questionably
                democratic technological platforms. In December 2020, Zoom came under fire for
                “work[ing] with the Chinese government to terminate Americans’ accounts and disrupt
                video calls aboutthe 1989 massacre of pro-democracy activists in Tiananmen Square,”
                and its past failures to protect users’ data from governments and law enforcement
                attracted the criticism of the human rights group Access Now (Zoom has since updated
                its privacy practices).<note place="foot" resp="author" > Drew Harwell and
                    Ellen Nakashima, “Federal Prosecutors accuse Zoom executive of working with
                    Chinese government to surveil users and suppress video calls,”<hi rend="italic"
                        >The Washington Post</hi>, December 18, 2020, <ref
                        target="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2020/12/18/zoom-helped-china-surveillance"
                    >Washington Post</ref>(accessed March 1, 2022). See, also, Micah Lee and Yael Grauer, “Zoom Meetings
                    Aren’t End-to-End Encrypted, Despite Misleading Marketing,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Intercept</hi>, March 31, 2020, <ref
                        target="https://theintercept.com/2020/03/31/zoom-meeting-encryption/"
                    >The Intercept</ref></note> Twitter has a history of silencing political dissent, failing to stem
                online harassment, and relative to traditional media outlets, disproportionately
                promoting state-sponsored propaganda and disseminating “fake news.” SlideShare is
                owned by LinkedIn, which in turn is owned by Microsoft—one of the “big five” tech
                companies that currently exercise a monopoly on Internet traffic. And, needless to
                say, Meta is facing a reckoning for its role in facilitating the spread of
                misinformation and toxic speech (an audit of the company warned that “its tools and
                algorithms” could drive “people toward self-reinforcing echo chambers of
                    extremism.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Greg Bensinger, “Does
                    Zuckerberg Understand How the Right to Free Speech Works?”<hi rend="italic">The
                        New York Times</hi>, July 8, 2020, <ref
                        target="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/08/opinion/facebook-civil-rights-audit.html"
                    >New York Times</ref></note> Even setting aside the troubling political ramifications of big tech’s
                rise, a larger problem exists: arguments in favor of moving conferences online (or
                ending institutional support for physical participation in them) tend to
                instrumentalize the conveyance of information insofar as they assume “information
                sharing” for the sake of individual career and institutional development to be the
                fundamental purpose of these conferences.<note place="foot" resp="author" 
                        > An op-ed in<hi rend="italic">Inside Higher Ed </hi>rehearsed this line
                        of thinking in the context of Covid-19. Acknowledging the precarious state
                        of higher education and faculty jobs, Interfolio CEO Andrew Rosen and
                        professor Jaime Lester offer this recommendation: 
                        <quote>In addition to
                        innovating around faculty’s access to data, colleges and universities need
                        to provide professional development for faculty that is focused on
                        individual career success and, as a result, their students’ successes. <hi
                            rend="italic">The common use of professional development funds to attend
                            disciplinary conferences does little to support individual career
                            success</hi>. Instead, opportunities for career counseling in the form
                        of individualized development plans, mentoring, learning communities and
                        grants to pursue research and teaching innovations are important to keep all
                        faculty motivated, progressing and supporting institutional strategic goals.
                        (emphasis mine)</quote>
                    
                     Never mind the vagueness of what is being suggested to
                        take the place of disciplinary conferences (who is administering these
                        “opportunities for career counseling”? What are the components of an
                        “individualized development plan,” and how does this “plan” meaningfully
                        differ from the self- and departmental assessments?). It’s enough to notice
                        that the authors recommend the cessation of funding for disciplinary
                        conferences to hire instead specialists to guide faculty toward advancing
                        “institutionalstrategic goals.” I’m grateful to Mimi Winick for discussing
                        with me the instrumentalization of knowledge that attends such conceptions
                        of academic conferencing. See Andrew Rosen and Jaime Lester, “Supporting
                        Faculty Careers Amid Uncertainty,” <hi rend="italic">Inside Higher Ed</hi>,
                        July 2, 2020, <ref
                            target="https://www.insidehighered.com/views/2020/07/02/supporting-faculty-careers-amid-season-uncertainty-opinion"
                        >Inside Higher Education</ref>
                  </note>
            </p>
                    
            <p>This isn’t to criticize digital conversations or interactions, nor is it to say that
                digital platforms aren’t able to provide meaningful and more inclusive forms of
                horizontal community. It is only to reemphasize what the pandemic years have made
                obvious. Digital alternativesdo not inherently resolve the problems that attend
                in-person meetings. Without proper attention paid to the underlying inequalities of
                higher education, such technologies in fact stand to deepen its existing two-tiered
                system, in which access to in-person communication is increasingly the domain of the
                privileged few while the rest ought to be satisfied with “virtual” forms of
                community or instruction. Some cash-strapped institutions, for instance, are
                considering not reimbursing faculty for in-person conferencing if a digital
                alternative is available.</p>
                    
            <p>This separation is reason for special concern at a moment when higher education is in
                crisis. For not only does fully online communication have a tendency to “fortify and confirm” people
                in their own opinions, creating a more polarized society (“Danger in the internet
                echo chamber”); the absence of the “rest” also creates an echo chamber at the <hi
                    rend="italic">actual</hi>academic conference, as attendees are less likely to
                engage with or feel beholden to digital participants than they are with fellow
                in-person participants. If we are to extrapolate Brown’s reasoning, the academic
                conference by virtue of being bounded is<hi rend="italic"> a </hi>place where we better recognize who “cohabitates” disciplinary spaces and
                wherein the need for “protocols of power sharing, enfranchisement, or commitment to
                negotiating diverse views and needs, inclusion, or plurality” may come into sharper
                focus relative to digital “deterritorialized” spaces. Hence why digital platforms
                perhaps haven’t emerged as full-fledged “alternatives” to physical attendance at
                conferences. Digital participation might be cheaper for struggling institutions, but
                the long-term political costs for scholars and professional organizations could
                prove steeper. When (hopefully) we find ourselves fully on the other side of the
                global pandemic, we might do well to assess whether a new normal of “networked”
                conferencing has created the sorts of communities we wish to inhabit. </p>
                    
            <p>This is a necessarily reductive argument, I realize, one that oversimplifies complex
                debates regarding social media, academic conferences, and online education, as well
                as a robust critical literature on the politics of space in the fields of literary
                studies, geography, sociology, gender studies, and more. It also neglects
                finer-grained developments in Zoom and Google Meet technologies to create boundaries
                on virtual classroom and conference attendance and participation. But I focus on the
                contributions of Brown and Forestal (in conjunction with Castells), because they
                take such a comprehensive view of the potential political consequences of digital
                spaces precisely at a moment when technologies for virtual gathering are imagined to
                redress the inequalities and inconveniences associated with physical, bounded space.
                Their ultimate concern strikes me as fairly uncontroversial: rather than making
                people feel less alienated, digital gatherings can accelerate alienation. </p>
                    
            <p>Hogg’s novel probes the extent of this danger.<note place="foot" resp="author"
                    > I risk anachronism, but I take my cue in part from Lee, who notes that
                    while “the network that Castells describes is historically dependent on
                    late-twentieth-century developments in information processing, communication,
                    production, and transportation … the bourgeois public sphere and the emergence
                    of the novel can be seen as contributing to [this] story of social
                    reorganization,” in which “network” and individual autonomy takes precedence
                    over “place” and “hierarchy.” Lee, “Charlotte Smith’s Network Story,” 40.
                </note> Admittedly, it’s a stretch to link historical instances of “imagined
                communities” to the rise of digital networks of affiliation today. But I’m not the
                first to suggest connections of this kind. Social media, for instance, is often
                compared to Americana’s old town square, and the Internet is regularly likened to
                the nineteenth-century Western frontier. And these historical analogues are meant to
                do more than merely describe digital interactions. As law professor Alfred C. Yen
                notes in an essay arguing against the use of the “Western frontier metaphor” in
                relation to the legal regulation of cyberspace, such metaphors also determine the
                character of the Internet interactions: “The Western frontier metaphor operates as
                propaganda supporting the minimal regulation of the Internet,” he argues.<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Alfred C. Yen, “Western Frontier or Feudal
                    Society: Metaphors and Perceptions of Cyberspace,”<hi rend="italic">Berkeley
                        Technology Law Journal, </hi>17, no. 4 (Fall 2002), 1225. </note>
                Ultimately, he suggests that the “continued application of the unreformed metaphor
                creates an incomplete and misleading influence on policy and crowds out other
                metaphors that offer alternate perspectives on the Internet.”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author" > Yen, 1232.</note> I take Yen’s call for “other metaphors”
                by which to speak of our contemporary era as inspiration to look to seventeenth- and
                eighteenth-century Protestantism for new language to address the problem of
                deterritorialized academic space today. </p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
            <head>The Politics of Religious Space</head>
                    
            <p>One significant development in the history of Protestantism was the
                reconceptualization of how it might expand in light of new technological
                advancements. From an older ideal of a formal, united, and trans-territorial
                Christendom (a concept “essentially linked to territory”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Andrew F. Walls,<hi rend="italic">The Cross-Cultural
                        Process in Christian History </hi>(Maryknoll, NY: Orbis Books, 2002),
                    34.</note>), the evangelical revival of Protestantism instead “developed
                consciously international structures” that were conceived as deliberately separate
                from (increasingly secular) national governments and which eventually resulted in an
                    “<hi rend="italic">informal</hi> spiritual empire, a <hi rend="italic"
                    >network</hi> of federated believers across increasingly distinct national
                    boundaries.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Christopher Clark and
                    Michael Ledger-Lomas, “The Protestant International,” in<hi rend="italic"
                        >Religious Internationals in the Modern World: Globalization and Faith
                        Communities since 1750</hi>, edited by Abigail Green and Vincent Viaene (New
                    York: Palgrave MacMillan, 2012), 23, 23-24. Emphasis mine.</note> Though the
                idea of “networked” Protestantism can be traced back to the Reformation, the
                structure and ramifications of this “network” became more pronounced in the
                eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.<note place="foot" resp="author" > Clark
                    and Ledger-Lomas, “Protestant International,” 24.</note> By the early nineteenth
                century, international Protestantism—that is, “networked” rather than
                territorially-defined Protestantism—dominated.<note place="foot" resp="author"
                    > Katherine Carté Engel, “The SPCK and the American Revolution: The Limits
                    of International Protestantism,”<hi rend="italic">Church History</hi>81, no. 1
                    (2012), 88.</note> Fascinatingly, the arguments in favor of this “networked”
                international Protestantism resemble those often given for the desirability of
                “network society” today, as both are assumed better to guarantee individual autonomy
                and more horizontal, decentered forms of social organization. </p>
            <p>Though Christendom’s formal end often is dated to the start of World War I,<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> See Walls,<hi rend="italic">Cross-Cultural
                        Process</hi>.</note> Philip Jenkins argues that the beginning of the end of
                Christendom probably can be traced to an earlier event: the rise of secular
                nationalism in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries.<note 
                    place="foot" > Philip Jenkins,<hi rend="italic">The Next Christendom: The
                        Coming of Global Christianity</hi>(New York: Oxford University Press, 2011),
                    14.</note> According to perhaps the most prominent account of this historical
                development, the religious wars of the seventeenth century led to the growing
                conviction that peace could only be achieved if religious power were ceded to the
                secular nation-state. Religious belief would be divorced from government and instead
                relegated to the private domain. </p>
                    
            <p>Sometimes overlooked is the fact that several Protestant institutions and actors <hi
                    rend="italic">also </hi>enthusiastically participated in and contributed to the
                rise of secular nationalism. For one thing, a number of Dissenting denominations saw
                themselves existentially threatened by a close<hi rend="italic"> </hi>union between
                church and state. In the view of these Dissenters, any<hi rend="italic"> </hi>form
                of state-enforced religious belief imposed from above was anathema, as it checked
                the exercise of one’s individual freedom of conscience, which, they felt, was one of
                the cornerstones of the Christian faith. Thus the Particular Baptist Robert Robinson
                declared in 1779 that “religious uniformity [was] an illegitimate brat of the mother
                of harlots,” and compared the various Protestant denominations to be properly akin
                to “little states, each governed by its own laws, and all independent [of] one
                another. Like confederate states they assembled by deputies in one large
                ecclesiastical body, and deliberated about the common interests of the whole.”<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Qtd. in Daniel E. White,<hi rend="italic"
                        >Early Romanticism and Religious Dissent</hi>(Cambridge: Cambridge
                    University Press, 2006), 7.</note> Instead of unity built on force, confederacy
                would be facilitated by the “industrialization of communications;” thus “the
                international message [of Protestantism] grew in symbiosis with the technologies
                required to broadcast and receive it.”<note place="foot" resp="author" >
                    Clark and Ledger-Lomas, “Protestant International,” 23.</note> In this sense,
                the Enlightenment discourse of individual freedom, inalienable rights, and global
                federation ended up informing prominent eighteenth-century Protestant conceptions of
                how to establish cooperation across denominational differences. International
                Protestantism, in other words, was partly driven by an optimism and set of moral
                values that bears some resemblance to the values and beliefs propounded by
                early-2000s cyber-utopianism. By “network[ing] human beings,” new technology would
                “foster communication, collaboration, sharing, helpfulness, and community” and
                eventually help in establishing more “free” societies.<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author" > Douglas Rushkoff,<hi rend="italic">Team Human</hi>(New
                    York; London: W. W. Norton &amp; Co., 2019), 26. See, also, Evgeny Morozov, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Net Delusion: The Dark Side of Internet Freedom</hi>(New
                    York: Perseus Books, 2012). </note></p>
                    
            <p>As the advent of the modern missionary movement in the 1790s demonstrates, by no
                means was this Protestant idealization of “freedom of conscience” at odds with
                Christian expansion. But the key difference between “modern” and past schemes of
                Christian expansion, at least in the minds of this subset of British evangelicals,
                was that <hi rend="italic">this</hi> new international Protestantism would be
                emancipatory rather than oppressive, creating self-sufficient, self-governing
                Christian communities rather than grinding foreign peoples under the heels of an
                authoritarian political-religious power. That is, they saw and defined <hi
                    rend="italic">their </hi>Christian expansion as the antithesis of a crusading
                (and thus often Catholic) Christianity, whose <hi rend="italic">modus operandi</hi>,
                as they perceived it, was to invade, conquer, and impose spiritual change by force.
                In the minds of these Protestants, missionaries wouldn’t invade or conquer—rather
                they would live “alongside” people in small communities, “touching” individual
                hearts, and thus provoking change from the ground up rather than the top down.<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Winter Jade Werner,<hi rend="italic"
                        >Missionary Cosmopolitanism in Nineteenth-Century British
                    Literature</hi>(Columbus, OH: The Ohio State University Press, 2020), 55-56,
                    89-91.</note> Links between missionary stations and newly Christian communities
                would spring up organically as each realized the extent to which their values and
                interests coincided. As a result, individual and national sovereignty would be
                preserved, even as Christianity brought more people into its fold. Katherine Engel
                characterizes this idealized conception of Protestant unity as an international
                “network” that was both “expansive and intentionally vague,” one which valorized a
                vaguely-conceived “fellowship” by which “geographic and theological differences”
                would be surmounted.<note place="foot" resp="author" > Engel, “SPCK,”
                    88.</note> As Walls puts it, “The expansion of Christendom involved laying down
                terms for other people; its development in the missionary movement involved
                preparedness to live on terms set by other people.”<note place="foot" resp="author"
                    > Walls,<hi rend="italic">Cross-Cultural Process</hi>, 34.</note>
            </p>
                    
            <p>But if western Protestantism abandoned Christendom partly due to its associations
                with authoritarianism and failure to represent pluralities in thought and belief, it
                seems clear that international Protestantism—in the form of the nineteenth-century
                missionary movement and its collusion with European imperialism—didn’t necessarily
                supply a remedy. As Clark and Ledger-Lomas observe of international Protestantism’s
                progress over the long nineteenth century, “Hierarchy and enmity soon entered into
                the Protestant family.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Clark and Ledger
                    Lomas, “Protestant International,” 24.</note> Obviously, the fundamentalism
                underwriting evangelicalism is a reason why international Protestantism could never
                to live up to the emancipatory expectations placed upon it; whatever their
                differences regarding the secular state, the late eighteenth-century wave of
                international Protestants shared with Christendom’s adherents core beliefs in the
                authority of the Bible and the absolute truth of Christianity. </p>
                    
            <p>That said, I want to suggest that the moral and democratic failure of international
                Protestantism in the nineteenth century can also be pegged to its one of its key
                    differences<hi rend="italic"> </hi>from Christendom. Attention to the spatial
                imagination of Protestant internationalism—its ideal of boundary-less “networks,”
                its valorization of individual freedom, and its accompanying suspicion of tradition
                and established hierarchies—could contribute to producing a certain type of <hi
                    rend="italic">anti</hi>-social personality, who viewed civil society as
                fundamentally at odds with the exercise of individual
                freedom. We see this anxiety in nineteenth-century British evangelicalism. Within
                the movement, there was an emphasis on “self-interest and individualism” (as
                prominent evangelicals declared themselves able to read and interpret the Bible free
                of an “elite priesthood” or larger hermeneutical community).<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Mark Knight,<hi rend="italic">Good Words: Evangelicalism
                        and the Victorian Novel</hi>(Columbus, OH: The Ohio State University Press,
                    2019), 135, 118.</note> Tempering the most radical manifestations of this
                individualism was an adherence among some evangelicals to a Pietist-influenced
                “communal tradition of applied interpretation that valued contribution from those
                who were not educated and encouraged modes of thought that were not purely isolated
                attempts at theoretical reconstruction.”<note place="foot" resp="author" >
                        Knight,<hi rend="italic">Good Words</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>135.</note>
                In other words, these evangelicals believed the in-person interactions of “sermons,
                group bible studies, family prayers, and other day-to-day activities”—communal
                interactions that necessarily took place within shared physical spaces—moderated and
                unchecked, pathological individualism.<note place="foot" resp="author" >
                        Knight,<hi rend="italic">Good Words</hi>, 135.</note></p>
            <p>It's tempting to think of digital space and its affordances as wholly unprecedented.
                But what the discussion above might demonstrate is that there are antecedents for
                considering the types of political subjectivities produced by “networked societies”
                versus face-to-face communities. What’s more, we may discover such past experiments
                in networked thinking to be less a testament to technological or social “progress”
                over the course of recent history, or, even, interesting analogues of our own times.
                Instead, they might alert us to blind spots in our current thinking in assessing the
                desirability and feasibility of substituting virtual for physical space.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
            <head>What Hogg Knew</head>
                    
            <p>Ian Duncan’s important essay on <hi rend="italic">Confessions of a Justified Sinner
                </hi>sees Robert Wringhim as the natural result and antagonist of civil society.
                Writing that the novel “allows us to … read fanaticism as the dialectical product of
                objective historical processes of modernization,” he concludes that Hogg ultimately
                “insists on the modernity of the Wringhim’s antinomian sect, cut off from a
                traditional society of customary or naturalized belief and founded on ‘abstract
                speculative principle’.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Ian Duncan,
                    “Fanaticism and Civil Society: Hogg’s<hi rend="italic">Justified Sinner</hi>,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Novel</hi>42, no. 2 (2009), 344.</note> Importantly,
                Wringhim’s “modern” religion, which he models on the beliefs and commitments of the
                Scottish Covenanters, also resonates with the religiosity of the early
                nineteenth-century radical Scottish evangelicals. As Adrian Hunter reminds us, Hogg
                witnessed the growing power of “secessionist churches,” which “by 1820 … had
                consolidated in the form of the Evangelical movement.”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Adrian Hunter, Introduction to<hi rend="italic">The Private
                        Memoirs and Confessions of a Justified Sinner</hi>, by James Hogg (Toronto:
                    Broadview Press, 2001), 26.</note> Rejecting political quietism, the most
                radical Scottish evangelicals instead drew inspiration from the historical example
                of the Covenanters, whom they praised for their fierce defense of Scotland’s
                religious and political freedoms during the bloody “Killing Times” of 1679 to 1688.
                Thus “to many in the establishment, the [evangelical] movement represented a
                dangerous assault on the Presbyterian tradition by a potentially revolutionary
                    constituency.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Hunter, Introduction,
                    26.</note></p>
                    
            <p>Ironically, the radical evangelicals who admired the Convenanters’ fight for freedom
                “hastened the drift towards [Scotland’s] assimilation to England.”<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Hunter, Introduction, 27.</note> “The
                weakening of the established Presbyterian Church” by evangelical secessionists,
                Hunter observes, “further undermined the concerted institutional resistance in
                Scotland to English domination.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Hunter,
                    Introduction, 26.</note> One imagines that it was to critique these developments
                that Hogg set his novel in the immediate wake of the “Killing Times” and made his
                homicidal “justified sinner” a Covenanter. A defender of Scottish nationalism, Hogg
                wished to draw attention to the ways that the attenuation of “traditional society”
                and its institutions in the pursuit of an “abstract” ideal of freedom (to use
                Duncan’s words) not only fostered dangerous forms of religious individualism; more
                forebodingly, the collapse of traditional institutions could also inadvertently lead
                to dangerous forms of political domination. Where radical evangelicalism tended to
                see in the Covenanters a straightforward morality tale of freedom fighters resisting
                an illegitimate foreign power, Hogg drew from the same historical archive to sound a
                more cautious note.</p>
                    
            <p>Specifically, Hogg’s apprehension of the threat “modern” religion posed to
                “traditional society” must be understood within the larger context of
                Protestantism’s shift toward more “networked” forms of organization. In other words,
                Hogg associates Wringhim’s distinctly modern antagonism toward society to an
                abstract speculative notion of <hi rend="italic">religious space</hi>—one tied to
                the seventeenth- and eighteenth-century decline of the older idea of Christendom
                and, in its place, the rise of an “expansive and intentionally vague,”
                “network”-based model of international Protestantism.<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Engel, “SPCK,” 88.</note>
            </p>
                    
            <p>Robert Wringhim, Hogg’s “justified sinner,” possesses a spatial imaginary strikingly
                akin to that yielded by the “decentered and flexible” network society of Yoon Sun
                Lee’s description insofar as he prizes the “relative autonomy” yielded by a “more
                flexible and decentered [form] of organization.” One could say that he is an adopter
                of what digital media scholar Heidi Campbell calls “pic-n-mix” religiosity: so sure
                is Wringhim in his own rectitude that he “mov[es] away from strict adherence to
                traditional forms of religiosity and institution to more fluid affiliations with
                religious beliefs and values.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Heidi
                    Campbell, “Understanding the Relationship between Religion Online and Offline in
                    a Networked Society,”<hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Academy of
                        Religion </hi>80, no. 4 (March 2012), 79.</note> Indeed, he is weirdly
                independent of the institution of the church—nowherein the novel is he described as
                regularly attending church or taking part in church activities—and seems to
                anticipate the sort of religious subjectivity Campbell sees the Internet producing:
                one invested in “connecting to like-minded people” even as it loosens itself of
                “traditional boundaries and affiliations.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    Campbell, “Religion Online and Offline,” 73, 66.</note> Campbell’s
                characterization of online religion, in fact, helps us understand how Wringhim’s
                independence of the bounded church and its attendant practices (“sermons, group
                bible studies, family prayers, and other day-to-day activities”) is linked to his
                friendship with the “like-minded” Gil-Martin (whom the reader knows is Satan
                probably, but whom Wringhim believes is Peter the Great in disguise). </p>
                    
            <p>Here, it’s important to understand how Peter the Great was regarded by
                eighteenth-century Britons. Duncan notes that Peter, “an archetype of sublime
                despotism haunting modern politics, foreshadows a post-Enlightenment,
                post-Napoleonic fantasy of totalitarian power and abjection.”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Ian Duncan, “Fanaticism and Enlightenment in<hi
                        rend="italic">Confessions of a Justified Sinner</hi>,” in <hi rend="italic"
                        >James Hogg and the Literary Marketplace: Scottish Romanticism and the
                        Working-Class Author</hi>, edited by Sharon Alker and Holly Faith Nelson
                    (New York: Routledge, 2009), Kindle.</note> Thus Peter/Gil-Martin is comparable
                to a “potentate of Christendom,” in his own words.<note place="foot" resp="author"
                    > Hogg,<hi rend="italic">Private Memoirs</hi>,<hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi>152.</note> But as the historian Anthony Cross observes, this was far
                from being the only—or even dominant—view of Czar Peter in the eighteenth
                    century.<note place="foot" resp="author" > Anthony Cross,<hi
                        rend="italic">Peter the Great Through British Eyes: Perceptions and
                        Representation of the Tsar Since 1698 </hi>(Cambridge: Cambridge University
                    Press, 2000).</note> By the time of Peter’s death in 1725, British views of
                Peter were fairly positive. In fact, many saw him as the embodiment of ideal
                Enlightenment rule. When James Thomson credits Peter with uniting disparate Russian
                communities not only with each other but Europe as a whole in his renowned poem <hi
                    rend="italic">The Seasons</hi>—writing, “far-distant Flood to Flood is social
                join’d”—he echoes a view popularized by Voltaire, which saw the czar less a despot
                and more the face of Enlightenment modernization, who sought to construct a civil
                society protected by fair governance and united in federation with the other states
                of Europe.<note place="foot" resp="author" > James Thomson, “The Seasons,”<hi
                        rend="italic">The Works of James Thomson </hi>(London: A. Millar, 1750),
                    222. In fact, Thomson amended <hi rend="italic">The Seasons</hi>“to add
                    thirty-eight lines in praise of the ‘matchless Prince,’” which reinforced the
                    hagiographic perception of Peter as a border-crossing monarch “who left his
                    native throne” for the sake of a more cosmopolitan knowledge. Cross, <hi
                        rend="italic">Peter the Great, </hi>171. See, also, chapter four.</note>
                Further boosting the Czar’s popularity was the belief that Peter harbored Protestant
                sympathies, which he was forced to conceal due to the pressures he faced from
                traditionalists at home.</p>
                    
            <p>Hogg was likely intimate with the bifurcated narratives regarding Peter—an
                authoritarian, aggressively-expansionist, religiously-intolerant despot on the one
                hand, and an exemplification of the new internationalist sensibilities of the
                Protestant Enlightenment on the other. Hence the repeated allusions to Peter in his
                story. Hogg suggests that the vogueish, modern, and<hi rend="italic"> </hi>seemingly
                relatively emancipatory internationalism embodied by Czar Peter is Janus-faced:
                Peter is an object-lesson in how the authoritarianism, militarism, and intolerance
                associated with the older ideal of Christendom can look something like
                Enlightenment-influenced international Protestantism.<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Duncan says Peter was considered both “brutal tyrant and
                    modernizing reformer,” and he views Peter as embodying the tension between a
                    pluralistic civil society and fanaticism’s “pure” politics. In other words,
                    Duncan reads the novel in terms of secular versus religious tensions rather than
                    in terms of intra-religious shifts. See Duncan, “Fanaticism and
                    Enlightenment.”</note>
            </p>
                    
            <p>Imagining Gil-Martin to be Peter appeals to Wringhim, then, because Peter seems to
                embody what Wringhim takes to be one of the primary aims of modern Protestantism:
                religious unification that is simultaneously individualistic. After all, his view of
                Peter/Gil-Martin is that he has sought knowledge not from institutions of learning
                or communities of people, but from Wringhim <hi rend="italic">individually</hi>.
                Gil-Martin claims, “I have no parents save one, whom I do not acknowledge,” and
                continues, “though I have servants and subjects more than I can number, yet, … I
                have left them, and retired to this city, and for all the society it contains, you
                see I have attached myself only to you.”<note place="foot" resp="author" >
                        Hogg,<hi rend="italic">Private Memoirs</hi>, 141.</note> Turning away from
                “society” to befriend someone who (he says) he values because he is like a “second
                    self,”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Hogg,<hi rend="italic">Private
                        Memoirs</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>132.</note> Gil-Martin develops what
                network studies scholars call a homophilic friendship with Wringhim—a type of
                relationship strongly associated with and facilitated by social media.<note
                     place="foot" > See, for instance, Miller McPherson, Lynn
                    Smith-Lovin, and James M. Cook, “Birds of a Feather: Homophily in Social
                        Networks,”<hi rend="italic">Annual Review of Sociology</hi>27, no. 1 (2001),
                    415-44.</note> Casting themselves as out-of-step with their respective
                communities, they bond over their (fringe) antinomian beliefs and create a two-man
                ideological echo chamber that pushes these beliefs into fanaticism.<note
                     place="foot" resp="author" > Brown points to a similar dynamic within
                    today’s anti-democratic right-wing. What had been a “potpourri of previously
                    isolated movements—white nationalist, libertarian, antigovernment, and
                    fascist—connected with each othervia the internet.” Brown, <hi rend="italic">In
                        the Ruins</hi>, 4.</note></p>
                    
            <p>This individualistic, homophilic approach to friendship would<hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>appeal to someone like Wringhim, who is oddly uninvested in the in-person
                communities and physical space of the church. His disinterest is even stranger in
                light of the beginning of Robert’s memoir, in which he remarks that his “reverend
                father” “designed me for his assistant and successor in the holy office.”<note
                     place="foot" > Hogg,<hi rend="italic">Private
                        Memoirs</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>117.</note> Despite his supposed
                preparation for the ministry, Robert never recounts worshipping at church. Indeed,
                the only scene in which Robert enters a church is when he goes to spy on Mr.
                Blanchard, the reverend who warns him to dissociate himself from Gil-Martin.<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Hogg,<hi rend="italic">Private Memoirs</hi>,
                    142.</note> Antagonistic to Mr. Blanchard’s preaching and ultimately the agent
                of his downfall, Wringhim attends church but as an<hi rend="italic"> </hi>outsider
                rather than an established member of the community. The space of church and the
                sociality of a congregation are entirely absent in Robert’s religion.</p>
            <p>This absence helps explain why Mr. Blanchard becomes a target of Robert’s enmity. In
                his recent<hi rend="italic"> </hi>reading of the novel<hi rend="italic">,
                </hi>Christopher Herbert focuses on Blanchard, noting that Hogg “appears to
                recommend that spirit of temperate religious moderation” identified with the
                    reverend.<note place="foot" resp="author" > Christopher Herbert,<hi
                        rend="italic">Evangelical Gothic: The English Novel and the Religious War on
                        Virtue from Wesley to Dracula</hi>(Charlottesville: University of Virginia
                    Press, 2019), 117.</note> But Herbert also wonders where exactly the line is
                drawn between Blanchard’s “moderation” and Wringhim’s “zeal.” “Mr. Blanchard,” he
                continues, “does not exactly specify the point at which zealous belief in the
                doctrines of reformed Christianity … passes into ‘dangerous extremity.’”<note
                     place="foot" > Herbert,<hi rend="italic">Evangelical
                        Gothic</hi>, 117.</note></p>
                    
            <p>The answer to Herbert’s query surely lies in the <hi rend="italic">spatial
                </hi>metaphors by which Blanchard communicates the dangers of taking God’s decrees
                to their extreme. Blanchard, notably, subscribes to the notion of religion rooted in
                the idea of definite, human community. His doctrine is exemplified in his
                understanding of religion as “the bond of society on earth, and the connector of
                humanity with the Divine nature<hi rend="italic">.</hi>”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Hogg,<hi rend="italic">Private Memoirs</hi>,<hi
                        rend="italic"> </hi>142.</note> Moreover, there is “nothing so dangerous to
                man as the wresting of any of its principles, or forcing them beyond their due
                    bounds.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Hogg,<hi rend="italic">Private
                        Memoirs</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>142.</note> In other words, he argues
                that true religion inheres as much in “the bond of society<hi rend="italic"> on
                    earth</hi>” as it does between the individual and the divine, and “damnable”
                religion is the result of forcing religious principles “<hi rend="italic"
                    >beyond</hi> due bounds.” Thus Blanchard ties his religious practice to a
                “shared earth,” a delimited<hi rend="italic"> </hi>shared space. This commitment to
                the bond of society born of necessarily cohabited space, Hogg seems to suggest, is
                what makes his religion social<hi rend="italic">, </hi>moral, and moderate. </p>
                    
            <p>No wonder, then, that of the various “divines” in the story, Blanchard is the only
                one who is ever depicted as preaching in a church. No wonder, too, why Wringhim and
                Gil-Martin dislike Blanchard. Where Blanchard sees true religion as proceeding in
                significant part from the social bonds that come of humanity sharing a common,
                finite earth, Wringhim and Gil-Martin both argue for the “boundlessness of the true
                Christian’s freedom,” a conviction they act on by disregarding spatial<hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>and moral<hi rend="italic"> </hi>bounds.<note 
                    place="foot" > Hogg,<hi rend="italic">Private Memoirs</hi>,<hi
                        rend="italic"> </hi>111.</note> Thus Wringhim neglects his physical church,
                as well as, increasingly, his immediate family and community in favor of an imagined
                “society of the just made perfect”—a society whose contours become somewhat more
                concrete to Wringhim when Gil-Martin describes how his “views of society” are
                carried out and enforced by “agents in every city, and every land, exerting their
                    powers.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Hogg,<hi rend="italic">Private
                        Memoirs</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>130.</note> By becoming one of
                Gil-Martin’s/Peter’s “agents,” Wringhim effectively rejects the bounded ties of
                congregation and immediate family for this diffuse, imagined Christian society of
                the “just,” a decision exemplified when Gil-Martin urges him to reject the familial
                “bonds of carnal nature” in favor of the “the bond, and the vows of the Lord.”<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Hogg,<hi rend="italic">Private
                        Memoirs</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>152.</note> Never mind that Wringhim
                doesn’t know nor does he ever meet one of Gil-Martin’s other “agents” in-person or
                otherwise. He becomes part of this imagined “network” anyway, because he believes
                its members share his views. And, as Wringhim becomes more radical, he increasingly
                adopts a stratified way of thinking of society: there is the imagined “society of
                the just” whose views (he supposes) exactly accord with his own, and there is
                everyone else, whose differing opinions and practices make them “mildew,” “enemies,”
                “reprobates, cast-aways.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Hogg,<hi
                        rend="italic">Private Memoirs</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>146, 151,
                    152.</note> In these ways, Wringhim’s antisocial tendencies, as well as his
                belief in a two-tiered society composed of the deserving and the reprobate, are
                linked to a deterritorialized Protestantism—a Protestantism that doesn’t conceive
                itself as delimited by any definite space, a religious individualism unmoderated by
                “communal traditions” or practices.<note place="foot" resp="author" >
                        Knight,<hi rend="italic">Good Words, </hi>135.</note>
            </p>
                    
            <p>For these reasons, Wringhim tries to effect change not from <hi rend="italic"
                    >within</hi> but from <hi rend="italic">without</hi> social structures. Despite
                occupying a leadership role within the church wherein he could consolidate and
                exercise his institutional authority, he instead focuses his efforts on exploding
                existing communities that he sees as inconsistent with his values. Strikingly, the
                modern internet troll helps illuminate Wringhim’s logic. According to Whitney
                Phillips, these trolls create and disseminate exaggerated or fake news stories,
                coopt online conversations, and harass and explode online communities, trying to
                stoke mob outrage, seemingly for no reason other than exposure<hi rend="italic"
                > </hi>and “owning the libs.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > See the
                    introduction of Whitney Phillips,<hi rend="italic">This is Why We Can’t Have
                        Nice Things: Mapping the Relationship Between Online Trolling and Mainstream
                        Culture</hi>(Cambridge: MIT University Press, 2015).</note> She may as well
                be creating laundry list of the tactics employed by Wringhim in the harassment of
                his brother and his brother’s friends. He disrupts their tennis game by intruding on
                the space of the court, mimicking and mocking their conversation and movements. And,
                the more he is met by “rude shocks and pushes, accompanied sometimes with hasty
                curses” in response to his interference, the more he “cling[s]” to his brother,
                keeping him from playing.<note place="foot" resp="author" > Hogg,<hi
                        rend="italic">Private Memoirs, </hi>64.</note> Finally, when he is asked<hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>to “keep without the range of the ball” so the game can
                continue without him being harmed, Wringhim responds, “Is there any law or enactment
                that can compel me to do so?”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Hogg,<hi
                        rend="italic">Private Memoirs</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>65.</note>
                Asserting his right to stay and say what he wants regardless of established
                boundaries and societal norms, he predictably ends up hurt—a turn of events that he
                interprets as violent suppression of his speech and beliefs. In Wringhim’s mind, of
                course, he has been victimized simply for exercising his individual freedoms, a
                narrative he disseminates publicly so as to fuel mob violence. And, for Wringhim and
                the modern troll alike, unleashing an extralegal mob on one’s targets has one
                significant benefit over using one’s institutional authority to effect change: the
                latter requires conversation and compromise, while the former, by design, bypasses
                both.</p>
                    
            <p>Thus Hogg establishes via Wringhim that religious “freedom” divorced from regard of
                shared space<hi rend="italic"> </hi>is individuating in the worst way possible.
                First, it valorizes a conception of individual freedom necessarily antagonistic to
                the moderating tendencies that come of one’s realization that human beings
                cohabitate a finite space. Second, it exacerbates societal divides, as the “more
                flexible and decentered” network promotes dangerous homophilic forms of association.
                Perhaps, then, it is unsurprising that in the digital, “networked” age, political
                theorists are reassessing the value of in-person spaces precisely in their capacity
                to “foster reciprocity and accommodation, through repeated interactions,” to use
                Forestal’s phrase. For, so long as the digital realm is associated with
                “boundlessness” it also harbors a dangerous, individuating conception of “freedom
                without society,” freedom wielded <hi rend="italic">only</hi> as <hi rend="italic"
                    >“</hi>a pure instrument of power, shorn of concern for others, the world, or
                the future.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Brown,<hi rend="italic">In the
                        Ruins, </hi>45.</note>
            </p>
                    
            <p>Reading the narratives like Hogg’s reminds us that space is neither value-neutral nor
                mere staging grounds for the more significant work of conversation and
                information-sharing. Rather, “human orderings of space and the meanings attributed
                to those orderings shape our conceptualizations of who and what we are, especially
                in life with others.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Brown,<hi
                        rend="italic">In the Ruins, </hi>51.</note> Here is where Hogg is
                particularly insightful. While Wringhim’s religiosity leads him to antisociality,
                Hogg—as Herbert notes—never reflexively equates <hi rend="italic">all </hi>religious
                belief with antisocial intolerance. Rather, Wringhim’s fervent religiosity is
                channeled into extremism by an assemblage of forces that today tend to be associated
                with “the rise of the digital”: his sense of belonging to a “radically
                deterritorialized and dedemocratized sociality” (to return to Brown’s words), as
                well as his conviction that the exercise of true individual “freedom” is <hi
                    rend="italic">inherently</hi> constrained by conditions of cohabitation or what
                Blanchard calls the “bond of society on earth.”<note place="foot" resp="author"
                    > Brown,<hi rend="italic">In the Ruins, </hi>183; Hogg, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Private Memoirs,</hi>142.</note> For Hogg, a particular ordering of space
                yields a particularly dangerous form of religious individualism.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
            <head>Strange Times and Strange Essays</head>
                    
            <p>In this essay, I’ve tried to elucidate the ways that my personal experiences in
                higher education—the financial precariousness of my institution, the uncertain
                conditions of my spouse’s job, the alarmingly optimistic predictions about the
                long-term leveling properties of digital scholarly and pedagogic “networks”—are
                filtered through my research interests. My own published work has focused almost
                entirely on nineteenth-century literature and religion, but, as this essay
                demonstrates, I find resonances between this content and my more casual interests in
                digital communities and modern networked society. Inescapably, these resonances
                inflect how I see current issues.</p>
                    
            <p>There is some saying, I think, about how breadth comes at the expense of depth.
                Certainly in the eclecticism of this essay, the truth of this adage is self-evident.
                In the effort to be timely, as well as to move across centuries, different types of
                media, and vastly different topics to think through this moment, I’ve left issues
                unaddressed and oversimplified much of the historical material I study. This is an
                experimental piece for me, but my hope is that this approach might yield new
                constellations of thought that otherwise would have been missed. </p>
                    
            <p>After all, in an essay partly about the forces that engender ideological echo
                chambers, it perhaps is apt that this piece resists another type of “echo chamber,”
                specifically the insistently presentist orientation of most popular writings about
                higher education and the Internet. As mentioned above, there is so much emphasis on
                the <hi rend="italic">unprecedentedness </hi>of digital technologies and
                communities, as though history and the narratives of the past (particularly
                fictional narratives) offer little to guide us forward in such “unprecedented”
                times. But such presentist rhetoric reinforces a certain myopia in how we conceive
                of higher education and the “disruptions” of digital technologies, for, whether we
                like it or not, we <hi rend="italic">already,</hi>reflexively, rely on historical
                precedents to conceive of and justify the “virtual” networks of the present. </p>
                    
            <p>And these metaphors are not merely descriptive. Often, historical spaces—the Wild
                West, the town square, even the “super highway”—are invoked in relation to the
                Internet only insofar as they are assumed to mirror the present. But it is no new
                insight that the historical metaphors by which we conceive of the present shape what
                might come in the future. Indeed, as evinced in his criticism of the Covenanters
                despite his sympathy with the cause of Scottish nationalism, Hogg himself perceived
                that more savvy deployments of the past were needed to yield better futures (at
                least, better than those being brought to fruition by Scottish radical
                evangelicals). That is, he saw that the political dangers of past “network
                societies” demonstrated how “networks” were never <hi rend="italic"
                    >intrinsically</hi> emancipatory, nor individual freedom ever an <hi
                    rend="italic">inherent</hi> political good.</p>
                    
            <p>Historian Joanne Meyerowitz’s essay on the difficulties of contemporary categories of
                sex and gender in capturing the “whole story” of “narratives of the past” gets at
                what I’m trying to say: “Historical texts are useful in this way because they pry us
                out of the familiar and thereby position us, in a sense, to anachronize the present
                … The past can show us that our own ways of seeing the world are contingent,
                curious, and changeable.”<note place="foot" resp="author" > Joanne
                    Meyerowitz, “Thinking Sex with an Androgyne,”<hi rend="italic">GLQ</hi>17, no. 1
                    (2011), 103.</note> Meyerowitz’s optimism that the past empowers us to see the
                present as “contingent” returns me to the context of higher education. In higher
                education, we think of “contingency” in relation to one of the term’s definitions,
                as “conditional” or dependent for existence on something else (i.e., in using the
                phrase “contingent faculty”). This sense of “contingency” places academic labor and
                higher education institutions in a position of defensive responsiveness. Often—and
                especially lately—it feels that we have little choice but to adapt as quickly as
                possible to larger economic, political, and technological forces out of our control.
                But Meyerowitz points to the past to remind us that “contingency” isn’t just the
                passive acceptance of present circumstances. Rather, “contingency” also<hi
                    rend="italic"> </hi>carries with it the recognition that our circumstances are
                changeable, can be “touched” (to return to the word’s etymological association with
                the Latin <hi rend="italic">tangere</hi>) precisely by how we decide to engage with
                the past. Texts such as Hogg’s, then, maybe aren’t only artifacts of a distant time
                and culture. Attentive to the ways new technologies enabled new forms of “imagined
                communities,” the novel also proves a rumination on our current orderings of space,
                offering a prescient view of the problems that might accompany uncritical acceptance
                of a supposedly inevitable “digital” and networked future. </p>
                </div>
            
            <div type="citation">
            <head>Works Cited</head>
                
            <bibl>Anderson, Benedict. <hi rend="italic">Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin
                    and Spread of Nationalism</hi>. New York: Verso Books, 1983. </bibl>
            <bibl>Bensinger, Greg. “Does Zuckerberg Understand How the Right to Free Speech Works?” <hi
                    rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, July 8, 2020, <ref
                    target="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/08/opinion/facebook-civil-rights-audit.html"
                >New York Times</ref></bibl>
            <bibl>Brown, Wendy. <hi rend="italic">In the Ruins of Neoliberalism: The Rise of
                    Antidemocratic Politics in the West.</hi> New York: Columbia University Press,
                2019.</bibl>
            <bibl>Buzard, James.<hi rend="italic"> Disorienting Fiction: The Autoethnographic Work of
                    Nineteenth-Century British Novels. </hi>Princeton: Princeton University Press,
                2005.</bibl>
            <bibl>Campbell, Heidi. “Understanding the Relationship between Religion Online and Offline
                in a Networked Society.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Academy of
                    Religion </hi>80, no. 4 (March 2012): 64-93.</bibl>
            <bibl>Carroll, Siobhan.<hi rend="italic"> An Empire of Air and Water: Uncolonizable Space
                    in the British Imagination, 1750-1850</hi>. Philadelphia: University of
                Pennsylvania Press, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl>Carté Engel, Katherine. “The SPCK and the American Revolution: The Limits of
                International Protestantism.” <hi rend="italic">Church History</hi> 81, no. 1
                (2012): 77-103.</bibl>
            <bibl>Castells, Manuel. <hi rend="italic">The Rise of the Network Society</hi>. Cambridge,
                MA: Blackwell Press, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl>Clark, Christopher and Michael Ledger-Lomas. “The Protestant International.” In <hi
                    rend="italic">Religious Internationals in the Modern World: Globalization and
                    Faith Communities since 1750</hi>, edited by Abigail Green and Vincent Viaene,
                25-52. New York: Palgrave MacMillan, 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl>Colley, Linda. <hi rend="italic">Britons: Forging the Nation 1707-1837</hi>. New
                Haven: Yale University Press, 1992.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cross, Anthony. <hi rend="italic">Peter the Great Through British Eyes: Perceptions
                    and Representation of the Tsar Since 1698. </hi>Cambridge: Cambridge University
                Press, 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl>Daniels, Jessie and Polly Thistlethwaite. <hi rend="italic">Being a Scholar in the
                    Digital Era: Transforming Scholarly Practice for the Public Good. </hi>Bristol,
                UK: Policy Press, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl>Duncan, Ian. “Fanaticism and Civil Society: Hogg’s <hi rend="italic">Justified
                    Sinner</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">Novel</hi> 42, no. 2 (2009): 343-48.</bibl>
            <bibl>---. “Fanaticism and Enlightenment in <hi rend="italic">Confessions of a Justified
                    Sinner</hi>.” In <hi rend="italic">James Hogg and the Literary Marketplace:
                    Scottish Romanticism and the Working-Class Author</hi>, edited by Sharon Alker
                and Holly Faith Nelson. New York: Routledge, 2009. Kindle.</bibl>
            <bibl>Forestal, Jennifer. “The Architecture of Political Spaces: Trolls, Digital Media, and
                Deweyan Democracy,” <hi rend="italic">American Political Science Review</hi> 111,
                no. 1 (2017): 149-61.</bibl>
            <bibl>Harwell, Drew and Ellen Nakashima. “Federal Prosecutors Accuse Zoom Executive of
                Working with Chinese Government to Surveil Users and Suppress video calls.” <hi
                    rend="italic">The Washington Post</hi>, December 18, 2020. <ref
                    target="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2020/12/18/zoom-helped-china-surveillance"
                >Washington Post</ref></bibl>
            <bibl>Herbert, Christopher.<hi rend="italic"> Culture and Anomie: Ethnographic Imagination
                    in the Nineteenth Century</hi>. Chicago: Chicago University Press, 1991.</bibl>
            <bibl>---. <hi rend="italic">Evangelical Gothic: The English Novel and the Religious War on
                    Virtue from Wesley to Dracula</hi>. Charlottesville: University of Virginia
                Press, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hobson, Katherine “Feeling Lonely? Too Much Time On Social Media May Be Why.” <hi
                    rend="italic">National Public Radio</hi>, March 6, 2017. <ref
                    target="https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2017/03/06/518362255/feeling-lonely-too-much-time-on-social-media-may-be-why"
                >National Public Radio</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>Hogg, James. <hi rend="italic">The Private Memoirs and Confessions of a Justified
                    Sinner. </hi>Edited by Adrian Hunter<hi rend="italic">. </hi>Toronto: Broadview
                Press, 2001.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hunter, Adrian. Introduction to <hi rend="italic">The Private Memoirs and Confessions
                    of a Justified Sinner</hi>, by James Hogg, 7-39. Toronto: Broadview Press,
                2001.</bibl>
            <bibl>Jenkins, Philip.<hi rend="italic"> The Next Christendom: The Coming of Global
                    Christianity</hi>. New York: Oxford University Press, 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl>King, Joshua. <hi rend="italic">Imagined Spiritual Communities in Britain’s Age of
                    Print. </hi>Columbus, OH: The Ohio State University Press, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl>Knight, Mark. <hi rend="italic">Good Words: Evangelicalism and the Victorian
                    Novel</hi>. Columbus, OH: The Ohio State University Press, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl>Lee, Micah and Yael Grauer, “Zoom Meetings Aren’t End-to-End Encrypted, Despite
                Misleading Marketing.” <hi rend="italic">The Intercept</hi>, March 31, 2020. <ref
                    target="https://theintercept.com/2020/03/31/zoom-meeting-encryption/">The Intercept</ref></bibl>
            <bibl>Lee, Yoon Sun. “Charlotte Smith’s Network Story.” In <hi rend="italic">Global
                    Romanticism: Origins, Orientations, and Engagements, 1760-1920</hi>, edited by
                Evan Gottlieb, 37-55. Lewisburg, PA: Bucknell University Press, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl>Linkins, Jason. “The Death of the Good Internet Was an Inside Job.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >The New Republic</hi>, December 31, 2019. <ref
                    target="https://newrepublic.com/article/156096/death-good-internet-inside-job-decade-hell"
                >New Republic</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>McPherson, Miller, Lynn Smith-Lovin, and James M. Cook. “Birds of a Feather:
                Homophily in Social Networks.” <hi rend="italic">Annual Review of Sociology</hi> 27,
                no. 1 (2001): 415-44.</bibl>
            <bibl>Meyerowitz, Joanne. “Thinking Sex with an Androgyne.” <hi rend="italic">GLQ</hi> 17,
                no. 1 (2011): 97-105.</bibl>
            <bibl>Morozov, Evgeny. <hi rend="italic">The Net Delusion: The Dark Side of Internet
                    Freedom</hi>. New York: Perseus Books, 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl>Phillips, Whitney. <hi rend="italic">This is Why We Can’t Have Nice Things: Mapping
                    the Relationship Between Online Trolling and Mainstream Culture</hi>. Cambridge:
                MIT University Press, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl>Rosen, Andrew and Jaime Lester. “Supporting Faculty Careers Amid Uncertainty.” <hi
                    rend="italic">Inside Higher Ed</hi>, July 2, 2020. <ref
                    target="https://www.insidehighered.com/views/2020/07/02/supporting-faculty-careers-amid-season-uncertainty-opinion"
                >Inside Higher Ed</ref></bibl>
            <bibl>Rushkoff, Douglas. <hi rend="italic">Team Human</hi>. New York; London: W. W. Norton
                &amp; Co., 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl>Smith, Michael D. “Are Universities Going the Way of CDs and Cable TV?” <hi
                    rend="italic">The Atlantic</hi>, June 22, 2020. <ref
                    target="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2020/06/university-like-cd-streaming-age/613291/"
                >The Atlantic</ref></bibl>
            <bibl>Tao, Yanqiu, Debbie Steckel, Jiří Jaromír Klemeš, and Fengqi You. “Trend Towards
                Virtual and Hybrid Conferences May Be an Effective Climate Change Mitigation
                Strategy.” <hi rend="italic">Nature Communications</hi>, December 16, 2021. <ref
                    target="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-27251-2">Nature</ref></bibl>
            <bibl>Taparia, Hans. “The Future of College is Online, and It’s Cheaper.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >The New York Times</hi>, May 25, 2020. <ref
                    target="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/05/25/opinion/online-college-coronavirus.html"
                >New York Times</ref></bibl>
            <bibl>Thompson, John B. <hi rend="italic">The Media and Modernity: A Social Theory of the
                    Media.</hi> Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl>Thomson, James. “The Seasons.” Winter Werner2024-04-11T15:41:00WW<note>There is no
                    editor listed; and, in fact, the preface says this collection of Thomson’s works
                    was “designed” by Thomson himself</note>Anna
                    Wingfield2024-03-15T10:50:00RAE<note>Is there an editor for this
                    collection?</note>In <hi rend="italic">The Works of James Thomson</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">. </hi>London: A. Millar, 1750.</bibl>
            <bibl>Tufecki, Zeynep.<hi rend="italic"> Twitter and Tear Gas: The Power and Fragility of
                    Networked Protest</hi>. New Haven: Yale University Press, 2017.</bibl>
            <bibl>Walls, Andrew F. <hi rend="italic">The Cross-Cultural Process in Christian History.
                </hi>Maryknoll: Orbis Books, 2002.</bibl>
            <bibl>Warner, Michael.<hi rend="italic"> Publics and Counterpublics. </hi>Princeton: Zone
                Books, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl>Werner, Winter Jade. <hi rend="italic">Missionary Cosmopolitanism in
                    Nineteenth-Century British Literature</hi>. Columbus: The Ohio State University
                Press, 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl>White, Daniel E. <hi rend="italic">Early Romanticism and Religious Dissent</hi>.
                Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl>Wohlgemut, Esther. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Cosmopolitanism. </hi>New York:
                Palgrave MacMillan, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl>Yen, Alfred C. “Western Frontier or Feudal Society: Metaphors and Perceptions of
                Cyberspace.” <hi rend="italic">Berkeley Technology Law Journal </hi>17, no. 4 (Fall
                2002): 1207-1264. </bibl>
            <bibl>Žižek, Slavoj. “Monitor and Punish? Yes, Please!” <hi rend="italic">Los Angeles
                    Review of Books</hi>, March 16, 2020. <ref
                    target="https://thephilosophicalsalon.com/monitor-and-punish-yes-please/">The Philosophical Salon</ref></bibl>
            </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
