<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title> 
                
                <title level="a">Annotated and Illustrated Reading Text of <title level="a">An Excursion up Scawfell Pike</title></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Dorothy Wordsworth</name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor">Paul Westover</editor> 
                
                <funder>Brigham Young University College of Humanities</funder>
                <principal>Paul Westover</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>T. J. McLemore</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                    </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                
                <idno type="edition">editions.2022.DW.SP-reading</idno>
                <idno type="resource">DW</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        
                        <title level="a" type="main">Annotated and Illustrated Reading Text of <title level="a">An Excursion up Scawfell Pike</title></title>
                        <ptr target="editions.2022.DW.SP-reading.html"/>
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                        <title level="s">Editions</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  PUT YOUR NAME HERE. AND CHANGE THE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION  -->
                <name>Lavender Earnest</name>
                <date>2022-09-30</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                
                <head>Annotated and Illustrated Reading Text of <title level="a">An Excursion up Scawfell Pike</title></head>
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">As outlined in the section introduction, this reading text is based on 
                    DCMS 51, with a necessary shift to the Kenyon Manuscript indicated at n21.</note>  <!--Add anchor in SP-A!-->
                                  
                <p>Sir George and Lady Beaumont spent a few days with us lately, and I accompanied them
                to Keswick. Mr. and Mrs. Wilberforce and their family happened to be at Keswick at
                the same time, and we all dined together in the romantic Vale of Borrowdale, at the
                house of a female friend, Miss Barker, an unmarried lady, who, bewitched with the
                charms of the rocks, and streams, and mountains of that secluded spot, has there
                built herself a house,<note place="foot" resp="editors">To be precise, Mary Barker&#8217;s
                home was in Rosthwaite. Green, in his <title level="m">Tourist&#8217;s New Guide</title> (1819),
                mentions the new structure and its surroundings: &#8220;On the banks of the Stonethwaite
                arm of the Derwent, there has recently been erected, by Miss Barker, an excellent house,
                commanding a fine view over the river, and of the rocky elevations, called Hay Stacks.
                There is scarcely amongst these northern vallies, a place, in which an equally valuable
                collection of painters&#8217; studies may be so speedily collected&#8221; (2:136). <!--<figure>                             
                    <graphic url="/sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B1.jpg" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                    <figDesc>Mary Barker&#8217;s former home in Rosthwaite, Borrowdale, now the Scafell Hotel. Photo: Paul Westover (October 2018)</figDesc>
                </figure>--></note></p>
            
            <!--Paul indicates that these pictures should be "pop ups". I'm assuming that means we'll have to do something different here-->
            
                
                 
           
                <p>and, though she is admirably fitted for society, and has as much enjoyment when
                surrounded by friends as any one <hi rend="italic">can</hi> have, her chearfulness has never
                flagged, though she has lived more than the year round alone in Borrowdale, at six
                miles distance from Keswick, with bad roads between.</p><!--<note resp="editors"><figure>
                <graphic url="sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B2.jpg" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                <figDesc><title level="m">View on the Road from Keswick</title> to Borrowdale by Joseph
                    Farington, engraved by F. R. Hay, published by T. Cadell and W. Davies, London,
                    1815. (Courtesy: Geography Department, Portsmouth University)</figDesc>
            </figure></note>-->
           
            <p>You will guess that she has resources within herself; such indeed she has. She is a
                painter and labours hard in depicting the beauties of her favourite vale; she is
                also fond of music and of reading; and has a reflecting mind: besides (though before
                she lived in Borrowdale she was no great walker) she is become an active climber of
                the hills, and I must tell you of a feat that she and I performed on Wednesday the
                7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this month. I remained in Borrowdale after
                Sir George and Lady Beaumont and the Wilberforces were gone, and Miss Barker
                proposed<note place="foot" resp="editors">Here we find a clue about the likely 
                relationship between the surviving manuscripts. In DCMS 51, DW first writes
                &#8220;Miss Barker proposed to me,&#8221; then crosses out &#8220;to me,&#8221;
                opting for a more economical expression. The Kenyon Transcript retains &#8220;to
                me&#8221; and other words crossed out in DCMS 51, suggesting that it was copied
                directly from the original letter to Johnson or else from an early copy that has
                not survived.</note> that the next day she and I should go to Seathwaite beyond
                the black lead mines<note place="foot" resp="editors">Borrowdale&#8217;s black lead 
                mines, also called plumbago or wad mines, produced high-quality graphite for 
                various purposes, notably pencil manufacture in nearby Keswick. The mines had 
                been open since the sixteenth century, and they featured in contemporary maps 
                and guidebooks. Mine tailings are still easily seen from Seathwaite.</note> 
                at the head of Borrowdale, and thence up a mountain called at the top <hi
                rend="italic">Ash Course</hi>, which we suppose may be a corruption of <hi
                rend="italic">Esk Hawes</hi>, as it is a settling between the mountains over
                which the people are accustomed to pass between Eskdale and Borrowdale; and such
                settlings are generally called by the name of &#8220;the Hawes&#8221;&#8212;as 
                Grisedale Hawes, Buttermere Hawes&#8212;from the German word Hals (neck).
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">DW is correct in her etymology&#8212;<hi
                rend="italic">hause</hi>, <hi rend="italic">hawse</hi>, and
                <hi rend="italic">hawes</hi> are northern forms of <hi rend="italic">halse,</hi>
                which does mean &#8220;neck&#8221; like its German cognate&#8212;and is 
                probably right to assume that local pronunciation has drifted somewhat. 
                The usual spelling of &#8220;Ash Course&#8221; today is &#8220;Esk Hause.&#8221;
                At this high pass, 2,470 feet above sea level, several footpaths 
                intersect&#8212; from Borrowdale, Eskdale, Langdale, and (indirectly) Wasdale.</note> At the top 
                of Ash Course Miss Barker had promised I should see a magnificent prospect; but
                we had some miles to travel to the foot of the mountain,
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">The distance from Rosthwaite to Seathwaite 
                Farm is about 2.5 miles, or 4 kilometers.</note> and accordingly went thither 
                in a cart&#8212;Miss Barker, her maid, and myself.</p> <!--<note place="foot" resp="editors"><figure>
                <graphic url="sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B4.jpg" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                <figDesc>The road to Seathwaite in October 2018. Photo: Paul Westover.</figDesc>
            </figure></note>-->
                
            <p>We departed before nine o&#8217;clock. The sun shone; the sky was clear and blue; and light
                and shade fell in masses upon the mountains; the fields below <hi rend="italic">glittered</hi>
                with the dew, where the beams of the sun could reach them; and
                every little stream tumbling down the hills seemed to add to the chearfulness of the
                scene.</p>
                
            <p>We left our cart at Seathwaite<note place="foot" resp="editors">DW seems mistakenly to 
                have written &#8220;Stonethwaite&#8221; rather than &#8220;Seathwaite&#8221; in her 
                letter&#8212;&#8220;Stonethwaite&#8221; persists in the Kenyon Transcript&#8212;but 
                in DCMS 51 she spots her error and makes the appropriate correction. See n19 for a 
                parallel instance.</note> and proceeded, with a man to carry our provisions, and a 
                kind neighbour of Miss Barker&#8217;s, a statesman and shepherd of the vale, as our companion 
                and Guide.</p><!--<note place="foot" resp="editors"><figure>
                <graphic url="sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B5.jpg" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                <figDesc>Seathwaite Farm, where the walkers left their cart behind. Photo: Paul Westover (October 2018).</figDesc>
            </figure></note>-->
                
            <p>We found ourselves at the top of Ash Course without a weary limb, having had the
                fresh air of autumn to help us up by its invigorating power, and the sweet warmth of
                the unclouded sun to tempt us to sit and rest by the way. From the top of Ash Course
                we beheld a prospect which would indeed have amply repaid me<note place="foot" resp="editors">
                Here De Sélincourt&#8217;s text (in <title level="m">DWJ</title>) has &#8220;repaid us&#8221; 
                rather than &#8220;repaid me,&#8221; accepting what may be WW&#8217;s pencil revision in DCMS 51.
                We retain the original reading in pen. (Interestingly, WW&#8217;s 1822 <title level="m">Guide</title> 
                ended up removing this passage altogether.) Meanwhile, the Kenyon Transcript has &#8220;I 
                beheld&#8221; rather than &#8220;we beheld&#8221; at the beginning of this sentence, suggesting
                that DW&#8217;s original point of view was first-person singular.</note> for a <hi rend="italic">toilsome</hi>
                journey, if such it had been; and a sense of thankfulness for the continuance of that vigour
                of body, which enabled me to climb the high mountain, as in the days of my youth, inspiring
                me with fresh chearfulness, added a delight, a charm to the contemplation of the magnificent
                scenes before me which I cannot describe. Still less can I tell you the glories of what we saw.</p><!--<note place="foot" resp="editors"><figure>
                    <graphic url="sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B6.jpg" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                <figDesc>View of Esk Hause from the lower slopes of Esk Pike (July 2006).
                    Photo: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=14456508">Bill Boaden, 2016</ref>.</figDesc>
            </figure></note>-->
            
            <p>Three views, each distinct in its kind, we saw at once: the vale of Borrowdale, of
                Keswick, of Bassenthwaite&#8212;Skiddaw, Saddleback, Helvellyn, numerous other mountains,
                and, still beyond, the Solway Frith,<note place="foot" resp="editors">The Solway Firth,
                an inlet of the Irish Sea, forms part of the border between North West England and 
                South West Scotland. &#8220;Firth&#8221; has solidified as the standard form, but in DW&#8217;s time,
                &#8220;firth&#8221; and &#8220;frith&#8221; were interchangeable.</note> 
                and the Mountains of Scotland. Nearer to us on the other side, and below us, were
                the Langdale Pikes&#8212;their own Vale below <hi rend="italic">them</hi>, Windermere&#8212;and,
                far beyond, after a long long distance, Ingleborough in Yorkshire. But how shall I
                speak of the peculiar deliciousness of the third prospect! At this time <hi
                rend="italic">that</hi> was most favoured by sunshine and shade. The green Vale
                of Esk&#8212;deep and green, with its glittering serpent stream was below us; and on we
                looked to the mountains near the sea&#8212;Black Comb and others&#8212;and still beyond, 
                to the sea itself in dazzling brightness.<note place="foot" resp="editors">Here in 
                DCMS 51, DW has deleted &#8220;At this same station, (making as it might be called 
                a 4th division or prospect).&#8221; The Kenyon Transcript retains the orientation 
                gesture with slight variation: &#8220;At this same Station making what may be called
                a 4th Division, turning round, we saw the mountains of Wasdale.&#8221;</note> 
                Turning round we saw the mountains of Wasdale in tumult; and Great Gavel, though the
                middle of the mountain was to us as its base, looked very grand.</p>
            
            <p>We had attained the object of our journey; but our ambition mounted higher. We saw
                the summit of Scaw Fell, as it seemed, very near to us: we were indeed, three parts
                up that mountain; and thither we determined to go. We found the distance greater
                than it had appeared to us; but our courage did not fail; however, when we came
                nearer we perceived that, in order to attain that summit, we must make a great
                dip,<note place="foot" resp="editors">The walkers showed wisdom in not attempting 
                this traverse via the col of Mickledore, a &#8220;dip&#8221; of some 454 feet. 
                The narrow ridge is difficult and potentially dangerous for non-experts. Wainwright
                writes colorfully in his <title level="m">Pictorial Guide</title>, &#8220;Medals 
                have been won for lesser deeds. This is a walk not to be undertaken lightly, and 
                not at all if time is short or if limbs are already tired&#8221; (4: Scafell Pike, 29). 
                </note> and that the ascent afterwards would be exceedingly steep and difficult, 
                so that we might have been benighted if we had attempted it; therefore, unwillingly,
                we gave it up, and resolved, instead, to ascend another point of the same mountain, 
                called <hi rend="italic">the Pikes</hi>, and which, I have since found, the measurers
                of mountains estimate as higher than the larger summit which bears the name of Scaw
                Fell,<note place="foot" resp="editors">In the <title level="m">Guide</title>, WW gives
                &#8220;Scaw Fell Head&#8221; rather than &#8220;Scaw Fell,&#8221; presumably to 
                disambiguate further.</note> and where the Stone <hi rend="italic">Man</hi> is built,
                which we, at the time, considered as the point of highest honour.</p>
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8220;Stone Man&#8221; is a pile of stones that
                marks the summit. DW is correct in her account of the altitude. People long considered
                Scafell (3,163 ft.) the highest peak on the massif, but &#8220;the measurers of 
                mountains&#8221; (beginning with Joseph Banks&#8217;s Trigonometrical Survey team in 1790) 
                concluded that Scafell Pike (3,209 ft.) was in fact higher. Early nineteenth-century 
                maps depict this little-explored neighborhood without much detail; indeed, some show 
                no mountains at all. However, both Jonathan Otley&#8217;s map of 1818 and Sidney Hall&#8217;s map 
                for WW&#8217;s 1822 <title level="m">Guide</title> make the distinction between Scawfell 
                and the Scawfell Pike or Pikes. Today, Scafell Pike, Ill Crag, and Broad Crag are 
                often designated collectively as the &#8220;Pikes of Scafell.&#8221;<!--<figure>
                    <graphic url="sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B8.jpeg" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                    <figDesc>Detail of Sidney Hall&#8217;s map for William Wordsworth&#8217;s 1822 <title level="m">
                        Description of the Scenery of the Lakes</title> (Courtesy: Brigham Young
                        University, Harold B. Lee Library). Notice the &#8220;dip&#8221; between Scafell 
                        and Scafell Pike, apparent in the hachure work.</figDesc>                
            </figure>
            <figure><graphic url="sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B7.jpg" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                <figDesc>This photo of the Scafell
                        massif, taken from Yewbarrow, gives a striking view of the notch, Mickledore, 
                        between the peaks. From this point of view, Scafell (on the right) appears to 
                        be higher, but in fact Scafell Pike is the taller by 47 feet. 
                        <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Scafell_massif.jpg">Photo: Doug Sim, 2014</ref>.<figDesc></figure>--></note>
            
            <p>&#8212;The Sun had never once been overshadowed by a cloud during the whole of our progress
                from the centre of Borrowdale; at the summit of the Pike there was not a breath of
                air to stir even the papers which we spread out containing our food. There we ate
                our dinner in summer warmth; and the stillness seemed to be not of this world. &#8212; We
                paused, and kept silence to listen, and not a sound of any kind was to be heard. &#8212; 
                We were far above the reach of the cataracts of Scaw Fell; and not an insect was
                there to hum the air. The vales before described lay in view; and, side by side with
                Eskdale, we now saw the sister Vale of Donnerdale terminated by the Duddon Sands.
                But the majesty of the mountains below and close to us, is not to be conceived. We
                now beheld the whole mass of Great Gavel from its base&#8212;the Den of Wasdale at our
                feet, the gulph immeasurable&#8212;Grassmire<note place="foot" resp="editors">De Sélincourt
                in <title level="m">DWJ</title> (oddly) gives &#8220;Grasmere&#8221; for &#8220;Grassmire.&#8221;
                Meanwhile, the Kenyon Transcript has &#8220;Grassmere.&#8221; Regardless of spelling, DW refers
                to the peak now generally called Grasmoor (2,795 ft., or 852 m), which overlooks Crummock Water.</note> 
                and the other mountains of Crummock&#8212;Ennerdale and <hi rend="italic">its</hi>
                mountains; and the sea beyond.</p><!--<note place="foot" resp="editors"><figure>
                    <graphic url="sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B9.JPG" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                <figDesc>View from the summit, looking north toward Great Gable, the North Western Fells
                    (including Grasmoor), and Skiddaw in the distance (upper right). On Skiddaw, the
                    Wilberforces, the Beaumonts, and William Green were having their own adventure.
                    Photo: Joe Jackson, <ref target="www.lakedistrict-walks.co.uk.">www.lakedistrict-walks.co.uk.</ref></figDesc>
            </figure></note>-->
                
            <p>While we were looking round after dinner our guide said to us that we must not linger
                long, for we should have a storm. We looked in vain to espy the traces of it; for
                mountains, vales, and sea were all touched with the clear light of the sun. &#8220;It is
                there,&#8221; he said, pointing to the sea beyond Whitehaven; and, sure enough, we there
                perceived a light cloud, or mist, unnoticeable but by a shepherd, accustomed to
                watch all mountain bodings.<note place="foot" resp="editors">DW seems to recall the 
                vigilant shepherd of WW&#8217;s <title level="m">Michael</title>: &#8220;And in his shepherd&#8217;s     <!--Do I need to put this within <poetry> tags?-->
                calling he was prompt / And watchful more than ordinary men. / Hence he had learned the
                meaning of all winds, / Of blasts of every tone&#8221; (lines 46&#8211;49). She may also echo
                STC&#8217;s <title level="m">The Rime of the Ancyent Marinere</title>: &#8220;I saw something
                in the Sky / No bigger than my fist; / At first it seem&#8217;d a little speck / And then it 
                seem&#8217;d a mist: / It mov&#8217;d and mov&#8217;d, and took at last / A certain shape I wist&#8221; 
                (Part III, stanza 1 in 1798 text). This same passage from <title level="m">Rime</title> 
                may influence DW&#8217;s description of cloud shapes as discussed in n22.</note>
                We gazed around again and yet again, fearful to lose the remembrance of what lay
                before us in that lofty solitude; and then prepared to depart. Meanwhile the air
                changed to cold, and we saw the tiny vapour swelled into mighty masses of cloud
                which came boiling over the mountains. Great Gavel, Helvellyn, and Skiddaw were
                wrapped in storm; yet Langdale, and the mountains in that quarter were all bright
                with sunshine. Soon the storm reached us; we sheltered under a crag;<note place="foot" resp="editors">
                Likely, &#8220;crag&#8221; candidates for the party&#8217;s shelter in place are in 
                Calf Cove, just below Ill Crag, as noted in the <ref target="https://arcg.is/1C01Lv">Story Map</ref>.</note> 
                and, almost as rapidly as it had come, it passed away, and left us free to observe
                the goings-on of storm and sunshine in other quarters.</p>
                
            
            <p>Langdale had now its share, and the Pikes were decorated by two splendid rainbows;
               Skiddaw also had its own rainbows, but we were truly glad to see <hi rend="italic"
               >them</hi> and the clouds disappear from <hi rend="italic">that mountain</hi>,
               as we knew that Mr. and Mrs. Wilberforce and their family (if they kept the
               intention which they had formed when they parted the night before)
               <note place="foot" resp="editors">The Kenyon Transcript has &#8220;when
               <hi rend="italic">we</hi> parted the night before&#8221; (emphasis added).
               DCMS 51 inserts &#8220;had&#8221; in pencil, resulting in &#8220;when they had
               parted from us the night before,&#8221; but we ignore pencil marks in creating the
               reading text. As noted previously, many penciled edits move the text in the
               direction of the 1822 <title level="m">Guide</title>; however, this sentence did
               not appear at all in WW&#8217;s printed text.</note> must certainly be upon Skiddaw at 
               that very time&#8212;and so it was. They were there, and had much more rain than
               we had; we, indeed, were hardly at all wetted; and before we found ourselves 
               again upon that part of the mountain called Ash Course every cloud had vanished
               from every summit.</p>
                
            <p>Do not think we here gave up our spirit of enterprise. No! I had heard much of the
                grandeur of the view of Wasdale from Stye Head, the point from which Wasdale is
                first seen in coming by the road from Borrowdale; but though I had been in Wasdale I
                had never entered the dale by that road, and had often lamented that I had not seen
                what was so much talked of by travellers.</p>
                
            <!--<note place="foot" resp="editors"><figure>
                <graphic url="sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B10.jpg" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                
                <figDesc>William Green, <title level="m">Sty Head, between Borrowdale and Wardale</title> [Wasdale]
                    (undated). Watercolor. Gift of the W. W. Spooner Charitable Trust, 2014. (Courtesy:
                    The Wordsworth Trust)</figDesc>
            </figure></note>-->
            
            <p>Down to that pass (for we were yet far above it) we bent our course by the side of
                Ruddle Gill,<note place="foot" resp="editors">That is, Ruddy Gill.</note> 
                a very deep red chasm in the mountains, which begins at a spring&#8212;that spring forms a
                stream, which must, at times, be a mighty torrent, as is evident from the channel
                which it has wrought out thence by Sprinkling Tarn to Stye head;</p><!--<note place="foot" resp="editors"><figure>
                <graphic url="sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B12.jpg" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                <figDesc>Sprinkling Tarn from just above. Photo: Paul Westover (October 2018).</figDesc>
            </figure></note>-->
            
            <p>and there we sate and looked down into Wasdale. We were now upon Great Gavel which
                rose high above us. Opposite was Scaw Fell, and we heard the roaring of the stream,
                from one of the ravines of that mountain, which, though the bending of Wasdale Head
                lay between <hi rend="italic">us</hi> and Scaw Fell, we could look into, as it were;
                and the depth of the ravine appeared tremendous; it was black, and the crags were
                awful.</p><!--<note place="foot" resp="editors"><figure>
                    <graphic url="sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B14.jpg" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                <figDesc>Sty Head Pass panorama. Photo: Paul Westover (October 2018).</figDesc>
            </figure></note>-->
                          
            <p>We now proceeded homewards by Stye head Tarn along the road into Borrowdale.</p>
                
            <!--<note place="foot" resp="editors"><figure>
                <graphic url="sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B15.jpg" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                <figDesc>Sty Head Tarn from below, looking back up to the Sty Head Pass. The old trail runs to
                    its right. Photo: Paul Westover (October 2018).</figDesc>
            </figure></note>-->
            
            <p>Before we reached Seathwaite<note place="foot" resp="editors">&#8220;Seathwaite&#8221; is an 
               emendation. DCMS 51 is difficult to read here but appears to have &#8220;Stonethwaite&#8221; 
               rather than &#8220;Seathwaite.&#8221; The Kenyon Transcript clearly has &#8220;Stonethwaite,&#8221;
               suggesting that the slip was part of DW&#8217;s original letter. Previous editors have retained it.
               Nonetheless, as in the earlier instance (see n6), &#8220;Stonethwaite&#8221; is certainly a
               mistake. The walkers would end their descent from Sty Head at Seathwaite, where they would 
               retrieve their cart. From that place, they would take the 2.5-mile road back to Mary Barker&#8217;s
               home in Rosthwaite, passing the turn to nearby Stonethwaite but not taking it. It is true 
               that Rosthwaite is situated on the Stonethwaite arm of the River Derwent and that the toponyms
               resemble each other, so some confusion was understandable. WW, in the <title level="m">Guide</title>,
               correctly has &#8220;Seathwaite&#8221; in this position.</note> a few stars had appeared,
               and we travelled home in our cart by moonlight.</p>
                
            <p>I ought to have described the last part of our ascent to Scaw Fell Pike. There, not a
                blade of grass was to be seen&#8212;hardly a cushion of moss, and that was parched and
                brown; and only growing rarely between the huge blocks and stones which cover the
                summit and lie in heaps all round to a great distance, like skeletons or bones of
                the earth not wanted at the creation, and there left to be covered with never-dying
                lichens, which the clouds and dews nourish; and adorn with colours of the most vivid
                and exquisite beauty, and endless in variety.</p><!--<note place="foot" resp="editors">
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="sites/default/files/imported/editions/DW/images/5B16.jpg" width="200px" rend="inline"/>
                <figDesc>Lichens high on the Scafell massif (near Ill Crag). Photo: Paul Westover (June
                    2011).</figDesc>
            </figure></note>-->
            
            <p>No gems or flowers can surpass in colouring the beauty of some of these masses of
                stone, which no human eye beholds, except the shepherd is led thither by chance or
                the traveller by curiosity; and how seldom must this happen! The other eminence<note place="foot" resp="editors">
                The &#8220;other eminence&#8221; is neighboring Scafell, which DW mentions earlier as the supposed
                &#8220;point of highest honour.&#8221; She may have a particular &#8220;adventurous traveller&#8221; 
                in mind: STC, who made a pioneering ascent of Scafell in 1802.</note> is that which is 
                visited by the adventurous traveller, and the <hi rend="italic">shepherd</hi> has no 
                temptation to go thither in quest of his sheep; for on the <hi rend="italic">Pike</hi>
                there is no food to tempt them.</p>
                
            <p>We certainly were singularly fortunate in the day; for when we were seated on the
                summit our Guide, turning his eyes thoughtfully round, said to us, &#8220;I do not know
                that in my whole life I was ever at any season of the year so high up on the
                mountains on so calm a day.&#8221; Afterwards, you know, we had the storm which exhibited
                to us the grandeur of earth and heaven commingled, yet without terror; for we knew
                that the storm would pass away; for so our prophetic Guide assured us. I forgot to
                tell you that I espied a ship upon the glittering sea while we were looking over Esk
                dale. &#8220;Is it a ship?&#8221; replied the Guide. &#8220;A ship! yes it can be nothing else, don&#8217;t
                you see the shape of it?&#8221; Miss Barker interposed, &#8220;It is a ship,<note place="foot" resp="editors">
                At this point (after &#8220;ship&#8221; and an indecipherable cancellation), DCMS 51 has
                a gap: more than half of the final page is missing, torn away. Our reading text therefore
                depends mainly on the Kenyon Transcript from here to the close. Note that our text differs
                in small details from those given in <title level="m">Letters</title> and <title level="m">DWJ</title>.
                The following fragments are legible on the final page of DCMS 51: &#8220;[?] to / of / 
                our / -mon performances o / -ker &amp; I each wrote a [?] / top of the Pike of Scaw Fell /
                -distant Friend, Sara Hutchin / South Wales. / October 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> 1818 / 
                Went up Scaw Fell on Wednesday the / 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October&#8212;1818.&#8221;</note> 
                of that I am certain&#8212;I cannot be mistaken, I am so accustomed to the appearance of
                ships at sea.&#8221; The Guide dropped the argument; but a minute was scarcely gone when
                he quietly said, &#8220;Now look at your ship, it is now a horse.&#8221; So indeed it was, with
                a gallant neck and head. We laughed heartily, and I hope when I am again inclined to
                positiveness I may remember the ship and the horse upon the glittering sea; and the
                calm confidence, yet submission of our wise Man of the Mountains, who certainly had
                more knowledge of <hi rend="italic">clouds</hi> than we, whatever might be our
                knowledge of <hi rend="italic">ships</hi>.<note place="foot" resp="editors">Readers may
                detect various echoes (possibly tongue-in-cheek) in this memorable passage on clouds, 
                prophetic guides, and the limits of perception. See, for instance, the exchange between
                Elijah and Ahab at the end of 1 Kings 18 (&#8220;there ariseth a little cloud out of the sea,
                like a man&#8217;s hand&#8221;); or, for a playful contrast, the exchange between Hamlet and Polonius
                on clouds as camels, weasels, or whales in <title level="m">Hamlet</title> III.2. In any case, 
                &#8220;That which is now a horse, even with a thought / The rack dislimns, and makes it 
                indistinct / As water is in water&#8221; (<title level="m">Antony and Cleopatra</title>    <!--Do I need to use <quote> tags here, or is it good as-is?-->
                IV.14.11&#8211;13). Compare also the cloud passage from Coleridge&#8217;s <title level="m">Rime</title>
                cited in n15.</note> &#8212;To add to our uncommon performances on this day Miss Barker
                and I each wrote a letter from the top of the Pike to our far distant friend in
                South Wales&#8212;Sara Hutchinson.<note place="foot" resp="editors">These letters from 
                the summit are unfortunately lost.</note></p>
                
            <p>I believe that you are not much acquainted with the Scenery of this Country, except
                in the Neighbourhood of Grasmere, your duties when you were a resident here, having
                confined you so much to that one Vale; I hope, however, that my long Story will not
                be very dull; and even I am not without a further hope, that it may awaken in you a
                desire to spend a long holiday among the Mountains, and explore their recesses.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">This final paragraph, really a postscript, appears
                only in the Kenyon Transcript, suggesting that it appeared in the original Johnson 
                letter but that DW felt no need to copy it into her notebook.</note></p>
                
            </div>  
        
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
