<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce86</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.86</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng.
                        Lett. c. 22.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York,
                        1965), I, pp. 52&#8211;53 [in part; verses not reproduced].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.86" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="86" type="letter">
        <head>86. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1794-04-13">13 April
                        1794</date>
          </head><p>Address: Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>./ New Palace Yard/ Westminster./
                        Single<lb /> Stamped: BRISTOL<lb />Postmark: AAP/ 15/ 94<lb />Watermarks: G R
                        in a circle; figure of Britannia<lb />Endorsements: Wrote to R.S. Ap<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. 11/ 1794; Received this Ap<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. 14.
                        &amp; 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>/ 1794<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng.
                        Lett. c. 22<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York,
                        1965), I, pp. 52&#8211;53 [in part; verses not reproduced].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#CollegeGreenBristol">College Green. Bristol.</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1794-04-13">April 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Sunday. 1794</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> tis a long while since any thing in the shape of a letter has
                    reachd me from your part of the world. <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">your brother</ref> is obstinate
                    either in anger or in system. you are busied in the concerns of the nation &#8212;
                    &amp; I have been &#8212; at Oxford the worst place in the world for letter
                    writing. Friday morning. <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref>
                    called me before the clock struck three. up I got &#8212; we breakfasted &amp;
                    talked till five when I departed in the Mail. the folly of my companions
                    taciturnified me &#8212; their frigidity of intellect petrified my organs of voice.
                    his most amorous <ref target="people.html#CombeEdward">Majesty</ref> was an
                    outside passenger but I could not approach his person &amp; was silent all
                    the way. the next morning I conveyd my baggage to the inn. &amp; secured a
                    place in the Caravan newly launched on the plan of your Greenwich machines.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Specially designed long coaches which
                        could carry more passengers than a standard coach.</note> this was seven o
                    clock &amp; the coach was to set out at eight. I walked on leisurely. the
                    morning was warm &amp; when I had got four miles &#8212; I sat me down by a brook
                    to wait the coach. the spot was within a mile of the school where some of my
                    younger days were passed.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">This incident
                        inspired Southey&#8217;s &#8216;To a Brook near the Village of Corston&#8217;, published in
                            <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797).</note> &amp; upon viewing the
                    course of the brook I discovered it to the same in which every morning I washed
                    my hands &amp; face. the lapse of twelve years have not obliterated one
                    image from my memory &#8212; &amp; I have seldom past half an hour more agreably
                    in solitude than the one yesterday morning. the caravan came &#8212; in I went &#8212;
                    &amp; away to Bristol.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> there is something in the recollection of scenes of childhood
                    that give a pleasing melancholy to the mind. I remember the various hours of
                    alternate gaiety &amp; sorrow, business &amp; play that diversied my
                    time at Corston. on this subject Bowles<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Lisle Bowles (1762&#8211;1850; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> has
                    written so very beautiful a sonnet, that I am sure the inserting it will delight
                    you. </p>
        <p rend="indent3">To the river Itchin near Winton<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">First published in William Lisle Bowles, <title level="m">Fourteen Sonnets, Elegiac and Descriptive. Written during a
                            Tour</title> (1789).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent5"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Itchin when I behold thy banks again,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Thy crumbling margin &amp; thy silver breast</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> On which the self-same tints still seem to rest,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Why feels my heart the shivering sense of pain?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Is it &#8212; that many a summers day has past</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Since in Lifes morn I carold on thy side?</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Is it that oft since then my heart has sighd</l>
          <l rend="indent2">As Youth &amp; Hopes delusive gleams flew fast?</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Is it &#8212; that those who circled on thy shore</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Companions of my youth, now meet no more?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Whateer the cause, upon thy banks I bend</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Sorrowing &#8212; yet feel such solace at my heart,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">As at the meeting of some long lost friend</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> From whom in happier hours we wept to part.</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1"> The author of this sonnet, tho indisputably one of the first
                    poets of the day, is little known. he was of Trinity College Oxford. I have only
                    seen his sonnets &#8212; they are so scarce that a friend of mine<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s friend is unidentified.</note>
                    transcribed them, &amp; so beautiful that I have copied his transcription. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> now <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I have two pieces of poetry of a very different nature to
                    fill up my letter. the first is by <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">an
                        undergraduate</ref> whom I saw at the Anatomy School &#8212; physiognomised,
                    &amp; introduced myself to. a man of extraordinary ability.</p>
        <p rend="indent5"> To a Painter</p>
        <p rend="indent4">from Anacreon<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Greek
                        lyric poet Anacreon (fl. C6 BC). Allen&#8217;s translation of Anacreon&#8217;s <title level="m">Ode</title>, no. 16, follows.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent5"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">O skilld each mimic grace to wake</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Thy all creative pencil take &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Master of the rosy art</l>
          <l rend="indent2">To my rapturd eye impart</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The form thats picturd on my heart.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Thy pencil from my love-strung lyre</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Shall catch Expressions vivid fire.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Artist &#8212; be it first thy care</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Soft &amp; black to paint her hair,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And if thy skill such power can show</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Breathing odours let it flow.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Paint her forehead gleaming white</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Thro her ringlets dewy-bright &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Where each eye-brows wont to end</l>
          <l rend="indent2">In her nor seperate nor blend</l>
          <l rend="indent2">But let the arches of her brow</l>
          <l rend="indent2">An union in partition show.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Paint her speaking eye of fire</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Kindling flames of fierce desire</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Like Minervas to my view</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Let it rise celestial blue &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And as hers who yokes the dove</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Let it swim in liquid love.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The nose &amp; cheeks must boast an hue</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Like roses bathed in milky dew.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Her lips imbued with nectard bliss</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Must swell to meet the eager kiss.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Let her polishd neck below</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Like the Parian marble glow</l>
          <l rend="indent2">While round it all the graces fly</l>
          <l rend="indent2">That hold &amp; charm the Lovers eye.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Hide beneath a purple vest</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Modest Artist &#8212; hide the rest.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Yet still some little be reveald</l>
          <l rend="indent2">To show what treasures are conceald.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Enough! no picturd Maid is she</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Herself her lovely self I see.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">O skilld &#8230; I see: Verse in double columns.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent5"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p>the four last lines run more literally thus.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Yet let some little glisten thro</l>
          <l rend="indent2">To show what charms are kept from view</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Enough &#8212; no absent Maid I seek</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Soon wonderous portrait &#8212; soon youll speak.</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent5"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This translation pleases me much. <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Charles Collins</ref> has met the author
                    at my rooms &amp; taken a great liking to him. by the by poor <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Carlo</ref> has met with a grievous
                    misfortune. Don Quixotes library has been purged. Wynn &amp; I &#8212; guess whats
                    to come. the Curate &amp; the Barber &#8212; twas a good fire. the book case open.
                        Jack<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to Johannes Secundus
                        (1511&#8211;1536), <title level="m">Liber Basiorum</title> (<title level="m">Book
                            of Kisses</title>), published in 1541.</note> you know is of an
                    inflammable nature &amp; he burnt well. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &amp; Maule<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">George Maule (d. 1851), educated at Westminster
                        School and Christ Church (matric. 1793, BA 1797, MA 1800). He was a friend
                        of Southey&#8217;s during his time at Oxford, and possibly during his school days.
                        Maule pursued a legal career, and in 1818 was made Solicitor to the
                        Treasury.</note> held <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Signor
                        Carlo</ref> on the sofa &amp; I burnt Jack. next morning Maule carried
                    off La Pucelle<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="m">La
                            Pucelle</title> (1755&#8211;1762), a mock-epic poem by Voltaire
                        (1694&#8211;1778).</note> &amp; poor <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref> has nothing luscious left to amuse himself with except
                    Solomons Song &amp; the story of Potiphars Wife.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="m">The Song of Solomon</title> is concerned
                        with secular love. <title level="m">Genesis</title> 39: 7&#8211;19 describes the
                        attempts of Potiphar&#8217;s wife to seduce Joseph.</note> we made a most
                    incomparable ballad on the subject. a parody of the Son of Alknomok<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The popular ballad composed by Anne Hunter
                        (1742&#8211;1821; <title level="m">DNB</title>) and anthologised as 'The
                        Death-Song of a Cherokee Indian' in [Joseph Ritson (1752&#8211;1803; <title level="m">DNB</title>)], <title level="m">A Select Collection of English
                            Songs,</title> 3 vols (London, 1783), I, p. ii.</note>
        </p>
        <p> &#8220;But Ill buy my Johannes Secundus again.&#8221;</p>
        <p rend="indent3">Ode to my Stick yclept the Sans Culottes</p>
        <p rend="indent5"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">O worthy to be sung in loftiest lays</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Stay of my steps along the rugged road.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">I strike the lyre to hymn thy praise</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> To thee I write an ode.</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> The laurel wreath I spread</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> To deck thy holly head</l>
          <l rend="indent2">For with thy upright frame &amp; strenuous crook</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Thou hast a very democratic look.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Truth fill thy votaries strains &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Thy influence lend </l>
          <l rend="indent4"> So may the world attend</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And learn morality from Sticks &amp; Canes.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">And here I would reform an ugly trick</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> In a parenthesis.</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> For if a Parson preach amiss</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The folks will say he is a Stick.</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> A title very wrong</l>
          <l rend="indent2">His prattle being weak &amp; sticks being strong.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">World of the wise &amp; unwise list my strains</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Ye who use sticks the strong</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> And ye more numerous throng</l>
          <l rend="indent3">That strut about with canes.</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> For I will show</l>
          <l rend="indent2">That a fashionable cane is like a fashionable Beau.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent4"> What is a Beau?</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Oh God of Definitions be my friend!</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Spirits of Lexicographers descend.</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> What is a Beau?</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Is it a man or no?</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">When at some mighty call</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Pards lyons tygers buffaloes grew tame &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And the fierce Ouran outangs all</l>
          <l rend="indent2">With all his cousin apes round Adam came</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Each to receive from him his destind name &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Did he the Father of mankind or no</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Behold one Beau?</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Tom Paine<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Paine
                            (1737&#8211;1809; <title level="m">DNB</title>), author of <title level="m">The Rights of Man</title> (1791&#8211;1792).</note> has said</l>
          <l rend="indent2">(And Thomas never speaks without good cause)</l>
          <l rend="indent2">That Lords &amp; Dukes were never known to Adam.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">It may perhaps appear against the laws</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Thus to declare that I his book have read.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Reeves<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">On 20 November 1792, John Reeves (1752&#8211;1829; <title level="m">DNB</title>) established the Association for Preserving
                            Liberty and Property against Republicans and Levellers.</note> may say
                        that I a traitor bad am.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">But more than Tom has said shall Robert sing.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">I say that Adam never knew a King.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And since nor Kings nor Courts did Adam know</l>
          <l rend="indent2">By what strange miracle could he have seen a Beau?</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent4"> Do coral rocks produce green peas?</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Do Oysters grow on Cherry trees?</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> When Nature only reignd the Queen</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> How could a Beau be seen!</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Twere hard to say what a Beau is</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> To say what he is not is easy.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">I will do this</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> To please ye.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent4"> He does not bear the upright manly gait</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Which honest Independance loves to wear</l>
          <l rend="indent3">He knows not firm in Stoic strength to bear</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The ills of Fortune &amp; the frowns of Fate.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Nor his the sinewy form the open eye</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The fearless front of virtuous honesty.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Nor firm on Freedoms adamantine rock</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Dares he to brave Oppressions powerful shock</l>
          <l rend="indent3">To breathe Defiance in his parting breath</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Smile on the scaffold &#8212; &amp; exult in Death.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Oh Bruin Bruin Bruin Bruin bear</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Do not from Alpine heights descend</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Do not thy journey to the valleys bend &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent3">For ah &#8212; thou knowest not all the dangers there.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Poor brother Bruin if thou shouldest be caught</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Thou dost not know thy lamentable lot!</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Wouldst thou conceive that Man should bore thy nose</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Teach thee to dance &amp; eke turn out thy toes,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And call the crowd around &amp; play his flute</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Till he himself appears the greatest brute.</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Ah Bruin Bruin</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Much do I feel for thee poor Bruin Bear!</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> These wicked Beaus will prove thy ruin</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And take thy grease to grease their Asses hair.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent6"> This plasters oer the Beau.</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> And Corn that most inestimable treasure</l>
          <l rend="indent2">{Which by the by is ten shillings &amp; nine pence</l>
          <l rend="indent2">{A bushel Winchester measure<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">A system of weights and measures, particularly used for
                            ale and wine.</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent3">He showers upon his greasy pate like snow.</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Then when the Barbers fashionable trade</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> The gentleman has made</l>
          <l rend="indent2">He takes his cane &amp; walks on the parade.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">When the Heads outside takes such pains</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Ah who will wonder at the lack of brains.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">And now I come to show</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Wherein the cane is like the Beau.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Is the Cane good for anything? &#8212; no.</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Is the Beau?</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Does &lt;it&gt; not bend if any one leans low?</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> So does the Beau.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">When wandering on fatigued &amp; slow</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The Pilgrim creeps along the lengthening plain &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Does he derive assistance from the Cane?</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And who derives assistance from the Beau?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">In this they differ, &amp; in this alone,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The cane had come to something good it may be,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">If it amid the wood uncropt had grown,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The Beau will always be a Baby.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Thus in an excellent comparison</l>
          <l rend="indent3">I prove the Cane &amp; Beau are as one.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Stick of Democracy &#8212; Stick Sans Culottes</l>
          <l rend="indent2">To thee I tune my democratic note</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Leveller the mighty thou resemblest me</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And I a stick myself resemble thee.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Unknown to bend art thou.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And I unknown to bow.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And tall &amp; thin art thou. &amp; so am I.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And ungenteel thy shape nor nice nor <del rend="strikethrough">neat</del>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent3">So that when we together walk the street</l>
          <l rend="indent2">We catch the passing puppys wondering eye.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Nor Sans Culottes &#8212; thy strenuous bulk was made</l>
          <l rend="indent2">To saunter up &amp; down the South Parade &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Nor I to move amid the minuets maze.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">But when we&#8217;re together</l>
          <l rend="indent3">We defy wind &amp; weather</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And merrily trudgest along the long ways.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Supporter of my strength. for oft tried aid</l>
          <l rend="indent2">For succor very very oft displayd</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Because thy strength has saved me many a fall</l>
          <l rend="indent2">In fine for all thy bounties one &amp; all</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Felt on the pathless heath &amp; rugged road</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Accept this most incomparable Ode.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">As thou hast propt my steps I prop thy name</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> For long shall last this tributary lay,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Nor soon o San Culottes thy fame</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> Shall fade in dull Oblivions reign away.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">But as thy native holly lifts its head</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> In horrent strength erect tho thou art gone</l>
          <l rend="indent3">So Sans Culottes shall bloom when I am dead</l>
          <l rend="indent4"> The garland evergreen of Southeys song.</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent7"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent10"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>how is M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Bs gout?</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>