<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce203</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.203</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Houghton
                        Library, bMS Eng 265.1 (17).  Previously  published: Joseph Cottle, Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert
                            Southey (London, 1847), p. 202 [in part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="203" type="letter">
<head>203. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph
                        Cottle</ref>, <date when="1797-03-06">6 March 1797</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: For/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottle/
                        High Street/ Bristol/ Single<lb/>Stamped: [partial] BR<lb/>Endorsements:
                        Southey/ March 97; 20 (<del rend="strikethrough">76</del>)<lb/>MS: Houghton
                        Library, bMS Eng 265.1 (17)<lb/>Previously published: Joseph Cottle, <title level="m">Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert
                            Southey</title> (London, 1847), p. 202 [in part].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<date when="1797-03-06">Monday. March 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1797.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> I have received an order from <ref target="people.html#Peacockunknown">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Peacock</ref> for
                    twelve Poems &amp; twelve Letters,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in
                            Spain and Portugal</title> (1797) and <title level="m">Poems</title>
                        (1797).</note> which as they are for country booksellers he takes of course
                    at booksellers price. it is better to get them from <ref target="people.html#Robinsonfamily">Robinson</ref> than pay the expence of
                    carriage, &amp; I should have ordered them this morning but that the weather
                    proved wet. he ordered at first 12 poems &amp; only six letters, telling me
                    he hoped on returning from his next journey to give me larger orders. I lent him
                    my own copy of the letters, which he immediately began to read aloud in the
                    adjoining room, so audibly that I could hear. if I may judge by the merriment it
                    excited the Book pleased his auditors hugely, &amp; when he had got to the
                    Lock of Hair he came in again &amp; desired a dozen instead of six. I then
                    showed him my sketches — he is always in a hurry, writes me a letter to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hunter — the murderer of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        Pierre<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Hunter (1741–1802;
                            <title level="m">DNB</title>) had published a translation of
                        Jacques-Henri Bernadin de St Pierre’s (1737–1814) <title level="m">Études de
                            la Nature</title> in 1796.</note> — begging him to give me some
                    information about engravers (with whom his translation of Lavater<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Kasparr Lavater (1741–1801), Swiss poet
                        and physiognomist. Hunter had published an English translation of his <title level="m">Essays on Physiognomy</title> in 1792.</note> connected him)
                    settles it that I shall have a set of plates engraved for a splendid edition of
                    my letters, that it will be proper to engage subscribers, &amp; determines
                    to make this a part of his business &amp; take orders this journey. all this
                    he tells me by letter last night after I was gone to bed, leaves me his
                    direction &amp; sets off this morning, with my Poems &amp; Letters.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> now <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> I am not
                    always in a hurry. he may engage names if he pleases, but I shall write to him
                    &amp; say, that if ever I get a series of views engraved, it will be to
                    publish such a series of poems as I once mentioned to you. for it would be
                    ridiculous to hold out the prospect of a better edition of a work just
                    published; &amp; on the contrary the poetical volume would be connected with
                    the other.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I shall get his books from <ref target="people.html#Robinsonfamily">Robinson</ref> tomorrow — if dry.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I feel inclined to complain heavily of you <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref>. here am I, committing grand
                    larceny upon my time, in writing to you &amp; you, who might sit by your
                    shop fire &amp; write me huge letters, have not found time to fill even half
                    a sheet. as you may suppose I have enough of employment. I work like an negro at
                    law, &amp; therefore neglect nothing else. for <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> he who never wastes time has always time enough. Madoc is in a
                    state of rapid progression. I have about thirty lines to conclude the first
                    book. this however must be deferred till I have borrowed certain books, as those
                    thirty lines must concenter much Bardic &amp; historical knowledge. I shall
                    therefore begin the second book this evening. tell <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> his copy is compleated as
                    far as the work has advanced, but that I shall not send him the first book till
                    I can read the two together, because he is already well acquainted with the old
                    one.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> When will the fine copies be finished? let me have them with all
                    convenient speed, &amp; send, at the same time, a common interleaved
                    one.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have yet many of the London lions, or literati, to see. <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George Dyer</ref> is to take me to Mary
                    Hayes, Miss <del rend="strikethrough">Kristall</del> Christall, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gregory, &amp; Taylor the Pagan<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The writer Mary Hays (1759–1843; <title level="m">DNB</title>); the poet Anne Batten Cristall (c. 1769–1848; <title level="m">DNB</title>); the author and biographer of Thomas Chatterton
                        (1752–1770; <title level="m">DNB</title>), Dr George Gregory (1754–1808;
                            <title level="m">DNB</title>); and the philosopher and translator Thomas
                        Taylor (1758–1835; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> my near neighbour.
                    you shall have my physiognomical remarks upon them. I am in daily expectation of
                    hearing from you &amp; receiving Foxs<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Fox (1740?–1809; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> books, not
                    forgetting the profiles of himself &amp; his family.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I hate this city more &amp; more; — tho I see little of it.
                    you do not know with what delight I anticipate a summer in Wales, [MS torn]
                    &amp; I hope to spend the summer of the next year there, [MS torn] talk
                    Welch most gutturally. I shall see Meirion this week, whose real name is <ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">William Owen</ref>. he is the
                    Author of the new Welch Dictionary.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Owen Pughe (1759–1835; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Geiriadur Cynmraeg a Saesoneg. A Welsh and English
                            Dictionary</title> (1793–1803).</note> a man of most uncommon erudition,
                    &amp; who ought to esteem me for Madocs sake. fare you well. remember me to
                    all friends. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> I shall write in a few days to <ref target="people.html#Lovellfamily">Joseph Lovell</ref>, &amp; direct the
                    letter to be left with you. parental tyranny is <del rend="strikethrough">a
                        h</del> dreadful. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love
                    to you &amp; <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">Robert, &amp; your
                        sisters</ref> &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> God bless you.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent2"> Yrs sincerely</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
