<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2304</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3575</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Beinecke Library, GEN MSS 298, Series I, Box
                        1, folder 36.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4
                        vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 327-330.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2304" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2304" type="letter">
        <head>2304. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>, <date when="1813-09-20">20 September
                        1813</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Miss Southey/ Greta Hall/ Keswick/
                        Cumberland<lb />Postmarks: 7 o&#8217;Clock/ SP. 21/ 1813 N.T.; B./ S.E./ 21/1813<lb />MS: Beinecke Library, GEN MSS 298, Series I, Box
                        1, folder 36<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4
                        vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 327-330.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-09-20">Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 20. 1813.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Edithling</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I owe you a letter, &amp; it is time the debt should be paid; so <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your
                        Mamma</ref> will let me write to you instead of her, especially as I have been stationary at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> ever since I wrote, &amp; consequently can have nothing to communicate.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As I know you read the newspaper for the sake of seeing whether Buonaparte has been killed, how the King<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of the United Kingdom 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>). He had been
                        unable to conduct public business since October 1810.</note> is, &amp; whether there are any new murders, you may probably
                    have seen there that your father is to be Poet-Laureat.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s appointment as Poet
                        Laureate was reported in the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 18 September 1813.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Son-Lunus</ref> who is an unbeliever about Pegasus,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The winged horse of mythology.</note> will perhaps not believe that the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> is going to give me a right to wear laurel round my head; <del>but</del>
                    if you &amp; he will look in a book about Petrarch<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francesco Petrarca (1304&#8211;1374), who was
                        crowned poet laureate with a laurel wreath in Rome in 1341. Southey could be referring to a number of books in his collection.
                        One possibility is Alexander Fraser Tytler, Lord Woodhouselee (1747&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Historical and
                            Critical Essay on the Life and Character of Petrarch</title> (Edinburgh, 1810), which contained such an engraving of Petrarch as a frontispiece [unpaginated]. The book was no. 2224 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> which is at the <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhora&#8217;s</ref>, &amp; is one of those upon
                    which she has bestowed a paper-morocco back, they you will see the portrait of a Poet Laureat with his crown on. The laurels
                        <del>must</del> should be gathered from the grove on that mountain where the nine sisters take care of my winged horse;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Mount Olympus, home of the Nine Muses.</note> &amp; it is not proper that I should
                    wear any others.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am teaching the two eldest of your Cousins to say la, la, la, look at the lamb &amp; the lark: &amp; wa, wa, wa,
                    we will walk. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Herbert</ref> learns this much more readily than <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">his brother</ref>. They are very good children, &amp; are grown very fond of me. I tickle
                    &amp; toss them whenever we meet, &amp; sometimes kiss Duke Bruin, who is Ursa Major or the Great Bear, &amp; is the best kissing
                    of the three. But kissing him is a very different thing from kissing my own <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha
                        Bruin</ref>, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref>, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabee-bo-bell</ref>. <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">My Aunt</ref> would be very willing to visit us, &amp; bring
                    the three Bears with her, but I fear <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> will not be persuaded to move. <ref target="people.html#HillErrol">Earl Bruin</ref>, the little wee bear, is very little older than <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref>, &amp; does not talk; but Marquis Bruin, the middle Bear, has an ursine
                    language of his own which is very winning. His daily subject of complaint is that nobody will be married, &amp; so he can get no
                    wedding cake.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You must tell <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your Mamma</ref> that I have seen a letter to day, from M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Piozzi<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The writer and celebrated Bluestocking, Hester Lynch Piozzi
                        (1741&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>).</note> to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Davies,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reynold
                        Davies (1752&#8211;1822), Curate of Streatham and a neighbour of Herbert Hill&#8217;s. He ran a school for small boys on land which he
                        leased from Hester Lynch Piozzi&#8217;s estate at Streatham Park.</note> which concerns me, &amp; which as the writer is only
                    seventy five years of age<del>d</del>, may perhaps make her jealous, if she heard of it from any other quarter than from me
                    myself. M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Piozzi hearing that I am at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>, &amp; expecting
                    to find me there when she comes herself, bids me beware of &#8220;a solitary woman&#8221; with &#8220;bright blue eyes&#8221; altho &#8220;her hair be grey.&#8221; &#8211;
                    She writes a sprightly letter, full of life &amp; spirits, &amp; in a <del>firm</del>, full, strong hand, which as a sample of
                    pen-womanship is remarkably fine, but considering her time of life, is really wonderful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have bought for you some Arabian Tales in three volumes,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Arabian Tales</title>, translated into English in 1792 by Robert Heron (1764&#8211;1807; <title>DNB</title>). The
                        &#8216;Dom-daniel&#8217; the &#8216;chief nursery and retreat&#8217; of evil magicians features in vol. 4 of Heron&#8217;s translation (esp. pp. 102, 191,
                        308, 339); and Southey&#8217;s <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> wherein you will find mention of the Dom daniel
                    which Thalaba destroyed: &amp; I have bought for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> the Persian &amp; Turkish
                        Tales.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably a volume of the <title>Persian and Turkish Tales. From the French of
                            M. Petis de la Croix</title> (1809), translated by William King (1663&#8211;1712; <title>DNB</title>). There was, however, a
                        problem with the book Southey had purchased; see Southey to Thomas De Quincey, 19 January 1814, Letter 2366.</note> I am
                    writing at this time upon your desk, which is the size of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your Mamma&#8217;s</ref>, &amp; I mean
                    to buy the fellow to it for Thisbe.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> A nickname for Southey&#8217;s niece <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara Coleridge</ref>.</note> I shall also buy bricks &amp; pictures for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do not forget your lessons while I am absent. I shall not be pleased if you lose ground. Tell <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Lunus</ref> to look over the poems which I made for him about <del>the</del> &lt;his&gt;
                    Greek &amp; have them all at the tip of his tongue when I return.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Your Mamma</ref> will like to know all the news of my intended operations which I can send
                    her. Tell her then that I am getting on well with my business, in every sense of the word. That I go to town on Friday, when <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> will be asked to dine with me at <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry&#8217;s</ref>: on Sunday I dine &amp; sleep at <ref target="places.html#HollandHouse">Holland House</ref>, &#8211; the Wednesday following dine at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                    Vaughans<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Thomas Wright Vaughan (1774&#8211;1859), author of <title>A View of the Present State of Sicily</title>
                        (1811).</note> with <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>, &amp; the next day with Madame Stael.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anne Louise Germaine de Sta&#235;l-Holstein (1766&#8211;1817), the writer and salonni&#232;re, who was much feted
                        during her 1813 visit to England.</note> Next week will compleat my main business, &amp; then another fortnight will set me
                    free from London. I mean to stop a day on my return at Worcester for the purpose of seeing Lucien Buonaparte.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucien Bonaparte (1775&#8211;1840), brother of Napoleon. Since 1810 he had been living under house
                        arrest in England, at Thorngrove in Worcestershire, and writing <title>Charlemagne, ou l&#8217;Eglise Delivree</title> (1814), an
                        epic poem which it had been suggested that Southey should translate.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now my dear Edithling, farewell. Give my love to <ref target="people.html#WilsonMrs">Wilsey</ref>; &#8211; the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctor</ref> enquired particularly for her. Say to your <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Aunt Coleridge</ref> that I long to sneeze &amp; snap my toes at home once more: &amp; tell
                    the <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhora</ref> that poor <hi rend="ital">I</hi> am getting sleep<hi rend="ital">y</hi>,
                    for it is half past nine o clock, sufficient for the day hath been the labour thereof. I am Simorghish<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> A mythological (and sleepy) bird. It has featured in <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), Book
                        11.</note> at all times, &amp; when absent from home it is better to be asleep than awake.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope Lord Nelson, Bona Fidelia, &amp; Madame Catalani continue well.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Cats owned by the Southey family.</note> Sir John Murray has probably gone the way of all geese. How is Paul the Pig, &amp;
                    how go on his distant relations from Guinea?</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> your affectionate father [signature cut-off]</salute>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> Next week I shall write to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>