<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2452</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3723</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2452" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2452" type="letter">
        <head>2452. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1814-06-28">28 June
                        1814</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Captain Southey. R. N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        Helens/ Auckland<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have sometimes been inclined to fancy, when taking perhaps a flattering view of my own temper of mind, that if
                    our genealogy <del>could be</del> were revealed it would lead us back to the land of Uz, &amp; to the house of Job.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Job</title> 1: 1. Job bore his misfortunes uncomplainingly.</note> Your last letter has almost persuaded me that we are
                    certainly Uzzites by extraction, &amp; of Jobs own blood; for, except in his history I know not where to find any thing so
                    patient, so mild, so truly gentle &amp; considerate, as the strain of that epistle, &#8211; &#8220;What the Devil could he have been thinking
                    about&#8221; you say. <del>Putting my old friend Scratch out of the question</del> this perhaps was rather &lt;hasty&gt; on your part, &#8211;
                    for putting my old friend Scratch<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Old Scratch&#8217;, a nickname for the Devil.</note> out of
                    the question, <del>I would</del> I <del>apparent</del> &lt;should have <del>supposed</del> thought&gt; that a man<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Grosvenor Bedford.</note> whose father suffered a stroke of palsy at nine on Thursday night,
                    &amp; died at six on Saturday morning, &#8211; might very well be supposed not to be in a state of mind for thinking calmly about my
                    odes on the <del>xxxxxx</del> Friday. Our ancestor in Uz would under such circumstances have forgiven a greater mistake.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It so happened <del>th</del> however that after having written to me he perceived that he had made a blunder, which
                    could not have been made if his mind had not been in a <del>xxxx</del> &lt;so&gt; disturbed a state. The last ode <del>was</del>
                    which reached him on the Friday, was consequently sent to <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref>. all possible
                    dispatch was used, the ode was published on the Tuesday, &amp; according to an arrangement between <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, sent after the
                    former to Portsmouth, there to be by him presented to the be&#246;ded personages.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> George IV
                        (1762&#8211;1830, Prince Regent 1811&#8211;1820, King of the United Kingdom 1820&#8211;1830; <title>DNB</title>); Alexander I (1777&#8211;1825;
                        Emperor of Russia 1801&#8211;1825); Frederick William III (1770&#8211;1840; King of Prussia 1797&#8211;1840). Southey&#8217;s Laureate tributes to
                        them were published in book form as <title>Congratulatory Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness The Prince Regent, His Imperial
                            Majesty The Emperor of Russia, and His Majesty the King of Prussia</title> (1814).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now after your late fit of bile I recommend you by all means to take a dose of Cheltenham salts.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> A popular patent remedy.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I received my parcel with the Odes on Sunday, &#8211; <del>the</del> it had been sent off on the Wednesday. A note in it
                    informed me that <del>in order</del> for the sake if despatch only 250 had been thrown off, &amp; requested corrections by return
                    of post. There <del>were</del> &lt;are&gt; two material misprints making a wrong sense which is worse than nonsense. p 7. to the
                        <hi rend="ital">sea</hi> instead of the <hi rend="ital">sun</hi> &amp; p 18 &#8211; the <hi rend="ital">breach</hi> of Tarragona
                    instead of the <hi rend="ital">beach</hi>. I had made also an <del>unfor</del> addition in p. 8 which was unluckily too late.
                    after</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="center"> Fear Sorrow &amp; Repentance following close;</l>
          <l rend="center"> And War, scarce deigning to conceal</l>
          <l rend="center"> Beneath the mantles folds his armed plight,</l>
          <l rend="center"> Dogging her steps with deadly eye intent,</l>
          <l rend="center"> Sure of his victim, &amp; in devilish joy</l>
          <l rend="center"> Laughing behind the mask.</l>
          <l rend="center"> Not thus doth Peace return,</l>
          <l rend="center"> A bright &amp; glorious visitant she comes &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="center"> Honour &amp;c<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> These lines were too late to have been inserted in
                            Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Ode to His Royal Highness The Prince Regent&#8217;, III, between lines 20&#8211;21.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1">I suppose <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> made out the titles of the Be&#246;ded in full form,
                    for I did not, &amp; that he entitled the odes congratulatory. And now you know as much about them as I do: &#8211; having I
                        <del>suppos</del> dare say received your parcel as soon as I did mine.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I think Lord Cochranes sentence too severe.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The naval officer and radical
                        Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>). He had been convicted of being part of a massive
                        fraud in dealings in government stocks. He was fined &#163;1000; sentenced to one year&#8217;s imprisonment in the King&#8217;s Bench and to
                        stand for an hour in the pillory. The latter was remitted. In addition, Cochrane was struck off the navy list, and expelled
                        from the House of Commons and from the chapel of the Knights of the Bath.</note> it will probably not be inflicted, &amp; in
                    my judgement ought not to have been passed, the offence not being one of those for which a specific punishment has been appointed
                    &amp; no discretion left in pronouncing it. Of course he will persist in his denial; &#8211; it is a symptom of grace in him, &#8211; &amp;
                    after what has past the choice lay between stiffly braving the clear conviction, &#8211; or shooting himself. Nothing can be clearer
                    than his guilt; but the proper consequences of expulsion, loss of honour &amp; of his commission fall heavily enough without
                    anything of greater ignominy. Were I the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> the pillory &amp; the
                    imprisonment should be instantly remitted; in doing this his former services &amp; his rank in the navy might be so referred to as
                    to produce a good effect. The Prince wants popularity &amp; wants advisers to show him <del>xx</del> how easily it may be
                    obtained. As for the Princess<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Caroline of Brunswick-Wolfenbuttel (1768&#8211;1821;
                            <title>DNB</title>), wife of the Prince Regent.</note> she is equally impudent &amp; mischievous.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> book of Roderick<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> may probably be finished tonight. The poem runs to 25 &amp; will
                    very speedily be compleated, &#8211; if there be no interruption. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        C</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> went yesterday to <ref target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref>. We are all well except <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref>
                    who is very poorly today with teething &amp; a cough.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> &#8211; God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1814-06-28">Tuesday 28 June 1814.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>