<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1990</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3261</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick
                        Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.188.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry
                        (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), II, pp. 12&#8211;15.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1990" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1990" type="letter">
        <head>1990. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">James
                        Montgomery</ref>, <date when="1811-11-29">29 November 1811</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> James
                        Montgomery./ Sheffield.<lb />Stamped: [partial] KESWICK/ 2<lb />MS: Keswick
                        Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.188<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry
                        (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), II, pp. 12&#8211;15.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1811-11-29">Nov. 29. 1811.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Montgomery, I have just laid down your last volume<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Wanderer in Switzerland, and
                            other Poems</title> (1811); reviewed by Southey alongside Montgomery&#8217;s
                            <title>The West Indies, and other Poems</title> (1810), <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 6 (December 1811), 405&#8211;419.</note> with a feeling of
                    regret, &#8211; not unmingled with something like self-reproach, that you &amp; I
                    should still be strangers to each other. My plans have twice been laid for
                    taking Sheffield in the way to London, for the sole purpose of seeing you, &amp;
                        <del>I</del> each time they have been defeated by unforeseen circumstances;
                    &#8211; but I might before this have told you what pleasure it would give me to shake
                    you by the hand, &amp; how proud I should be to do it under my own roof. Come
                    &amp; visit me as soon as the fair season returns. You will find plain fare,
                    books, perfect liberty, &amp; a sincere welcome from persons who already love
                    &amp; admire the poet. You shall have a bedroom from whence you will see the
                    moonlight upon Derwentwater. I will row you upon the Lake, &amp; be your guide
                    upon the mountains.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When shall we see your World before the Flood?<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The World Before the Flood</title>
                        (1813), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 11 (April
                        1814), 78&#8211;87.</note> The Deluge is one of those subjects which I had chosen
                    many years ago, before historical pursuits had in a great measure, weaned me
                    from poetry. In 1801 <del>when</del> on my passage from Lisbon to England, the
                    imaginations which had long been floating in my mind matured into something like
                    a plan.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s plan for a poem
                        on Noah, <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 2&#8211;3.</note> To account for the universal
                    corruption which deserved such a chastisement I supposed an universal monarchy,
                    &#8211; such as Louis 14<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis XIV
                        (1638&#8211;1715; King of France 1643&#8211;1715).</note> or Buonaparte<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821).</note>
                    would establish, &#8211; an absolute Tyrant, &amp; a persecuting &amp; atheistic
                    hierarchy. I conceived that the perversion of morals extended even to those who
                    opposed this system, &#8211; &amp; that while they were organizing a sort of Irish
                        Rebellion<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A rebellion on the
                        lines of that by the United Irishmen in 1798.</note> against it, the Ruling
                    Powers anticipated them, &amp; by a general massacre like that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bartholomews day,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The massacre of French Huguenots in Paris that began on 23 August
                        1572, the eve of the feast of St Bartholomew.</note> filled up the measure
                    of iniquity. Some striking characters &amp; situations grew out of this
                    conception, but <del>two objections</del> I laid it aside feeling how impossible
                    it was to amalgamate in the readers <del>xxxxx</del> mind so much pure fiction
                    with a history so familiar.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ConderJosiah">Josiah Conder</ref> told me your poem is
                    in the couplet. I have no prejudice in favour of any one measure for narrative
                    poetry, &#8211; the tone &amp; character of the narrative always with me determine
                    what the metre should be, &#8211; but of all measures the heroic couplet seems to me
                    the most unsuitable for narration. You have broken yours by a free admixture of
                    pauses in your West Indies, &amp; in so doing you have gained much; still I
                    dislike it, it continually seduces the writer to commit sins against good sense
                    &amp; good English, he aims at pointing his meaning instead of bringing it
                    distinctly out, gets into all the tricks of antithesis, &amp; when he should be
                    thinking &amp; feeling, passes off a sort of way-jolt of words both upon himself
                    &amp; &lt;his&gt; readers. Our poetry owes half its barbarisms to this metre.
                    You will do with it all that can be done, &amp; I have no doubt will avoid its
                    natural faults as far as they can be avoided. Were I to use a regular rhymed
                    measure for narration, I think it should be the trinal rhyme of Dante,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dante Alighieri (c. 1265&#8211;1321),
                            <title>Divina Commedia</title> (1308&#8211;1321), which has an interlocking
                        three-line rhyme-scheme.</note> breaking its endlessness by dividing it into
                        <del>xxxxxx</del> paragraphs, &amp; considering myself as beginning <del>a
                        new</del> anew with every fresh one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of your last volume<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        All the poems mentioned in this paragraph appeared in Montgomery&#8217;s
                            <title>The West Indies, and Other Poems</title> (1810). The &#8216;last poem&#8217;
                        was &#8216;M. S.&#8217;, pp. 151&#8211;160.</note> the Harp of Sorrow, the Cast Away Ship,
                    &amp; the last poem are what I most delight in. Some of the stanzas respecting
                    the Blenheim<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Montgomery&#8217;s &#8216;The
                        Cast-Away Ship&#8217;, pp. 142&#8211;148, commemorated the loss of HMS
                            <title>Blenheim</title>, a 90-gun second rate ship of the line which
                        sank off Madagascar in 1807 with the loss of 590 crew, and also the
                        unsuccessful voyage undertaken by Sir Edward Troubidge (c. 1787&#8211;1852;
                            <title>DNB</title>) the son of the <title>Blenheim</title>&#8217;s commander,
                        Sir Thomas Troubridge (c. 1758&#8211;1807; <title>DNB</title>), to locate the
                        wreck.</note> are the finest things of the kind in all our poetry, &#8211;
                    exceeding the Royal George of Cowper,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Cowper (1731&#8211;1800; <title>DNB</title>). His &#8216;The Loss of the
                        Royal George&#8217; (1782) commemorated the sinking of the British flagship with
                        the loss of 800 lives on 29 August 1782.</note> which <del>I have</del> was
                    before unrivalled. &#8220;On Indias long-expecting strand&#8221;, &#8211; &amp; the concluding
                    stanza are as fine as they can be. &amp; those lines He sailed above his fathers
                    head Unconscious where it lay, &#8211; are to my feelings perfectly sublime. The
                    concluding poem carries me with it throughout. This is one of those pieces
                        <del>which</del> in your own peculiar manner, a manner to which I have never
                    seen any resemblance except in the odes of Klopstock,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Friedrich Gottlieb Klopstock (1724&#8211;1803) German poet,
                        whose odes Southey had encountered in a translation by William
                        Taylor.</note> as they have been read to me in literal English. Like
                    Klopstock I think you sometimes contemplate things in a solar microscope rather
                    than in their natural proportions. The Mole-Hill<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The West Indies, and Other Poems</title> (1810),
                        pp. 129&#8211;141.</note> is, <del>to my</del> according to my judgement, an
                    instance of this over-stretch of imagination: &#8211; <del>a</del> I <del>fault</del>
                    am perfectly sensible that the desire of avoiding this fault has sometimes led
                    me into an opposite extreme.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You &amp; I have not only contemplated the same subject for a
                    poem, but we have thought upon the same manner of narration. <ref target="people.html#StandertHughChudleigh">Standert</ref> showed me some
                    letters of yours in one of which you described your early notion of a lyrical
                    epic, &#8211; I had the same <del>th</del> conception in writing both my
                        <del>romanc</del> mythological poems,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801) and <title>The Curse of
                            Kehama</title> (1810).</note> tho not to the full extent to which you
                    seem to have carried it, &#8211; Our hopes, as well as our day-dreams, have the same
                    directions. I feel as ardently as you do respecting the Missions, &amp; I look
                    &lt;forward&gt; as you do to a state of things on earth, when the perfect
                    establishment of the system of Christ Jesus shall extinguish moral evil, &amp;
                    therewith that physical evil which is its result.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Come to me in the spring &amp; let us talk over these things.
                    Write to me sometimes, &amp; let us tell each other of our embryo works, &amp;
                    censure them while censure can be useful. I have always one poem in hand, &amp;
                    another brooding. That which at present <del>xxxx</del> employs the little time
                    I can afford for poetry, is upon the foundation of the Spanish Monarchy by
                        Pelayo.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> An early idea for what
                        became <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> It had
                    long appeared to me a fine subject, &amp; the deep interest which I take in
                    Spanish affairs, induced me at this time to select it, because the circumstances
                        <del>are</del> sufficiently <del>similar to</del> &lt;resemble&gt; those of
                    the present contest to call forth the same feelings. In what spirit it is begun
                    you shall see in my next, &#8211; if this should induce you to accept me for a
                    correspondent.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> farewell.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yours with true esteem</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>