<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2115</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3386</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        24.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2115" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2115" type="letter">
        <head>2115. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1812-06-16">16 June 1812</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer<lb />Endorsement: June 16. 1812<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        24<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> My letter which past yours on the road, will have told you that I shall be from home during the middle of July. My
                    movement depends upon <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref>, from whom I have not heard since, &#8211; but at any rate
                    I shall certainly &amp; sans doubt <del>xx</del> return by the first of August, &amp; you had better make your arrangements to
                    travel with <ref target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco</ref>, &amp; for the sake of seeing sights by the way take the road
                    of Oxford, Ludlow &amp; Chester, in which case you may give <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">his Honour</ref> a call en
                    passant, if he be in the country, as probably he will. I hope <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref> will come with
                    you, he will enjoy himself far more than he did last time, now that you are a sound man. &#8211; The <ref target="people.html#BrowneWade">Brownes</ref> are at Ludlow, which is a place worth going a days journey to see, the Castle
                    being one of our finest ruins.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <hi rend="ital">This</hi> year I cannot look at Scotland, <del>but I will</del> my hands are too full. Look how my affairs stand.
                    I am in the midst of the Regency debates<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The parliamentary debates about the establishment
                        of the Regency following George III&#8217;s (1738&#8211;1820; King of the United Kingdom 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>) relapse of
                        October 1810; see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.1 (1812), 523&#8211;575.</note> &amp; (God be thanked &#8211; )
                    within three days of the end of the Register. Then comes the Quarterly to which I must go dens et unguis.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Tooth and claw&#8217;.</note> Then have I to finish the Life of Nelson<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813), an expansion of Southey&#8217;s article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810),
                        218&#8211;262.</note>
          <del>x</del> contracted for by <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> more than two years ago, &amp; only a third part
                    done: &#8211; this however when it becomes the order of the day will soon be compleated. Then the Book of the Church<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title>, not published until 1824.</note> likewise agreed
                    for with him, &#8211; this also may be a months work, &amp; will probably be one of my <del>most</del> best performances. I expect to do
                    this, &amp; finish the Omniana,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Omniana, or Horae Otiosiores</title> (1812).</note> &amp; get on a good spell with my hist: of Brazil,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second volume of the <title>History of Brazil</title>, published in 1817.</note> before the
                    Register is called for again,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813).</note> &#8211; supposing (which is always a matter of uncertainty) that
                    it answers well enough to induce the publishers to continue it. Its failure would be a serious evil to me, for tho it gives me six
                    months full &amp; close employment, those six months are employed to more profit than the whole twelve months could be in any
                    other manner. In fact while it lasts, &amp; I am able to <del>x xxxx</del> perform my part, it gives me as much as I want. But
                    between ourselves I doubt its continuance, &amp; should not be displeased to receive a pressing letter from <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn ">Ballantyne</ref> urging me to set forward with the fourth volume.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> has written me a very friendly letter, inclosing his correspondence with <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Lord Hertford</ref> concerning that good ship the Historiographer to which he would fain
                    have had me appointed.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s campaign for the post of Historiographer Royal which had
                        become vacant on the death of Louis Dutens (1730&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>) on 23 May 1812.</note> It seems he applied to <ref target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lord Liverpool</ref> &amp; Ryder,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Tory
                        politician Dudley Ryder, 1st Earl of Harrowby (1762&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>). A Pittite loyalist and member of Perceval&#8217;s
                        cabinet, he became Lord President of the Council on the formation of Lord Liverpool&#8217;s ministry in June 1812.</note> &amp; then
                    got at the Chamberlain thro Ld Yarmouth.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Charles Seymour-Conway (1777&#8211;1842;
                            <title>DNB</title>), who, as heir to the Marquessate of Hertford, held the courtesy title Lord Yarmouth. He was a close
                        friend of the Prince Regent, who appointed him to the post of vice-chamberlain in 1812 &#8211; the Chamberlain was his father, the
                        Marquess of Hertford.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> wrote to Ld Melville,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Saunders
                        Dundas, 2nd Viscount Melville (1771&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), who had become First Lord of the Admiralty earlier in
                        1812.</note> &#8211; so there was no want of good will, nor of applications. The best part of his account is that the salary is 200
                    &#163; &#8211; I had always believed it 400, from your report, &amp; inasmuch as it falls short am the less disappointed. Stanier Clarke<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), whom Southey loathed.</note> is
                    of course chosen by the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> himself. It is a pity <del>he is such</del> that
                    so much industry should be thrown away upon a man so little able to direct it for he is a most extraordinary blockhead. Do look at
                    my review in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> vol. of the Annual of his Hist: of Maritime Discovery,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Stanier Clarke, <title>The Progress of Maritime Discovery</title>
                        (1803); reviewed by Southey in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 12&#8211;20.</note> &#8211; the very worst book I ever
                    saw or at least of all books the one which evinced the greatest want of good sense in the author. Among other blunders not less
                    curious he gave a <hi rend="ital">Portugueze</hi> King a <hi rend="ital">Jew</hi> physician for his <hi rend="ital">Confessor</hi>.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> An error Southey pointed out in <title>Annual Review for
                            1803</title>, 2 (1804), 19. The king in question was John II (1455&#8211;1495; King of Portugal 1481&#8211;1495).</note> I dare say he
                    will not be idle, &amp; whatever he brings out, tho it will disgrace the title inevitably (for there is no cure for being a
                    blockhead), will yet be something gained in the way of documents.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wish <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">Wellesley</ref> could have <del>been</del> joined the ministry, but would rather have the present men without them, than them
                    without <ref target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Ld Liverpool</ref> &amp; the Sidmouths<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The former Prime Minister, Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>), who became Home Secretary
                        in 1812, and his band of about eight followers.</note> who have long <del>been</del> had my good wishes &amp; opinion.
                        <del>Any thing but</del> Any thing rather than the <hi rend="ital">Gregres</hi>.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Gregres were idols of wood and clay in West Africa.</note> If you do not understand that admirable name, compounded of the
                    initial letters of <ref target="people.html#GreyCharles">Grey</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Grenville</ref>,
                    look in any book about the Gold Coast for an account of the rubbish which the negroes worship, &amp; you will find that gregre is
                    the name of a brainless God &#8211; in French gris-gris.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I owe <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> a letter of thanks, but it must wait till I make it a
                    letter of business. &#8211; I had nearly forgotten to beg you would tell him that if he will send me either the MS. or the proofs of
                        <ref target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blancos</ref> article,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Blanco White&#8217;s
                        review of William Walton (1783/4&#8211;1857; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Present State of the Spanish Colonies; Including a
                            Particular Report of Hispanola, or the Spanish Part of Santo Domingo</title> (1810), appeared in <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 14 (June 1812), 235&#8211;264.</note> I will <del>x</del> very gladly comment upon it, &#8211; if he wishes it. With
                    me the subject stands over for next years Register, because the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> vol. of the Debates of the Cortes was not
                    printed in time.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Diario de las Discusiones y Actas de las Cortes, 1810&#8211;1813</title> (1811&#8211;1813), no. 3288 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library. Southey gave his opinions on South American affairs in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>
                        (1813), 367&#8211;421.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you get my money before you are leaving town, <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> can get it
                    franked, in want of a franker in ordinary. I hope you will establish a new communication in Downing Street if Vansittart<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicolas Vansittart, 1st Baron Bexley (1766&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>) had become Chancellor
                        of the Exchequer on 20 May 1812.</note> should continue Brooksbank<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Constantine
                        Brooksbank (1778&#8211;1850) was Spencer Perceval&#8217;s Private Secretary. He remained at the Treasury as Senior Clerk of the Minutes
                        1812&#8211;1815, rising to be Chief Clerk of the Treasury.</note> there.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-06-16">June 16. 1812.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>