<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2218</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3489</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. d.
                        3.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2218" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2218" type="letter">
        <head>2218. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1813-02-03">3
                        February 1813</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 28. Queen
                        Ann Street. <del>West</del>/ Cavendish Square<lb />Postmark: 2 o&#8217;Clock/ 8 FE/ 1813<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d.
                        3<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter has arrived at a time when I am too uncomfortable for any other occupation than answering it. <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">Ediths brother</ref> is here, &#8211; in a very bad state of health &#8211; &amp; yesterday he broke a
                    blood vessel: after bleeding about a pint &amp; half at the mouth the h&#230;morrhage stopt, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmundson</ref> bled him afterwards &amp; the blood was in a very inflammatory state, &#8211; this evening he seems &amp; feels
                    worse &amp; I am in momentary fear that the h&#230;morrage will return. &#8211; To persons not used to such things the sight is frightful, &#8211;
                    &amp; tho I <del>put xxx xxxx xxx</del> endeavoured with some success to allay his apprehensions &amp; his sisters,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edith Southey, Sara Coleridge and Mary Lovell, all involved in nursing George at Greta
                        Hall.</note> &#8211; I am myself the worse for the circumstance. Whatever be the event of the present attack, the poor fellow is
                    full of diseases which the yellow fever left behind, &amp; which will most likely bring him to the grave.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will desire <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> to send you what <del>xxx</del> more
                    he has of Roderick<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> MS drafts of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                        (1814).</note> &#8211; the 5 &amp; 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#8211; books will go to London under the same frank-imperial <del>as</del>
                    which carries this. I have begun the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#8211; this is being rather more than half way thro. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> is one of those men who <del>is always</del> &lt;are&gt; more
                    especially than others in the predicament noticed in our liturgy of leaving undone those things which they ought to have done,
                    &amp; &#8211; which they intend to do. Hence his inattention to you. My London acquaintances are very numerous, &#8211; my friends but few.
                        <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> who would have been solicitous to offer you any civilities in his power
                    lives thirteen miles from town at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Mary Cray. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> is in
                    Wales, &amp; <del>be he where he</del> wherever he is, he is always as <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> most
                    happily said of him at Oxford, <hi rend="ital">doing something else</hi>. There is no one for whom he has a sincerer regard than
                    he has for me, &amp; yet I have been in London for four or five weeks &amp; he has never asked me to dinner. This apparent
                    indifference or neglect is usual with him, &amp; gives great offence to his Welsh neighbours, who impute it to his Grenville
                        blood.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn&#8217;s mother was the sister of <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord
                            Grenville</ref>.</note> But it is because he is always in that state of litter, &amp; confusion which you would expect in
                    a man who before he was married used to <del>do</del> begin doing half a hundred things before he put his breeches on, &amp; who
                    used to have books &#8211; pen &#8211; ink &#8211; &amp; paper &#8211; breeches, <del>xx</del> galluses, neckcloth, &amp; rolls &amp; butter all upon the
                    breakfast table at the same time. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When I come to London, which I shall work hard to accomplish by the end of April, I will take you to Sotheby<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poet and translator William Sotheby (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G Beaumont</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref>, &#8211;
                        <del>&amp; bring them to you xx</del> &#8211; they keep gay houses at which it is fit that a physician should be seen. That you will
                    succeed I have no doubt whatever, &amp; that, early enough to feel yourself still a young man when you are enjoying success. I am
                    nearly ten years <del>older</del> your senior, &amp; older in habits &amp; feelings, &amp; perhaps constitution than in years: you
                    will be up the ladder before I shall, &amp; yet I hope to enjoy myself at the top.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The last <del>xx xx</del> portion of the Nelson mss.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The MS of <title>The
                            Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> was sent off yesterday, but the printer<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        James Moyes (d. 1839), of Greville St, Hatton Garden, London.</note> has ten sheets before him. I dedicate it to <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, <del>more</del> &lt;as much&gt; with a view to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> interest as for the civilities which he has shown me &#8211; indeed they may be called more than mere civilities, for
                    without solicitation he <add>men</add> used all his endeavours to get me the historiographers office.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Croker had campaigned for Southey&#8217;s appointment as Historiographer Royal in 1812. He was not successful, and
                        the post went to James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>); see Southey to John Wilson Croker, 10 June 1812,
                        Letter 2113.</note> This book was no scheme of my own, it grew out of the reviewal, &#8211; &amp; the reviewal was forced upon me:
                    but I think it is likely to answer <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> purpose in a future edition, &amp; that it
                    will do me credit.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Nelson</title> was an expansion of Southey&#8217;s article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810),
                        218&#8211;262. Southey correctly predicted its success; it went through six editions in his lifetime.</note> With the
                        Register<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s employment on the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> ceased
                        after 1813.</note> it seems probable that I shall ere long have done. <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> the bookseller is a dirty fellow, &amp; it will be more than I expect if I <del>am able</del> am lucky
                    enough to get out of his hands the 200&#163; which I have embarked in the concern.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        had, unwisely as it turned out, invested in the <title>Register</title>.</note> On my next visit to London I must make
                    arrangements to enable me to have done with him. Possibly there will be no eventual Injury, tho certainly some immediate
                    inconveniences but I distinctly feel that my marketable <del>reputation</del> value is on the rise. As for Roderick,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> it is not to be looked at as a thing for the market. But I shall
                    not object to contract for a poem more on a level with the general intellect &#8211; &amp; it will answer my purpose if a bookseller
                    will give me 500&#163; for the same quantity as <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> has just got 3000&#163; for. His decline
                    will not be my rise, I should be sorry indeed if my rise could depend on any such circumstances, &#8211; but that he <del>xxx</del>
                    &lt;must&gt; decline is as certain as that <del>there are</del> rules by which composition <del>may be</del> must be tried. He may
                    &amp; probably will produce other poems as good as his first, <del>but</del> it is out of his power to produce better. Perhaps I
                        <del>x</del> may be in the same case, &#8211; still there would be a difference, &#8211; for he has had little to do with feeling, &amp;
                    less with thought.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The scheme to which I look on as the sheet anchor of my new ways &amp; means, is a view of the revolutions of the
                    last fifty years, in all places &amp; in all things, &#8211; under some such title as the Age of George 3.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of the United Kingdom 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>). Despite the enthusiasm of
                        Southey and John Murray, this project, also known as a &#8216;View of the World&#8217; and &#8216;Cosmographia&#8217;, never came to fruition.</note>
                    This is a fresh project &#8211; not more then three days old, <del>x</del> the Pisgah-View<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Deuteronomy</title>, 34:1, where Moses is commanded to climb to the top of Pisgah, so a view from a high place; an
                        overview.</note> is in the highest degree promising, &#8211;&amp; there is a good deal of matter in <del>t</del> my various
                    reviewals convertible into this form.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You ask if I remember Paul.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">John Dean Paul, 1st Baronet (1775-1852). He was
                        admitted to Westminster School in 1787 and was therefore a year senior to Southey. Paul went on to become a partner in the
                        London bank Strachan, Paul, Paul and Bates.</note> A man of colour, &#8211; or something very <del>near</del> &lt;like&gt; it. He
                    was about a year my senior. I knew <del>nothing</del> little of him at school, &amp; nothing after he left it, except that he
                    became so purse-proud as to make himself ridiculous.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In my next I will <del>put</del> look out for you my memoranda about consumption<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been collecting information for his brother since at least 1811; see Robert Southey to Henry
                        Herbert Southey, 18 November 1811, Letter 1985. Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s <title>Observations on Pulmonary Consumption</title>
                        was published by Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme and Brown in 1814.</note> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmundson</ref>
                    is bleeding <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George</ref> in the next room, &#8211; &amp; we shall have a nervous night, &#8211; even
                    if nothing worse. Children all well. God bless you. Your ordinary letters are almost as dear as if they were prescriptions, &#8211; but
                    if they are like your last for contents the oftener they arrive the better.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1813-02-03">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 3. 1813.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> When you have done with the six books of Roderick convey them to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                            Uncle</ref>.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>