<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2295</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3566</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4813D.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2295" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2295" type="letter">
        <head>2295. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, [<date when="1813-08-31">c.
                        late August 1813</date>]</head><p>MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4813D<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note: News of the disturbances in Sicily mentioned in this letter began to appear in British
                        newspapers from 21 August 1813 onwards. This letter therefore probably dates from this period.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Bleda,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jayme Bleda (1550&#8211;1622), <title>Coronica de Los Moros de
                            Espana</title> (1618); no. 3346 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> D Juan de Persia,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Juan de Persia (1560&#8211;1604), <title>Relaciones, donde se Tratan las Cosas Notables de Persia, in
                            Guerras de Persianos, Turcos y Tartaros</title> (1604); no. 3699 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
                        Clavijo,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ruy Gonzales de Clavijo (d. 1412), <title>Embajada a Tamorlan</title>
                        (1582).</note> Mendoza,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Either: Diego Hurtado de Mendoza (1503&#8211;1575), <title>Guerra de
                            Granada hecha por el Rey de Espana Don Felipe II</title> (1610), an edition of 1674 was no. 3537 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library; or, Pedro de Salazar y Mendoza, <title>Monarquia de Espana</title> (1770), no. 3635 in the sale catalogue
                        of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Alvares<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Alvares (c. 1465-c. 1540),
                            <title>Historiale Description de l&#8217;Ethiope</title> (1558); no. 37 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp;
                        Gomara<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably <title>The Conquest of the Weast Indies</title> (1576), an English
                        translation of Francisco Lopez de Gomara (c. 1511&#8211;1566?), <title>Hispania Victrix</title> (1552).</note> I have. I have also
                    the first part of Pedro de Cieza 12mo, Anvers 1554.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Cieza de Leon (c. 1520&#8211;1554),
                            <title>Cronicas del Peru</title> (1553). Southey&#8217;s edition of 1554 was no. 3196 in the sale catalogue of his library. The
                        remaining three parts were gradually published 1871&#8211;1979.</note> Nic. Antonio<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Spanish bibliographer Nicol&#225;s Antonio (1617&#8211;1684). Southey used the revised edition of his <title>Bibliotheca Hispana Vetus et
                            Nova</title>, published in 1783&#8211;1788, no. 3309 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> says he wrote four parts but
                    that only one was published. Nic. Antonio however is not infallible &amp; if there is a second part I shall not hesitate at giving
                    two guineas for it, &#8211; which is going to a Collectors price. My first part contains 121 Chapters the last of which is &#8216;De Los
                    Monestarios que se han fundado en al Peru desde el tiempo que se descubrio hasta este a&#241;o de mil 7 quinientos y cinquenta
                    a&#241;os.&#8217;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Translates as: &#8216;Of the monasteries which were founded in Peru from the time of its discovery
                        until the current year 1750&#8217;.</note> &#8211; by this you can easily ascertain if the edition of 1557 has really a second part; &#8211; I
                    may as well add that the first contains 285 double pages.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a jornada de Africa by Juan Baptista de Morales, Seville 1622<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Juan
                        Bautista de Morales (1597&#8211;1664), <title>Jornado de Africa del Rey D. Sebastian de Portugal</title> (1622); no. 3440 in the
                        sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; another by Hieronimo de Mendonca in Portugueze.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jeronimo de Mendonca (c. 1558&#8211;c.1607), <title>Jornada de Africa</title> (1607).</note> &#8211; If <del>it be</del>
                    there be a different one at the sale it must be worth more to me than to any other person. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Marmol I dare not think of. &#8211; And indeed there is a new edition which I would as willingly have.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luis del Marmol Carujal (1520&#8211;1600), <title>Historia del Rebellion y Castigo de los Moriscos del
                            Reyno del Granada</title> (1600); Southey eventually acquired an edition of 1797, no. 3522 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Argensola I would give a guinea for, &#8211; which is just three times what it would have cost if it had ever fallen in
                    my way at Lisbon.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> An unidentified edition of either Bartolom&#232; Leonardo de Argensola
                        (1561&#8211;1631), Spanish priest, poet and historian or his brother Lupercio Leonardo de Argensola (1559&#8211;1613).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know nothing about Valles<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a work by the famous Spanish doctor,
                        Francisco Valles (1524&#8211;1592), or the Spanish historian Pedro de Valles (fl. 1540s).</note> or Puente<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a work by the Spanish Jesuit, Luis de la Puente (1554&#8211;1624).</note> &#8211; considering them as two pigs in
                    a poke, the first would be worth a 7/6 venture &amp; the latter <del>xxxx</del> 10/6.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Hernandia does not tempt me.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Ruiz de Leon (fl. 1750s),
                            <title>Hernandia, Triumphos de la Fe, y Gloria de las Armas Espanoles, Poema Heroyco</title> (1755); Southey obtained a
                        copy, no. 3722 in the sale catalogue of his library. The poem was a fictional re-telling of the Spanish conquest of Mexico in
                        1519&#8211;1521.</note> I have too much to do with matters of fact to have any leisure for indulging my own fancies, <del>far</del>
                    still less for following in idle curiosity those of others.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What a subject for a painter would the discovery of Charles&#8217;s body be!<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Probably the renovations taking place at St George&#8217;s Chapel, Windsor. On 1 April 1813, the Prince Regent had attended the
                        opening of the coffin of Charles I (1600&#8211;1649; reigned 1625&#8211;1649; <title>DNB</title>). It was reported that &#8216;the left eye [of
                        the corpse], in the first moment of exposure, was open and full, though it vanished almost immediately&#8217;, see Sir Henry Halford
                        (1766&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Account of What Appeared on Opening the Coffin of King Charles the First, in the
                            Vault of King Henry the Eighth in St George&#8217;s Chapel at Windsor</title> (1813), p. 8.</note> The manner in which the past
                    &amp; the present &amp; the future are all brought &lt;before&gt; me in that scene gives it an aweful &amp; visionary character
                    which makes it more truly <del>x</del> impressive than any historical fact <del>xxx</del> within my recollection. &#8211; If the Prophet
                    Daniel were at hand I would go to him to know what the Princes dreams were that night.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Daniel</title> 2: Daniel interprets the dream of the Babylonian king Nebuchadnezzar II (c. 634&#8211;562 BC).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I agree with you entirely as to the Signs of the Times. Between the breaking up of one system, &amp; the
                    consolidation of another centuries of turbulence &amp; <del>xxx</del> misery have always intervened: &amp; that <del>we are</del>
                    one of these political &amp; moral cycles is nearly <del>xx</del> full, seems to be but too certain. Monarchy is rotten &amp;
                    republicanism has been cankered in the bud. Even in America where the people were prepared for it, &amp; indeed <del>driven</del>
                    impelled to it by all their history, habits, <del>feelings</del>, principles, feelings &amp; institutions, Washington<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Washington (1732&#8211;1799), general and first President of the United States of America,
                        1789&#8211;1797.</note> himself felt, after the war was over &amp; the point gained, &#8211; that the experiment was premature. That union
                    no doubt will fall asunder, but whenever it does New England has better prospects than Old England.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The explosion in Sicily I see has taken place, a fine diversion in favour of Suchet!<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> There were food riots in Palermo on 18&#8211;19 July 1813 and British troops were diverted from their intended
                        destination of Spain to Sicily, in order to help maintain order. The Sicilian ministry resigned at the end of July 1813 and
                        British control of the island became ever more apparent. Southey points out that these events could only help Louis Gabriel
                        Suchet, Duc d&#8217;Albufera (1770&#8211;1826), French marshal and commander in eastern Spain.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have no fears about Germany, now that Germany is fairly roused.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The War
                        of the Sixth Coalition had begun in northern Germany once Prussia declared war on France in February 1813.</note> The contest
                    is for life or for death, &#8211; &amp; my philosophy is to be found in the vulgar phrase God&#8217;s above the Devil! &#8211;</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>