<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2016</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3287</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Previously  published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
                    19&#8211;22.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2016" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2016" type="letter">
        <head>2016. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1812-01-13">13 January
                        1812</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Bristol<lb />Endorsement: 1812/ Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 13<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Previously published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
                    19&#8211;22.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-01-13">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 13. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is most unusually long since I have heard from you, &amp; I have been in hopes of hearing that your enquiries
                    concerning the Military Male Asylum<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Royal Military Asylum, Chelsea founded in 1801 to
                        educate the children of soliders in the regular army who had died in the service of their country. It was also known as The
                        Duke of York&#8217;s School, after its patron. Danvers was trying to place his nephew, John Danvers, there.</note> had proved
                    succesful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have had the most unsettled winter I ever remember, &#8211; the weather never steady for three days <del>xxxxxx</del>,
                    yet thank God we have never had so healthy a house for so long a time together. <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edmundson</ref> has never made his appearance except as a visitor since we returned from the south, &#8211;
                    &amp; we never before were half so long without standing in need of his assistance. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>
                    has been <del>xxxx</del> here for two or three weeks, while his family are at his father-in-laws<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Castle (d. 1815), Co. Durham solicitor. He was Clerk to the Crown in the county and held various legal
                        appointments in the Bishop of Durham&#8217;s household.</note> &#8211; he leaves us on Tuesday to join them there. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is expected shortly, as soon as his Lectures<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge&#8217;s lecture series on Shakespeare, Milton and the English poets had begun at Scot&#8217;s
                        Corporation Hall, Fleet St, London, on 18 November 1811 and finished on 27 January 1812. He did not arrive in Keswick for
                        another month.</note> are over he says he shall set off, &#8211; tomorrow is the last of the course, &amp; I dare say he will come,
                    if it were only for the pleasure of showing himself after having done something. I think he will take up his abode here when he
                    comes, &amp; shall not be surprized if he becomes once more a family man as he ought to be. If he is disposed to industry I can
                    put employment into his hands, &#8211; for if I had half a dozen pair of my own, there would be work enough for all.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am a good deal interested with a young homo who has found his way to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, &amp; is lodging at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dares,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gideon Dare (dates
                        unknown), farmer and owner of Chestnut Hill Cottage at Applethwaite.</note> if you remember the house &#8211; nearly opposite
                    <ref target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calverts</ref>, &#8211; between the Penrith &amp; <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref> roads. His name is <ref target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref>, &#8211; his father member for Shoreham,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Timothy Shelley (1753&#8211;1844), MP for New Shoreham, Sussex, 1802&#8211;1818.</note> his grandfather a baronet.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Bysshe Shelley, 1st Baronet of Castle Goring (1731&#8211;1815).</note> This youth being 19
                    &amp; at Oxford, fell in metaphysics, &amp; as is usual for metaphysicians his next step was to fall in atheism, &#8211; what followed
                    however was not quite so usual. For happening to have a great deal of genius, a great deal of enthusiasm, &amp; high notions of
                    sincerity &amp; virtue, he thought that having discovered <del>xxx</del> truths of such infinite utility to mankind it was his
                    bounden duty to disseminate them: so he printed a little brochure of six pages which he called the Necessity of Atheism,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Necessity of Atheism</title>, published in March 1811. It was co-authored with Thomas Jefferson Hogg (1792&#8211;1862;
                            <title>DNB</title>), who was also expelled from the university.</note> &amp; sent this paper with this taking title to
                    every body he could think of who was likely to set him right if he were wrong, or whom it would be desirable to convert to the
                    saving no-faith if he were, as he supposed himself to be, right. Not that he was quite certain of this, &#8211; for one of the
                    correspondents whom he thus introduced himself to, recommended him to try the effect of prayer, &amp; he actually prayed for two
                    months, &#8211; till finding that tho he <del>took</del> &lt;observd&gt; the prescription as regularly as if it had been to take three
                    table spoonfuls of julip, no effect followed, he gave up the course.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Mary
                        Barker, 8 January 1812, Letter 2014.</note> Among other persons he sent his discoveries to all the Bishops. The consequence
                    was, as you may suppose, that he was expelled <del>fr</del> the University. His father then turned him out of doors. The story
                    does not end here. Among the persons whom he had been anxious to convert was <del>x</del> one of his sisters, a girl of great
                    genius by his account, who was then at school.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hellen Shelley (1799&#8211;1885), who was being
                        educated at Miss Fenning&#8217;s School at Church House, Clapham, near London.</note> A correspondence between them being forbidden
                    he contrived to carry it on thro one of her schoolfellows, &amp; this was discovered, &#8211; &amp; the <ref target="people.html#ShelleyHarriet">young Lady</ref> in question became subject to such grievous persecution at school, that
                    when she went home at the holydays she was <del>xxx</del> compleatly miserable at the prospect of returning. To relieve her
                    distress <ref target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelly</ref> proposed a journey to Scotland, &#8211; off they set (she 17) &amp;
                    were married, &amp; here they are now with a sister of hers,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Elizabeth Westbrook
                        (1782&#8211;1855).</note> living upon 200&#163; a year which her father<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Westbrook
                        (1751&#8211;1835), had retired from his main business as a vintner and hotel manager, but still owned a London coffee shop and a
                        tavern.</note> allows them, while the Duke of Norfolk who is his fathers intimate friend<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Howard, 11th Duke of Norfolk (1746&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), an active Whig, he controlled the
                        borough for which Timothy Shelley was returned as an MP.</note> endeavours to bring about a reconciliation. &#8211; As for the
                    marriage, tho it has irritated his family, it seems to <del>xx xx</del> be a very good thing for him, &amp; unless I am very much
                    deceived he will ripen if he lives into a very valuable man. His father may deprive him of about 6000 a year, but as much more is
                    entailed upon him, &#8211; this is at present a source of some discomfort to him, as he disapproves of entail, primogeniture &amp;c &#8211; .
                    To tell you all the odd things about him would fill a larger sheet than I have allowed myself for the whole letter. I hope he will
                    continue here till you make us your visit in the summer.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our crate of crockery from M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rings<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Elizabeth Ring
                        (d. 1816), owner of the Bristol Pottery, from which Southey had bought some new crockery.</note> has not yet arrived, &#8211; I
                    wrote lately to <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">S. Reid</ref> to make inquiry concerning it at Liverpool, &amp; not having
                    receiving any reply take it for granted that he is visiting some of his relations in the South.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s letter to Reid appears not to have survived.</note> &#8211; To tell you that I am very busy would be to
                    tell you what need not be told. I am hard at work upon the Register for 1810,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title> (1812).</note> &amp; am moreover deeply pledged to the Quarterly Review.
                    The next number will have a long article of mine upon the Inquisition:<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The History of the Inquisitions; including the Secret Transactions of those Horrific Tribunals</title> (1810);
                            <title>Letter upon the Mischievous Influence of the Spanish Inquisition as it actually exists in the Provinces under the
                            Spanish Government. Translated from El Espa&#241;ol, a periodical Spanish Journal published in London</title> (1811);
                            <title>Narrativa da Persegui&#231;&#227;o de Hippolyto Joseph Da Costa Pereira Furtado de Mendon&#231;a, Natural da Colonia do
                            Sacramento, no Rio-da-Prata, prezo e Processado em Lisboa pelo pretenso Crime de Fra-Ma&#231;on, ou Pedreiro Livre</title>
                        (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (December 1811), 313&#8211;357.</note> &amp; perhaps a reviewal of <ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomerys</ref> poems.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Montgomery,
                            <title>The West Indies, and other Poems</title> (1810) and <title>The Wanderer in Switzerland, and other Poems</title>
                        (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (December 1811), 405&#8211;419.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not know what profit <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> has derived from his
                    lectures, &#8211; expect that it has been much less than it would have been if the public had had any reliance upon him, &#8211; many persons
                    having declined subscribing because they expected that he would never go thro the course. But the accounts which have reached me
                    of the matter &amp; manner of his discourses are as favourable as they could be. I wrote to <ref target="people.html#MorganJohnJames">John Morgan</ref> to have them taken down in short-hand:<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Southey to John James Morgan, 13 November 1811, Letter 1983.</note> &#8211; it was found that this would be
                    too expensive, &#8211; absorbing the whole profits, &#8211; but <ref target="people.html#MorganJohnJames">Morgan</ref> told me one of his
                    auditors (a friend of <ref target="people.html#RobinsonHenryCrabb">Henry Robinsons</ref>) had begun <del>to xx</del> the task
                    &amp; meant when the course was ended to surprise <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> by presenting him with
                    a fair transcript.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Payne Collier (1789&#8211;1883; <title>DNB</title>), the literary
                        editor and forger, took down a short-hand transcript of seven (out of seventeen) of these lectures, finally published as
                            <title>Seven Lectures on Shakespeare and Milton by the late S. Coleridge</title> (1856).</note> This if it has been done,
                    as I believe it has, will be of main importance. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> send their love &#8211; remember me to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Estlin</ref>, &#8211; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Foot<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Foot (c. 1742&#8211;1827), daughter of Southey&#8217;s old schoolmaster, William Foot (1707&#8211;1782). John
                        Prior Estlin had taken over William Foot&#8217;s school.</note> &amp; all other friends &#8211; &amp; believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>