<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2439</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3710</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25; Houghton
                        Library, Harvard, bMS Eng 265.2 (10) (poem).  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2439" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2439" type="letter">
        <head>2439. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1814-06-14">14 June 1814</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9. Stafford Row/ Buckingham Gate/ London/ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 17 JU 17/
                        1814<lb />Endorsement: 14 June 1814/ with ode to the King of Prussia<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25; Houghton
                        Library, Harvard, bMS Eng 265.2 (10) (poem)<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-06-14">Tuesday June 14. 1814</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will get this on Friday, &amp; if you should have sent the other two to the printer, he may very well have the
                    whole ready for publication on Monday morning.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The paragraph deals with arrangements for
                        the publication of Southey&#8217;s three odes paying tribute to the Prince Regent and celebrating the 1814 visit to London of
                        Alexander I (1777&#8211;1825; Emperor of Russia 1801&#8211;1825) and Frederick William III (1770&#8211;1840), ruler of Prussia since 1797;
                        published as <title>Congratulatory Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness The Prince Regent, His Imperial Majesty The Emperor of
                            Russia, and His Majesty the King of Prussia</title> (1814).</note> I have worked hard at them, &amp; like them a good deal
                    better in their way that I did the Carmen.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s first Laureate poem <title>Carmen
                            Triumphale</title> (1814).</note> Your letter tomorrow will give me your opinion, &amp; if they should be printed, a
                    puzzle will occur whether copies ought to be presented to the personages <hi rend="ital">be&#246;ded</hi> a new word for the nonce. I
                    believe my best way will be to write to <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, send him some copies &amp;
                    request him to dispose <del>of it</del> of them, as may be proper.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to John
                        Wilson Croker, 14 June 1814, Letter 2440.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should have been ready a day sooner, if of all <del>guest</del> imaginable guests chance had not sent to me last
                    week an officer<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French officer was Eustace Baudouin (b. c. 1792). He served in the
                        army of Louis Gabriel Suchet, 1st Duc d&#8217;Albufera (1770&#8211;1826), Marshal of France, and saw action at the first siege of
                        Tarragona, 1811. In the same year he was captured by the guerilla army of Joaquin Cuevas Ibanez y de Valonga, Baron de Eroles
                        (1784&#8211;1825). Baudouin spent time in Britain as a prisoner of war, and at one point was held at Oswestry, in Shropshire. On his
                        release, he visited the Wordsworths before returning to France. Baudouin had made contact with Wordsworth in 1812 via mutual
                        acquaintances: his brother was engaged to Caroline (1792&#8211;1862), daughter of Wordsworth and Annette Vallon (1766&#8211;1841).
                        Caroline and Jean Baptiste Baudouin (b. c. 1780) married in February 1816. Southey travelled to France and visited them and
                        their infant daughter in 1817, when he also renewed his acquaintance with Eustace Baudouin, who had retained his dislike for
                        potatoes; see Southey to Edith Southey, 17 May 1817.</note> of Suchets army, who served at the siege of Tarragona, &amp; was
                    afterwards taken by Eroles! I could not help more than once thinking what hearty satisfaction I should have had in cleaving him
                    from shoulder to chine if we had met in Catalonia. However <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> who has seen many
                    Frenchman pronounced him a remarkably good specimen: he had grace enough to admit that the war was unjust; &#8211; &amp; tickled me a
                    little by remarking that the Spaniards were very hard-hearted; &#8211; to which I made answer that they had <del>xx</del> not invited
                    him &amp; his countrymen. There is some grace in the poor fellow &#8211; he is only 22, &amp; had been living twelve months in Scotland
                    upon &#8216;<hi rend="ital">tatees</hi>&#8217;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Potatoes.</note> for breakfast, dinner &amp; supper, to
                    save money out of 18d. a day for buying <del>decent</del> clothes &#8211; <del>till</del> &lt;having landed at Leith<del>x</del> in
                    November with nothing but nankeen dresses.&gt; his friends in France found means to write to <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> whom they knew, &#8211; &amp; so he came to thank <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">W.</ref> for good services, on his way home, &amp; then must come &amp; see me
                        <del>too</del> &lt;also&gt;, with a fine French compliment in his mouth. I must not forget to tell you that he has foresworn
                        &#8216;<hi rend="ital">tatees</hi>&#8217; for life. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">The Docstor</ref> will show you a worthier poem of
                    mine upon the Russian war than either of these odes.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;The March to Moscow&#8217;, a &#8216;droll
                        ballad&#8217;, published in the <title>Courier</title>, 23 June 1814.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="center"> Ode</p>
          <p rend="center"> To the King of Prussia</p>
          <p rend="center"> 1.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center"> Welcome to England, to the happy Isle,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Brave Prince of gallant People! Welcome thou,</l>
            <l rend="center"> In adverse as in prosperous fortune tried!</l>
            <l rend="center"> Frederick, the well-beloved!</l>
            <l rend="center"> Greatest &amp; best of that illustrious name.</l>
            <l rend="center"> Welcome to these free shores!</l>
            <l rend="center"> In glory art thou come,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Thy victory perfect, thy revenge compleat.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <p rend="center"> 2.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center"> Enough of sorrow hast thou known,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Enough of evil hath thy realm endured,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Oppress&#8217;d, but not debased,</l>
            <l rend="center"> When thine indignant soul</l>
            <l rend="center"> Long suffering, bore its weight of heaviest woe.</l>
            <l rend="center"> But still, thro that dark day</l>
            <l rend="center"> Unsullied Honour was thy counsellor;</l>
            <l rend="center"> And Hope, that had its trust in Heaven,</l>
            <l rend="center"> And in the heart of man</l>
            <l rend="center"> Its strength, forsook thee not.</l>
            <l rend="center"> Thou had&#8217;st thy faithful people&#8217;s love,</l>
            <l rend="center"> The sympathy of noble minds;</l>
            <l rend="center"> And wistfully, as one</l>
            <l rend="center"> Who through the weary night has long&#8217;d for day</l>
            <l rend="center"> Looks eastward for the dawn,</l>
            <l rend="center"> So Germany to thee</l>
            <l rend="center"> Turn&#8217;d in her bondage her imploring eyes.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <p rend="center"> 3.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center"> Oh grief of griefs, that Germany,</l>
            <l rend="center"> The wise, the virtuous land,</l>
            <l rend="center"> The land of mighty minds,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Should bend beneath a vile Barbarian&#8217;s yoke!</l>
            <l rend="center"> Oh grief of griefs, to think</l>
            <l rend="center"> That she should groan in bonds,</l>
            <l rend="center"> She who had blest all nations with her gifts!</l>
            <l rend="center"> There had the light of Reformation risen,</l>
            <l rend="center"> The light of Knowledge there was burning clear.</l>
            <l rend="center"> Oh grief, that her unhappy sons</l>
            <l rend="center"> Should toil &amp; bleed &amp; die,</l>
            <l rend="center"> To quench that sacred light,</l>
            <l rend="center"> The wretched agents of a Tyrants will!</l>
            <l rend="center"> How often hath their blood</l>
            <l rend="center"> In his accursed cause</l>
            <l rend="center"> Reek&#8217;d on the Spaniard&#8217;s blade!</l>
            <l rend="center"> Their mangled bodies fed</l>
            <l rend="center"> The Wolves &amp; Eagles of the Pyrenees,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Or stiffening in the snows of Moscovy,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Amid the ashes of the watch-fire lay,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Where dragging painfully their frozen limbs,</l>
            <l rend="center"> With life&#8217;s last effort, in the flames they fell.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <p rend="center"> 4.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center"> Long, Frederick, did&#8217;st thou bear</l>
            <l rend="center"> Her sorrows &amp; thine own;</l>
            <l rend="center"> Seven miserable years</l>
            <l rend="center"> In patience did&#8217;st thou feed thy heart with hope;</l>
            <l rend="center"> Till, when the arm of God</l>
            <l rend="center"> Smote the blaspheming Tyrant in his pride,</l>
            <l rend="center"> And Alexander with the voice of power</l>
            <l rend="center"> Raised the glad cry, deliverance for mankind,</l>
            <l rend="center"> First of the Germans, Prussia broke her chains.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <p rend="center"> 5.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center"> Joy, joy for Germany,</l>
            <l rend="center"> For Europe, for the World,</l>
            <l rend="center"> When Prussia rose in arms!</l>
            <l rend="center"> Oh, what a spectacle</l>
            <l rend="center"> For present &amp; for future times was there,</l>
            <l rend="center"> When for the public need</l>
            <l rend="center"> Wives gave their marriage rings,</l>
            <l rend="center"> And mothers, when their sons</l>
            <l rend="center"> The Band of Vengeance join&#8217;d,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Bade them return victorious from the field,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Or with their country fall.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <p rend="center"> 6.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center"> Twice o&#8217;er the field of death</l>
            <l rend="center"> The trembling scales of Fate hung equipoised:</l>
            <l rend="center"> For France, obsequious to her Tyrant still,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Mighty for evil, put forth all her power;</l>
            <l rend="center"> And still beneath his hateful banners driven,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Against their <del>mother-land</del> father-land</l>
            <l rend="center"> Unwilling Germans <del>raisd</del> &lt;bore&gt; unnatural arms.</l>
            <l rend="center"> What tho&#8217; the Boaster made his temples ring</l>
            <l rend="center"> With vain thanksgivings for each doubtful day &#8211;</l>
            <l rend="center"> What tho&#8217; with false pretence of peace</l>
            <l rend="center"> His old insidious arts he tried &#8211;</l>
            <l rend="center"> The spell was broken! Austria threw her sword</l>
            <l rend="center"> Into the inclining scale,</l>
            <l rend="center"> And Leipsic saw the wrongs</l>
            <l rend="center"> Of Germany avenged.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <p rend="center"> 7.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center"> Ne&#8217;er till that aweful time had Europe seen</l>
            <l rend="center"> Such multitudes in arms;</l>
            <l rend="center"> Nor ever had the rising Sun beheld</l>
            <l rend="center"> Such mighty interests of mankind at stake;</l>
            <l rend="center"> Nor o&#8217;er so wide a scene</l>
            <l rend="center"> Of slaughter e&#8217;er had Night her curtain closed.</l>
            <l rend="center"> There on the battle-field</l>
            <l rend="center"> With one accord the grateful Monarchs knelt,</l>
            <l rend="center"> And raised their voice to Heaven;</l>
            <l rend="center"> &#8220;The cause was thine, O Lord!</l>
            <l rend="center"> O Lord! thy hand was here!&#8221;</l>
            <l rend="center"> What Conquerors e&#8217;er deserved</l>
            <l rend="center"> So proud, so pure a joy!</l>
            <l rend="center"> It was a moment when the exalted soul</l>
            <l rend="center"> Might almost wish to burst its mortal bounds,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Lest all of life to come</l>
            <l rend="center"> Vapid &amp; void should seem</l>
            <l rend="center"> After that high-wrought hour.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <p rend="center"> 8.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center"> But thou hadst yet more toils,</l>
            <l rend="center"> More duties &amp; more triumphs yet in store.</l>
            <l rend="center"> Elbe must not bound thine arms,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Nor on the banks of Rhine</l>
            <l rend="center"> Thine Eagles check their flight,</l>
            <l rend="center"> When o&#8217;er that barrier stream,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Awakened Germany</l>
            <l rend="center"> Drove her invaders with such rout &amp; wreck</l>
            <l rend="center"> As overtook the impious Gaul of old,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Laden with plunder, &amp; from Delphi driven.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <p rend="center"> 9.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center"> Long had insulting France</l>
            <l rend="center"> Boasted her arms invincible,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Her soil inviolate;</l>
            <l rend="center"> At length the hour of retribution comes!</l>
            <l rend="center"> Avenging nations on all sides move on;</l>
            <l rend="center"> In Gascony the flag of England flies,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Triumphant, as of yore,</l>
            <l rend="center"> When sable Edward led his peerless host.</l>
            <l rend="center"> Behold the Spaniard &amp; the Portugal,</l>
            <l rend="center"> For cities burnt, for violated fanes,</l>
            <l rend="center"> For murders, massacres,</l>
            <l rend="center"> All monstrous, all unutterable crimes,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Demanding vengeance with victorious cries,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Pour from the Pyrenees.</l>
            <l rend="center"> The Russian comes, his eye on Paris fix&#8217;d,</l>
            <l rend="center"> The flames of Moscow present to his heart;</l>
            <l rend="center"> The Austrian to efface</l>
            <l rend="center"> Ulm, Austerlitz, &amp; Wagram&#8217;s later shame;</l>
            <l rend="center"> Rejoicing Germany</l>
            <l rend="center"> With all her nations swells the avenging train,</l>
            <l rend="center"> And in the field &amp; in the triumph first,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Thy banner, Frederick, floats.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <p rend="center"> 10.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center"> Six weeks in daily strife</l>
            <l rend="center"> The veteran Blucher bore the brunt of war.</l>
            <l rend="center"> Glorious old man,</l>
            <l rend="center"> The last &amp; greatest of his master&#8217;s school,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Long may he live to hear</l>
            <l rend="center"> The people bless his name!</l>
            <l rend="center"> Late be it ere the wreath </l>
            <l rend="center"> That crowns his silver hair</l>
            <l rend="center"> Adorn his monument!</l>
            <l rend="center"> Glorious old man,</l>
            <l rend="center"> How oft hath he discomfited</l>
            <l rend="center"> The boasted Chiefs of France,</l>
            <l rend="center"> And foil&#8217;d her vaunting Tyrant&#8217;s desperate rage!</l>
            <l rend="center"> Glorious old man,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Who from Silesia&#8217;s fields,</l>
            <l rend="center"> O&#8217;er Elbe, &amp; Rhine, &amp; Seine,</l>
            <l rend="center"> From victory to victory marching on,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Made his heroic way; till at the gates</l>
            <l rend="center"> Of Paris, opened by his arms, he saw</l>
            <l rend="center"> His King triumphant stand.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <p rend="center"> 11.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center"> Bear back the sword of Frederick now!</l>
            <l rend="center"> The sword which France amid her spoils display&#8217;d,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Proud trophy of a day by treachery won.</l>
            <l rend="center"> With laurels wreathe the sword;</l>
            <l rend="center"> Bear it in triumph back,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Thus gloriously regain&#8217;d!</l>
            <l rend="center"> And when thou lay&#8217;st it in its honour&#8217;d place,</l>
            <l rend="center"> O Frederick, well-beloved,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Greatest &amp; best of that illustrious name,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Lay by its side thine own,</l>
            <l rend="center"> A holier relic there!</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <p rend="center"> 12.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center"> Frederick, the well-beloved!</l>
            <l rend="center"> Welcome to these free shores,</l>
            <l rend="center"> To England welcome, to the happy Isle!</l>
            <l rend="center"> In glory art thou come,</l>
            <l rend="center"> Thy victory perfect, thy revenge compleat.</l>
          </lg>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>