<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2080</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3351</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                        University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos,
                            The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838
                        (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 123&#8211;124.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2080" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2080" type="letter">
        <head>2080. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>,
                    <date when="1812-04-17">17 April 1812</date>
          </head><p>Watermark: [partial] 1806<lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 158 1812/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        April/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            <lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                        University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos,
                            <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title>
                        (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 123&#8211;124.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-04-17">April 17. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Four treasury franks have reached me, &amp; I have examined all
                    the papers which they contained. Some of them as relating to Portugal are to me
                    highly interesting &amp; valuable, &#8211; but these are irrelevant to the immediate
                    object. It would not be possible from these papers to do any thing <del>x</del>
                    more than give the dates of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpole life &amp;
                    professional appointments, accompanied with a general eulogium &amp; with
                    testimonials of his merit in his public capacity.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Walpole (1736&#8211;1810), Envoy Extraordinary and
                        Minister Plenipotentiary to Portugal, 1771&#8211;1800. Southey had been asked to
                        write his life.</note> To do what ought to be done, the diplomatic
                    correspondence should be examined, from which a summary of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpoles conduct as a statesman may be drawn. But when several large
                    volumes in folio are to be mastered, this becomes a serious undertaking, which I
                    fear it would be quite impossible to execute in time for the present year, &#8211; the
                    bulk of the Annals<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Southey&#8217;s
                        work on the historical section of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1810</title> (1812).</note> being as yet unfinished. I must therefore
                    reluctantly request that it be postponed for the next years volume, &amp; as
                    soon as my hands are clear, not of all their engagements (for that is never
                    likely to be the case) but of this heaviest &amp; most pressing one, which they
                    will be by the end of the ensuing month, &#8211; I will then con amore<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;with love&#8217;.</note> apply myself to this
                    memoir, if the correspondence be entrusted to me either here &lt;during the
                    summer&gt;, or at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>, when I
                    make my visit there at the fall of the leaf. One advantage will arise from the
                    delay, &#8211; that the memoir may pass under the eyes of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                    Walpoles friends before it be committed to the press. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I need not say that the perusal of this correspondence will
                    &lt;be a&gt; most important assistance to my own history, &#8211; giving me the most
                    authentic information for a period during which there are no printed documents
                    whatever.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do you read the Correio Brazilienze?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Correio Braziliense</title> (also known as
                        the &#8216;Literary Warehouse&#8217;) was a journal in Portuguese. Edited by Hipolito
                        Jose da Costa (1774&#8211;1823), it was printed in London and ran from 1808&#8211;1822.
                        It was critical of the Portuguese monarchy and advocated liberal ideas.
                        Southey possessed a complete set, no. 3203 in the Sale catalogue of his
                        Library.</note> I am so well pleased with the principles of the Editor that
                    I can forgive the few instances of prejudice &amp; pride which he discovers,
                    &amp; should much like to become acquainted with him. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> keeps a bad look out for
                    me, I never heard of this work till I saw a number of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Burns<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Burn (fl.
                        1770s-1810s), was a member of the Lisbon Factory. He was well-known to
                        Herbert Hill and John May and had first met Southey in Lisbon in 1796. He
                        moved to London in 1806 and Richmond in 1815.</note> at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>, &amp; I cannot now get these
                    booksellers to hunt out the <del>counter</del> journal established by D
                        Domingos<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Domingos de Sousa
                        Coutinho, 1st Conde e Marques do Funchal (1760&#8211;1833), member of the
                        Portuguese legation in London 1803&#8211;1814 and the target of attacks by the
                            <title>Correio Braziliense</title>. The journal Southey refers to is
                        probably <title>O Investigador Portuguese em Inglaterra</title> (1811&#8211;19),
                        no. 3409 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
          <del>again</del> in opposition to it, &#8211; tho I know there is such a one, having
                    seen it at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dysons.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Thomas Fournice Dyson (1767&#8211;1843) of Everton. He had formerly
                        lived in Lisbon and moved in the same circles there as Southey in 1800&#8211;1801.
                        His wife, Anne Baldwin Sealy (c. 1780&#8211;1857), was the sister of Henry Herbert
                        Southey&#8217;s first wife, Mary-Harriet (d. 1811).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco</ref> &#8211; the
                        Espa&#241;ol<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Blanco White was the
                        editor of the <title>Espanol</title> 1810&#8211;1814.</note> is coming down to me
                    this summer. I am now concluding a chapter containing a view of the conduct of
                    the Central Junta, a good deal of which will be new to the English public.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e the government formed in 1808&#8211;1810
                        to coordinate Spanish efforts against the French. For Southey&#8217;s account,
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.1 (1812),
                        353&#8211;380.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> joins me in
                        remembrances to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref>.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>