<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2037</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3308</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Robert
                        Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp.
                        385&#8211;389.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2037" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2037" type="letter">
        <head>2037. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1812-02-13">13 February
                        1812</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Miss Barker<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert
                        Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp.
                        385&#8211;389<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-02-13">Feby 13. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You are right honest woman, Senhora, &#8212; an awkward sort of compliment to a Lady, it must be confessed, considering
                    what is meant by making an honest woman, &#8212; no matter for that. I love you the better for the honesty with which you speak of Sir J
                    Moore &amp; when you have read my Register for <hi rend="ital">1809</hi> where I have said more of him &amp; as much of him as
                    your heart could desire, you will think me very honest too.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809,</title> 2.1 (1811), 56&#8211;108. Mary Barker had been reading the <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 421&#8211;441, 306&#8211;321, on Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>) and the
                        first siege of Zaragoza (1808).</note> There is a second siege of Zaragoza in that volume,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 508&#8211;525.</note> not less impressive than the first; &amp;
                    there is an attack upon the <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdettite</ref> Reformers, written with as much force as any thing
                    which I have ever yet produced,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 31&#8211;32, 201, 233, 257&#8211;282.</note> &#8212; for you must know that I am
                    become a great enemy to what is called Parliamentary Reform; &#8212; it is a vile twopenny-halfpenny business, holding out nothing but a
                    deceitful economy, &amp; substituting Profit &amp; loss in the place of every thing which has hitherto been considered as great
                    &amp; generous.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will find out who purchased Ennerdale<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ennerdale, a small lake southwest
                        of the Derwent. It is not clear which estate Southey is describing.</note> as soon as I meet with any person who can tell me;
                    it will probably prove a useless piece of information, for it is not likely the purchasers will be induced to sell, what they have
                    no intention of selling, unless a great price be held out to them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I give you joy of the <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Imperials</ref> criticism, &amp; of Miss Linwoods
                        tragedy.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly the composer and author Mary Linwood (c. 1783&#8211;1850s?), rather than
                        her aunt, Mary Linwood (1755&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), whose copies in needlework of one hundred pictures of old and modern
                        masters were exhibited in London from 1798&#8211;1841. The younger Mary Linwood published <title>Leicestershire Tales</title> (1808)
                        and a long poem, <title>The Anglo-Cambrian</title> (1818).</note> Happy Senhora to be so favoured! By way however of making
                    you some amends for what you may have suffered at this tragedy I will tell you that <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> has just published one without his name,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Count Julian</title> (1812).</note> which tho it has little common dramatic interest, &amp; partakes of that obscurity
                    which distinguishes all his verse, is yet a most wonderful production, &amp; has passages in it of exquisite beauty, &amp; of
                    unsurpassable sublimity. Count Julian is the title. The same characters of those of Pelayo, but very differently represented.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814). Julian, Count of Ceuta, is a
                        legendary figure who was supposed to have aided the Moorish invasion of Spain in 711/712.</note> Julian is the hero, &amp;
                    very finely is the character conceived. &#8212; It does not accord with my plans to give any dignity to Julian I take him, as the scanty
                    historical accounts we have, represent him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A notion has come into my head for a poem, which if it ripen will get the world staring even more than Kehama has
                    done, or my unborn Quaker-hero will do.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Oliver Newman</title>, published posthumously in 1845.</note> You have had a Mahommedan poem in Thalaba, &amp; a Hindoo
                        one,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801) and <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> this is to be a Heavenly one
                    &#8212; that is, the scene is to be in the next world, &#8212; I want to see if I cannot make a Heaven of my own, &amp; believe in it into the
                    bargain. Now as it is my firm belief, according to the doctrine of the Bards,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> As
                        outlined, for instance, in William Owen Pughe, <title>The Heroic Elegies and Other Pieces of Llywarc Hen</title> (1792).
                        Southey would have investigated this subject whilst researching <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> that they who get out of
                    this stage of existence into a better, are out of reach of evil, &amp; that no other change takes place but that of perpetual
                    progression in knowledge &amp; power, &#8212; that is, growth without the sense of alteration. it is clear that I can have no story
                    involving any thing like those hopes &amp; fears which are as necessary to narration, almost, as plums to a plum-pudding. But it
                    seems feasible to borrow them from earth, &#8212; by making my story human, but taking the point of view of it wholly from heaven, &amp;
                    bringing up the actors there at last, to rejoin those who have gone before them.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        published no such poem.</note> The possibility I feel, &amp; have a better map of Heaven in my head than ever Swedenborg
                        had,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Emmanuel Swedenborg (1688&#8211;1772), <title>Treatise Concerning Heaven and
                            Hell</title> (1800), no. 2760 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> tho to be sure it is not quite so
                    definite in all its parts. Now I believe this would not only be a very delightful task but that it would be a very useful one as
                    well, for my Heaven is such a one that whether the reader chose to believe it or not, it would lay hold of him &amp; as much alter
                    his feeling of death &amp; immortality as the Paradise Lost modified his notions of Adam &amp; Eve,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Paradise Lost</title> (1667).</note> &#8212; or to come nearer
                    to the mark, as Shakespeare influences his conceptions of Richard the Third &amp; Henry 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard III (1452&#8211;1485, King of England 1483&#8211;1485; <title>DNB</title>) and Henry V (1386&#8211;1422,
                        King of England 1413&#8211;1422; <title>DNB</title>), as portrayed in the Shakespeare plays of those names.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The evil is Senhora, that occupations multiply upon my hands, &#8212; &amp; the hands do not multiply for the
                    occupations. On one hand I am called upon for the Quarterly Review, &#8212; on another for the Register,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title> (1812).</note> &amp; &#8212; here is Pelayo<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early incarnation of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> on the stocks, &#8212; a life
                    of Nelson advertised &amp; only a third part of it written,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Nelson</title>, published in two volumes (1813).</note> &#8212; the concluding vol. of Brazil<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> to be finished if possible this summer, &#8212; &amp;c &amp;c. And when one
                    thing is done, there seems to be just as much . . . the Review comes once a quarter, the Register once a year, &amp; I do but
                    breathe from one job, to begin upon another. If I could but . . . that Historiographers birth,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The post of Historiographer Royal. The incumbent, Louis Dutens (1730&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), died on 23 May
                        1812, but Southey was not appointed to succeed him.</note> I would drop some of these things, &amp; divide my time between
                    poetry &amp; my own historical pursuits; for such is the perversity of the age that the more reputation I get, the more I am
                    called off to busy myself upon temporary topics.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Farewell. I rejoice to think that your marvellous oak is by this time nearly seasoned, &amp; that I may begin to
                    think of the cabinet. Two shelves I think deep enough to contain a fools-cap quarto, (the depth of this half sheet is amply
                    sufficient) &amp; two drawers below. Something in this way, if you can understand my drawing;<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey has drawn a small rectangular cabinet on the MS.</note> &#8212; or if it will look better to have no drawers
                    below the Doors, then a third shelf within &#8212; I do not mean <hi rend="ital">three shelves</hi>, but two besides the <hi rend="ital">ground floor</hi>. but you are the Queen of the Kickmanjiggers &#8212; Queen said I? &#8212; yea verily the Empress &#8212; Autocratrix &#8212; or
                    Grand-Senhora, &#8212; which I take it is the highest title you could have, were you a Turk. So do you exercise your own taste.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent6"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent7"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> There can be no doubt that the <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Imp.</ref> will gladly lend <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir E</ref>. the island &#8212; but oh if he should think it necessary to be there it
                        deceives him! &#8212;</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>