<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1934</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3205</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Manuscripts and Archives
                        Section, New York Public Library, Lee Kohns Collection, Box
                        15.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1934" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1934" type="letter">
        <head>1934. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Robert
                        Gooch</ref>, <date when="1811-06-10">10 June 1811</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Robert Gooch Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Croydon/ Surry<lb />Postmarks: E/ 12JU12/ 1811; [partial]
                        10oclock/ JU12<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Manuscripts and Archives
                        Section, New York Public Library, Lee Kohns Collection, Box
                        15<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> My influence with the booksellers is not very great, yet I am not
                    without hopes that it may be in my power to open some channels thro which you
                    may benefit the public in a manner profitable to yourself. I have told <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> that I can perhaps
                    procure a life of <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref> for the
                    next Edinb. Ann. Register, &#8211; that is the vol. for 1810, which will be published
                    early in the next year.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See &#8216;Life of
                        Dr. Beddoes&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2
                        (1812), 516&#8211;537.</note> The pay is ten guineas per sheet, &amp; the subject
                    may fairly fill &lt;from&gt; two to three. Stocks life will supply you with the
                    leading facts, &#8211; but Stock is not a man by any means capable of writing a
                    philosophical account of <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref>.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Edmonds
                        Stock (1774&#8211;1835), <title>Memoirs of the Life of Thomas Beddoes, M.D. With
                            an Analytical Account of His Writings</title> (1811).</note> Some
                    personal anecdotes I can <del>supply yo</del> communicate, from my own
                    knowledge, &amp; can procure any specific information which you may wish to
                    possess.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Probably also I can introduce you to the Quarterly Review, this
                    however is said far more from a reliance upon you, than upon my own interest in
                    that quarter, <del>for</del> I have never seen either the <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Publisher</ref> or <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Editor</ref>, &amp; after all,
                    personal recommendations would be of no avail, if the papers recommended did not
                    approve themselves. The only sure mode of proceeding is, that you should chuse
                    your own subject &amp; prepare an article. That upon Medical Reform would have
                    done admirably. &#8211; You can easily find a text, &amp; I will put your paper into
                        <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> hands. The pay here also
                    is 10 guineas. &#8211; There is no reason why you should confine yourself to a medical
                    subject if any other occurs to you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> These retail employments are the most gainful, &#8211; or at least they
                    have this advantage that their returns are immediate &amp; certain. But it has
                    occurred to me that you might, almost with a certainty of equal profit, &amp;
                    with a probability of far greater, employ yourself upon a work which is
                    intimately connected with your profession, &amp; would tend to advance you in
                    it, which in itself is worthy of your time &amp; talents, &amp; would prove a
                    delightful occupation. I mean a history at once popular &amp; philosophical of
                    the art of medicine. There are <del>many</del> I know histories of this art of
                    great extent &amp; prodigious labour: &#8211; but they are exclusively professional
                    &amp; from their bulk probably very little known to the profession themselves.
                    What I propose to your consideration is a work wanting in general history, &#8211;
                    tracing the origin of the art, following its progress till from a superstition
                    it became a science, explaining the various theories which have encumbered it,
                    &amp; enlivening the detail by biographical sketches, accounts of the various
                    schools of medicine, &#8211; &amp; c. it would be a history of diseases also, &#8211; that
                    is of the changes in the physical nature of man <del>xxxx</del> produced by
                    changes of habit, &amp; by other causes, as yet unascertained, but some of which
                    you would probably be enabled to discover in the course of your enquiries. Two,
                    three, or four octavo volumes upon such a plan would be sure of sale, &amp; any
                    bookseller, I believe, would gladly contract for them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will at once perceive the bearings of a subject like this,
                    &amp; the rank which &lt;such&gt; a philosophic<del>al</del> history would hold
                    in general literature.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall be in your neighbourhood soon after this reaches you. We
                    set out from home on Tuesday next, &amp; on the Monday following shall probably
                    reach <del>your</del> our journey&#8217;s end. After that day you will find me, just
                    in your way to London, at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> &#8211;
                    at <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle&#8217;s</ref> Parsonage.
                    It will give me great pleasure to see you there, &amp; to introduce you to him.
                    It would give me still more if you could be prevailed upon to make a visit to
                    the North, before you leave Croydon &amp; settle in town. I should be very glad
                    to have you for my guest, &#8211; here is a lovely country, &#8211; amusement enough both
                    for the botanist &amp; mineralogist out of doors, &#8211; &amp; plenty of books for
                    wet weather. And you could take your friend <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Henry</ref> on the way either
                    going or returning. Bear this in mind &amp; believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yours with sincere esteem</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1811-06-10">June 10. 1811.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>