<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2415</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3686</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                  1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                  only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                  redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                        Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                  that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                  additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                  all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Eustace R. Conder, Josiah Conder: A Memoir (London, 1857). Previously published: Eustace R. Conder,
               Josiah Conder: A Memoir (London, 1857), pp. 166&#8211;169.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript
               Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
               Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University
               Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
               Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University; the John Rylands Library,
               Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
               Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public
               Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
               Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne;
               the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the English Department of
               Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2415" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey&#8217;s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2415" type="letter">
        <head>2415. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ConderJosiah">Josiah Conder</ref>, <date when="1814-05-04">4 May
                  1814</date>
          </head><p>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Eustace R. Conder, <title>Josiah Conder: A
                     Memoir</title> (London, 1857)<lb />Previously published: Eustace R. Conder, <title>Josiah Conder: A Memoir</title> (London, 1857),
                  pp. 166&#8211;169.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-05-04">May 4, 1814.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the Reviews.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Copies of the <title>Eclectic Review</title> of
                  which Conder was proprietor.</note> . . . They contain much to repay a perusal, and a man need not be as tolerant as I am to excuse
               a little that he may disapprove, for the sake of a great deal which deserves his approbation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Like all other journals, it sins sometimes on the side of severity, and drags an unhappy author into notice for the
               mere purpose of disgracing him. If it professed to notice every work which comes out, it would, of course, be proper to condemn all
               that deserved condemnation; but even in that case, it is condemnation enough to be merely noticed without praise. Beyond this, severity
               is unnecessary (except where there be some especial demerit), and therefore, I think, not to be justified. . . .</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Faults of this kind will never injure the sale of the journal, for even in that portion of the public for whom it is
               more particularly designed, the more amusing it is the better it will be received.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                     <title>Eclectic Review</title> was non-denominational, but it was founded and run by Nonconformists and clearly aimed at this
                  market: all profits were donated to the British and Foreign Bible Society. The <title>Evangelical Magazine</title> (1793&#8211;1904)
                  looked to a similar audience, but lacked the <title>Eclectic</title>&#8217;s broad view of literature, focusing more on missionary
                  endeavours and religious publications.</note> In this point of view I think there are <hi rend="ital">some</hi> theological articles
               which would have been better adapted to the <title>Evangelical Magazine</title>. Professing to be eclectic, it is certainly not
               necessary to notice works which have no other merit than that of being orthodox according to the creed of the <title>Review</title>. Of
               divinity, I should think that one article for controversy and one for edification would be a sufficient proportion for each number &#8211;
               speaking entirely with reference to the interests of the publisher. The publisher also should write more in it himself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the October number, page 368, I was pleased to see that you had said of artists exactly what I had said of men &#8211;
               that, to judge their works fairly, we must look at them in the same light in which they were considered by the authors. You will find
               my sentence, with its wide application, in the reviewal of Bogue and Bennet, page 91.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A review
                  of Walter Scott&#8217;s <title>The Bridal of Triermain, or the Vale of St. John</title> (1813), <title>Eclectic Review</title>, 9 (October
                  1813) argued: &#8216;it is necessary, in order to obtain a fair estimate of the artist&#8217;s powers, or to appreciate his success, that his
                  readers understand his intentions &#8211; the effect he designed, and the object to which this effect was to be subservient&#8217;. Southey
                  compares this with his own assessment of David Bogue (1750&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>) and James Bennet (1774&#8211;1862;
                  <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of Dissenters, from the Revolution in 1688&#8211;to the Year 1808</title> (1812); Walter Wilson
                  (1781&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History and Antiquities of Dissenting Churches</title> (1808&#8211;1814); <title>Neal&#8217;s History of
                     the Puritans</title> (1812), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 10 (October 1813), 91: &#8216;To write history as it ought to be written,
                  requires a power of intellectual transmigration with which few persons are gifted. The author, if he would deal justly toward those
                  whose actions he professes to record, should go back to their times, and, standing where they stood, endeavour, as far as is
                  possible, to see things as they appeared within their scope of vision, in the same light, and from the same point of view, and
                  through the same medium&#8217;.</note> There is another remark of yours which shows that your thoughts and mine have been travelling in
               the same direction; it is when you ask whether the character of a poem determines its form, or the form determines its character. No
               man but a poet could have asked the question. I find the metre influences the style so materially, that nothing ever embarasses me so
               much as the choice of the mould in which a new poem shall be cast. The only thing of which experience has made me certain is, that
               blank verse, of all measures the easiest to a beginner, is the most difficult to a proficient in versification.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomery</ref> (he is easily recognised) has given me the best kind of praise,
               though he has considered as an ode a poem to which I affixed a generic name purposely, that an ode might not be expected.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The review of <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (1814) in <title>Eclectic Review</title>, n.s. 1 (May
                  1814), 431&#8211;436 (esp. 432, 435&#8211;436).</note> The Greeks, on such an occasion, would have had an oration; our custom required something
               in verse. The circumstances and the subject therefore led me to compose an oration in verse, to which the running strain of
               thanksgiving gives the unity which is required in a poem. I am at work upon an epithalamium for <ref type="m" target="people.html#WalesCharlottePrincess">the Princess&#8217;s</ref> marriage, which in its moral tone may redeem that class of compositions
               from their merited contempt.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince
                     Regent&#8217;s</ref> only child Charlotte, had been engaged since December 1813 to the Hereditary Prince of Orange, William (1792&#8211;1849;
                  King of the Netherlands 1840&#8211;1849), the husband selected for her by her father and his advisers. As Poet Laureate, Southey was
                  required to write on the occasion. He started the required poem (<title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen Nuptiale</title>) but in the
                  event it was not needed as the engagement was broken off in June 1814. The <title>Lay</title> was recycled in 1816 to celebrate
                  Charlotte&#8217;s marriage to Leopold of Saxe-Coburg (1790&#8211;1865; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I see by the <title>Evangelical Magazine</title> that a Cornish minister is about to travel from Bayonne to Lisbon,
               distributing Bibles and Testaments and tracts as he goes.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The minister was a Mr Smith of Penryn
                  (dates unknown). The <title>Evangelical Magazine</title>, 22 (February 1814), 155, asked readers to donate money and to pray for the
                  success of his endeavours: &#8216;Here new channels of benevolence may be opened; and if the smiles of Heaven descend on the undertaking,
                  Bigotry may receive a more fatal wound&#8217;.</note> Indeed, this is very rash, and dreadfully ill timed. The partisans of the
               Inquisition in Spain have by no means given up the hope of recovering the ground which they have lost. In Portugal, on the other hand,
               those persons who know the evil which that devilish institution has brought upon their country, are endeavouring silently to destroy
               its power. I know of nothing which would tend so materially to defeat the efforts of the good in one country, and to assist the
               persecuting party in the other, as the appearance of this heretical missionary. He himself may be thrown into prison (which no doubt he
               would cheerfully encounter) &#8211; this is a light evil; but he may bring his own country into most unpleasant difficulties with the Spanish
               Government; and I am perfectly sure that he must impede the good work which he is desirous of accelerating. God knows, there never was
               a man who felt a more rooted abhorrence than I do for the abominations of Popery, or who longs more earnestly to see the Bible brought
               into action against them. But this mode of proceeding is madness. The only way to get the Bible into use there is through the agency of
               persons of their own religion and their own country. There are some priests who are really pious enough to do it. An Englishman settled
               in Spain might have an edition of the licensed Spanish Bible printed there, and distribute it through such persons. There is no other
               way in which we could interfere safely, and even this might involve him in some difficulties. If you should ever, as you talked of,
               embark in a Magazine, let it be a part of your plan to collect for the missionary societies as much previous information as can be
               found to direct their future or assist their present establishments. At this time, a paper upon the state of religion in the Peninsula,
               written with proper knowledge of the subject, might perhaps prevent this very injurious and mischievous experiment.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>