<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1870</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3141</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS
                        11.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 299&#8211;301 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1870" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1870" type="letter">
        <head>1870. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1811-02-12">12
                        February 1811</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ South Parade/ Bath<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS
                        11<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 299&#8211;301 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1811-02-12">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 12. 1811.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am not disappointed in Count Julian,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Count Julian: A Tragedy</title> (1812).</note> &#8211; it is too Greek for representation in these times, but it is
                    altogether worthy of you. The thought &amp; feeling which you have frequently condensed in a single line is unlike any thing in
                    modern composition. The conclusion too is Greek. I should have known this play to be yours had it fallen in my way without a name.
                    There was one written ten years ago<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rough&#8217;s <title>The Conspiracy of Gowrie</title>,
                        published anonymously in 1800.</note> by <ref target="people.html#RoughWilliam">Rough</ref> which <hi rend="ital">aimed</hi>
                    at being what this <hi rend="ital">is</hi>; &#8211; this has the profundity which was attempted there. I see nothing to be expunged, but
                    I see <del>in</del> many <del>places</del> &lt;of&gt; what a school boy would call <hi rend="ital">hard</hi> passages. Sometimes
                    they are like water which however beautifully pellucid may become dark by its very depth, &#8211; your own vase of burnished gold is a
                    better illustration, &#8211; the very richness of the metal occasions its darkness. Sometimes they are like pictures, unless you get
                    them in precisely the right point of view, their expression is lost. I cannot tell how this is to be remedied, if it is
                    remediable: it is what makes the difference between difficult &amp; easy authors. &#8211; I will not yet specify what the passages are
                    which are obscure, because upon every fresh perusal, some of them will flash upon me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Never was a character more finely conceived than Julian, &#8211; that image of his seizing the horses is in the very
                    first rank of sublimity, &#8211; it is the grandest image <del>I ever</del> &lt;of power&gt; that ever poet produced.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You could not have placed the story in a finer dramatic light, &#8211; but it has made you elevate some vile renegados
                    into respectability. In my plan Sisabert<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A character in <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814). In legend he was the son of King Witiza (c. 687&#8211;710; King of the Visigoths 694&#8211;710) and sided with
                        the Moors when they invaded Spain. Southey did not carry out his intention for Sisibert&#8217;s death.</note> will die by Florindas
                    hand, for attempting to imitate Rodrigo,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. to attempt to rape Florinda.</note> before
                    the battle of Covadonga,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pelayo&#8217;s (681&#8211;737) victory over the Moors at the battle of
                        Covadonga in 722. It is now regarded as the beginning of the Reconquista.</note> &amp; Opas<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Oppas (d. after 712), allegedly Bishop of Toledo; the model for Orpas in Southey&#8217;s <title>Roderick</title>. In
                        Book 25, lines 95&#8211;109, Roderick&#8217;s horse tramples Orpas to death.</note> will be cut down by Rodrigos own hand. I go on very
                    slowly &#8211; what I have done is too good to be sacrificed, but it will make the poem as faulty in structure as Shakespere J
                        C&#230;sar,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Tragedy of Julius Caesar</title> (c. 1599).</note> &#8211; &amp; I shall be a third of the way thro it before Pelayo
                    appears. &#8211; My pace will soon be quickened, <del>for</del> the way opens before me, hitherto there has been but one personage in
                    view, tomorrow I introduce <del>another</del> &lt;others&gt;, &amp; shall soon get into the business of the poem. &#8211; You wonder
                    that I can think of two poems at once, &#8211; it proceeds from weakness &#8211; not from strength. I could not stand the continuous
                    excitement which you have gone thro in your tragedy &#8211; in me it would not work itself off in tears, &#8211; the tears would flow while in
                    the act of composition, &amp; they would leave behind a throbbing head, &amp; a whole system in the highest state of nervous
                    excitability, which would soon induce disease in one of its most fearful forms. From such a state I recovered in 1800 by going to
                    Portugal, &amp; suddenly &lt;changing&gt; climate, occupation &amp; all external objects, &amp; I have kept it off since by a good
                        <del>xxxx</del> intellectual regimen.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When I have read Pelayo<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early incarnation of <title>Roderick, the Last
                            of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> again &amp; again I will then make out a list of the passages which appear so
                    difficult that ordinary readers may be supposed <del>not to</del> incapable of understanding them. When you perceive that they may
                    be difficult to others it will be easy, in most instances, to make the meaning more obvious. Then you must print the Tragedy. It
                    will not have many more admirers than Gebir,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Gebir</title> (1798), which Southey had admired since its publication.</note> but they will be of the same class &amp;
                    cast, &amp; with Gebir it will be known hereafter, when all the rubbish of our generation shall have been swept away.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What will you do next? I <del>do not</del> cannot reconcile myself to the abandonment of the Phoc&#230;ans, &#8211; the
                    fragments of which are so masterly.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor&#8217;s epic &#8216;The Phocaeans&#8217;, two fragments had
                        appeared in <title>Poetry, by the Author of Gebir</title> (London, 1802). The poem told the story of the inhabitants of a
                        Greek city in Asia Minor, who, faced with a Persian invasion, sailed westward, taking refuge initially in Spain, then Corsica
                        and Italy, before settling in southern France where they triumphed over the natives and established their society. Modelled on
                        the <title>Aeneid</title>, Landor&#8217;s poem also had similarities to Southey&#8217;s own attempt at a foundation epic,
                            <title>Madoc</title> (1805). &#8216;The Phocaeans&#8217; was never finished.</note> &#8211; Narrative is better than dramatic poetry,
                    because it admits of the highest beauties of the drama; &#8211; there are two characters in Roman history which are admirably fit for
                    either, but in both cases their history suits the drama better than the epic, &#8211; Sertorius<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The Roman general and statesman Quintus Sertorius (c. 126&#8211;73 BC), who established an independent state in the Iberian
                        peninsular in 83&#8211;73 BC.</note> &amp; Spartacus.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Spartacus (c. 109&#8211;71 BC), leader of
                        slaves in the Third Servile War.</note> When I was a boy the abortive attempt at restoring the republic by Caligulas
                        death<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Roman emperor Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus Germanicus (AD 12&#8211;41). His
                        assassins attempted &#8211; but failed &#8211; to restore the republic. Instead, Caligula&#8217;s uncle Claudius (10 BC&#8211;AD 54) was declared
                        emperor by the Praetorian Guard.</note> was one of my dramatic attempts. Another was that impressive story in Tacitus of 300
                    slaves (I think this was the number) put to death for not preventing the murder of their master, whom one of them <del>xxxx for
                        xxxxx xxxxxxxx death</del> had killed.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Publius Cornelius Tacitus (AD 56&#8211;117),
                            <title>Annals</title>, 14: 42&#8211;45. In AD 61 the prefect of the city of Rome, Pedanius Secundus, had been murdered by one of
                        his slaves. As a punishment, his entire household of 400 slaves was executed; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 26
                        &#8211;[c. 29] April 1794, <title>Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part One</title>, Letter 88.</note> The Emperor Majorian is a
                    fine character.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Iulius Valerius Maiorianus (c. 420&#8211;461), ruler of the Western Roman
                        empire from 457 to his death. He was the last effective Roman Emperor in the west and re-conquered Spain.</note>
          <del>B</del> I wish I could throw out a subject that would tempt you, &#8211; but rather to a poem than a play, for tho your powers for
                    both are equal, &amp; the play the more difficult work of the two, yet in my judgement the poem is the <del>higher kind</del>
                    preferable species of composition.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>