<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		
		<fileDesc>
			
			<titleStmt>
				<!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
				<title level="a">Teaching Romantic Drama: Production and Performance of the <title level="m">Haunted Tower</title></title>
				
				
				<author role="primary">
					<name>Frederick Burwick</name>
				</author>
				
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				
				<respStmt>
					<resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
					<name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
				</respStmt>
				
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Director</resp>
					<name>Thora Brylowe</name>
				</respStmt>
				
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
					<name>Orrin N.C. Wang</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
					<name>Jessica Tebo</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
					<name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			
			<editionStmt>
				<!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
				<edition>YYYY-MM-DD</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado
					Boulder</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
				<availability status="free">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
						or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
						purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
						use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
						are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
						with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
						permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
						requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/ editor(s) and
						advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization
						should be forwarded to Romantic Circles: <address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
							<addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
						</address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
						conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
						them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
						have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
						Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
						continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
						a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
						use.</p>
				</availability>
				<!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
				<idno type="edition"
					>praxis.2011.theatre.burwick</idno>
				<idno type="resource"
					>theatre</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
						<title level="a" type="main">Teaching Romantic Drama: Production and Performance of the <title level="m">Haunted Tower</title>
						</title>
						<author role="secondary">
							<persName>
								<forename>Frederick</forename>
								<surname>Burwick</surname>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
						<ptr
							target="praxis/theatre/praxis.2011.theatre.burwick"/>
						<!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
					</analytic>
					
					
					<monogr>
						<title level="m"
							>Teaching Romantic Drama</title>
						<title level="s">Praxis</title>
						
						<imprint>
							<publisher> Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University
								of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
							<pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
							<!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
							<date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					
					
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " to &#8220; or
						&#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed except in the case of
						diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
						keyboard</p>
					<p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
					<p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
						such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
						been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
					12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E"
					xml:id="g">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
						20014-02-27</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E"
					xml:id="dcType">
					<bibl>NINES categories for document type at
						http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on
						2014-02-27</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E"
					xml:id="d">
					<bibl>NINES categories for discplines at
						http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on
						2014-02-27</bibl>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
				<catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
				<catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
				<!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
				<keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
					<term subtype="tags"/>
					<term subtype="tags"/>
					<term subtype="tags"/>
					<term subtype="tags"/>
					<term subtype="tags"/>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
				<name><!-- coder --></name>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding the text</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<!--END OF HEADER-->
	<!-- The Following is primarily relevant to Praxis volumes, but can be adapted for Editions -->


	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">
				<head>
					<title level="a">Teaching Romantic Drama: Production and Performance of <title level="m">The Haunted Tower</title></title>
				</head>
				<byline>
					<docAuthor>
						<name ref="BurwickFrederick">Frederick Burwick</name>
					</docAuthor>
					<affiliation>Professor Emeritus, University of California Los Angeles</affiliation>
				</byline>

				<ab>Audio files for <title level="m">The Haunted Tower</title> can be found <ref target="http://www.sjsu.edu/faculty/douglass/music/album-haunted.html">here</ref>.</ab>
				<p>Even after directing a dozen full productions of the plays of the Romantic period,<note place="foot" resp="editors">
						Thomas Morton, <title level="m">Speed the Plough</title>, Grasmere, England, August 11, 2000; Elizabeth Inchbald, <title level="m">To Marry or Not to Marry</title>, 
					Grasmere, England, August 10, 2001; Christian Dietrich Grabbe, <title level="m">Jest, Satire, Irony, and
							Deeper Meaning</title>, Northwest Campus Auditorium, UCLA, March 1, 2; 3; Balch Auditorium, Scripps College, March 5,
						2002; Joanna Baillie, <title level="m">The Tryal</title>, Grasmere, England, August 9, 2002;Thomas Lovell Beddoes, <title level="m">Death’s Jest Book</title>,
						Northwest Campus Auditorium, UCLA, Feb. 28, March 1, 2; Balch Auditorium, Scripps College, March 6; Lincoln Center, Fordham
						University, August 2; Grasmere, England,
						August 22, 2003; Elizabeth Inchbald, <title level="m">Animal
							Magnetism</title>, Balch Auditorium, Scripps College, March 4; Northwest Campus Auditorium, UCLA, March 5, 6, 7; CSU Long
						Beach; Grasmere, England, August 13, 2004;
							Hannah Cowley, <title level="m">A Bold Stroke for a Husband</title>,
						Northwest Campus Auditorium, UCLA, March 4, 5, 6; University Theater, CSU Long Beach, March 10; Chapman University, March 12;
							Grasmere, England, August 12, 2005; Marquis de Sade, <title level="m">The Haunted Tower</title> (<title level="m">La
							Tour enchantée</title>), Northwest Campus Auditorium, UCLA, March 3, 4, 5; University Theater, CSU Long Beach, March 9;
							Grasmere, England, August 11, 2006; Thomas Moore, <title level="m">The Gipsy Prince</title>, Balch Auditorium, Scripps
						College, June 20, 2009.</note> I continue to alter my teaching of production and performance with each new play. One reason
					for change is that each play brings its own peculiar set of demands on the cast. Another reason for change is that each new cast
					brings a different set of talents to be developed. A third factor is my own evolving attention to the characteristics of period
						acting.<note place="foot" resp="editors">
						Frederick Burwick, “Ideal Shattered: Sarah Siddons, Madness, and the Dynamics of Gesture,” in <title level="m">Notorious Muse: The Actress in British
							Art and Culture 1776-1812</title>, ed. Robyn Asleson (Yale UP,
						2003), pp. 129-50; and Burwick, “Telling Lies with Body Language,” <title
							level="m">Spheres of Action: The Concept of Performance</title>
						<title level="m">in Romantic Thought</title>, ed. Alex J. Dick and Angela Esterhammer (U of Toronto P, 2008).</note>
				</p>
				<p>As an introduction to the drama of 1780-1830, with emphasis on production and performance, English 97H: <emph>Romantic Drama.
					Production and Performance</emph>, includes practice in acting styles of the period (gesture, elocution, delivery), historical theater
					construction, period costumes, and stage design. Although a large number of theater majors, music majors, and English majors turn
					out, auditions are open to all students. They are asked to prepare a monologue, a song, and to provide a “cold” reading of a
					dramatic passage. In selecting the play to be performed each year, the primary concerns are to find a play that will challenge
					student abilities, that will be accessible to our audiences, that will be rich in historical relevance, and that will depict the
					temper and tastes of the period. Because the theater of the period is musical theater, there is also the difficulty of securing a
					musical score. Many productions relied on interpolated songs, and even where full scores exist, those score were often altered
					with changes in the cast from one season to the next. Obviously the music, then as now, had to suit the abilities of the cast.</p>
				<p>As offered during the Winter Quarter (January through March) 2006, the course actually began with enrollment/auditions at the
					end of November in the preceding term. The course description was also the call to auditions.<note place="foot"
						resp="editors"> English 97H. Romantic Drama. Production and Performance. Marquis de
							Sade. <lb/> (by permission of instructor only; auditions to be held in Southbay Room, Covel Common, 7-10 p.m. Nov.
						21 and 22): Introduction to the drama of 1780-1830, with emphasis on production and performance, including practice in acting
						styles of the period (gesture, elocution, delivery), historical theater construction, period costumes, and stage design.
						Because the course aims at performance and production, eight weeks will be spent in mastering the play, rehearsing, preparing
						costumes, set, and props, followed by two weeks to perform (four performances on the UCLA campus, followed by invitational
						performances at nearby campuses). The play selected for Winter Quarter, 2006, was the Marquis de Sade’s 
						<title level="m">La Tour enchantée</title> (1788; revised 1810), adapted as <title level="m">The
							Haunted Tower</title> (1789) by James Cobb, with a musical score by Stephen Storace.</note> Casting and stage crew assignments were completed the
					following week,<note place="foot" resp="editors">
						<hi>DRAMATIS PERSONÆ</hi>
						<list>
							<item>Lord William, disguised as Palamede — Erik Finck</item>
							<item>Edmund, Baron of Oakland, usurper — Greg Cragg
							</item>
							<item>De Courcy, brother to Lady Elinor — Charles Maas
							</item>
							<item>Edward, son of false Baron — Brian Hayden
							</item>
							<item>Grouffing, collector of taxes — Danny Cowan
							</item>
							<item>Hugo, old servant of Oakland Castle — A. J. Rodriguez
							</item>
							<item>Lewis, servant to Lady Elinor — Robby Nadler
							</item>
							<item>Robert, servant of Oakland Castle — Amy Cox
							</item>
							<item>Charles, servant to De Courcy — Debbie Fry</item>
							<item>Lady Elinor, in love with Lorville — Kristin Crawford</item>
							<item>Adela, in love with Edward — Schuyler Hudak</item>
							<item>Cicely, maid to Lady Elinor — Lauren Cheak
							</item>
							<item>Martina, village girl, sister to Maud — Melanie Wong</item>
							<item>Maud, village girl, sister to Martina — Tammy Wang
							</item>
							<item>Fishermen, Servants, Huntsmen, Cooks, Soldiers — <lb/>
								Sean Berquist<lb/>
								Yvette Holzwarth
								<lb/>
								Nathalie Walker<lb/>
								Kelsey Ramos</item>
							<item>Musicians:<lb/>
								Jong-Ling Wu (keyboard, flute)<lb/>
								Marjorie Burns (keyboard)<lb/>
								Stephanie Cash (clarinet)<lb/>
								Audrey Van Norman (cello)<lb/>
								Trevor Pratt (violin) </item>
							<item>Vocal Director: Stephen Pu
							</item>
							<item>Production Manager: Vicki Leung
							</item>
							<item>Stage Manager: Dean Leng </item>
							<item>Lighting: Justyna Maslowska</item>
							<item>Costuming: Megan Correnti<lb/>
								Mary Huang<lb/>
								Sarah Densmore</item>
							<item>Set Design: Jenna Murphy</item>
						</list>
					</note> so that all participants had the play script and musical score over the December holidays. Rehearsals commenced
					immediately with beginning of the winter term, 7 to 10 p.m. Tuesdays and Thursdays 1<hi rendition="#sup">st</hi> through 8<hi
						rendition="#sup">th</hi> week, with additional vocal rehearsals on Wednesday evenings. Because the course aims at performance
					and production, the first eight weeks (of the ten-week quarter term) are spent in mastering the play, rehearsing, preparing
					costumes, set, and props, followed by two weeks to perform. Performances were scheduled at the end of the 8<hi rendition="#sup"
						>th</hi> week: UCLA, March 3, 4, matinee and evening of March 5; Cal State Long Beach, March 9.</p>
				<p>The selection of the play to be performed each year is usually made during the preceding summer, when I have the opportunity
					to browse through the archives of the Theatre Museum in Covent Garden, London. During the summer of 2005 I came across <title level="m">The Haunted Tower, a Comic
						Opera</title>, with the compete musical score by Stephen Storace (1763-1796))
					and the libretto by James Cobb (1756-1818). Opening at Drury Lane November 24, 1789, this comic opera was a significant success, with
					eighty-four performances in its first two seasons, many more throughout the 1790s, and frequent revivals for the next half
						century.<note place="foot" resp="editors">
						Genest, <title level="m">The English Stage</title>, 6:586-88.</note> For the
					purpose of this essay, it seemed useful to highlight a single production, so that a coherent set of examples could be provided for
					all aspects of our efforts in a single term.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> For their usefulness in teaching Romantic
						Drama, I am especially indebted to three essays by Marjean Purinton: “On
						Teaching <title level="m">A Bold Stroke for a Husband</title> and Other Comedies by Romantic Women Playwrights,” <title
							level="j">European Romantic Review</title> 17.3 (July 2006): 351-60; “Romantic Praxis: Teaching British Romanticism with
						Drama.”  <title level="m">Engaged Romanticism</title>.  Ed. Mark Lussier and Bruce Matsunaga (Newcastle: Cambridge Scholars Press, 2008), 228-41; “Teaching
						Orientalism through British Romantic Drama: Representations of Arabia,” <title level="m">Romantic Border Crossings</title>. 
						Ed. Jeffrey Cass and Larry Peer
						(Aldershot: Ashgate, 2008), 135-146.</note>
					<title level="m">The Haunted Tower</title> provides an excellent example because of its particularly rich fabric of historical,
					social, theatrical, and musical issues. Having in previous years directed Elizabeth
						Inchbald’s <title level="m">Animal Magnetism</title> and Hannah Cowley’s
						<title level="m">A Bold Stroke for a Husband</title>, I was ready to prompt students to give special attention to disguise and
					role-playing as a dramatic means of exposing prejudicial assumptions about gender, class, and national character. <title level="m"
						>The Haunted Tower</title> proved a good choice both pedagogically and dramatically, providing insight into social issues,
					political tensions, national and international turmoil. The representation of English-French relations on the very eve of the
					Revolution would, in itself, amply justify the focus on <title level="m">The Haunted Tower</title>. The fact that it is also a
					play adapted from the French of the Marquis de Sade for performance on the English
					stage gives it an added dimension of political complexity.</p>
				<div type="section">
					<head>Discovering Storace and Cobb</head>

					<p>Storace and Cobb began their
						collaboration with a translation of <title level="m">The Doctor and the Apothecary</title>, which opened at Drury Lane on October 25, 1788.
						This production closely followed the Viennese
						original, <title level="m">Doktor und Apotheker</title> (1786), with a score by Carl Ditters von Dittersdorf (1739-1799) 
						and libretto by Gottlieb Stephanie (1741-1800). After the great success of <title level="m"
							>The Haunted Tower</title>, Cobb and Storace continued their collaboration with another comic opera, <title level="m">The Siege of Belgrade</title>,
						first performed on January 1, 1791; <title level="m">The Pirates</title>, performed at the King’s Theatre on November 21, 1792; 
						and <title level="m">The Cherokee</title>,
						performed December 20, 1794. In addition to his collaboration with Cobb, Storace also wrote the score for <title level="m">No Song No Supper</title>, an
						opera in two acts by Prince Hoare (1755-1834), performed at Drury Lane
						April 16, 1790. For Hoare’s libretto Storace introduced some of the music that
						he had written in Venice of his opera, <title level="m">Gli equivoci</title> (December 27, 1786), based on Shakespeare’s
							<title level="m">Comedy of Errors</title>. The music forGeorge Colman’s
							<title level="m">The Iron Chest</title> (March 12, 1796) was also composed by Storace.</p>
					<p> Although I was excited about working with a musical score that included 29 songs, with overture and finale, I also
						recognized that the music would be a challenge vocally to a student cast. 
						The success was due to the Vocal Director, Stephen Pu, graduate student in Musicology at UCLA. In an attempt to trace the origin
						of the plot, and hoping to find hints on performance, I turned to Michael Kelly’s
							<title level="m">Reminiscences</title> (1826). Kelly performed with the
						Storaces in Vienna and returned with them to London in March, 1787. Kelly made regular trips to Paris in search of material for the London stage.
						At the Comédie-Italienne in Paris, 1790, Kelly saw <title level="m">Raoul Barbe-Bleue</title>, a comic opera by Ernest Modeste Grétry (1741–1813), 
						with libretto by Michel-Jean Sedaine (1719-1797). Kelly not only persuaded George Colman to write an English adaptation,
							Kelly himself composed the musical score. <title level="m">Blue-Beard; or,
							Female Curiosity</title> opened at Drury Lane on January 16, 1798.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section">
					<head>Cobb's Adaptation of Sade</head>

					<p>When Kelly made the trip to Paris in
						1788, he returned with a work entitled, <title level="m">La tour enchantée, un opéra-comique</title>. In searching for the
						author of this French work, I discovered that it was none other than the infamous Marquis de Sade, who had sent it, along with several other plays,
						to theaters in Paris in late summer, 1788.<note place="foot" resp="editors">
							<title level="m">La tour enchantée, un opéra-comique</title>, as described in the Marquis de Sade’s 
							<title level="m">Catalogue raisonné</title> (October 1, 1788), was the concluding episode to
							a sequence of six plays entitled <title level="m">L’union des arts.</title> On February 27, 1791, Monsieur Framery, agent
							for playwrights, informed Sade that several of the plays had been accepted
							for performance. They remained unstaged, but <title level="m">La tour enchantée, un opéra-comique</title> made its way
							from Paris to London. </note> This discovery
						was not mine. John and Ben
							Franceschina provide a comparison of the French and English versions in the introduction to their translation,
							<title level="m">The Plays of the Marquis de Sade,</title> 3 vols. (2000).
						Serendipitously, I also discovered that UCLA’s Clark Library possessed a manuscript of Sade’s 
						<title level="m">La tour enchantée</title> and that the manuscript of Cobb’s libretto was in the Larpent Collection at the nearby Huntington Library.</p>
					<p>During the Fall term I set to work with the necessary adaptations. First, I turned to Brian Holmes (San Jose State University) 
						to adapt the musical score for performance
						by a chamber ensemble (violin, viola, flute, keyboard) rather than a full orchestra. Brian also provided an additional song
						for a scene that had been omitted by Cobb (“My love is not a problem” II.vi). This
						song is sung by a tax collector, whom two young ladies are trying to persuade to enter the Haunted Tower (“Attune the pipe”
						II.vi). The first week began with discussion of plot, character, and acting styles, and many improvisation exercises in period
						acting accompanied scene by scene blocking of the play. For the first several weeks vocal rehearsals were held separate from
						acting rehearsals, but because this production is so extensively musical, the two had to be integrated by the fourth week.
						Additional time was required for vocal rehearsals right up to the time of performance at the end of the eighth week. For our
						final dress/tech on Thursday, March 1, we had the benefit of an exclusive audience of specialists: Catherine Burroughs (Wells College), Jeff
							Cox (Colorado), and Jane Moody (York), who provided a useful critique
						following the performance.</p>
					<p>The great advantage of utilizing performance and production in teaching Romantic Drama is that the students learn the
						material literally from the inside out. They gain an understanding of the language, the acting, and the music that mere
						reading cannot provide. With this particular play, the students were made aware of gender issues, as well as national tensions
						(French vs. English) and social tensions (aristocracy vs. lower classes) that prevailed during the period. As the only work of
						the Marquis de Sade to be performed on the London stage during his own lifetime,
							<title level="m">The Haunted Tower</title> also gave students insight into the international reach of the drama of the
						period.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section">
					<head><title level="m">The Haunted Tower</title> and its Historical Context</head>

					<p>The task of rendering <title level="m">La tour enchantée</title> palatable to an English audience was far more
						complicated than simply excising Sade’s comments about the English. Cobb had to tell the
						story from an English rather than a French perspective. He was
						greatly assisted in this task by Storace, who provided several set pieces to
						reinforce a sense of British tradition: an opening chorus “To Albion’s Genius” (I.i), a hunting song, “Hark! The sweet horn”
						(I.iii), a chorus to the “Roast Beef of Old England”(II.vii), and a drinking song
						praising English ale, “And now we're met, a jolly set” (III.iv).<note place="foot" resp="editors"> The songs for this
							production are available at “Romantic-Era Songs: A Site Devoted to Theater and Popular Songs,” <ref
								target="http://www.sjsu.edu/faculty/douglass/music/index.html"
								>http://www.sjsu.edu/faculty/douglass/music/index.html</ref>
							<lb/> For account of past productions, with images and musical excerpts, see the site prepared by Laura Mandell (Miami
							University, OH): <ref
								target="http://www.units.muohio.edu/visualrhetoric/rc/burwick.html">
								<hi>http://www.units.muohio.edu/visualrhetoric/rc/burwick.html</hi>
							</ref>
						</note> Further, Cobb’s version, with its marriage between Lady Elinor de Courcy and
						Lord William, restored to his estate as the true Baron of Oakland, reestablishes harmony between France and England. The division between the
						aristocracy and the common folk is not overcome, but the virtues and advantages of the commoners are repeatedly affirmed.
						Indeed, the significant contribution of the subplot, the love of Edward and Adela, was to emphasize the sincerity and
						integrity of the lower classes. Michael Kelly declares that the subplot “was
						taken from an Italian intermezzo opera,” and it was clear that Stephen Storace
						intended the role of Adela as a showcase for his sister Anna Storace’s
						accomplishments, “both as a singer and an actress.” Kelly describes his own solos
						as Lord William, “From hope's fond dream” (I.i) and “Spirit of my sainted Sire” (III.iv), as “fine songs,” but notes that the
						latter was “one of the most difficult songs ever composed for the tenor voice.”<note place="foot" resp="editors">
							<title level="m">Reminiscences of Michael Kelly, of the King's Theatre, and Theatre royal Drury Lane, including a period of nearly 
								half a century; with original anecdotes of many distinguished
								persons, political, literary, and musical</title>. Written by Theodore
								Edward Hook, from materials furnished by Michael Kelly. 2 vols.
							(London, H. Colburn, 1826), 1:318-20.</note>
					</p>
					<p>Revolutionary themes are incorporated but controverted: the corrupt aristocracy is overthrown, but the usurping Baron
						was only a fake aristocrat. The class hierarchy is topsy-turvy. In his endeavor to fulfill his father’s expectations as heir
						to the Baron’s estate, “plain Edward the ploughman” introduces his beloved Adela, a cottager, into court disguised as Lady
						Elinor. Meanwhile, to avoid the unwanted marriage, Lady Elinor pretends to be her own maid-in-waiting and Lord William passes
						himself off as a court jester. As jester, Lord William mocks the false Baron, who can only pretend to sexual attraction and
						prowess, but is still rich enough to pay for flattery and other services: </p>
					<quote>
						<lg>
							<l>Whate'er your faults, in person, mind,</l>
							<l>(However gross) you chance to find,</l>
							<l>Yet why should you despair?</l>
							<l>Of flattery you must buy advice,</l>
							<l>You're rich enough to pay the price,</l>
							<l>So that removes your care.</l>
							<lb/>
							<l>(“Tho’ time has from your lordship’s face” II.ii).</l>
						</lg>
					</quote>
					<p>Several songs express the honesty and freedom of the lower class. Cicely, for example, sings of her freedom “From high birth
						and all its fetters” which allows her, in contrast to Lady Elinor who is bound in an arranged marriage, to choose the “youth I
						love” (III.iii). Edward and Adela ridicule aristocratic pretensions in their duet, “Will great lords and ladies” (I.iii). The
						conflict between upper and lower class is given full expression in the sestetto, “Alas! behold the silly maid” (II.iv), and
						more directly in the cat-fight duet with Adela and Lady Elinor, “Begone! I discharge you!” (III.iii).</p>
					<p>As John and Ben
							Franceschina argue in the head note to their translation, a more persistent evidence of Cobb’s reliance on his source is “in the lyrics 
							and situations of several songs that
						seem to serve parallel functions in both shows.”<note place="foot" resp="editors">
							Sade, <title level="m">The Plays of the Marquis de Sade.</title> Trans. and ed. John and Ben Franceschina.
							3:4. “For example, Juliette’s opening air, 'Love, listen to my sorrow' evokes Adela’s 'Whither, my love!' (I.iii) in Cobb’s libretto. 
							Both pieces depict long-suffering heroines yearning to be
							reunited to their long-lost lovers in lyrics that evoke images of bondage, lovers’ tokens, and an obsession with the
							lover’s image. Lorville’s lament recalling his leaving his lover behind, 'Oh! Juliette' is echoed in Cobb’s libretto with
							Charles’s 'My native land I bade adieu' (I.iv), in which the
							noble servant character philosophizes about the girl he left behind. In both airs, the characters singing imagine that the
							intensity of emotion has changed on the part of the women involved. In the English work, Charles accepts the situation
							with wry humor; in the French, Lorville responds melodramatically in images of bondage and death.” </note> Indeed, <title
							level="m">La tour enchantée</title> provides prime evidence of Sade’s skill
						as lyricist, and Cobb followed Sade’s
						lead in his English adaptation. It was also to Cobb’s great advantage that he had
						the collaboration of Stephen Storace, whose score has been judged “the most
						successful full-length opera that Drury Lane staged in the entire century.”<note
							place="foot" resp="editors">Roger Fiske, <title level="m">English Theatre Music in the Eighteenth Century</title>
							(Oxford UP, 1986), p. 501; cited in <title level="m">The Plays of the Marquis de
									Sade</title>, p. 3</note>
					</p>
					<p>Sade’s setting was contemporary. Cobb changed the setting back to the time of William the Conqueror. In adapting <title level="m">The Haunted
							Tower</title>, I brought the time forward again to the reign of George III in order to make the references to the French
						Revolution more evident. Among other changes, I restored the opening dialogue between Juliette and Louise (Lady Elinor and
						Cicely), which provides at the very beginning of the play the explanation of the haunting. I also restored the scene in which
						an attempt is made to persuade Grouffignac, the tax collector, to enter the haunted tower. Here I made the further change of
						giving the task of seducing the tax collector to two village girls rather than to Juliette and Louise. </p>
					<p>Much of the humor of the play derives from differences in manner and speech between French and English, and between
						upper and lower classes. These differences are compounded by the many role reversals. Having fled as a young boy to France, 
						the exiled Lord William has survived as the Frenchman Sir Palamede, is concealed
						in the De Courcy estate dressed as a girl by Cicely, and presented at the English court as a Jester. In his role as the
						usurping Baron, Edmund the ploughman is boorishly clumsy in affecting grand airs, and obnoxious in his presumption of sexual
						liberties. To marry her beloved Edward, Adela must disguise herself as Lady Elinor, and Lady Elinor, to avoid marriage to
						Edward, pretends to be her own maid-in-waiting.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section">
					<head>Period Acting and Gesture</head>

					<p>Practice in physical expression, “carriage and deportment,” were a part of the improvisational warm-up exercises at the
						beginning of each class. A major source on body language in the period is Johann
							Jacob Engel’s <title level="m">Ideen zu einer Mimik</title> (1785). “Adapted to the English Drama” by Henry Siddons in 
						<title level="m">Practical Illustrations of Rhetorical Gesture
							and Action</title> (1807; 2nd ed. 1822). Siddons retained Engel’s emphasis on “natural” gestures and augmented his commentary with
						cross-references to the English stage, with numerous examples drawn from the acting of John Philip Kemble and Sarah
							Siddons.<note place="foot" resp="editors">
							Johann Jacob Engel (1741-1802) based his observations in his <title
								level="m">Ideen zu einer Mimik</title> (2 vols. Berlin, 1785/86; rpt. Hildesheim, 1968) primarily on the performances
							of Friedrich Ludwig Schröder and August Wilhelm Iffland. Engel, contemporary with Lessing, Mendelssohn, Goethe, and Schiller, 
							was a recognized critic of the drama.
							Following his work, <title level="m">Über Handlung, Gespräch und Erzählung</title> (<title level="m">On Plot, Dialogue,
								and Narrative</title>; 1774), his study of gesture was recognized as the major work on mimic, mimetic, and mimismetic
							expression. See: Doris Bachmann-Medick, <title level="m">Die ästhetische Ordnung des Handelns. Moralphilosophie und
								ästhetik in der Populärphilosophie des 18. Jahrhunderts</title> (Stuttgart: Metzler, 1989), pp. 78-137.</note>
						Anecdotal, yet with many well-delineated examples of the mannerisms of individual performers, 
						Michael Kelly’s <title level="m">Reminiscences</title> (1826) provides useful
						insights into character acting.<note place="foot" resp="editors">
							Kelly, <title level="m">Reminiscences</title>; see note 8 above.</note> Many
						of the illustrations for the Boydell Shakespeare Gallery document stage gesture and movement,<note place="foot" 
							resp="editors">
							<title level="m">The Boydell Shakespeare Gallery</title>, ed. Frederick
								Burwick and Walter Pape (Bottrop: Peter Pomp, 1996).</note> and the Kemble Promptbooks give detailed information
						on blocking.<note place="foot" resp="editors">
							<title level="m">John Philip Kemble’s Promptbooks of Plays by Shakespeare, and others, published between 1799-1811</title>, 11 vols., ed.
								Charles H. Shattuck. Charlottesville: Published for the Folger
							Shakespeare Library by the University Press of Virginia, 1974. </note>
					</p>

					<p>Typical improvisational exercises involved creating scenarios for selected poses among the sixty-nine plates from Engel/Siddons: Suspicion,
						Contempt, Pride, Phlegm, Hauteur, Doubt, Scorn, Astonishment, etc. In their initial reaction, students found the gestures
						highly stylized and artificial. The strangeness of period conventions, however, soon became familiar with practice. Typical of
						these exercises were the enactment Doubt and Apprehension in the manner of John
							Philip Kemble’s performance of Hamlet’s soliloquy: <lb/>
						<figure>
							<graphic width="400px" url="/prod/sites/default/files/imported/pedagogies/theatre/images/apprehension.jpg"/>
							<figDesc>Apprehension, Engel/Siddons Plate 10</figDesc>
						</figure></p>
						<p>Fig. 1 Apprehension, Engel/Siddons Plate 10</p>
						<p>The pace and the movement of arms are synchronized with the movement of the mind: now moving slowly, now irregular,
						now agitated and quick. “The moment that a difficulty presents itself, the play of the hands entirely ceases – the eye, which,
						as well as the head, had a gentle and placid motion, while the thought was easy, and unfolded itself without labour, [...] in
						this new situation looks straight forward, and the load falls on the heart, until, after the first shock of doubt [...]
						suspended activity resumes its former walk.” The pace, the tilt of head, the movement of the hands and arms, must undergo a
						transformation from agitation to control. As if he catches himself, he stops still, gathers composure, then delivers his
						soliloquy. Hamlet’s reflections bring him to a crux: “To die, to sleep;/ To sleep, perchance to dream” (III.i). Hamlet comes
						to a full halt, pauses a moment, then exclaims “ay, there’s the rub,” and at the same moment should give the exterior sign of
						that which his interior penetration alone has enabled him to discover.</p>
				</div>

				<div type="section">
					<head>Set Design, Costume, and Performance</head>

					<p>In spite of a strong commitment to recreating the conditions of Romantic performance, I make only a modest attempt to
						recreate stage designs and no attempt at all to imitate what was accomplished with traps, painted backdrops, wing-in-groove
						scenery, or the lamp lighting of the period.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> On stage design and mechanics, see:
							Ulf Küster, ed.<title level="m"> Theatrum Mundi, Die Welt als Bühne</title>
							(Munich: Minerva, 2003); on stage lighting, see: Terence Rees, <title level="m">Theatre Lighting in the Age of Gas</title>
							(London: The Society for Theatre Research, 1978); on special effects, see: Burwick, “Romantic Drama: from Optics to Illusion,” 
							<title level="m">Literature and Science: Theory and
								Practice</title>, ed.Stuart Peterfreund (Boston: Northeastern
							University Press, 1990), pp. 167-208.</note> Instead, I rely on conventional stage lighting, colored spots, and, as much as
						possible, single-set staging with a minimum use of larger props (tables, chairs). The set for <title level="m">The Haunted
							Tower</title>, designed and constructed under the supervision of Jenna Murphy and her crew of five students, was based on
						the title-page copper-plate engraving by Simkins depicting the original setting for <title level="m">The Haunted Tower</title>
						in 1790.<note place="foot" resp="editors">
							<title level="m">The Haunted Tower, a Comic Opera in Three Acts, as Performed at the Theatre Royal Drury Lane, the Music Selected, Adapted, &amp; 
								Composed by Stephen Storace</title> (London: Longman and Broderip, 1790).</note> As
						may be seen in the photographs below, the set was dominated by a 17-foot haunted tower, flanked by flats with two gnarled trees
						on one side, and an arcade of pillars on the other. The tower featured an up-stairs window, from which a light flickered as
						cued in the script.</p>
					<p n="18">Those who were involved in costume design had the complex task of gleaning from source books costumes suitable for
						period, nationality, class, and trade.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> Among the numerous reference books for
							historical costume, the two that we relied on for this production were: Jack
								Cassin-Scott, <title level="m">Costumes and settings for staging historical plays</title>, vol. 4
								<title level="m">The Georgian Period</title> (London: Batsford, 1979), and Auguste Racinet, 
							<title level="m">Le costume historique: Cinq cents planches, trois cents en couleurs,
								or et argent, deux cents en camaieu. Types principaux du vêtement et de la parure, rapprochées de ceux de l'intérieur
								de l'habitation dans tous les temps et chez tous les peuples, avec de nombreux détails sur le mobilier, les armes, les
								objets usuels, les moyens de transport, etc.</title> (Paris: Firmin-Didot, 1888). Vol. 1 is mainly explanatory text
							with an "Introduction générale"; Vols. 2-6, each with half-title only, are mainly plates accompanied by descriptive text;
							Vol.7 is index in pamphlet binder. We also consulted: Sharon Ann
								Burnston, <title level="m">Fitting &amp; proper: 18th century clothing from the collection of the Chester County
									Historical Society</title>, photography by George J.
								Fistrovich (Texarkana: Scurlock, 1998). </note> It was important that the usurping false Baron of Oakland be
						represented in character and costume as crudely flamboyant. His costume was exaggeratedly ostentatious:</p>
					<p>
					<figure>
							<graphic width="400px" url="/prod/sites/default/files/imported/pedagogies/theatre/images/baronoakland.jpg"/>
							<figDesc>Baron, Costume designed by Megan Correnti</figDesc>
						</figure> 
					</p>
					<p>Fig. 2 Baron, Costume designed by Megan Correnti</p>
						
						
						<p> By contrast, the French aristocrat De Courcy, brother to Lady Elinor, had to maintain a conservative dignity:</p>
					<p>
							<figure>
								<graphic width="400px" url="/prod/sites/default/files/imported/pedagogies/theatre/images/decourcy.jpg"/>
							<figDesc>De Courcy, Costume designed by Megan Correnti</figDesc>
						</figure></p> 
						<p>Fig. 3 De Courcy, Costume designed by Megan Correnti</p>
						
						
				<p>		The village girls, Martina and Maud, are among the characters in the opening scene with arrival on the Kentish shore
						of the ship bearing Lady Elinor and her retinue from <name ref="France">France</name>. As the play opens, the two
						appear as modest peasants. In Act II, scene vi, however, they are called upon by the lecherous Baron to seduce Grouffing, the
						tax-collector, in order to persuade him to fetch the chest of gold stored in the haunted tower. For this scene, in which they
						sing “Attune the pipe,” their modest peasant dresses must be modified into seductive attire.</p>
					<p>
					<figure>
							<graphic width="400px" url="/prod/sites/default/files/imported/pedagogies/theatre/images/martinaandmaud.jpg"/>
							<figDesc>Martina and Maud, Costumes designed by Megan Correnti</figDesc>
						</figure>
					</p>
					<p>Fig. 4 Martina and Maud, Costumes designed by Megan Correnti</p>
					

					<p> In the comedies of the period, an heiress and her maid are often depicted as companions: the lady demur and modest, the
						maid daring, witty, and saucy. The relationship between Lady Elinor and her maid Cicely adheres to this pattern, except that
						Cicely is several degrees more assertive and commanding. She constantly interrupts Lady Elinor, gives orders to Sir Palamede,
						and directs their actions. Her solo in Act I, “Nature to woman still so kind,” based on a Welch folk tune, asserts her sense
						of a woman’s advantage.</p>
					<p>
					<figure n="5">
							<graphic width="400px" url="/prod/sites/default/files/imported/pedagogies/theatre/images/cicelyandelinor.jpg"/>
							<figDesc>Cicely and Lady Elinor (I.ii)</figDesc>
						
						</figure> </p>
					<p>Fig. 5 Cicely and Lady Elinor (I.ii)</p>
						
						
						<p>Although herself a member of the serving class, Cicely is haughty and officious when addressing other servants. In
						Act I, scene ii, as depicted, she is insulting in her rude dismissal of Maud, the village girl who has offered shelter and
						guidance to the newly arrived party from France. The gestures, it may be noted, are
						those prescribed by Engel/Siddons: Palamede’s contemplative curiosity, Maud’s offended astonishment, Cicely’s arrogant authority.</p>
					<p>
					<figure
							n="6">
						<graphic width="400px" url="/prod/sites/default/files/imported/pedagogies/theatre/images/palamede-maud-cicely.jpg"/>
							<figDesc>Palamede, Maud, and Cicely (I.ii)</figDesc>
						</figure></p>
					<p>Fig. 6 Palamede, Maud, and Cicely (I.ii)</p>
				<p>	The role of Lord William is, in effect, several roles in one. He was but a boy of twelve when the false slander
						against his father, the Baron of Oakland, forced him into exile. Following the death of his father, a distant cousin, Edmund
						the ploughman, has seized power as usurping Baron. In France, William took on the
						disguise of Palamede, and matured into a promising young soldier in service to De Courcy. Here he fell in love with Lady
						Elinor and she with him. Her father, however, has pledged her in marriage to the heir of the Baron of Oakland. Lord William,
						of course, is the rightful heir, but he dare not make that claim until he has received the official pardon from the King. He
						thus must remain docile and submissive, even to the demands of Cicely. Assisting him to gain access to Lady Elinor’s quarters
						in her father’s estate, Cicely has disguised him as Lily, a maid-in-waiting. As Lily, William/Palamede was also able to make
						the crossing in the same ship with Lady Elinor. He is caught in the dilemma of asserting his masculinity while Cicely
						teasingly reminds him of his female role. Whatever other roles he is forced to assume, the audience must perceive that he is
						indeed his own man and capable heir to his father’s lands. When he steps forth from the haunted tower dressed in his father’s
						armor, singing the powerful aria, “Spirit of my sainted sire” (III.iv), he has fully assumed his proper heroic stature. The
						backflashes that explain the usurpation and exile are provided, first, by the village girl Maud, then by Hugo, faithful
						servant of the family. Cicely’s abrupt dismissal of Maud in the above depicted scene (I.ii) is motivated by her anxiety that
						she will lose control of the situation if Maud reveals too much of William’s eminent restoration. When William is introduced
						as De Courcy’s court jester, the Baron ridicules his debased status, but deftly turns the tables with a satirical song
						laughing at the Baron’s impotent and ineffectual prowess. </p>
					<p>
					<figure n="7">
						<graphic width="400px" url="/prod/sites/default/files/imported/pedagogies/theatre/images/huntsmenandrobert.jpg"/>
							<figDesc>The Huntsmen (Chorus) and Robert (I.iii)</figDesc>
						</figure> 
					</p>
					<p>Fig. 7 The Huntsmen (Chorus) and Robert (I.iii)</p>
						
					<p>	As noted above, Cobb and Storace fortified the Englishness of their adaptation by introducing traditional English themes in their songs. How
						the entrance and exit of a chorus was managed at Drury Lane I could discover neither
						in Kelly’s account in his <title level="m">Reminiscences</title> nor in Genest’s commentary on the premier performance.<note place="foot"
							resp="editors">
							Kelly, <title level="m">Reminiscences</title>, 1:318-20; Genest, <title level="m">The English Stage</title>, 6:586-88. </note> My
						solution was to present a quartet (two sopranos, an alto, and a tenor) with changes in costume but always the same as
						characters. For the opening chorus (I.i) they were costumed as fishermen, as huntsmen led in song by Robert (I.iii), as
						servants to the false Baron (I.iii), as cooks, again led by Robert in singing the “Roast Beef of Old <name
							ref="England">England</name>”(II.vii), and as soldiers (I.iv and III.vi). The chorus thus had four costume
						changes, but they were instructed always to synchronize their movements and gestures, as in the above scene as huntsmen. The
						one exception was their signature entrance: they would march on stage perfectly coordinated, then stumble and bump into each
						other when they came to a halt.</p>
					<p>
					<figure>
							<graphic width="400px" url="/prod/sites/default/files/imported/pedagogies/theatre/images/decourcyandbaron.jpg"/>
							<figDesc>De Courcy and the Baron (III.i)</figDesc>
						</figure>
					</p>
					<p>Fig. 8 De Courcy and the Baron (III.i)</p>

					<p>The comic center of <title level="m">The Haunted Tower</title> is the lecherous and self-aggrandizing fake Baron. He
						exploits and abuses the lower classes as mere objects of his desires. Just clever enough to be aware of his own clumsiness in
						pretending to nobility, he constantly suspects that others of rank and power are laughing at his pretensions and attempting to
						undermine his authority. His suspicions are not ill-founded. In the scene depicted above (III.i), the Baron expresses to De
						Courcy his fears that a revolution, led by De Courcy’s court jester, is at hand. De Courcy, of course, perceives that the
						court jester is Sir Palamede, one of his own retinue. He knows Palamede’s affections for his sister, yet he has assumed that
						Lady Elinor would not dishonor her father’s pledge that she marry the son of the Baron of Oakland. In performing the role of
						the false Baron, Greg Cragg followed my cues in adapting several of Robert Baddeley’s mannerisms, 
						including what Michael Kelly described as Baddeley’s “habit of smacking his lips always when
							speaking.”<note place="foot" resp="editors">
							Kelly, Reminiscences, 2:70. See also: William Davenport Adams. <title level="m">A Dictionary of the
								Drama: A Guide to the Plays, Playwrights, Players, and Playhouses of the United Kingdom and America, from the Earliest
								Times to the Present</title>. 2 vols. (London: Chatto &amp; Windus, 1904), 1:99.</note> In this performance the
						Baron’s lip-smacking made his words seem all the more lecherous. In the early scenes he performed his entrances with a pompous
							strut.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> See Engel/Siddons, <title level="m">Rhetorical Gesture</title>, on Pride, Hauteur,
							Voluptuary, and Vulgar Arrogance, pp. 51, 52, 97, 153.</note> Only when he realizes that he is under siege by the rightful
						heir of Oakland does his pretentious “Hauteur” lapse into distraught fear.</p>
					<p>
					<figure >
							<graphic width="400px" url="/prod/sites/default/files/imported/pedagogies/theatre/images/edward-adela-baron.jpg"/>
							<figDesc>Edward, Adela, and the Baron (III.i)</figDesc>
						</figure>
					</p>
					<p>Fig. 9 Edward, Adela, and the Baron (III.i)</p>

					<p>At the beginning of Act III, De Courcy finally meets Adela, the peasant girl who has been impersonating his sister.
						Edward, son of the false Baron, is in love with the peasant girl Adela. Just as Lady Elinor must accept her father’s decision
						that she marry the heir of the Baron of Oakland, Edward must comply with his father’s eager pursuit of the marriage which will
						lend legitimacy to his own claims of nobility. Edward contrives the plot to disguise Adela as Lady Elinor and thus consummate
						the marriage before the real Lady Elinor arrives. The real Lady Elinor arrives too early, but is readily persuaded by Cicely
						to play along with the hoax in order to escape an unwanted marriage to Edward. This scene commences with De Courcy in pursuit
						of Sir Palamede, whom he now fears has turned traitor and seeks to elope with his sister. After the false Baron informs him
						that a revolution is underway, Edward arrives half-drunk from his tryst with Adela, whom he has introduced into the Oakland
						court as Lady Elinor. Considering his sister’s honor insulted by Edward’s overly familiar claims of intimacy with “my wife
						that is to be,” De Courcy is about to draw his sword. At this moment Adela arrives, and is greeted as “Lady Elinor” by the
						Baron and his son. Suspecting that this false identity must be a plot of Palamede’s, De Courcy declares, “I perceive, my lord,
						you have been imposed on, but you shall soon be avenged.” Edward and Adela stand aside looking guilty and exposed, while the
						Baron tries to puzzle out how he might have been “imposed on.” Not suspecting his son’s ruse and unable to determine any
						source of imposition, he follows after De Courcy to “ask whether I ought to be in a passion or not.” The scene closes with
						Adela singing a plaintive love song to Edward, “Love from the heart” (III.i). In referring to the penultimate scene (III.v),
						when “the Baron enters with his sword drawn, and some old armour awkwardly put on,” Genest cites Hannah Cowley’s remarks on Baddeley’s performance: “a
						great actor, holding a sword in his left hand, and making awkward passes with it, charms the audience; and brings down such
						applauses as the bewitching dialogue of Farquhar pants for in vain.”<note place="foot" resp="editors">
							Genest, <title level="m">The English Stage</title>, 6:588; Hannah Cowley, Preface, <title level="m">The Town Before You: a Comedy, as
								acted at the Theatre-Royal, Covent Garden</title> (London: Printed by G. Woodfall, for T. N. Longman, 1795), p.
							vi.</note> The implication would seem to be that by some degradation of popular taste, the comedy of gesture has gained an
						unwarranted advantage over the comedy of witty dialogue. The charge is not without truth: Romantic comedy is not particularly
						noted for its clever dialogue, and it does rely frequently on body language, indeed more and more so with the increasing
						popularity of pantomime and melodrama. But this was not a passing phase. The Baron frantically waving his sword still brings
						down the house. Nevertheless it is also true that the dialogue contains a great deal of allusive irony concerning the politics
						of revolution.</p>
					<p>Although the performers were well cued on pacing their delivery to allow that irony to emerge, many of the potential
						laugh-lines were missed by the student audiences during our four performances at UCLA. The cast and crew were therefore
						pleased and surprised by the much more responsive audience of literary scholars attending the performance on March 9, at the
						41st Annual Comparative Literature Conference, California State University, Long Beach. The success of our performances were
						due entirely to the talent and dedication of the students involved. Gifted singers like Schuyler Hudak as Adela, Kristin
						Crawford as Lady Elinor, and Lauren Cheak as Cicely brought Storace’s score to
						life, and Stephen Pu as vocal director enabled the entire cast to achieve excellence in virtuoso solos as well as complex
						choral pieces.</p>
					<p>In the final scene (III.vi), Lord William is revealed as rightful Baron of Oakland. He reconciled with De Courcy who
						affirms that no obstacle interferes with his father’s pledge of Lady Elinor’s hand in marriage. Edward is free to marry Adela.
						The comic opera concludes with the first Grand Finale to be performed on a London Stage: <quote>
							<lg>
								<l>The banished ills of heretofore</l>
								<l>At happy distance viewing;</l>
								<l>Of the past we’ll think no more,</l>
								<l>While future bliss pursing. <lb/>
									(III.vi)</l>
							</lg>
						</quote> Crucial here is that Lord William exonerates the false Baron of all crimes related to his usurpation and committed
						under his rule. The “happy ending” reconciles French-English animosities and class conflict at the very moment in history,
						immediately following the outbreak of the French Revolution, when these tensions were at a peak. Whether or not the audience
						saw any contemporary relevance in this doctrine of reconciliation, the finale gave an optimistic “feel good” conclusion to a
						comedy of disguise, deceit, and sadistic exploitation.</p>
					<lb/>
					<lb/>
					<ab>Audio files for <title level="m">The Haunted Tower</title> can be found <ref target="http://www.sjsu.edu/faculty/douglass/music/album-haunted.html">here</ref>.</ab>
				</div>
				
			</div>
			
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
