<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. </title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
				<author>
					<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
				</author>
				<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>
					<date>2009-03-15</date>
				</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="edition">people</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date from="2009-03-15" to="2011-08-15">March 15, 2009; updated August 15, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:>
						<address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
						<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
							Circles.</item>
						<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
					</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>Lynda Pratt</author>
						<title>Biographies</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. </title>
						<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
						<author>
							<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
						</author>
						<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
							<pubPlace>University of Maryland</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
					<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>&#163; has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="g" corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
					<category xml:id="people">
						<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
					<category xml:id="places">
						<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g21" scheme="#genre"/>
				<catRef target="./people.html" scheme="#people"/>
				<catRef target="./places.html" scheme="#places"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change n="8" when="2011-08-15" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="7" when="2011-07-06" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="6" when="2011-03-20" who="#AB">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
				<list>
					<item>corrections from proofing</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="5" when="2011-02-21" who="#AB">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
				<list>
					<item>Part II added</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="4" when="2009-03-10" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="3" when="2009-03-02" who="#AB">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
				<list>
					<item>corrections from proofing</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="2" when="2009-02-20" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="1" when="2009-02-20" who="#AB">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
				<list>
					<item>TEI Encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="paratext">
				<head>Biographies</head>
				<p>These pages provide information about contemporaries to whom Southey was
					connected, in particular, correspondents, family and friends. </p>
				<p>Information about minor acquaintances and about contemporaries whom Southey did
					not meet or correspond with can be found in the editorial notes to individual
					letters.</p>
				<p><hi rend="ital">DNB</hi> indicates that further information can be found in the
					new Oxford <title>Dictionary of National Biography</title>.</p>
				<p><hi rend="ital">Hist P</hi> indicates that further information can be found in
						<title>The History of Parliament</title>. </p>
				<lb/>
				<list type="simple">
					<item n="1">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="Adderley">Adderley, Richard Boyle (dates
							unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#Adderley"> a friend of Southey’s during his time at
							Westminster School.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="2">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="AikinArthur">Aikin, Arthur (1773–1854;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#AikinArthur">son of John Aikin and nephew of Anna Letitia
							Barbauld. A Unitarian intellectual, writer and lecturer on chemistry and
							mineralogy and from 1803-1808 the editor of the <title>Annual
								Review</title>, the journal for which Southey wrote before he became
							a regular contributor to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. </gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="3">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="AikinJohn">Aikin, John (1747–1822;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#AikinJohn"> physician, author and brother of Anna Letitia
							Barbauld. In the mid-1790s, Southey and Aikin moved in the same circles
							in London. Aikin was a regular contributor to periodicals and his review
							of <title>Joan of Arc</title> appeared in the <title>Analytical
								Review</title> in 1796. In 1797 Aikin and his son, Arthur Aikin,
							translated the first volume of Necker’s <title>On the French
								Revolution</title>. Southey translated the second. In the mid-1790s,
							Southey (using a variety of pseudonyms) corresponded with Aikin in the
							latter’s capacity as literary editor of the <title>Monthly
								Magazine</title>.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="4">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="AllenRobert">Allen, Robert (1772–1805):</term>
						<gloss target="#AllenRobert"> surgeon and journalist. Educated at Christ’s
							Hospital (where he was a contemporary of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and
							Charles Lamb) and University College, Oxford (BA 1796, MA 1803, MB and
							MD 1803). He first met Southey, who was flirting with a career in
							medicine, at the Anatomy School in Oxford in early 1794. They became
							firm friends, Southey later describing how in 1794 Allen had been his
							‘bosom-companion’ and had ‘rendered many hours delightful which would
							otherwise have passed in the destructive daydreams of solitude’. Allen
							wrote poetry and, in Oxford in June 1794, introduced Southey to
							Coleridge. In 1794–1795, Allen was possibly a convert to Pantisocracy.
							In 1796, he enrolled at the Westminster Hospital and married a wealthy
							widow, Catherine, daughter of Nathaniel Forster (1726–1790; <title
								level="m">DNB</title>). She died within a year. In 1797, with the
							encouragement of Anthony Carlisle, he became deputy surgeon with
							England’s Second Royals, then stationed in Portugal. He was back in
							Britain by 1802 and from 1803 until his death worked as a journalist,
							writing for (according to Charles Lamb) the London newspapers the <title
								level="j">Oracle</title>, <title level="j">True Briton</title>,
								<title level="j">Star</title> and <title level="j"
							>Traveller</title>.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="5">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BarbauldAnnaLetitia">Barbauld, Anna Letitia (née
							Aikin; 1743-1825; DNB):</term>
						<gloss target="#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">poet, essayist and children’s author,
							sister of John Aikin and aunt of Arthur Aikin, Southey’s editor at the
								<title>Annual Review</title>. She married the Revd Rochemont
							Barbauld (1749-1808) on 26 May 1774. Barbauld and Southey met in 1797
							and had many acquaintances in common, including George Dyer, William
							Godwin and Joseph Johnson. Barbauld was publicly linked with the
							literary and scientific experimentalism of Southey’s circle, and
							featured in the <title>Anti-Jacobin</title> satire ‘The Pneumatic
							Revellers’ (1800). She and Southey both contributed to the
								<title>Monthly Magazine</title> and the <title>Annual Review</title>
							and occasionally socialised, in particular during Southey’s time in
							London in 1801-1802. However, his attitude to her was ambivalent. He
							agreed with her advice to Coleridge (whom Barbauld admired and promoted)
							not to lose himself in ‘the maze of metaphysic lore’, but condemned the
							verses in which she articulated this as ‘trite’. He also punned on her
							surname, calling her ‘Bare-bald’ because he attributed to her a hostile
							review of Charles Lamb’s play <title>John Woodvil; a Tragedy</title>
							(1802) in the <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803),
							688-692.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="6">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BarkerMary">Barker, Mary (c. 1780-1853):</term>
						<gloss target="#BarkerMary"> author, painter and close friend of Robert
							Southey. Born in Congreve, Staffordshire, daughter of Thomas Barker, an
							ironmaster, and Mary Homfray. Author of <title>A Welsh Story</title>
							(1798), she moved in literary circles. She met Southey in Portugal in
							1800 and subsequently visited the Southeys frequently in Bristol, London
							and Keswick. Godmother of Southey’s first child, Margaret (d. 1803).
							Southey had a high opinion of Mary Barker’s talents and proposed that
							she should illustrate <title>Madoc</title> (1805). She appears as the
							‘Bhow Begum’ in <title>The Doctor</title> (1834-1847). Mary Barker lived
							at Greta Lodge in Keswick, next to Greta Hall, between 1812 and 1817,
							becoming a close friend of the Coleridges and Wordsworths, as well as
							the Southeys, and teaching music to the girls of the families. Financial
							difficulties forced her to move to Boulogne in 1819 and she never
							returned to England. Southey met her for the last time on his trip to
							France in 1825. In 1830 she married a Mr Slade, who was much younger
							than her and thought to be a ‘mere adventurer’ by her Keswick
							friends.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="7">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BarnesFrederick">Barnes, Frederick ‘Ginger’
							(1771–1859):</term>
						<gloss target="#BarnesFrederick"> clergyman. A friend of Southey’s during
							his time at Westminster School and Oxford. In later life, Barnes held
							several livings in Devonshire.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="8">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BeaumontSirGeorge">Beaumont, Sir George Howland,
							7th Baronet (1753-1827; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#BeaumontSirGeorge">art patron, landscape painter, coal mine
							owner. He was a friend and patron of Wordsworth, Coleridge, Southey,
							Constable and Scott, inviting them to his estate at Coleorton,
							Leicestershire. Sir George was an enthusiastic amateur painter and owner
							of many Italian landscapes. Southey first met Beaumont in the Lakes in
							1803 and corresponded with him and his wife.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="9">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BeaumontLadyMary">Beaumont, Margaret, Lady (née
							Willes; 1756-1829):</term>
						<gloss target="#BeaumontLadyMary">married Sir George Beaumont on 6 May 1778
							and accompanied him on his tours of Europe, England and Wales. She was
							on friendly terms with Southey and her husband’s other proteges.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="10">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BeddoesThomas">Beddoes, Thomas (1760–1808;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#BeddoesThomas"> chemist and physician. Born at Shifnal,
							Shropshire, son of Richard Beddoes and Ann Whitehall. Educated at
							Bridgnorth Grammar School, by private tutor, and at Pembroke College,
							Oxford (matric. 1776, BA 1779, MB and MD 1786), and Edinburgh. Reader in
							Chemistry at Oxford from 1788. In the early 1790s, a growing reputation
							as a radical led to his surveillance by Home Office spies and failure to
							gain the Regius Chair in Chemistry. He left Oxford for Bristol in 1793
							and married Anna Edgeworth (1772–1824), sister of the novelist Maria
							(1768–1849; <title>DNB</title>), in the following year. Beddoes was
							involved in the political protest movements of the mid-1790s and
							possibly first met Southey in 1795, during the latter’s immersion in
							Bristol politics. In 1799, Beddoes opened the Pneumatic Institute (from
							1802 the Preventive Medical Institution for the Sick and Drooping Poor)
							in Hotwells, Bristol. Southey participated in the experiments with gases
							carried out by Beddoes and Humphry Davy, and recorded in <title>Notice
								of Some Observations Made at the Medical Pneumatic
								Institution</title> (1799). Beddoes was a prolific writer on
							medical, political and educational reform. He was also a poet: author of
								<title>Alexander’s Expedition</title> (1792) and a contributor to
							Southey’s <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799). Southey respected
							Beddoes’s medical judgment, consulting him on more than one occasion. In
							1809 he recorded that ‘From Beddoes I hoped for more good to the human
							race than from any other individual’. However, disagreements about
							poetry ensured that their personal relationship was not warm. Southey
							dismissed Beddoes as a ‘hypercritic of the Darwin school’ and was
							furious when his ‘Domiciliary Verses’ (a parody of Samuel Taylor
							Coleridge, William Wordsworth and Southey) found its way into the first
							volume of the <title level="m">Annual Anthology</title>. Joseph Cottle,
							who was responsible for the poem’s inclusion, was ordered by Southey not
							to solicit any further contributions from Beddoes.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="11">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="Bedfordfamily">Bedford family:</term>
						<gloss target="#Bedfordfamily"> the Bedford family lived at Westminster and
							Brixton. The household consisted of the parents, Charles (c. 1742-1814) and Mary
							Bedford, three sons (Grosvenor, Horace and Harry) and a cousin, Mary
							Page. Southey was on good terms with the entire family. He made use of
							the library in their Westminster home and wrote the first draft of
								<title>Joan of Arc</title> during an extended stay at their house in
							Brixton in summer 1793. Southey corresponded with Grosvenor and
							Horace.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="12">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford, Grosvenor
							Charles (1773–1839):</term>
						<gloss target="#BedfordGrosvenorCharles"> civil servant and miscellaneous
							writer. The son of Charles Bedford (Deputy Usher of the Exchequer, as
							Horace Walpole’s substitute). Educated at Westminster School (adm.
							1784), but did not attend university. Assistant clerk in the Exchequer
							Office, 1792–1803; clerk of the cash book, 1803–1806; clerk of the
							registers and issues, 1806–1822; chief clerk in the auditor’s office,
							1822–1834. Admitted to Gray’s Inn, 26 January 1797. Bedford did not
							marry, despite regularly seeking Southey’s advice on his love affairs.
							Bedford and Southey met at Westminster School and their friendship
							endured for the remainder of their lives. Bedford had literary
							inclinations. He was involved in the ill-fated <title>Flagellant</title>
							(1792), contributed poems to the <title>Monthly Magazine</title> (1797)
							and the first volume of the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799), and
							privately published his translation of Musaeus, <title>The Loves of Hero
								and Leander</title> (1797). He worked with Southey on
								<title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807) and
							contributed an unsigned notice of Southey’s <title>Roderick, the Last of
								the Goths</title> (1814) to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. His
							other publications included <title>A Letter to the Right Hon. William
								Pitt on his Political Experiments</title> (1804, anonymous) and a
								<title>Memoir</title> of Barré Charles Roberts (1814).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="13">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BedfordHenry">Bedford, Henry (‘Harry’) (dates
							unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#BedfordHenry"> the younger brother of Grosvenor and Horace
							Bedford.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="14">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BedfordHoraceWalpole">Bedford, Horace Walpole (c.
							1776–1807):</term>
						<gloss target="#BedfordHoraceWalpole"> civil servant and miscellaneous
							writer. The younger brother of Grosvenor Charles Bedford and named after
							his father’s patron. He was educated at Westminster School (adm. 1784),
							where his nickname was ‘the Doctor’ or ‘Dr. Johnson’. He did not attend
							university and later held a post at the British Museum. Like his older
							brother, he did not marry. Southey’s friendship with Horace began at
							school and their correspondence (though occasionally intermittent)
							lasted until at least 1797. Southey’s relationship with Horace was
							slightly different from that with Grosvenor Charles Bedford. He treated
							Horace as a younger brother: encouraging him and worrying about his
							tendency to laziness. He also fostered the younger man’s literary
							ambitions. Horace’s poems appeared in the <title>Monthly
								Magazine</title> (1797) and the <title>Annual Anthology</title>
							(1799).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="15">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombe, Charles (dates
							unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#BiddlecombeCharles"> neighbour and friend. Biddlecombe met
							Southey in summer 1797 when the latter moved to the village of Burton in
							Hampshire. Southey described him as ‘rich enough to buy books, and very
							friendly, all that a neighbour should be’. Biddlecombe married in 1798,
							but his wife died in childbirth in March 1799, leaving him with an
							infant daughter. During Southey’s numerous absences, Biddlecombe appears
							to have looked after the cottage at Burton and when it was finally given
							up in 1802 arranged for a sale of part of the furniture and stored some
							of Southey’s possessions, including books, for a number of years. During
							his 1817 visit to France, Southey ran into Biddlecombe, whom he had not
							seen for several years, and his invalid daughter, describing the latter
							as ‘short and plethoric, with a countenance of prepossessing good
							nature’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="16">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BiggsNathaniel">Biggs, Nathaniel (dates
							unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#BiggsNathaniel"> a printer and stationer in Bristol. He
							printed books, including works by Beddoes, Coleridge, Estlin and
							Southey, for congeries of publishers in London and the South-West of
							England. In the mid-late 1790s, he entered into a business partnership
							with Joseph Cottle, printing the Bristol edition of Coleridge and
							Wordsworth’s <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title> (1798), and the
							revised editions of 1800 and 1802.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="17">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BoucherJonathan">Boucher, Jonathan (1738-1804;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#BoucherJonathan">schoolmaster, clergyman and lexicographer.
							Southey corresponded with him in 1802 concerning Thomas Chatterton
							(1752-1770; <title>DNB</title>).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="18">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BunburyCharlesJohn">Bunbury, Charles John
							(1772–1798):</term>
						<gloss target="#BunburyCharlesJohn"> soldier. Educated at Westminster
							School, where he was a friend of Southey’s, and Trinity College,
							Cambridge. In 1789, Bunbury presented Southey with a copy of Thomas
							Warton’s <title>Poems</title> (3rd edn, 1779). Their friendship did not
							last. In 1793, Bunbury tried to avoid Southey when the latter was
							visiting Cambridge. Southey, in turn, claimed that Bunbury’s
							‘debauchery’ was the direct result of his public school education.
							Bunbury joined the army and died at the Cape of Good Hope. Bunbury’s
							father, the artist Henry William Bunbury (1750–1811;
							<title>DNB</title>), and his younger brother, Sir Henry Edward Bunbury
							(1778–1860; <title>DNB</title>), later became close friends of Southey’s
							and members of his circle in Keswick.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="19">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BurnettGeorge">Burnett, George (c. 1776–1811;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#BurnettGeorge"> writer. The son of John Burnett, a farmer,
							of Huntspill, Somerset. Educated at Balliol College, Oxford (matric.
							1793). His varied career included time spent as a student at a
							dissenting academy in Manchester, pastor to a Unitarian congregation in
							Great Yarmouth, medical student at the University of Edinburgh,
							assistant to John Rickman, domestic tutor to the sons of Lord Stanhope,
							assistant surgeon to a militia regiment and (in Poland) tutor to the
							family of Count Zamoyski. Burnett was also a professional writer, whose
							works included <title>View of the Present State of Poland</title> (1807;
							from essays originally published in the <title>Monthly
							Magazine</title>), <title>Specimens of English Prose Writers</title>
							(1807; a companion to George Ellis’s <title>Specimens of the Early
								English Poets</title>) and <title>Extracts from the Prose Works of
								Milton</title> (1809).</gloss>
						<gloss>Southey met Burnett at Balliol and the two became friends. Burnett
							was one of the originators of Pantisocracy and in true Pantisocratic
							spirit proposed to Martha Fricker, who turned him down. In 1795, he
							shared lodgings with Southey and Coleridge in Bristol. From 1797–1798,
							he was minister to a Unitarian congregation in Great Yarmouth, Norfolk,
							where he also tutored Henry Herbert Southey. Burnett moved in
							metropolitan literary circles and was friendly with Charles Lamb and
							John Rickman. His relationship with Southey and Samuel Taylor Coleridge
							became deeply ambivalent — by 1803 he was accusing both of treating him
							badly. Burnett was an opium addict and his last years were probably
							spent in poverty. He died in the Marylebone Infirmary.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="20">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="BurneyJames">Burney, James (1750-1821;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#BurneyJames">naval officer and writer, second son of the
							music historian Dr Charles Burney (1726-1814; <title>DNB</title>) and
							brother of Charles (1757-1817; <title>DNB</title>) and Frances (Fanny;
							1752-1840; <title>DNB</title>). He was sent to sea at the age of 10. In
							1772 he sailed in the <hi rend="ital">Resolution</hi> on James Cook’s
							(1728-1779; <title>DNB</title>) second voyage to the South Seas and on
							his return home in 1774 acted as an interpreter for Omai, the first
							Tahitean to visit Britain. Burney sailed on Cook’s third voyage and
							witnessed the latter’s death in 1779. He rose to the rank of Captain,
							but a reputation for insubordination brought his active naval career to
							an end in 1784. In the 1790s, Burney embarked on a second career as a
							writer, publishing an edition of William Bligh’s (1754-1817;
								<title>DNB</title>) <title>A Voyage to the South Sea in HMS
								Bounty</title> (1792). His magnum opus was <title>A Chronological
								History of the Discoveries in the South Sea or Pacific Ocean</title>
							(1803-1817). Southey and Burney shared an interest in travel writing and
							maritime history. The two became good friends and corresponded over
							several years, socialising when Southey visited London.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="21">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ButtJohnMarten">Butt, John Marten
							(1774–1846):</term>
						<gloss target="#ButtJohnMarten"> clergyman and author. Only son of George
							and Mary Martha Butt and brother of Mary Martha Sherwood (1775–1851;
								<title>DNB</title>), author of <title>The Fairchild Family</title>.
							Educated Westminster (adm. 1788) and Christ Church, Oxford (matric.
							1792, BA 1796, MA 1799). Curate of Witley, Worcestershire; Rector of
							Oddingley, Worcestershire from 1806 and Vicar of East Garston, Berkshire
							from 1806. Author of <title>The Last Vision of Daniel</title> (1808) and
							other works. His first wife was Mary Ann Congreve; his second, Jemima
							Hubbal. Butt was a friend of Southey’s at Westminster School and
							Oxford.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="22">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="CadellThomas">Cadell, Thomas (1773–1836;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#CadellThomas"> bookseller. The son of the London bookseller
							Thomas Cadell (1742–1802; <title>DNB</title>), he took over his father’s
							business in 1793, working in partnership with William Davies (d. 1820;
								<title>DNB</title>).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="23">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="CampbellHenry">Campbell, Henry ‘Horse’
							(1774–1846):</term>
						<gloss target="#CampbellHenry"> clergyman. Educated at Christ Church, Oxford
							(BA 1792). A university friend of Southey’s, they did not keep in touch
							in later life. Their last meeting was at Falmouth in 1801, when Campbell
							was on his way to take up the living of St John's in Antigua. Later he
							returned to England and was curate of Nailsworth and then
							Cowley.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="24">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle, Anthony (1768–1840;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#CarlisleAnthony"> surgeon and anatomist. Born at
							Stillington, Durham, the third son of Thomas Carlisle and his first wife
							Barbara (d. 1768). Studied medicine in York, Durham and London, and was
							appointed surgeon to the Westminster Hospital in 1793. He married Martha
							Symmons in 1800 and in the same year was one of the founding members of
							the Royal College of Surgeons, serving as its president in 1829 and
							1839. He moved in metropolitan literary and scientific circles,
							attending Mary Wollstonecraft on her death-bed in 1797. He was elected a
							Fellow of the Royal Society in 1804, held the post of Professor of
							Anatomy at the Royal Academy from 1808 and later that of
							surgeon-extraordinary to the Prince Regent. Carlisle was knighted when
							George IV acceded to the throne. Carlisle and Southey met in c. 1795,
							probably through their mutual friend Grosvenor Charles Bedford. In c.
							1798 Carlisle, Southey and John May collaborated on a scheme for a
							convalescent asylum to assist the poor after their discharge from
							hospital. Although Carlisle and Southey corresponded, their letters to
							one another seem not to have survived.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="25">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="CenaculoManuel">Cenáculo, Manuel do
							(1724-1814):</term>
						<gloss target="#CenaculoManuel"> Bishop of Beja, 1770-1802, Archbishop of
							Evora 1802-1814. Member of the Franciscan Order and Professor of
							Theology at the University of Coimbra 1751-1755. Cenaculo was closely
							associated with the reforms of the Marquis of Pombal, Prime Minister of
							Portugal 1750-1777, and retired to his bishopric when Pombal fell in
							1777, devoting his energies to his library and promoting education. When
							Southey visited Portugal in 1800-1801 he obtained a letter of
							introduction to the Bishop from his uncle, Herbert Hill, and visited him
							at Beja in April 1801.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="26">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ClarksonCatherine">Clarkson, Catherine (née Buck;
							1772-1856; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#ClarksonCatherine">a native of the Suffolk town of Bury St
							Edmunds, she married Thomas Clarkson in 1796. She shared his radicalism
							and became close friends with the Wordsworths, Southey, Coleridge and
							Crabb Robinson.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="27">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ClarksonThomas">Clarkson, Thomas (1760-1846;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#ClarksonThomas">campaigner for the abolition of the slave
							trade, and a friend of the Wordsworths, Coleridge and Southey. He moved
							to the Lake District in 1794 and lived in retirement at Eusemere, near
							Pooley Bridge, Ullswater, until 1806. Clarkson and his wife returned to
							her native Suffolk in 1806, and remained there until his death. He
							returned to the campaign against the slave trade in 1804 and wrote
							ceaselessly in the cause until the passing of the 1833 Act abolishing
							slavery in the British empire.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="28">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ColeridgeDavidHartley">Coleridge, David Hartley
							(1796–1849; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#ColeridgeDavidHartley"> eldest son of Samuel Taylor
							Coleridge and Sarah Fricker; and Southey’s nephew.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="29">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ColeridgeDerwent">Coleridge, Derwent (1800-1883;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#ColeridgeDerwent"> third son of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and
							Sarah Fricker; and Southey’s nephew. Anglican clergyman, writer and
							educationist. First Principal of St Mark’s teacher training college in
							Chelsea 1841-1864.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="30">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ColeridgeGeorge">Coleridge, George
							(1764–1828):</term>
						<gloss target="#ColeridgeGeorge"> clergyman and schoolmaster. The older
							brother of Samuel Taylor Coleridge. Southey and George Coleridge were —
							especially later in life, when the latter acknowledged Southey’s
							services to Samuel Taylor Coleridge’s family — on terms of mutual
							respect.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="31">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge, Samuel Taylor
							(1772–1834; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor"> poet, critic, philosopher and
							Southey’s brother-in-law. His complex — at times passionate —
							four-decade relationship with Coleridge had a major impact both on
							Southey’s life and on his critical posterity. It began in Oxford in
							summer 1794 when Robert Allen introduced Southey to a visitor from
							Cambridge — Coleridge. It was a fateful meeting, leading to the failed
							scheme of Pantisocracy, literary collaboration, and — eventually —
							mutual disenchantment. As Southey later recorded: ‘that meeting fixed
							the future fortunes of us both ... Coleridge had at that time thought
							little of politics, in morals he was as loose ... as men at a university
							usually are, but he was a Unitarian. my morals were of the sternest
							Stoicism ... that same feeling which made me a poet kept me pure ... Our
							meeting was mutually serviceable, — I reformed his life, &amp; he
							disposed me toward Xtianity’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="32">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Coleridge, Sara
							(1802-1852; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter"> fourth and youngest child of
							Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Sarah Fricker; and Southey’s niece.
							Translator, writer and indefatigable editor of her father’s works. In
							1829 she married her first cousin, Henry Nelson Coleridge.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="33">
						<hi rend="bold">Coleridge, Sarah: <hi rend="ital">see</hi> Fricker, Sarah
							(1770-1845)</hi>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="34">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="CollinsCharles">Collins, Charles
							(c.1777–1806?):</term>
						<gloss target="#CollinsCharles"> school friend. The son of William Collins
							and his wife Sarah Astell of Maize Hill, Greenwich, Kent. Educated at
							Westminster and Christ Church, Oxford (matric. Jan 1793). Married Jane
							Forman, by whom he had one son. Died c. 1806. Collins’s biography is
							difficult to reconstruct as <title>Records of Old Westminsters</title>
							and <title>Alumni Oxoniensis</title> both confuse him with his son, also
							named Charles Collins, and give a later date of death. A note, now in
							the Huntington Library, written by an eponymous descendant confirms that
							he died young. In 1815, Southey referred to Collins’s widow and in 1828
							described him as long dead. Southey met Collins at Westminster and later
							described him as ‘one of my most intimate school and college friends’.
							However, by early 1794 their friendship had cooled and they seem to have
							had no contact with one another after Southey’s departure from Oxford
							later that year.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="35">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="CollinsJeremiah">Collins, Jeremiah
							(1774–1853):</term>
						<gloss target="#CollinsJeremiah"> clergyman. Educated at Balliol College,
							Oxford (BA 1794). He eventually returned to his native Cornwall, where
							he became chaplain of the Truro Infirmary. He and Southey were friends
							for a short time in Oxford, but by mid-1794 they were permanently
							estranged.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="36">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="CombeEdward">Combe, Edward (c.
							1773/4–1848):</term>
						<gloss target="#CombeEdward"> clergyman. Son of Richard Combe of Harley St.
							Educated at Westminster (adm. June 1785) and Christ Church, Oxford
							(matric. October 1792, BA 1796, MA 1803). Admitted to Lincoln’s Inn,
							January 1795. Perpetual Curate of Barrington, Somerset, 1810; Rector of
							Earnshill and of Donyatt from 1821. Southey met Combe at Westminster and
							later described him as one of his ‘most intimate acquaintances’ during
							his years at school. Combe was known by the nicknames ‘His Majesty’ or
							the ‘King of Men’. Although their close friendship did not outlast
							Oxford, Southey did visit Combe in 1824.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="37">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="CorryIsaac">Corry, Isaac (1753-1813;
								<title>DNB</title>; <title>Hist P</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#CorryIsaac">prominent Irish politician. Born in Newry, son
							of the merchant and MP, Edward Corry. Educated Royal School, Antrim and
							BA, Trinity College, Dublin, 1773. Succeeded his father as MP for Newry
							in the Irish Parliament, 1776. Originally an opposition MP, he first
							gained office as surveyor-general of the ordnance in 1788 and rose to be
							Irish chancellor of the exchequer in 1799 -1804. Always a controversial
							figure, he fought a duel with the opposition MP, Henry Grattan
							(1746-1820; <title>DNB</title>), in 1800. He supported the British
							government’s policies of Union between Britain and Ireland and Catholic
							Emancipation, but was still dismissed by the prime minister, William
							Pitt (1759-1806; <title>DNB</title>) in 1804. Rickman secured Southey
							the post of Corry’s secretary in 1801-1802.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="38">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="Cottlefamily">Cottle family:</term>
						<gloss target="#Cottlefamily"> the children of Robert Cottle, an
							unsuccessful Bristol tailor and draper. The family included Amos, Joseph
							and Robert (?1780–1858), a painter and founder of his own religious sect
							(‘the Cottlelites’), and five sisters, Elizabeth (c. 1764-1789), Mary (?1772-1839), Ann (?1780-1855), Sarah (d. 1834) and Martha (c. 1785-1800). Southey seems to
							have been acquainted with the entire Cottle family. After their secret
							marriage in November 1795, his wife Edith lived with the Cottle sisters
							for some of the time Southey was absent in Spain and Portugal.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="39">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="CottleAmos">Cottle, Amos Simon (1768?–1800;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#CottleAmos"> poet and translator. Elder brother of Joseph
							Cottle. Educated at the school run by Richard Henderson (1736/7–1792) at
							Hanham, near Bristol, and Magdalene College, Cambridge (matric. 1795, BA
							1799). He then embarked on a legal training. He spent the final year of
							his life in London, where he was a friend of George Dyer and Charles
							Lamb, and died in his chambers at Clifford’s Inn. Author of
								<title>Icelandic Poetry, or, The Edda of Saemund, Translated into
								English verse</title> (1797; published by Joseph Cottle and with
							dedicatory poem by Southey). Several of his other poems were collected
							posthumously in the fourth edition of Joseph Cottle, <title>Malvern
								Hills, With Minor Poems and Essays</title> (1829). Southey probably
							met Amos Cottle through his younger brother Joseph. The two shared an
							interest in Scandinavian literature and mythology and it was Southey who
							encouraged Amos to produce a verse, rather than prose, translation of
							the <title>Edda</title> and who reviewed it in the <title level="m"
								>Critical Review</title>.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="40">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="CottleJoseph">Cottle, Joseph (1770–1853;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#CottleJoseph"> Bristolian author, bookseller and publisher.
							Although Coleridge’s biographer James Dykes Campbell joked ‘I never
							heard of ... [Cottle’s] having ... any [parents], and think it very
							doubtful. I should think he was found under a booksellers counter
							wrapped in Felix Farley’s newspaper’, Joseph was in fact the second
							child of Robert and Sarah Cottle. He was educated at the school run by
							Richard Henderson (1736/7–1792) at Hanham, near Bristol. In 1791 he
							opened a shop as a printseller, stationer, binder and bookseller in
							Bristol. Cottle abandoned bookselling in 1798 but continued publishing.
							Between 1791 and 1800, he sold, printed or published 114 works, in
							congeries with Joseph Johnson, Benjamin Flower, H. D. Symons and others.
							In 1800 he began to sell his copyrights to the London firm of Longman. A
							poet and prose writer, his works included: <title>Poems</title> (1795),
								<title>Malvern Hills</title> (1798; with a prefatory poem by
							Southey), <title>Alfred</title> (1800), <title>The Fall of
								Cambria</title> (1808), <title>Early Recollections, Chiefly Relating
								to the Late Samuel Taylor Coleridge, During his Long Residence in
								Bristol</title> (1837) and <title>Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor
								Coleridge and Robert Southey</title> (1847).</gloss>
						<gloss>Cottle and Southey were introduced by Robert Lovell in 1794. Although
							not wealthy, Cottle provided generous financial help to Southey
							throughout the 1790s, even lending him money for his wedding ring. He
							published <title>Joan of Arc</title> and the majority of Southey’s
							earliest works, including <title>Poems</title> (1797) and <title>Letters
								Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title>
							(1797). His professional collaboration with Southey also included
							contributing poems to the <title>Annual Anthology</title> and co-editing
							the works of their fellow Bristolian Thomas Chatterton (1752–1770;
								<title>DNB</title>). What Cottle did not know, was that Southey
							viewed his poetry with a merriment that verged on contempt. The two men
							met less frequently after Southey’s move to Keswick in 1803, but
							maintained their correspondence. Southey’s final tour of the West
							Country in 1836–1837 included a visit to Cottle in Bristol. After
							Southey’s death, Cottle was a central figure in the successful campaign
							to erect a monument to his memory in Bristol cathedral. He recorded his
							association with Southey for posterity in his controversial
								<title>Reminiscences</title> (1847), itself a reworking of the
							equally contentious <title>Early Recollections</title> (1837).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="41">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="CroftHerbert">Croft, Herbert 5th Baronet
							(1751–1816; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#CroftHerbert">writer and lexicographer. Born at Dunster
							Park, Berkshire, the son of Richard Croft. He inherited the Croft
							baronetcy from a relative in 1797, but no money or lands to accompany
							the title. He practised as a barrister in London in the late 1770s, and
							gained some reputation as a miscellaneous writer. Perennially short of
							money, Croft changed direction and graduated from University College,
							Oxford in 1785 and was appointed Vicar of Prittlewell in Essex and
							chaplain of the British garrison in Quebec. Most of his time in the late
							1780s and early 1790s was devoted to a new dictionary, but, despite
							amassing 11,000 entries, he could not find enough subscribers to publish
							the book and the project was abandoned in 1793. In 1795 Croft was
							arrested for debt and fled to Hamburg, only returning to England in
							1800-1802, after which he lived in France, dying in Paris. In 1780 Croft
							had published <title>Love and Madness</title>, the story of James
							Hackman (c. 1752-1779; <title>DNB</title>), who had shot Martha Ray
							(1742?-1779; <title>DNB</title>), the lover of the Earl of Sandwich
							(1718-1792; <title>DNB</title>). The book contained a lengthy digression
							into the life of the Bristol poet Thomas Chatterton (1752-1770;
								<title>DNB</title>). Southey published a letter in the
								<title>Monthly Magazine</title> for November 1799, accusing Croft of
							obtaining some of Chatterton’s letters by deception from the poet’s
							mother and sister, and refusing to pay them any share of his profits
							from <title>Love and Madness</title>. Croft’s defence, to say the least,
							was evasive. In 1803 Southey and Joseph Cottle published a new version
							of Chatterton’s works for the benefit of his sister and niece.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="42">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="DanversCharles">Danvers, Charles (c. 1764-1814):</term>
						<gloss target="#DanversCharles"> Bristol wine merchant, trading under the
							name Danvers and White. He was distantly related to the regicides Sir
							John Danvers (1584/5–1655; <title>DNB</title>) and General Thomas
							Harrison (c. 1616–60; <title level="m">DNB</title>) and to the diarist
							Celia Fiennes (1662–1741; <title>DNB</title>). (Southey possessed a
							manuscript of Fiennes diary which he had been given by the Danvers
							family and included unacknowledged excerpts from it in his and
							Coleridge’s <title>Omniana</title> (1812)). Danvers’ father had ‘been a
							person of some property’, though the family’s fortunes had since
							declined. Danvers seems to have had two brothers and two sisters. He
							never married. A dissenter, he died in London ‘during a short tarriance
							there’ and was buried in Asplands Burial Ground, Hackney.</gloss>
						<gloss>Danvers knew Southey from childhood. In 1797, their friendship
							flourished when Southey and his wife lodged in a house in Kingsdown,
							next door to Danvers and his mother. In 1799, Southey finished the
							fifteen book version of <title>Madoc</title> in Mrs Danvers’ ‘parlour on
							her little table’. When Southey went to Portugal in 1800–1, he left a
							copy of his poetic magnum opus with Danvers and also delegated the task
							of collecting materials for the third <title>Annual Anthology</title> to
							him and Davy. This volume did not appear. Danvers visited Southey at
							Keswick in summer 1805 and kept a journal of his tour, now in the
							British Library, Add MS 30929. Extracts from this were published in
							Kenneth Curry, ‘A note on Wordsworth’s “Fidelity”’, <title>Philological
								Quarterly</title>, 32 (1953), 212–214.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="43">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="DanversMrs">Danvers, Mrs. (d. 1803):</term>
						<gloss target="#DanversMrs"> mother of Charles Danvers. She lived at
							Kingsdown in Bristol and became very close to Southey when he was
							resident in the city in the late 1790s and 1802-1803. After her death in
							the influenza epidemic of 1803, Southey described her as someone ‘whom I
							regarded with something like a family affection.’</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="44">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="DaveyJohn">Davey, John (d. 1798):</term>
						<gloss target="#DaveyJohn"> master of Balliol College, Oxford
							1785–1798.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="45">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="DavyHumphry">Davy, Humphry (1778-1829;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#DavyHumphry"> born in Penzance, son of Robert Davy, a
							woodcarver. Educated at Penzance and Truro grammar schools and
							apprenticed to an apothecary-surgeon in Truro. Davy had wide interests
							as a young man, writing poetry as well as conducting chemical
							experiments on the nature of heat, light and acidity. In October 1798 he
							went to Bristol to work for Thomas Beddoes at his Pneumatic Institution,
							which opened in March 1799. Davy soon became friendly with Southey and
							Coleridge, and they both participated in his experiments with nitrous
							oxide, or ‘laughing gas’. Southey published some of Davy’s early poems
							in the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799) and (1800) and suggested
							Davy should write a poem on Mango Capac, the first Inca, after Southey
							had failed in his plan to identify Madoc with the Inca ruler. In January
							1801 Davy moved to London to work at the Royal Institution, where he
							became a Professor in 1802. After this time Southey saw much less of
							Davy. However, his work on electricity was regarded as a brilliant
							contribution to Britain’s scientific reputation and he was elected
							President of the Royal Society in 1820.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="46">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="DeaconKate">Deacon, Kate:</term>
						<gloss target="#DeaconKate"> a friend of Grosvenor Charles Bedford and his
							family. Daughter of Mr and Mrs Deacon.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="47">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="Deaconfamily">Deacon, Mr and Mrs:</term>
						<gloss target="#Deaconfamily"> friends of Grosvenor Charles Bedford and his
							family.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="48">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="DoddJamesWilliam">Dodd, James William
							(?1759/60–1818):</term>
						<gloss target="#DoddJamesWilliam"> an Usher at Westminster School from
							1784.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="49">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="DolignonLouisa">Dolignon, Louisa (d. 1802):</term>
						<gloss target="#DolignonLouisa"> the widowed Mrs Dolignon and her sisters,
							the Misses Delamere, were friends of Southey’s aunt Elizabeth Tyler.
							Southey spent time at the Delamere home (Theobalds) in Hertfordshire,
							and Louisa Dolignon seems to have acted as his guardian during his time
							at Westminster School. William Vincent wrote to her (and not to
							Southey’s parents) regarding his involvement in <title>The
								Flagellant</title>. Southey, in turn, went from Westminster to the
							Delameres’ house after his suspension from school. Southey later
							recorded his ‘utmost reverence and affection’ for Dolignon.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="50">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="Doyly">Doyly:</term>
						<gloss target="#Doyly"> an acquaintance of Southey’s during his time at
							Westminster School. Kenneth Curry identified him as Thomas D’Oyly
							(1772–1855). However, the contexts in which he figures in Southey’s
							correspondence suggests that a more likely candidate is Sir John D’Oyly
							(1774–1825; <title>DNB</title>), King’s Scholar at Westminster. Whilst
							at Cambridge, he won Sir W. Browne’s Medal for a Latin Ode (1795) and
							the Chancellor’s Second Medal (1796). An excellent linguist, he later
							worked as a civil servant in Ceylon.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="51">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="DuppaRichard">Duppa, Richard (c. 1768–1831;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#DuppaRichard"> writer (mainly on botany, art, literature and
							politics) and draughtsman. Son of William and Susannah Duppa. Educated
							(late in life) at Trinity College, Oxford (matric. 1807); entered Middle
							Temple 1810; graduated LLB Trinity Hall, Cambridge in 1814. His
							publications included: <title>A Brief Account of the Subversion of the
								Papal Government in 1798</title> (1799), <title>A Selection of
								Twelve Heads from the Last Judgment of Michael Angelo</title>
							(1801), <title>Memoirs of a Literary and Political Character</title>
							(1803), and <title>The Life and Literary Works of Michael Angelo
								Buonarotti, with His Poetry and Letters</title> (1806). The latter
							contained translations by Southey and William Wordsworth.</gloss>
						<gloss>Southey and Duppa were introduced by Edmund Seward in Oxford in 1793.
							Duppa was related to Seward and, according to family lore, distantly
							related to Southey. Part of Southey’s circle, he was at one time engaged
							to Mary Page, the cousin of Grosvenor Charles and Horace Walpole
							Bedford. In the 1790s, Southey sought Duppa’s advice about projected
							illustrated editions of his poems. Later, Duppa provided the material on
							art in Southey’s <title>Letters from England</title> (1807).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="52">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="DyerGeorge">Dyer, George (1755–1841;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#DyerGeorge"> author and advocate of political reform. Son of
							John Dyer, a shipwright of Bridewell, London. Educated at Christ’s
							Hospital and Emmanuel College, Cambridge (BA 1778). From the late 1780s
							to mid 1790s he was active in reformist causes, a member of the
							Constitutional Society and author of <title>An Inquiry into the Nature
								of Subscription to the Thirty-Nine Articles</title> (1789, 2nd
							revised edn 1792), <title>Complaints of the Poor People of
								England</title> (1793) and <title>A Dissertation on the Theory and
								Practice of Benevolence</title> (1795). After 1795, he abandoned
							active politics, turning instead to scholarship and literature. He was a
							prolific poet whose works included, <title>Poems, Consisting of Odes and
								Elegies</title> (1792), <title level="m">The Poet’s Fate</title>
							(1797), and <title>Poetics</title> (1812).</gloss>
						<gloss>Dyer met Southey in c. 1794–1795, probably through Coleridge. He was
							enthusiastic about Pantisocracy and encouraged the publication of
								<title>The Fall of Robespierre</title> (1794). He seems to have
							corresponded with Southey from the mid 1790s, but none of these early
							letters survive, making it difficult to judge the actual extent of their
							friendship. It is, however, fair to say, that this has probably been
							underestimated. A handful of letters written by Southey to Dyer from
							later periods do exist. Dyer’s close connections with Southey’s literary
							circle are evidenced in a letter sent to him by Joseph Cottle, 22 April
							1797 now in the Houghton Library (Autograph File: Cottle,
							Joseph).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="53">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="EgertonThomasJohn">Egerton, Thomas and John (both,
							dates unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#EgertonThomasJohn"> London publishers and booksellers.
							Southey and his collaborators Bedford and Wynn, employed the Egertons as
							printers for the first five numbers of the schoolboy magazine <title>The
								Flagellant</title>, which appeared between 1–29 March 1792. The
							fifth issue contained a controversial essay denouncing flogging as an
							invention of the devil. Under pressure from Dr William Vincent, the Head
							Master of Westminster School, the Egertons revealed that Southey was its
							author. Southey was expelled and the Egertons’ involvement with
								<title>The Flagellant</title> ceased. The remaining four issues,
							5–26 April 1792, were printed by the Pall-Mall bookseller and printer
							Edward Jeffrey (dates unknown).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="54">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="EllisGeorge">Ellis, George (1753-1815;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#EllisGeorge">man of letters. Ellis entered parliament in
							1796 as junior member for Seaford; he never spoke in the house, and did
							not stand for re-election. He collaborated with George Canning
							(1770-1827; <title>DNB</title>) and William Gifford on the journal
								<title>The Anti-Jacobin</title>; and he was a friend, from 1801, of
							Walter Scott. Ellis’s <title>Specimens of the Early English
								Poets</title> (1790, 2nd edn. 1801, 3rd edn. 1803) provided the
							model for Southey’s <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>
							(1807).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="55">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley, Peter (1774–1825;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#ElmsleyPeter"> classical scholar. Son of Alexander Elmsley.
							He was named after his uncle, the famous London bookseller from whom he
							inherited a considerable fortune. Educated at Westminster and Christ
							Church, Oxford (matric. 1791, BA 1794, MA 1797, BD and DD 1823), he was
							described as ‘the fattest undergraduate of his day’ (<title level="m"
								>DNB</title>). Ordained and presented to the living of Little
							Horkesley, Essex, on his uncle’s death in 1802 he relinquished his
							duties and income to a curate, though he continued to hold the living
							until 1816. He made a brief move to Edinburgh, where he met the founders
							of the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, to which he became a
							contributor. He returned to London and in 1807 moved to Kent, where he
							lived with his mother until 1816. During this time he produced editions
							of Aristophanes, Sophocles and Euripides and a number of learned papers
							on classical subjects, published in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>
							and other periodicals. He travelled at length in Europe c. 1816–1818 and
							settled in Oxford in 1818. In 1823 (having been unsuccessfully proposed
							for the Regius Chair of Divinity at Oxford and having turned down the
							See of Calcutta) he was elected Camden Professor of Ancient History and
							Principal of St Alban Hall, Oxford, offices he held until his death in
							1825.</gloss>
						<gloss>Southey and Elmsley met at Westminster School and remained lifelong
							friends, though relatively little of what seems to have been an
							extensive correspondence survives. Elmsley was also a great friend of
							Charles Watkin Williams Wynn and the latter erected a memorial tablet to
							him in Christ Church Cathedral, Oxford.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="56">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="EstlinJohnPrior">Estlin, John Prior (1747–1817;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#EstlinJohnPrior"> Unitarian minister, at Lewin’s Mead
							Chapel, Bristol, and school master. Educated at the Warrington Academy,
							he moved to Bristol in 1771. Married Mary Coates (1753–1783) and then
							Susanna Bishop (d. 1842). He was on good terms with a number of writers,
							including Southey (whom he had taught briefly when he took over Mr
							Foot’s school, Bristol), Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Anna Letitia
							Barbauld (1743–1825; <title>DNB</title>). His publications included
								<title>The Nature and Causes of Atheism</title> (1797).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="57">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="EstlinMrs">Estlin, Mrs:</term>
						<gloss target="#EstlinMrs"> Susanna Bishop (d. 1842), the second wife of
							John Prior Estlin.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="58">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="FavellRobert">Favell, Robert (1775–1812):</term>
						<gloss target="#FavellRobert"> soldier. Educated at Christ’s Hospital, where
							he was a friend of Samuel Taylor Coleridge. Obtained an army commission,
							fought in the Peninsular War and was killed at the battle of Salamanca.
							There is some confusion over Favell’s first name — with some sources
							citing it as Joseph or Samuel — see C. A. Prance, <title>Companion to
								Charles Lamb. A Guide to People and Places 1760–1847</title> (1983),
							pp. 112–113 and Duncan Wu, ‘Unpublished drafts of sonnets by Lamb and
							Favell’, <title>Charles Lamb Bulletin</title>, n.s. 75 (1991),
							100.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="59">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="FlowerBenjamin">Flower, Benjamin (1755–1829;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#FlowerBenjamin"> writer and publisher of the radical
							newspaper the <title>Cambridge Intelligencer</title>. In 1799, Flower
							was sentenced to six months imprisonment and a fine of £100 for a libel
							against Richard Watson (1737–1816; <title>DNB</title>), the Bishop of
							Llandaff.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="60">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="FoxLordHolland3">Fox, Henry Richard, 3rd Lord
							Holland (1773-1840; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#FoxLordHolland3">Whig politician and Hispanophile; nephew of
							the Whig politician Charles James Fox (1749-1806; Foreign Secretary
							1782, 1783, 1806; <title>DNB</title>).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="61">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="FreelingFrancis">Freeling, Francis,1st Baronet
							(1764-1836; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#FreelingFrancis"> postal administrator and book collector. A
							supporter of William Pitt (1759-1806; <title>DNB</title>), in the 1790s
							Freeling was involved in monitoring the activities of corresponding
							societies and supporters of the French revolution. A bibliophile, he was
							elected to the fellowship of the Society of Antiquaries in 1801. Southey
							and Freeling were both the sons of Bristol tradesmen. They corresponded
							over financial matters connected to Southey and Joseph Cottle’s 1803
							edition of the works of their fellow Bristolian, Thomas Chatterton
							(1752-1770; <title>DNB</title>).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="62">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="FrickerEdith">Fricker, Edith (1774–1837;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#FrickerEdith"> Southey’s first wife. The third surviving
							child of Stephen Fricker and Martha Rowles. Southey and Edith met as
							children in Bristol. They married in secret on 14 November 1795 at St
							Mary Redcliffe, Bristol. As her sister Sarah later explained, Southey
							‘left ... [Edith] at the Church door’ and the following day departed for
							Spain and Portugal. Edith spent the early days of her marriage living
							with the Cottle sisters and using her maiden name, only reverting to
							‘Southey’ when the secret became public in early 1796. Recent
							biographers of Southey have questioned the state of his marriage,
							particularly given his lively — even flirtatious — friendships with Mary
							Barker and Caroline Bowles, who became his second wife in 1839. Compared
							to these other women, or to her sister Sarah, Edith is a relatively
							shadowy figure, plagued by physical and mental illness. The deaths of
							four of her eight children, in particular that of her daughter Isabel in
							1826, hastened her decline. She suffered a complete collapse in 1834 and
							was taken to The Retreat, the pioneering, Quaker-run asylum in York,
							where she was diagnosed as of ‘unsound mind’ and treated with
							‘purgatives, remedies, [and] leeches’. She was released in 1835 ‘as
							admitted’ — that is, uncured and incurable. Edith spent her final years
							at her home, Greta Hall, where she was cared for by Southey and her
							daughters Bertha and Kate. Southey described her death as a release from
							‘a pitiable state of existence’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="63">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="Frickerfamily">Fricker family:</term>
						<gloss target="#Frickerfamily"> Stephen Fricker and his second wife Martha
							Rowles and their six surviving children: Sarah, Mary, Edith, Martha (b.
							1777), Eliza (b. 1778) and George (b. 1785). The failure of his business
							speculations (including the manufacture of sugar pans) contributed to
							Stephen Fricker’s early death and to a sharp decline in the fortunes of
							his family. The family home was sold, Mrs Fricker moved into lodgings in
							Bristol and opened a dame school, and her three eldest daughters became
							seamstresses, whose clients included Southey’s mother and aunt,
							Elizabeth Tyler. Southey knew the Frickers from childhood and was
							‘partly educated’ with the three eldest girls. The similarity between
							their situation and his own (Southey’s father was also a bankrupt) was
							perhaps an important factor in what was to be a lifelong
							relationship.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="64">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="FrickerGeorge">Fricker, George (1785–1813):</term>
						<gloss target="#FrickerGeorge"> Southey’s only brother-in-law. Southey was
							intermittently successful in gaining him employment, at a bank in
							Bristol in 1800 and on one of Rickman’s statistical projects in 1804.
							Though Southey respected George’s good qualities, he was frustrated by
							his ‘uncommon dullness’. He died at Greta Hall after a long
							illness.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="65">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="FrickerMartha">Fricker, Martha (1777-1850):</term>
						<gloss target="#FrickerMartha">Southey’s sister-in-law. She never married
							and spent her final years on the Isle of Wight, with her sister
							Eliza.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="66">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="FrickerMary">Fricker, Mary (1771–1862):</term>
						<gloss target="#FrickerMary"> Southey’s sister-in-law. The second surviving
							child of Stephen Fricker and Martha Rowles. In the early 1790s she
							worked as an actress in Bath and Bristol theatres. She married Robert
							Lovell in January 1794, in spite of the disapproval of his family. Their
							son, also called Robert, was born in 1795. After Lovell’s death in 1796,
							Southey tried to persuade his family to provide for his widow and child.
							He was only partially successful. The Lovells gave Robert Lovell Junior
							the occasional gift (for example, £20 in 1802) and made some
							contribution to the boy’s early education, but they did not provide
							consistent, long-term support. As a result, Mary and her son were
							dependent upon Southey. They lived with or near to the Southeys for the
							rest of the 1790s and early 1800s and in 1803 accompanied them to their
							new home, Greta Hall. Mary remained with the Southeys after her son’s
							apprenticeship to a London printer. She finally moved out when the house
							was given up after Southey’s death in 1843. She spent her final years
							living with Kate, Southey’s unmarried daughter, and died on 10 August
							1862. She was buried in the Southey grave in Crosthwaite churchyard, on
							the outskirts of Keswick.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="67">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="FrickerSarah">Fricker, Sarah (1770–1845):</term>
						<gloss target="#FrickerSarah"> Southey’s sister-in-law. The eldest surviving
							child of Stephen Fricker and Martha Rowles. Sarah and Southey were
							childhood friends and it was through her that Southey met Robert Lovell
							in late 1793. Sarah married Samuel Taylor Coleridge on 4 October 1795.
							Her relationship with Southey, who provided her with advice and support
							during her later marital difficulties, was affectionate, and at times
							jokey and rumbustious. Indeed, Sarah’s daughter and namesake recorded
							that Southey had been romantically interested in Sarah Fricker first,
							only later turning his attentions to her sister Edith.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="68">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="GiffordWilliam">Gifford, William (1756-1826;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#GiffordWilliam">long known to Southey as a Tory critic and
							editor of <title>The Anti-Jacobin</title>, Gifford became the first
							editor in 1809 of a new conservative journal begun on Southey’s advice –
							the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. Gifford then approached Southey
							through their mutual friend Grosvenor Charles Bedford to be a
							contributor. Gifford continued as editor until 1824, frequently the
							target of Southey’s ire over the cuts and interpolations he made to
							Southey’s contributions. In earlier life a shoemaker, Gifford was the
							author of two powerful verse satires, <title>The Baviad</title> (1791)
							and <title>The Mӕviad</title> (1795).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="69">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="GilbertWilliam">Gilbert, William (1763–c. 1825;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#GilbertWilliam"> poet and astrologer. Born in Antigua, son
							of Nathaniel Gilbert, speaker of the Antiguan House of Assembly. In 1788
							he came to England to work as a lawyer, but suffered a mental collapse
							and was placed in an asylum run by Richard Henderson (1736/7–1792) at
							Hanham near Bristol. (In an earlier career as a schoolmaster, Henderson
							had numbered Joseph Cottle among his pupils.) Gilbert was released after
							a year and went to London, where he worked as an astrologer and maker of
							magic talismans. In 1795 he went to Bristol, where he became friends
							with Southey and Coleridge. In 1796 he published <title>The Hurricane: a
								Theosophical and Western Eclogue</title>. He disappeared in 1798. It
							was thought he had left Bristol in search of the ‘Gilberti’, an African
							tribe with whom he believed he had a spiritual affinity. Southey made
							enquiries after him, but to no effect. Although by 1820 Southey spoke of
							Gilbert as long dead, he was in fact probably still alive, dying c.
							1825.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="70">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="GodwinWilliam">Godwin, William (1756–1836;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#GodwinWilliam"> philosopher and novelist. Southey was an
							early enthusiast for his <title>An Enquiry Concerning Political
								Justice</title> (1793), which he read shortly after its publication.
							He met Godwin in London in 1797 and disliked him.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="71">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="GuthrieJohn">Guthrie, John (d. 1824):</term>
						<gloss target="#GuthrieJohn">bookseller, originally from Aberdeenshire he
							moved to Edinburgh where he was a founder of the firm Tait &amp;
							Guthrie. When he moved to Edinburgh in autumn 1803, Henry Herbert
							Southey lodged with him at 2 Nicolson St.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="72">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HaslewoodJoseph">Haslewood, Joseph (1769–1833;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#HaslewoodJoseph"> London solicitor, who became a well-known
							bibliographer and antiquary. He edited many early English texts and
							created a very important collection of ephemeral literature. Southey
							corresponded with him about the works of Thomas Chatterton (1752-1770;
								<title>DNB</title>).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="73">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HaysMary">Hays, Mary (1759–1843;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#HaysMary"> writer. Brought up in a Dissenting home in
							London, she first found fame with her <title>Cursory Remarks on an
								Enquiry into the Experience and Propriety of Public Worship</title>
							(1792). This propelled her into the circle of radicals around the
							publisher Joseph Johnson (1738-1809; <title>DNB</title>). Hays’s
								<title>Memoirs of Emma Courtney</title> (1796) gained her some
							notoriety, as it was a thinly-disguised version of her relationship with
							the radical William Frend (1757-1841; <title>DNB</title>). She was
							caricatured in, among other places, Charles Lloyd’s <title>Edmund
								Oliver</title> (1798), but her main claim to posthumous fame has
							been her feminist writings, especially <title>An Appeal to the Men of
								Great Britain in Behalf of Women</title> (1798). Southey met Hays in
							London in 1797 and corresponded with her in the early 1800s.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="74">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HazlittWilliam">Hazlitt, William (1778-1830;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#HazlittWilliam">writer and painter. He first met Southey in
							1803, whilst in the Lakes on a commission from Sir George Beaumont to
							paint Coleridge, Hartley Coleridge and Wordsworth. Their relationship
							was, though, to be conducted largely in the public sphere, via the
							medium of newspapers and reviews. The catalyst for so public a
							relationship was undoubtedly Southey’s appointment as Poet Laureate in
							September 1813. Over the next decade or so Hazlitt produced a series of
							reviews and essays devoted to Southey and his works. His observations on
							the new Poet Laureate appeared in the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>
							on 18 and 20 September 1813, followed by his appraisal of the Laureate’s
							first ‘official’ publication (the ode <title>Carmen Triumphale</title>)
							in the pages of the same newspaper on 8 January 1814. His critique was
							continued in the review of <title>The Lay of the Laureate</title>,
							gained new ferocity in pages of the <title>Examiner</title> during the
							1817 controversy over the illicit publication of Southey’s <title>Wat
								Tyler</title>, continued in the <title>Lectures on the English
								Poets</title> (1818-19) and culminated in the pen-portrait of
							Southey in <title>The Spirit of the Age</title> (1825).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="75">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HeberRichard">Heber, Richard (1774–1833;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#HeberRichard"> book-collector. Son of Reginald Heber,
							clergyman and landowner. Educated at Brasenose College, Oxford (BA 1796,
							MA, 1797). Heber edited some minor classical writers, but his main
							interest was his book collection, which finally totalled over 100,000
							volumes housed in eight different locations. Though he concentrated on
							early English poetry and drama his library included classical works and
							a wide selection of European and Latin American literature. Heber was
							exceptionally generous in lending his books, and let Southey use his
							copy of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>. Heber was MP for Oxford
							University 1821-1825, but resigned and spent several years on the
							continent after rumours of a homosexual relationship began to circulate.
							However, he was never prosecuted and eventually returned to
							England.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="76">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HillHerbert">Hill, Herbert (1750–1828):</term>
						<gloss target="#HillHerbert"> Southey’s maternal uncle. Hill was the product
							of a second marriage, and after his father’s death was left short of
							money (even having to ‘pay his own school bills when it was in his
							power’) and on extremely bad terms with his older half-brother. Hill was
							educated at Christ Church, Oxford (BA 1772, MA 1774). From 1792–1807, he
							was chaplain to the British factory at Lisbon. On his return to England,
							Hill took up a living at Staunton-Upon-Wye, remaining there until 1810
							when the Duke of Bedford presented him to a living in Streatham. In 1808
							Hill married a woman twenty-five years his junior, Catherine Bigg (b. c.
							1775), a friend of Jane Austen (1775–1817; <title>DNB</title>). The
							marriage produced six surviving children, all of whom were on good terms
							with Southey and his family. Hill’s son and namesake, Herbert Hill
							Junior (1810–1892), married Southey’s daughter Bertha in 1839.</gloss>
						<gloss>Hill took a paternal interest in his nephews, and helped finance
							Southey’s education. Hill’s concern about Southey’s refusal to take the
							path mapped out for him (a path leading to ordination), his relationship
							with Edith Fricker, and his politics, led him to visit England in 1795.
							He returned to Portugal with Southey in tow. Oblivious to the fact that
							his nephew had married Edith the day before their departure, Hill used
							every opportunity to introduce Southey to more suitable women.
							Nevertheless, the time Southey spent with his uncle in 1795–1796 greatly
							strengthened their relationship, which remained close until Hill’s death
							in 1828. Hill encouraged his nephew’s interests in Spanish and
							Portuguese history and literature, and later bought books and
							manuscripts on his behalf. Southey dedicated his
								<title>Colloquies</title> (1829) to his uncle.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="77">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HillMargaret">Hill, Margaret (known as ‘Peggy’
							and, occasionally, &#8216;Margery&#8217;) (d. 1801):</term>
						<gloss target="#HillMargaret"> Southey’s cousin, probably the daughter of
							his mother’s brother Joseph Hill.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="78">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HillThomas">Hill, Thomas (1760–1840;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#HillThomas"> book-collector and part-proprietor of the
								<title>Monthly Mirror</title>. Born in Lancaster in May 1760, he
							went at an early age to London, where for many years he carried on an
							extensive business as a drysalter at Queenhithe. He patronized Robert
							Bloomfield (1766–1823; <title>DNB</title>), whose <title>The Farmer’s
								Boy</title> he read in manuscript and recommended to a publisher. In
							his role as part-owner of the <title>Monthly Mirror</title> he
							befriended one of its contributors, the youthful Henry Kirke White
							(1785-1806; <title>DNB</title>). Southey believed that Hill owned
							probably ‘the best existing collection of English poetry’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="79">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HoodAlexanderCaptain">Hood, Alexander
							(1758-98):</term>
						<gloss target="#HoodAlexanderCaptain"> naval officer, Captain of the <hi
								rend="ital">Mars</hi>, in which Tom Southey served. Killed 21
							April 1798 when the <hi rend="ital">Mars</hi> captured the French
							vessel, <hi rend="ital">L’Hercule</hi>.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="80">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HoodAlexanderViscount">Hood, Alexander, Viscount
							Bridport (1726–1814; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#HoodAlexanderViscount"> a cousin of the Captain of the <hi
								rend="ital">Mars</hi>, Vice Admiral of England and Commander of the
							Channel Fleet 1795-1800.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="81">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HookJames">Hook, James (c. 1772–1828;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#HookJames"> Dean of Worcester and brother of the writer and
							hoaxer Theodore Hook (1788–1841; <title>DNB</title>). Educated at
							Westminster School and St Mary Hall, Oxford (his admission to Christ
							Church was blocked in 1792 because of his involvement in ‘acts of
							insubordination’ whilst at school). Hook was one of the editors of the
							schoolboy magazine, <title>The Trifler</title>, and a keen musician and
							artist. He was a friend of Southey’s during his time at Westminster, but
							their friendship did not last beyond schooldays.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="82">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HorsemanJohn">Horseman, John (1776–1844):</term>
						<gloss target="#HorsemanJohn"> clergyman. The son of an Oxfordshire cleric,
							he was educated at Corpus Christi, Oxford (BA 1795), where he remained
							as a fellow from 1795–1819. He was Rector of Heydon and Little Chishill
							from 1810. He was a university friend of Southey’s. Although they lost
							touch in the mid 1790s, in 1835 after a gap of ‘one and forty years’
							Horseman wrote to Southey recalling their old acquaintance. At the time
							of their reunion, Southey was not aware that at the height of the
								<title>Wat Tyler</title> controversy in 1817, a ‘John Horseman’ —
							presumably the same one — had sent his political opponent William Smith
							(1756–1835) a transcript of another production of the Poet Laureate’s
							radical youth — ‘To the Exiled Patriots’. Horseman’s letter is now in
							the William R. Perkins Library, Duke University.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="83">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HoweThomas">Howe, Thomas (dates unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#HoweThomas"> clergyman. Possibly the son of John Howe of
							Honiton, Devon. Educated at Emmanuel College, Cambridge and Balliol
							College, Oxford. Howe was Rector of Huntspill, Somerset 1804–1823. He
							was Southey’s tutor at Oxford in 1793–1794.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="84">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="HucksJoseph">Hucks, Joseph (1772–1800):</term>
						<gloss target="#HucksJoseph"> writer. Educated at Cambridge, Hucks
							accompanied Samuel Taylor Coleridge on his 1794 tour, publishing an
							account — <title>A Pedestrian Tour Through North Wales, in a Series of
								Letters</title> — the following year. Southey — and Coleridge —
							renewed their acquaintance with him during their visit to Exeter in 1799
							and Hucks contributed three poems to Southey’s <title>Annual
								Anthology</title> (1800). He died of consumption in 1800. In an
							unpublished preliminary notice to his <title>Specimens of the Later
								English Poets</title> (1807) Southey recalled the ‘many pleasant
							&amp; rememberable hours’ he and Hucks had spent together.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="85">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="JacksonWilliam">Jackson, William
							(1748-1809):</term>
						<gloss target="#Jackson,William"> builder, owner and co-occupier of Greta
							Hall.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="86">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="JardineAlexander">Jardine, Alexander (d. 1799;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#JardineAlexander"> army officer and author. He was appointed
							to the post of Consul in Galicia in 1791. He was a friend of William
							Godwin and Joel Barlow (1754–1812; <title>DNB</title>), and his writings
							included <title level="m">Letters from Barbary, France, Spain, Portugal
								&amp;c.</title> (1788). He and Southey met during the latter’s
							1795–1796 visit to the Iberian peninsula. He figures in both Southey’s
							correspondence from this period and in <title level="m">Letters Written
								During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title>
							(1797).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="87">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="JardineMrs">Jardine, Mrs (first name and dates
							unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#JardineMrs"> widow of David Jardine (1766–1797), Minister of
							the Trim Street Unitarian Chapel, Bath. She was the daughter of George
							Webster of Hampstead. The Jardines owned a small estate at Pickwick,
							near Bath.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="88">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey, Francis, Lord (1773–1850;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#JeffreyFrancis">Scottish, Whig lawyer and critic, from 1803
							editor of the <title>Edinburgh Review</title> and, as such, Southey’s
							bete noire for damning reviews of his, Wordsworth’s and Coleridge’s
							poetry (Jeffrey is credited with coining the term ‘Lake school’); see
								<title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 1 (October 1802), 63-83. Southey
							affected indifference but was acutely sensitive to Jeffrey’s reviews.
							Jeffrey’s reluctance to support war with Napoleonic France also incurred
							Southey’s wrath, as appears in the notes to <title>Carmen
								Triumphale</title> (1814), in which Southey enjoys demonstrating how
							the <title>Edinburgh</title>’s predictions of defeat were erroneous as
							well as morale-sapping. The two men met in Edinburgh in October 1805,
							and Southey ever after consoled himself for the printed criticisms by
							remembering Jeffrey’s diminutive stature.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="89">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="JenningsJames">Jennings, James (1772–1833;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#JenningsJames"> writer. Born in Huntspill, Somerset, son of
							a village shopkeeper, John Jennings, and his wife Elizabeth Fear.
							Educated locally and at North Petherton School. Apprenticed to a Bristol
							apothecary in 1786. He contributed poems to the <title>European
								Magazine</title> and in 1794 published <title>The Times</title>, a
							satire. Jennings moved to London shortly after his marriage to Charlotte
							Sawier, probably the only daughter of Southey’s landlady Mary Sawier, in
							1795. He returned to work in his family’s shop in 1801 and remained in
							Huntspill until the mid-1810s, when economic depression led to the
							failure of the business. He continued with his literary pursuits,
							contributing to the <title>Monthly Magazine</title> (from 1807) and
							publishing <title>Poems, Consisting of the Mysteries of Mendip, the
								Magic Ball</title> (1810). He returned to London in 1817 and worked
							as a professional writer, with some support from Sir William Paxton, a
							wealthy banker. His works included the <title>Family Cyclopaedia</title>
							(1821), <title>Observations on Some of the Dialects of the West of
								England</title> (1825) and <title>Ornithologia</title> (1828). He
							founded the short-lived Metropolitan Literary Institution in 1823 and
							was editor of the <title>Metropolitan Literary Journal</title>
							(1824).</gloss>
						<gloss> Jennings met Southey (and Coleridge) in Bristol in c. 1794. Although
							they were not close friends, he and Southey corresponded (the
							correspondence has not survived) and remained in contact until c. 1828.
							Jennings was a great admirer of Southey’s writing, but the admiration
							was not reciprocated. Southey nicknamed him ‘poor Trauma’ and ‘the
							traumatic poet’, though he admired Jennings’s ‘moral character’.
							Jennings shared Southey’s interest in educational methods, and in 1813,
							in collaboration with the local rector at Huntspill, established a
							school conducted on Lancaster and Bell’s monitorial system. Jennings
							included anecdotes of Southey and Coleridge’s early careers in the
								<title>Metropolitan Literary Journal</title> (1824).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="90">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="JervisAdmiral">Jervis, Admiral John, 1st Earl of
							St Vincent (1735-1823; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#JervisAdmiral"> Commander in Chief of the British
							Mediterranean Fleet 1796-9, 1800-1801, First Sea Lord 1801-1804.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="91">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="KellyMontague">Kelly, Montague Henry (dates
							unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#KellyMontague"> educated at Westminster School (adm. 1786).
							A friend of Southey’s during his schooldays.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="92">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="KiddJohn">Kidd, John (1775–1851):</term>
						<gloss target="#KiddJohn"> doctor and author of medical treatises. Educated
							at Westminster School and Christ Church, Oxford (matric. 1793, BA 1797).
							A friend of Southey’s during his time at Oxford, and possibly a school
							friend as well.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="93">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="KingJohn">King, John [Nicholas Johann Koenig]
							(1766-1846):</term>
						<gloss target="#KingJohn"> Bristol-based surgeon, painter and linguist,
							originally from Berne, Switzerland. He came to England at some stage in
							the 1790s and studied medicine under John Abernethy (1764-1831;
								<title>DNB</title>) at St Bartholomew’s Hospital, before settling at
							Clifton in Bristol. He married Emmeline Edgeworth (1770-1817), a sister
							of the novelist Maria (1768-1849; <title>DNB</title>). Southey came to
							know King well when he succeeded Davy in his role at the Pneumatic
							Institution in 1801. Southey saw much less of King after he moved to
							Keswick in 1803, but he continued to speak warmly of his personal
							qualities and medical skill.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="94">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="KosterJohnTheodore">Koster, John Theodore
							(c.1750-1828):</term>
						<gloss target="#KosterJohnTheodore"> English sugar merchant, whom Southey
							met in Portugal during his visit of 1800-1801 and again in Liverpool in
							1804. Koster lodged in Keswick in 1815-1816 after suffering heavy
							financial losses and later relocated to France, where he died at
							Bordeaux. Koster’s home in Lisbon was a meeting place for those
							interested in the arts and sciences and he was a man of wide interests,
							a member of the Portuguese Royal Academy of Sciences and a writer on
							economic matters, including <title>A Statement of the Trade in Gold
								Bullion</title> (1811). His son, Henry Koster (1793-1820) was also a
							friend of Southey’s.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="95">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LambCharles">Lamb, Charles (1775–1834;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#LambCharles"> essayist. Educated at Christ’s Hospital, where
							he was a friend of Samuel Taylor Coleridge, he was later a clerk at the
							East India Company. Lamb and Southey met in 1795. Their relationship
							started to blossom in 1797, when Lamb — accompanied by Charles Lloyd —
							paid Southey an unexpected visit. Southey and Lamb shared an interest in
							Francis Quarles (1592–1644; <title>DNB</title>). They quarrelled briefly
							— and publicly — in 1823, but were reconciled. Although they
							corresponded, Southey’s letters to Lamb have not survived.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="96">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LambMaryAnne">Lamb, Mary Anne (1764-1847;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#LambMaryAnne"> writer. Sister of Charles Lamb. She suffered
							from bouts of insanity and in 1796 she killed their mother. After this
							incident she was cared for by her brother or in asylums. The siblings
							wrote <title>Tales from Shakespeare</title> (1809) together.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="97">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LambThomasDavis">Lamb, Thomas Davis (1775–1818;
								<title>Hist P</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#LambThomasDavis"> politician. The eldest son of Thomas
							Phillipps Lamb and his wife Elizabeth Davis. Educated at Westminster
							(adm. 1788); Edinburgh University (1792) and Christ Church, Oxford
							(matric. Dec 1793). Lamb’s family were wealthy, politically influential
							and well-connected. His father was the government manager at Rye,
							Sussex. Lamb’s career benefited from the patronage of Lord Liverpool
							(1727–1808; <title>DNB</title>) and his eldest son, Lord Hawkesbury
							(1770–1828; <title>DNB</title>), a future Prime Minister. Lamb was
							private secretary to Hawkesbury, then Secretary of State for Foreign
							Affairs, 1801–1802, and in 1802 was offered but rejected the consulship
							at Lisbon, a post worth between £2000–2500 per year. He sat as an M.P.
							for Rye from 1802–1806, though he seems never to have spoken in the
							House of Commons. He vacated his seat when appointed to the post of Law
							Clerk at the Home Office by the Ministry of ‘Talents’. Following in the
							footsteps of his grandfather and father, he was Mayor of Rye from
							1803–1804, 1809–1810 and 1816–1817. He never married.</gloss>
						<gloss>Southey described Lamb as ‘one of my oldest — &amp; once one of my
							most intimate friends’. The two met whilst pupils at Westminster and
							Southey stayed with Lamb’s family in Rye on more than one occasion. They
							drifted apart (though, Southey later noted, ‘without dissention’) during
							Southey’s time at Oxford. Lamb seems to have made an effort to renew
							their acquaintance, seeking Southey out in London in 1802. In later
							years, however, Southey’s opinion of him soured. He described him as one
							who had ‘discarded decency’ and on reading of Lamb’s death in a
							newspaper admitted that he had: ‘ ... thought more of him, poor fellow,
							in consequence, than I had done for the last four-and-twenty years ...
							[He] had become a mere idle heir of fortune, and not having his estates
							to manage while his father lived, had not even that occupation to keep
							him from frivolities. He was an old man at thirty, and that too being of
							a family in which it is degeneracy to die at an age short of
							fourscore.’</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="98">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LambThomasPhillipps">Lamb, Thomas Phillipps
							(?1752–1819; <title>Hist P</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#LambThomasPhillipps"> politician. The father of Thomas Davis
							Lamb. He was married to Elizabeth Davis and lived at Mountsfield Lodge,
							near Rye. By the mid-eighteenth century the Lamb family had become the
							dominant force on Rye corporation and wielded great political influence
							in the borough. Lamb was the government agent in Rye and sat as an M.P.
							for the town 1812–1816 and 1819, though (like his son) he is not known
							to have spoken in the House of Commons. He was Mayor of Rye some 18
							times between 1775–1817. Southey twice visited the Lambs home in Rye in
							1791 and 1792 and was on excellent terms with Thomas Phillipps Lamb,
							perhaps seeing him as a surrogate father-figure. Their correspondence
							lapsed during Southey’s time at Oxford and was briefly renewed in
							1798.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="99">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LandorWalterSavage">Landor, Walter Savage
							(1775-1864; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#LandorWalterSavage">writer and poet (in English and Latin)
							whose 1798 gothic poem Gebir, Southey declared, contained ‘some of the
							most exquisite poetry in the language’. Landor inherited wealth in 1805
							and in 1808 met Southey at Bristol, offering to pay for the publication
							of future poems that Southey might write. Thus encouraged, Southey
							completed <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), sending drafts to
							Landor, and <title>Roderick the Last of the Goths</title> (1814). In
							1812 Landor himself published a poem on Spain, <title>Count
								Julian</title>, with Southey’s help. In 1808, to Southey’s
							admiration, Landor enlisted as a volunteer in the Spanish army fighting
							Napoleon in the Peninsula. Returning in 1809, he lived at Llanthony
							Abbey in Wales, where Southey visited him in 1811. Landor left England
							to live in France and Italy in 1814. He received Southey’s advice on his
								<title>Imaginary Conversations</title> (1824-46), visited Southey in
							Keswick in 1832, returned to England in 1836 and met Southey for the
							last time in Bristol in 1837. In 1843 Landor published a tribute after
							Southey’s death in <title>The Examiner</title>; he also sought
							advancement for Charles Cuthbert, Southey’s son, in the church. Admired
							by Dickens, Browning, Swinburne and Trollope, Landor spent his final
							years in Italy and died in Florence.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="100">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LeGriceSamuel">Le Grice, Samuel
							(1775–1802):</term>
						<gloss target="#LeGriceSamuel"> soldier. The younger brother of Coleridge’s
							school fellow, Charles Valentine Le Grice (1773–1858). Educated at
							Christ’s Hospital, where he was a contemporary and friend of Charles
							Lamb, and Trinity College, Cambridge. He obtained an army commission and
							died in Jamaica.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="101">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LewisRichard">Lewis, Richard (1771–1843):</term>
						<gloss target="#LewisRichard"> clergyman and schoolmaster. Educated at
							Balliol and Corpus Christi Colleges, Oxford (matric. 1792, BA 1796). He
							became a curate and master of the grammar school in Honiton, Devon. A
							friend of Southey’s at Oxford, they lost touch in later years.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="102">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot, Nicholas (c.
							1771/2–1847):</term>
						<gloss target="#LightfootNicholas"> clergyman and schoolmaster. Son of
							Nicholas Lightfoot of Moretonhampstead, Devon. Educated at Balliol
							College, Oxford (matric. 1790, BA 1794). Perpetual curate for
							Churcheton, Devon from 1795 and Rector of Stockleigh Pomeroy from
							1831–1847. Southey met Lightfoot at Balliol and their friendship endured
							until his death. Southey briefly considered sending his brother Edward
							Southey to be educated by Lightfoot and in later life stayed with him
							during visits to the south west of England.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="103">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LloydCharles">Lloyd, Charles (1775–1839;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#LloydCharles"> poet. Eldest child of Charles, a wealthy
							Quaker banker, and his wife Mary. He matriculated at Caius College,
							Cambridge in 1798 but did not take his degree. He married Sophia
							Pemberton in 1799 and they moved to Ambleside in 1800. His works
							included: contributions to Samuel Taylor Coleridge’s
								<title>Poems</title> (1797), <title>Blank Verse</title> (1798)
							(co-authored with Charles Lamb), the controversial roman-&#224;-clef
								<title level="m">Edmund Oliver</title> (1798), <title>Nugae
								Canorae</title> (1819), <title>Desultory Thoughts in London</title>
							(1821), <title>Poetical Essays on the Character of Pope</title> (1821),
							and <title>The Duke d&#8217;Ormond</title> (1822). Lloyd’s later life
							was clouded by mental illness. He was briefly confined in the Quaker-run
							asylum The Retreat, York and died in a sanatorium near
							Versailles.</gloss>
						<gloss>Lloyd met Southey at Burton in August 1797, when he and Charles Lamb
							unexpectedly turned up on Southey’s doorstep. Lloyd remained with
							Southey and his family for several months. Southey recognised in him a
							fellow man of strong emotions, a kindred — yet also unlike — spirit, and
							worried that Lloyd’s ‘feelings ... are not so blunt as we could wish
							them — or as they should be for his own happiness’. Indeed Lloyd’s
							continued presence was increasingly unwelcome and in 1798 his
							tale-telling led to a major quarrel between Southey and Coleridge which
							was not healed until 1799. After Southey moved to Keswick in 1803, Lloyd
							was on the fringes of his circle. In his edition of Cowper (1836–1837),
							Southey made his final public observations on Lloyd’s tragic history:
							‘[his] intellectual powers were of a very high order ... when in company
							with persons who were not informed of his condition, no one could descry
							in him the slightest appearance of a deranged mind.’</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="104">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LongmanThomas">Longman, Thomas Norton (1771-1842;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#LongmanThomas"> senior partner in a long-established and
							prestigious firm of London publishers. Southey began publishing with
							Longman and his partners in 1799 and their association continued until
							his final collection, <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837-1838). Southey
							often jokingly referred to the firm as ‘the Long Men’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="105">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LoshJames">Losh, James (1763–1833;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#LoshJames"> barrister. Second son of John Losh. Born at
							Woodside, Carlisle, he was educated at Trinity College, Cambridge (BA
							1786) and Lincoln’s Inn (called to the Bar 1789). He visited Paris in
							1792 and on his return to England moved in a circle of metropolitan and
							Cambridge-based radicals and reformers that included George Dyer,
							William Godwin, John Horne Tooke (1736–1812; <title>DNB</title>), John
							Tweddell (1769–1799; <title>DNB</title>), Felix Vaughan (dates unknown),
							and William Wordsworth. In 1795–1796, ill-health forced his relocation
							to Bath, where he moved in the same circles as Southey. Losh was amongst
							the earliest readers of the manuscript of the first complete version of
								<title>Madoc</title> and had literary ambitions of his own,
							publishing an edition of Milton’s <title>Areopagitica</title> (1791) and
							a translation of Benjamin Constant’s <title>Observations on the Strength
								of the Present Government in France</title> (1797). He married
							Cecilia Baldwin in February 1798 and moved permanently to Newcastle at
							the end of the same year. In later life he was a successful lawyer,
							businessman and local politician.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="106">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="Lovellfamily">Lovell family:</term>
						<gloss target="#Lovellfamily"> a family of Bristol-based Quakers and
							a family of Bristol-based Quakers and pin manufacturers. Robert Lovell (1746-1804) and his first wife Edith Bourne (1745-1782) had two sons, Joseph and Robert (Southey’s brother-in-law), and five daughters. Lovell’s second marriage to Lydia Hill (1754-1816) produced five more children. Southey was on reasonable terms with all
							the Lovells, but their relationship was clouded by struggles over
							adequate financial provision for the son and widow of Robert
							Lovell.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="107">
						<hi rend="bold">Lovell, Mary: <hi rend="ital">see</hi> Fricker, Mary
							(1771-1862)</hi>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="108">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LovellRobert">Lovell, Robert (1771–1796;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#LovellRobert"> poet. Born in Bristol, the son of a wealthy
							Quaker manufacturer (initially of cabinets and later of pins), and his
							first wife Edith Bourne, a Quaker minister. Lovell possibly entered the
							manufacturing business (on his death he was described as a pin
							manufacturer) but was ill at ease in the commercial world. In 1794 he
							married Mary Fricker. His family disapproved of the match because she
							was not a Quaker and had worked as an actress. Their son, also named
							Robert, was born in 1795. Lovell died at Bristol on 3 May 1796 of a
							fever contracted on a trip to Salisbury and exacerbated by refusing to
							take medical advice before returning home. One of his final letters to
							his wife is in the Huntington Library, San Marino, another in Bristol
							Reference Library. Lovell’s father was reluctant to provide regular
							financial support for Mary Lovell and her child, and both became part of
							Southey’s extended household.</gloss>
						<gloss>Lovell and Southey were introduced by Sarah Fricker in Bristol in
							late 1793. Lovell was also a poet, his <title>Bristol: A Satire</title>
							appeared in 1794, and he and Southey embarked on a period of
							collaboration: planning two co-authored collections, only one of which
							was published under the pseudonyms ‘Bion’ [Southey] and ‘Moschus’
							[Lovell] in late 1794. Lovell was also involved in the 1794 revisions to
							Southey’s <title>Joan of Arc</title>. The advent of Coleridge in
							summer–autumn 1794 seems to have led (at least temporarily) to a
							reorientation of literary relationships. Lovell was pushed to the
							margins. His contribution to <title level="m">The Fall of
								Robespierre</title> was dropped and Coleridge was openly critical of
							his poetry. Lovell was, however, involved in Pantisocracy and it was
							through him that Southey and Coleridge were introduced to Joseph Cottle.
							After Lovell’s death, Southey tried — and failed — to produce a
							subscription edition of his poems, to raise money for his widow and
							child. However, Lovell’s writings were included in the <title>Annual
								Anthology</title> (1799 and 1800) and <title>Specimens of the Later
								English poets</title> (1807). In a notice published in
								<title>Literary Memoirs of Living Authors of Great Britain</title>
							(1798), David Rivers described Lovell’s poetry as being ‘entitled to
							considerable distinction’. Southey described receiving the news of
							Lovell’s death as ‘the most sudden check I ever experienced’. The full
							extent of their relationship is difficult to gauge because of the
							survival of only two letters from what must have been an extensive
							correspondence.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="109">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="LovellRobertJr">Lovell, Robert, Junior
							(1795-1836):</term>
						<gloss target="#LovellRobertJr"> the son of Mary and Robert Lovell, his
							father’s early death left him with few prospects (significantly less
							than those of Samuel Taylor Coleridge’s children, whose paternal
							relations were capable of greater generosity). In 1803 the money paid by
							the Lovell family for his education ceased. Southey and John May tried
							to get Robert Lovell Junior into Christ’s Hospital. They failed. The boy
							was apprenticed to a London printer and effectively separated from his
							mother, who lived with the Southeys in Keswick. The impact of this on
							his character seems to have been profound. In 1836 his first cousin Sara
							Coleridge described his lack of social skills: ‘From nine years old he
							has had to shift and scramble a good deal for himself, to bear up
							against a hard world which would have crushed &lt;or injured&gt; the
							frame it did not render to a certain degree tough &amp; unyielding ...
							[he] never had the opportunity of acquiring a taste for domestic,
							scarcely even for social enjoyment: we ought not to wonder that he is
							deficient in many qualities which can only be fostered thereby.’ Robert
							Lovell Junior predeceased his mother. He disappeared whilst on a
							European walking tour in 1836.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="110">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="MaberGeorgeMartin">Maber, George Martin (d.
							1844):</term>
						<gloss target="#MaberGeorgeMartin"> clergyman. Educated at St Paul’s School,
							London and then at Cambridge. He was personal chaplain to Lord Bute and
							from 1795 Rector of Merthyr Tydfil. Maber and Southey met during a
							voyage to Portugal in November 1795.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="111">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="MauriceMichael">Maurice, Michael
							(1766-1855):</term>
						<gloss target="#MauriceMichael"> Unitarian minister and schoolmaster. Born
							at Eastwood, Yorkshire, he was educated at Leeds Grammar, Hoxton Academy
							and Hackney College. In 1787 he converted to Unitarianism. From
							1787-1792 he was assistant minister of the Old Meeting, Great Yarmouth
							Norfolk. He was a foundation member of the Unitarian Society in 1791 and
							in 1792 was elected evening preacher at the chapel at Hackney in which
							Joseph Priestly preached in the mornings. In 1794 he married Priscilla
							Hurry, daughter of a Yarmouth timber merchant. They had ten children, of
							whom the fifth was the theologian Frederick Denison Maurice (1805–1872;
								<title>DNB</title>). Maurice was distantly connected by marriage to
							William Taylor. The latter was involved in securing a place for Henry
							Herbert Southey at the school Maurice ran at Normanston manor house,
							near the Suffolk port of Lowestoft.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="112">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="MayJohn">May, John (1775–1856):</term>
						<gloss target="#MayJohn"> merchant, financier and business agent. A member
							of a wealthy family, both his father (Joseph) and grandfather were
							successful merchants in Lisbon. He was educated at Newcome’s Academy,
							Hackney, where he was taught by George Coleridge, with whom he became
							lifelong friends. May went to Lisbon in 1793, in order to learn the
							family trade, returning to England in 1796. May married Susannah Frances
							Livius in 1799. The marriage produced four children. May and Southey met
							in Portugal in 1796. Their friendship was to last until the latter’s
							death. May acted as a financial adviser and agent to Southey, lending
							him money — including sums to finance Henry Herbert Southey’s education
							— and purchasing goods on his behalf. Southey reciprocated when May
							experienced a severe financial crisis in 1821 by lending him his life
							savings of £620. May visited the Southeys on several occasions and acted
							as godfather to Southey’s two eldest children — Margaret Edith
							(1802–1803) and Edith May (1803–1871), the latter named in his honour.
								<title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816) was
							dedicated to him ‘in testimony of the highest esteem and
							affection’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="113">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="MontaguBasil">Montagu, Basil (1770–1851;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#MontaguBasil"> lawyer and author, illegitimate son of John
							Montagu, 4th Earl of Sandwich (1718–1792; <title>DNB</title>) and the
							actress Martha Ray (d. 1779; <title>DNB</title>). Montague, like
							Southey, was a member of Gray’s Inn, and was called to the Bar in 1798.
							He was a friend of William Wordsworth and Samuel Taylor Coleridge and in
							1795 Wordsworth and his sister, Dorothy, undertook the upbringing of his
							two-year old son, Basil (1793-1830), by his first wife.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="114">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="MoreHannah">More, Hannah (1745–1833;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#MoreHannah"> writer and philanthropist. Southey and More met
							in October 1795, when he visited her house at Cowslip Green, just
							outside Bristol.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="115">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="MorganJohnJames">Morgan, John James (d.
							1820):</term>
						<gloss target="#MorganJohnJames"> businessman. His friendship with Southey
							dated from their time as pupils at Williams’ School, Bristol. From
							1810–1816, Morgan and his wife took in Samuel Taylor Coleridge and
							attempted to cure him of his opium addiction. When Morgan’s finances
							collapsed in 1813, Southey, Charles Lamb and other friends contributed
							to an annuity for him.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="116">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="MorganMary">Morgan, Mary (b. 1782):</term>
						<gloss target="#MorganMary"> the wife of one of Southey’s oldest friends,
							John James Morgan.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="117">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="NaresRobert">Nares, Robert (1753–1829;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#NaresRobert"> philologist, clergyman and reviewer. From
							1779–1783 Nares was tutor to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn and his older
							brother, Watkin. He was Usher at Westminster School from 1786–1788,
							where he continued his tutoring of the Wynn boys and where he
							undoubtedly met Charles Wynn’s friend Southey. In 1793 Nares was the
							founder-editor of the pro-government review the <title>British
								Critic</title>.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="118">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="NicholsJohn">Nichols, John [as Editor of the
								<title>Gentleman’s Magazine</title>] (1745-1826;
							<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#NicholsJohn">editor and owner of the <title>Gentleman’s
								Magazine</title>, 1792-1826. Printer, author and noted antiquarian.
							Among his many works was <title>Literary Anecdotes of the Eighteenth
								Century</title> (1812-1815).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="119">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="OpieAmelia">Opie, Amelia (1769–1853;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#OpieAmelia"> writer. Born in Norwich, her father was the
							physician James Alderson (d. 1825). Brought up in radical and Unitarian
							circles, she published poetry in the radical Norwich periodical,
								<title>The Cabinet</title>, in 1794. In 1798 she married the
							painter, John Opie (1761-1807; <title>DNB</title>) and moved to London,
							only returning to Norwich on his death in 1807. Opie contributed poems
							to Southey’s <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799) and (1800) and
							became a prolific novelist after the success of <title>Father and
								Daughter</title> (1801). In 1825 she converted to Quakerism and
							devoted the rest of her life to charitable works.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="120">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="PalmerMiss">Palmer, Miss:</term>
						<gloss target="#PalmerMiss"> a close friend of Southey’s aunt, Elizabeth
							Tyler. Her father was John Palmer (1702/3–1788), proprietor of the
							Theatre Royal, Bath, and her only brother the theatre proprietor and
							postal reformer John Palmer (1742–1818; <title>DNB</title>).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="121">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ParryCalebHillier">Parry, Caleb Hillier
							(1755-1832; <title>DNB </title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#ParryCalebHillier">physician. He was educated at the
							Warrington Academy and Edinburgh and settled in Bath in November 1779.
							He developed a large practice and participated in local scientific and
							agricultural societies. His <title>An Inquiry into the Symptoms and
								Causes of the Syncope Anginosa Commonly Called Angina
								Pectoris</title> (1799) was the first monograph on the pathology of
							angina pectoris. Parry was a friend of Edward Jenner (1749-1823;
								<title>DNB</title>), and dedicatee of the latter’s book on
							vaccination. His celebrity patients included Edmund Burke (1729/30-1797;
								<title>DNB</title>). He was the father of Charles Henry Parry
							(1779-1860; <title>DNB</title>), who was a companion of Coleridge on his
							visit to the Harz Mountains in 1799. Parry and Southey undoubtedly knew
							each other via mutual friends in Bath. They corresponded in 1798 about a
							print of Joan of Arc.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="122">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ParsonsJohn">Parsons, John (1761-1819):</term>
						<gloss target="#ParsonsJohn"> Master of Balliol College, Oxford
							1798-1819.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="123">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="PeacheyWilliam">Peachy, William, Colonel and
							later Lieutenant-General (c. 1763-1838):</term>
						<gloss target="#PeacheyWilliam">a Keswick resident, M.P. for Yarmouth
							(1797-1802) and Taunton (1826-30). An officer in the Wiltshire militia
							and a convivial host at his home in Keswick and later on Derwent Isle,
							Derwentwater. Southey was very fond of Peachy’s wife, Emma Frances
							Charter, for whom he wrote a poetic epitaph when she died in 1809. His
							third daughter, Emma (February 1808-May 1809), was named after her.
							Others in the Peachy circle who visited the Lakes were his
							sister-in-law Elizabeth Charter and her uncle Sir Charles Malet
							(1752-1815) and his family, and Peachy’s second wife, a widow, Mrs
							James Henry.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="124">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="Peacockunknown">Peacock (first name and dates
							unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#Peacockunknown"> Southey lodged with Peacock and his wife in
							Newington Butts in 1797. Peacock was involved in the book trade,
							possibly as a travelling salesman. The Peacocks were unhappily married
							and later in life Mrs Peacock was central in having her husband
							committed to a private asylum. On at least two occasions, Peacock wrote
							to Southey from his ‘place of confinement’ and in 1816 Southey made
							enquiries about his case.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="125">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="PeckwellRobertHenry">Peckwell, Robert Henry (later
							Blosset; 1776–1823):</term>
						<gloss target="#PeckwellRobertHenry"> lawyer. Eldest son of Rev. Henry and
							Bella Peckwell. In 1811, he assumed his mother’s surname. Educated
							Westminster (adm. 1785) and Christ Church, Oxford (matric. 1792, BA
							1796, MA 1799). Admitted to Lincoln’s Inn 1795, called to the Bar 1801;
							Serjeant-at-Law 1809. Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Bengal,
							1821; knighted 1822. Author of <title>Cases on Controverted Elections in
								the Second Parliament of the United Kingdom</title> (1805–1806). He
							never married. Peckwell was a friend of Southey’s during his time at
							Westminster School and Oxford.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="126">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="PeggeChristopher">Pegge, Christopher (d.
							1822):</term>
						<gloss target="#PeggeChristopher"> a fellow of Christ Church, Oxford and
							from 1790 Lees Reader in Anatomy. He was elected a Fellow of the Royal
							Society in 1795 and was knighted in 1799.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="127">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="PembertonSophia">Pemberton, Sophia (d.
							1830):</term>
						<gloss target="#PembertonSophia"> daughter of a Birmingham manufacturer, she
							married Charles Lloyd on 24 April 1799. They moved to Old Brathay, near
							Ambleside, in 1800. They had nine children and a notably happy family life, despite
							Charles Lloyd&#8217;s bouts of mental instability. Thomas De Quincey
							(1758–1859; <title level="m">DNB</title>) claimed that ‘as a wife and
							mother’ Sophia was ‘unsurpassed’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="128">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="PhillimoreJoseph">Phillimore, Joseph (1775–1855;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#PhillimoreJoseph"> lawyer. Educated at Westminster School
							and Christ Church, Oxford (matric. 1793, BA 1797, BCL 1800, DCL 1804).
							He won prizes at Christ Church for Latin verse (1793) and prose (1798),
							and the university English essay prize (1798) for his dissertation,
							‘Chivalry’. Southey and Phillimore met at Westminster School, and their
							friendship lasted until the end of Southey’s time at Oxford. When
							Southey returned to Oxford in 1820 to receive an honorary DCL,
							Phillimore, by then Regius Professor of Civil Law, participated in the
							degree ceremony. Phillimore was not very tall, hence his nickname
							‘little Joe’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="129">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="PooleThomas">Poole, Thomas (1766–1837;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#PooleThomas"> tanner and farmer of Nether Stowey in
							Somerset. He met Southey and Coleridge during their walking tour of 1794
							and became a friend of both and a crucial financial support to
							Coleridge. Poole helped untangle the financial difficulties left by
							Coleridge’s failed periodical, <title>The Watchman</title>, found a
							house at Nether Stowey for Coleridge’s family in 1797 and provided much
							financial assistance for them while Coleridge was in Germany in
							1798-1799. Poole was the central figure in reconciling Coleridge and
							Southey in August 1799. Southey last met Poole on his tour of the West
							Country in 1837.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="130">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="PrattSamuelJackson">Pratt, Samuel Jackson [pseud.
							Courtney Melmoth] (1749-1814; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#PrattSamuelJackson"> writer and actor. In 1803 he sent
							Southey a copy of his <title>Gleanings</title>, which contained a poem
							in praise of Southey’s popular ballad ‘Mary’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="131">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ProbyJohnCarysfort">Proby, John Joshua, 1st Earl
							of Carysfort (1751–1828; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#ProbyJohnCarysfort"> politician and writer. Educated at
							Westminster School and Trinity College, Cambridge. In the mid 1790s,
							Carysfort developed an interest in Southey’s poetry, communicating with
							him through his cousin and Southey’s patron Charles Wynn. Southey
							arranged for Carysfort to be sent copies of his books, though any
							letters he wrote to the peer have not survived. Carysfort’s critiques of
							‘The Retrospect’ and <title>Madoc</title> are in National Library of
							Wales, NLW MS 4819E. Carysfort’s own <title>Dramatic and Narrative
								Poems</title> were published in 1810.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="132">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ProbyWilliam">Proby, William Allen
							(1779–1804):</term>
						<gloss target="#ProbyWilliam"> naval officer, eldest son of John Joshua
							Proby, 1st Earl of Carysfort. He was made a captain in 1798 when only
							19, probably because of his political connections.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="133">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="PugheWilliamOwen">Pughe, William Owen (1759–1835;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#PugheWilliamOwen"> lexicographer, grammarian, editor,
							antiquarian and poet. The son of John Owen, he adopted the surname Pughe
							in 1806 after inheriting property from a relative. A leading member of
							the Society of Gwyneddigion and the Society of the Cymmrodorion, his
							publications included: <title>The Heroic Elegies of Llywarch Hen</title>
							(1792), <title>The Myvyrian Archaiology</title> (1801, 1807) and
								<title>The Cambrian Biography</title> (1803). In 1796–1797, Southey
							and Pughe engaged in a (pseudonymous) debate about the Welsh language in
							the pages of the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>. Later in 1797, Southey
							consulted Pughe about details for his Welsh-American poem
								<title>Madoc</title>.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="134">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ReesOwen">Rees, Owen (1770-1837;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#ReesOwen"> publisher and bookseller. He was born at
							Geli-gron, Wales, eldest brother of Thomas Rees (1777-1864;
								<title>DNB</title>), Unitarian minister and writer on theological
							history. Owen Rees migrated to Bristol where he became a bookseller. He
							later moved to London and in 1797 was taken into partnership by the
							publisher Thomas Norton Longman. From 1799 Longman and Rees became
							Southey’s main publishers. Rees retired from the business in early
							1837.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="135">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ReidSamuel">Reid, Samuel (c. 1775–1821):</term>
						<gloss target="#ReidSamuel">a Bristol friend of Southey’s; possibly related
							to the insurance broker William Reid (dates unknown). Sam Reid had
							intended to pursue a career as a Unitarian minister, but abandoned it
							after a crisis of faith. In 1806 he moved to Liverpool, where he worked
							as a private tutor.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="136">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="RickmanJohn">Rickman, John (1771–1840;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#RickmanJohn"> statistician. Only son of Thomas Rickman,
							vicar of Newburn, Northumberland. Educated at Guildford Grammar School
							(1781–1785) and Oxford (matric. Magdalen Hall, 1788, and migrated to
							Lincoln College, BA 1792). After graduation he joined his father, who
							had retired to live in Christchurch, Hampshire. Rickman worked as a
							private tutor and read widely in economics. He edited the
								<title>Commercial, Agricultural and Manufacturer’s Magazine</title>
							(until 1801). In 1796 he wrote a private paper in which he argued for
							the benefits to the nation of a census. George Rose, MP for
							Christchurch, showed this to the politician Charles Abbot (1757-1829;
								<title>DNB</title>) and in March 1801 the latter steered the census
							bill into law. Rickman was responsible for the first four censuses
							(1801, 1811, 1821 and 1831) and paved the way for the fifth (1841). In
							1801 he became Abbot’s personal secretary whilst the latter was Chief
							Secretary for Ireland. On Abbot’s election to the post of Speaker of the
							House of Commons, Rickman became the Speaker’s secretary. In 1820 he
							became Clerk Assistant to the Commons with a salary of £2500 per year.
							He married Susannah Postlethwaite (d. 1836) in 1805. Rickman's
							friendship with Southey began at Burton in 1797 and endured for the rest
							of their lives. Shortly after their first meeting, Southey described him
							as ‘rough, coarse, well informed on all subjects, believing nothing,
							jacobinical’. Later in life Rickman became high tory, anti-Malthusian
							and anti-semitic. He regularly provided ideas and information
							(especially statistics) for Southey’s articles in the <title>Quarterly
								Review</title> and authored the majority of Southey’s April 1818
								<title>Quarterly</title> essay on the Poor Laws. Southey and Rickman
							planned to collaborate on a sequel to the <title>Colloquies</title>
							(1829) but this was prevented by John Murray’s (1778–1843) financial
							problems.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="137">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="Robinsonfamily">Robinson family:</term>
						<gloss target="#Robinsonfamily"> London booksellers and publishers. George
							Robinson (1736–1801; <title>DNB</title>) and his brothers James Robinson
							(d. 1803/4; <title>DNB</title>), John Robinson (1753–1813;
								<title>DNB</title>), and possibly Henry Robinson (d. in or after
							1813; <title>DNB</title>).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="138">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="RoscoeWilliam">Roscoe, William (1753–1831;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#RoscoeWilliam"> lawyer, banker and leading public figure in
							his native Liverpool, which he represented in Parliament 1806-1807.
							Roscoe was a Unitarian and a radical. He was also an expert on Italian
							history and literature and collected a notable library and series of
							Italian paintings, as well as writing <title>The Life of Lorenzo de’
								Medici</title> (1796). He corresponded with Southey in 1798 on the
							whereabouts of William Gilbert.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="139">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="RosserRobert">Rosser, Robert (d. 1802):</term>
						<gloss target="#RosserRobert"> Bristol-based printer. Best known for printing the <title>Bristol Mercury</title>.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="140">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="RoughWilliam">Rough, William (1772/3–1838;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#RoughWilliam"> lawyer and poet; only son of William Rough.
							Educated Westminster (adm. 1786, King’s Scholar 1789) and Trinity
							College, Cambridge (matric. 1792, BA 1796, MA 1799), he entered Gray’s
							Inn in 1796, and was called to the Bar at the Inner Temple in 1801. He
							married Harriet (1778–c. 1820), an illegitimate daughter of John Wilkes
							(1725–1797; <title level="m">DNB</title>). He served in the judiciary in
							Demerara and Essequibo and later Ceylon and was knighted in 1837. His
							literary works included <title>Lorenzo di Medici</title> (1797),
								<title>The Conspiracy of Gowrie</title> (1800), and <title>Lines on
								the Death of Sir Ralph Abercromby</title> (1800). He was also a
							contributor to the <title>Gentleman’s Magazine</title> and the
								<title>Monthly Magazine</title>. Rough and Southey were friends
							whilst at Westminster School and remained in contact in later life. He
							was rumoured to have contributed to <title>The Flagellant</title>
							(1792).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="141">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SawierMrs">Sawier, Mrs (d. before April
							1798):</term>
						<gloss target="#SawierMrs"> Mary Sawier was the widow of a Bristol
							accountant and Southey’s landlady in College Street, Bristol in 1795.
							Her daughter married James Jennings.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="142">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ScottWalter">Scott, Walter (1771-1832;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#ScottWalter">poet and novelist. He and Southey first met in
							October 1805 and they corresponded on a range of literary and political
							topics from then until Scott’s death. In 1813 Scott, who had declined
							the post, played a key role in Southey’s appointment as Poet
							Laureate.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="143">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SetonBarbara">Seton, Barbara (dates
							unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#SetonBarbara"> the only child of George and Barbara Seton
							and a cousin of Agnes (1764–1852; <title>DNB</title>) and Mary
							(1763–1852; <title>DNB</title>) Berry, friends of Horace Walpole
							(1717–1797; <title>DNB</title>). In 1807, she married the Rev. James
							Bannister, Rector of Iddesleigh. Her date of death is unknown, but she
							is said to have been living in Honiton, Devon in 1838. Seton met Southey
							during his second visit to Portugal in 1800-1801, and corresponded with
							him until 1810. She was on very good terms with both Southey and his
							wife.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="144">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SewardAnna">Seward, Anna (1747-1809;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#SewardAnna">the ‘swan of Lichfield’– a poet, encouraged in
							youth by Erasmus Darwin (1731- 1802; <title>DNB</title>). Her writings
							included <title>Poems on Subjects Chiefly Devotional</title> (1760),
								<title>Elegy on Captain Cook</title> (1780), <title>Monody on Major
								Andre</title> (1781) and <title>Louisa: A Poetic Novel</title>
							(1784). Walter Scott edited her <title>Poetical Works</title> for
							Ballantyne in 1810; her voluminous correspondence was published in 1811.
							Seward was quick to recognise Southey as a poet to be watched: her 1797
							‘Philippic on a Modern Epic’ condemned the ‘Baneful’ politics of his
								<title>Joan of Arc</title>, but simultaneously heralded it as the
							work of ‘sun-born Genius’. She continued to follow Southey’s career with
							some interest. In 1802 she wrote to the <title>Poetical
							Register</title>, lauding him as a ‘genuine Poet’, though cautioning the
							reader against adopting ‘his capricious systems’. She read
								<title>Madoc</title> shortly after its 1805 publication and
							published a lengthy defence of it in the <title>Gentleman’s
								Magazine</title> in 1808. When Southey got wind (via a letter sent
							by Seward to Charles Lloyd) of her high opinion, he wrote to her. This
							initiated a correspondence that lasted until Seward’s death and that led
							to their one meeting in Lichfield in summer 1808. Late in life, Southey
							provided a comic account of the ‘jubilant but appalling solemnity’ of
							this encounter. However, his attitude to Seward was more ambivalent than
							this suggests. He was keenly aware of – and attentive to - her place in
							literary history, noting that she ‘was not so much over-rated at one
							time, as she has been since unduly depreciated’ (<title>Poetical
								Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837- 1838), V, pp.
							xv-xviii).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="145">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SewardEdmund">Seward, Edmund (c.
							1770/71–1795):</term>
						<gloss target="#SewardEdmund"> the youngest son of John Seward of Sapey,
							Worcestershire. Educated at Balliol College, Oxford (matric. 1789, BA
							1793). Seward was one of Southey’s closest friends at Oxford, and an
							important influence on him. An early enthusiast for Pantisocracy, Seward
							later withdrew from the scheme and felt himself partly to blame for what
							he described as ‘having contrived to bring [Southey] ... into ... a
							calamitous &amp; ruinous ... adventure, from which I might at first
							perhaps have diverted him’. Southey was deeply shocked by Seward’s death
							from a ‘fever’, and later addressed his elegy ‘To the Dead Friend’ to
							him. In a letter to James Montgomery, 6 May 1811, Southey recalled him
							as ‘an admirable man in all things, whose only fault was that he was too
							humble ... In his company my religious instincts were strengthened ...
							Sick of the college-chapel &amp; of the church, we tried the meeting
							house, — &amp; there we were disgusted too. Seward left College, meaning
							to take orders; — I who had the same destination, became a Deist after
							he left me’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="146">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="Sewardfamily">Seward family:</term>
						<gloss target="#Sewardfamily"> a Worcestershire family consisting of four
							brothers and three sisters. The death of Southey’s close friend Edmund
							Seward in 1795 was followed by that of his brother John (educated at St
							John’s College, Cambridge, MB 1795, and physician to the Worcester
							infirmary) in December 1797. Some time afterwards, the eldest brother,
							William (a lawyer, based in Ledbury, Herefordshire) shot himself. A
							fourth brother, whose name Southey does not record, was a ‘mere farmer’
							of a ‘methodistical turn’. Of the sisters, one married Mr Severn (a
							clergyman) and two remained unmarried. In the mid 1790s, Southey was on
							good terms with most — if not all — of the siblings and corresponded
							with at least Edmund and one of the Seward sisters.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="147">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SharpRichard">Sharp, Richard (1759–1835;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#SharpRichard"> businessman, Dissenter, radical and writer,
							but most famous for his conversational powers – hence his nickname
							‘Conversation’ Sharp. He was born in Newfoundland, the son of the elder
							Richard Sharp, an army officer. But the family soon returned to England
							and Sharp took over his grandfather’s hat-making business, later moving
							into the West India trade. He was a member of various radical
							organisations in the 1790s and Whig MP for Castle Rising 1806-1812 and
							Portarlington 1816-1819. Sharp’s only major publication was the
							anonymous <title>Letters and Essays in Poetry and Prose</title> (1834),
							but he was a friend and adviser to many literary men. He encouraged
							Southey to proceed with <title>Kehama</title> (1810).</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="148">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SmithElizabeth">Smith, Elizabeth (c.
							1764-1859):</term>
						<gloss target="#SmithElizabeth"> wife of Thomas Smith and a noted collector
							of autographs and manuscripts.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="149">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SmithThomas">Smith, Thomas (c. 1770-1822):</term>
						<gloss target="#SmithThomas"> country gentleman and JP, of Unitarian and
							liberal views and literary and scientific interests. He was born in
							Cirencester, and later owned estates at Bownham House, near
							Minchinhampton , Gloucestshire and at Easton Grey, near Malmesbury,
							Wiltshire. He trained as a barrister but a speech impediment meant that
							he never practiced. He was known as the ‘Macenas of his neighbourhood’
							for his patronage of men of letters and his philanthropy. He had a wide
							circle of friends in public life, including the economist David Ricardo
							(1772-1823; <title>DNB</title>) and John Whishaw (c. 1764-1840), ‘the
							Pope of Holland House’. Smith was married to Elizabeth Chandler, a
							fellow Unitarian. She was a noted collector of autographs and books.
							They had at least one child, a daughter, who was painted by James
							Northcote (1746-1831; <title>DNB</title>) in 1803. Southey was on very
							good terms with the Smiths, whom he probably knew through Charles
							Danvers. Southey visited them at Bownham in 1803, where he made use of
							their extensive library. He also sought out new items for Elizabeth
							Smith’s autograph collection. These included a MS of Coleridge’s then
							unpublished ‘Kubla Khan’, now BL Add MS 50847, sent by Southey in
							February 1804. In turn, Thomas Smith subscribed to the Southey-Cottle
							edition of Thomas Chatterton (1752-1770; <title>DNB</title>) and lent
							Southey books.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="150">
						<hi rend="bold">Southey, Edith: <hi rend="ital">see</hi> Fricker, Edith
							(1774-1837; <title>DNB</title>)</hi>
					</item>
					<item n="151">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyEdward">Southey, Edward (1788–1847):</term>
						<gloss target="#SoutheyEdward"> Southey’s youngest brother, he spent much of
							his childhood in the household of Elizabeth Tyler. Southey was much
							preoccupied with arranging Edward’s education, though plans to send him
							to St Paul’s School did not work out. It is not certain where he was
							educated. Southey despaired, noting ‘I never saw a lad with a better
							capacity or with habits more compleatly bad’. Edward was to lead an
							increasingly rackety, disreputable life, trying his hand at being a
							sailor, soldier and, eventually, a provincial actor.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="152">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyEliza">Southey, Eliza (1776–1779):</term>
						<gloss target="#SoutheyEliza"> Southey’s younger sister.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="153">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyHenryHerbert">Southey, Henry Herbert
							(1783–1865; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#SoutheyHenryHerbert">physician. Southey’s younger brother.
							With the help of his uncle Herbert Hill, Southey provided money for
							Henry Herbert’s education at Norwich and Edinburgh. His concerns about
							his younger brother’s lack of application proved — eventually — to be
							ill-founded, and in later life the two enjoyed a close
							friendship.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="154">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyJohn">Southey, John (d. 1806):</term>
						<gloss target="#SoutheyJohn"> the eldest brother of Southey’s father. His
							work as a lawyer led to him accumulating a substantial fortune of
							£100,000. Although he was unmarried, he refused to help either Robert
							Southey Senior, thus ensuring the latter’s imprisonment for debt in
							1792, or his nephews, to whom he left nothing in his Will. Southey
							visited his uncle in 1802, describing his miserly existence to John May.
							In 1806, he recorded that his uncle ‘had thanked God upon his death bed
							that he had cut me off’. Southey retaliated by writing a poem attacking
							the deceased.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="155">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyMargaret">Southey, Margaret
							(1752–1802):</term>
						<gloss target="#SoutheyMargaret"> Southey’s mother. Born Margaret Hill, she
							married Robert Southey Senior in 1772. The marriage produced nine
							children, of whom five died young. She was dominated by her older
							half-sister, Elizabeth Tyler, with whom Southey spent a great deal of
							his childhood. After the bankruptcy and death of her husband in 1792,
							Margaret moved to Bath, running a boarding house in Westgate Buildings.
							Her continued financial difficulties — possibly exacerbated by the
							extravagance of her half-sister — caused Southey great anxiety. Margaret
							died on 5 January 1802 after a long illness.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="156">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">Southey, Margaret Edith
							(1802-1803):</term>
						<gloss target="#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau"> the first-born child of Robert and
							Edith Southey, who both doted on her. She died of hydrocephalus in
							August 1803.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="157">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyMary">Southey, Mary (dates unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#SoutheyMary"> Southey’s paternal aunt, also referred to as
							‘Aunt Maria’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="158">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyRobertSnr">Southey, Robert, Senior
							(1745–1792):</term>
						<gloss target="#SoutheyRobertSnr"> Southey’s father. A failed Bristol
							linen-draper, he was briefly imprisoned in 1792 ‘for a bill endorsed for
							a deceitful friend’. His release was secured by Elizabeth Tyler. He died
							in December 1792, after what his eldest son described as a ‘long’
							decline.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="159">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyTom">Southey, Thomas (‘Tom’) [brother]
							(1771–1838):</term>
						<gloss target="#SoutheyTom"> sailor and farmer. Southey’s younger brother
							and the one to whom he was in the 1790s closest. Tom entered the navy as
							a midshipman at the age of 12, saw action in several major battles of
							the French revolutionary wars (including Cape St Vincent and
							Copenhagen), was captured on one occasion, wounded on several others,
							and was made a lieutenant as reward for his bravery in the fight between
								<hi rend="ital">Mars</hi> and <hi rend="ital">L’Hercule</hi> on 21
							April 1798. He made Captain in 1811, but never commanded a ship. After
							he retired from the navy, he tried his hand at farming and as a customs
							officer. His last posting was at Demerara, British Guiana, and he died
							on shipboard on the return voyage to England. He married Sarah Castle in
							1810 and produced a large family. Tom’s lack of financial stability
							meant that some of the burden of supporting him fell on his brothers
							Robert and Henry Herbert Southey. Tom’s knowledge of the navy and
							seafaring, and his observations of foreign climes, provided important
							information for many of Southey’s writings, including his poetry and
								<title>The Life of Nelson</title> (1813). Tom’s only publication was
								<title>A Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827),
							written with his brother Robert’s encouragement.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="160">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyThomas">Southey, Thomas [uncle] (d.
							1811):</term>
						<gloss target="#SoutheyThomas"> younger brother and at one time the business
							partner of Southey’s father, Robert Southey Senior. He spent his later
							years in Taunton, Somerset. Although unmarried, childless, and wealthy
							Thomas Southey was on distant terms with his brother Robert’s sons.
							Thomas Southey’s Will held no surprises — it cut his nephews off without
							a penny, ‘his last boast being ... that no one of his own name should
							ever be a shilling the better for him’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="161">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="StracheyGeorge">Strachey, George
							(1776–1849):</term>
						<gloss target="#StracheyGeorge"> officer of the East India Company. Son of
							John Strachey. Educated at Westminster (adm. 1787) and Trinity College,
							Cambridge (BA 1795; MA 1822). Writer EICS (Madras) 1796; Assistant in
							the Military, Secret and Political Department, 1798; Joint Assay Master,
							1807; Private Secretary to the Governor, 1808; Judge and Magistrate of
							the Zillah of Cuddapah, 1809; Junior Secretary to Government, 1812;
							Chief Secretary, 1813; retired 1824. Strachey was Southey’s ‘substance’
							(an older boy assigned to induct a new pupil into school rules and
							rituals) at Westminster School. During their schooldays, Strachey
							(perhaps in response to the scandal surrounding <title>The
								Flagellant</title>) was one of many acquaintances who treated
							Southey ‘like a scabby sheep’, dropping him. They were later only
							partially reconciled, but enough for Southey to commemorate Strachey’s
							departure for India in 1798 with a sonnet (‘Fair be thy fortunes in the
							distant land’) published in the <title>Morning Post</title>. Southey
							attempted to maintain their correspondence, but it had lapsed by April
							1805 when he confessed that as Strachey had not replied to his letters,
							he would ‘not ... write to him again, nor in any way force myself upon
							him.’</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="162">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="StuartDaniel">Stuart, Daniel (1766–1846;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#StuartDaniel">newspaper proprietor and journalist.
							Originally a printer, he bought the <title>Morning Post</title> in 1795
							and turned it into the leading anti-government newspaper and a very
							profitable venture. Though he sold the <title>Morning Post</title> in
							1803, he retained an interest in the <title>Courier</title>, which he
							acquired in 1800-1801, though it is disputed how much influence he had
							over the newspaper’s contents. Stuart employed Southey to write poems
							for the <title>Morning Post</title> at a guinea a week in 1798-1799, and
							again in 1801-1803. This ‘laureateship’ was crucial to Southey’s
							finances.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="163">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="TaylorWilliam">Taylor, William (1765–1836;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#TaylorWilliam"> reviewer and translator. Born in Norwich,
							the only child of William and Sarah Taylor. Taylor’s interest in German
							culture culminated in his <title>Historic Survey of German
								Poetry</title> (1828–1830). He was also a prolific contributor to
							the <title>Annual Review, The Athenaeum, Monthly Magazine</title>, and
								<title level="m">Monthly Review</title>. Southey and Taylor met in
							1798, whilst the former was on a visit to Great Yarmouth, where his
							brother Henry Herbert Southey was being tutored by George Burnett.
							Taylor introduced Southey to his great friend Frank Sayers (1763–1817;
								<title>DNB</title>) — whose 1792 collection <title>Poems</title> had
							influenced Southey’s early work — and also to radical and dissenting
							circles in Norwich. Taylor gave Southey the idea for the <title>Annual
								Anthology</title> and was an acute, if frequently blunt, critic of
							his work. From 1803–1804, he edited the Norwich newspaper <title>The
								Iris</title>, to which Southey contributed poetry. Southey described
							Taylor as ‘one of the three great men of my acquaintance ... the more I
							know him and the longer I know him, the more do I admire his knowledge
							and love his moral character.’</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="164">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ThomasDr">Thomas, Dr (first name and dates
							unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#ThomasDr"> a native of Hereford, father of William Bowyer
							Thomas. He was involved in the management of Herbert Hill’s business
							affairs.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="165">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas, William Bowyer (d.
							1802):</term>
						<gloss target="#ThomasWilliamBowyer"> a native of Hereford, Thomas was the
							business agent for Herbert Hill, Southey’s uncle. His job also involved
							him in the tangled finances of Elizabeth Tyler, Hill’s half-sister and
							Southey’s aunt. Thomas met Southey during the latter’s 1795–1796 visit
							to Portugal. Southey stayed with him in Hereford in 1798 and through
							Thomas gained access to the cathedral library. In 1800 Thomas married a
							cousin, a woman Southey greatly admired. Thomas died suddenly in
							1802.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="166">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="ThorpMr">Thorp, William (1727-1800):</term>
						<gloss target="#ThorpMr"> well-known hosier in Oxford, with a shop in Broad
							Street; Mayor of Oxford, 1775-6 and 1789-90. Thorp and his son and
							namesake, William Thorp (1762-1835), Vicar of Sandfield, 1807-35, were
							friends of Southey’s during his time at Oxford.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="167">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="TobinJamesWebbe">Tobin, James Webbe (1767–1814;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#TobinJamesWebbe">abolitionist son of a Nevis sugar planter,
							Tobin became friends with Coleridge and Wordsworth, whom he may have
							visited in 1797 in Somerset. In Bristol he befriended Humphry Davy and
							participated in the nitrous oxide experiments at Thomas Beddoes’s
							Pneumatic Institution. A prospective Pantisocrat, Tobin later
							contributed five poems to the second volume of Southey’s <title>Annual
								Anthology</title> and urged Southey to produce a third. A political
							radical and, in the mid-1790s, a follower of William Godwin, Tobin began
							to lose his eyesight when in America and Nevis in 1793-94. In 1804 Tobin
							was bereaved of his brother and companion John (1770-1804), and fell out
							with Coleridge, who resented his advice on money and health matters. In
							1807 he married and from 1809 till his death lived on Nevis, campaigning
							against cruelty to slaves.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="168">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="TurnerSharon">Turner, Sharon (1768-1847;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#TurnerSharon">lawyer and historian who lived at Red Lion
							square near the British Museum and used the manuscripts thus accessible
							to him to compile a <title>History of the Anglo-Saxons</title>, 4 vols
							(1799-1805), on which Southey drew in <title>Madoc</title> (1805). A
							long term friend and correspondent of Southey, in 1817 Turner gave legal
							advice over the <title>Wat Tyler</title> piracy.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="169">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="TylerElizabeth">Tyler, Elizabeth
							(1739–1821):</term>
						<gloss target="#TylerElizabeth"> the older, unmarried half-sister of
							Southey’s mother. She had spent her early life looking after an elderly
							relative and on his death received an inheritance which she then spent
							on living the high life. Her extravagance was a source of great concern
							to her relatives, in particular her half-brother Herbert Hill. Elizabeth
							Tyler was painted by Joshua Reynolds and moved in cultural circles in
							Bath and Bristol, counting amongst her friends the Palmers, owners of
							the Theatre Royal, Bath. Southey was largely brought up in her
							household, an experience he later described in a series of
							autobiographical letters to John May. Southey quarrelled with his aunt
							over his relationship with Edith Fricker and involvement in
							Pantisocracy, and on a wet night in 1794 she threw him out. They never
							saw or spoke to one another again. Southey later speculated that
							Elizabeth Tyler, whose grandmother had died ‘in confinement’, suffered
							from a form of insanity, noting that ‘her habitual violence of temper is
							now increased by long indulgence absolutely to a state of
							derangement’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="170">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="VincentWilliam">Vincent, William (1739–1815;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#VincentWilliam"> Head Master of Westminster School 1778–1802
							and later Dean of Westminster. A Tory, in 1792 he used a public sermon
							at St Margaret’s, Westminster, to defend the constitution and the
							prevailing social order. He published works on the geography and
							commerce of the classical world.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="171">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="WakefieldGilbert">Wakefield, Gilbert (1756-1801;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#WakefieldGilbert"> radical writer. Born in Nottingham, the
							son of George Wakefield, Rector of St Nicholas’s Church. He attended
							Jesus College, Cambridge, graduating with a BA in 1776. Wakefield was a
							Fellow of the College 1776-1779 and a deacon 1778-1779. But he resigned
							the former post on his marriage and the latter on his conversion to
							Unitarianism. Thereafter he was a teacher (at Warrington Dissenting
							Academy 1779-1783) and a professional writer, mainly on classical,
							religious and political topics. He was one of the Pitt government’s
							fiercest critics and was imprisoned for two years in Dorchester gaol for
							his <title>A Reply to Some Parts of the Bishop of Landaff’s
								Address</title> (1798). Southey visited him in prison.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="172">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="WedgwoodThomas">Wedgwood, Thomas (1771-1805;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#WedgwoodThomas"> chemist. Third son of the potter Josiah
							Wedgwood (1730-1795; <title>DNB</title>). He inherited a substantial
							fortune of the death of his father and dedicated this to supporting
							writers and scientists. He was a patron of Beddoes’ Pneumatic Medical
							Institution and of Samuel Taylor Coleridge. He participated in Davy’s
							Bristol experiments with nitrous oxide and later attended his lectures
							at the Royal Institution.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="173">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="WeeksShadrach">Weeks (also spelled ‘Weekes’),
							Shadrach (dates unknown):</term>
						<gloss target="#WeeksShadrach"> childhood friend of Southey. A servant of
							Elizabeth Tyler, Southey’s aunt, and a recruit to Pantisocracy.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="174">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="WingfieldJohn">Wingfield, John (c.
							1757–1825):</term>
						<gloss target="#WingfieldJohn"> Under-Master at Westminster School
							1788–1802.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="175">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="WollstonecraftMary">Wollstonecraft, Mary
							(1759–1797; <title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#WollstonecraftMary"> author. Southey was a great admirer of
							Wollstonecraft and dedicated his ‘The Triumph of Woman’ (published in
							his <title>Poems</title> (1797)) to her. They met in London in 1797,
							where they moved in the same radical circles. Southey mourned her death
							in his 1797 poem ‘To A. S. Cottle’.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="176">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="WordsworthDorothy">Wordsworth, Dorothy (1771–1855;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#WordsworthDorothy"> writer. She and Southey probably met in
							1795 but their relationship only flourished after Southey and his family
							moved to Keswick in 1803.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="177">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="WordsworthMary">Wordsworth, Mary
							(1770-1859):</term>
						<gloss target="#WordsworthMary"> wife of William Wordsworth. The Southeys
							became better acquainted with her after their move to Keswick in
							September 1803.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="178">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth, William (1770–1850;
								<title>DNB</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#WordsworthWilliam"> poet. Wordsworth and Southey met in
							Bristol in 1795. Their relationship became closer after the Southeys
							moved to Keswick in 1803 and particularly after the death of John
							Wordsworth in 1805.</gloss>
					</item>
					<lb/>
					<item n="179">
						<term rend="bold" xml:id="WynnCharlesWW">Wynn, Charles Watkin Williams
							(1775–1850; <title>DNB</title>, <title>Hist P</title>):</term>
						<gloss target="#WynnCharlesWW"> politician. The second son of Sir Watkin
							Williams Wynn, 4th Baronet, and his second wife Charlotte Grenville. He
							was educated at home by a tutor, the Rev. Robert Nares, and later at
							Westminster (adm. 1784) and Christ Church, Oxford (matric. 1791, BA
							1795, MA 1798, DCL 1810). Entered Lincoln’s Inn in 1795 and was called
							to the Bar in 1798. He married Mary Cunliffe, daughter of a baronet, in
							1806. Wynn had excellent family and political connections as his
							maternal grandfather was the Prime Minister George Grenville (1712–1770;
								<title>DNB</title>). He served as an M.P. for Old Sarum (1797–1799)
							and for Montgomeryshire (1799–1850). From 1806–1807, he served in the
							Ministry of Talents (led by his uncle Lord Grenville) and secured a
							pension for Southey, which he described as ‘the only benefit I reap from
							12 months of office’. From 1822–1828, he held a cabinet post as
							President of the Board of Control. Wynn met Southey at Westminster and
							the two remained friends for rest of their lives. He contributed to
								<title>The Flagellant</title> (1792) under pseudonyms which included
							‘St Pardulph’. Wynn (who was not personally wealthy) gave Southey an
							annuity of £160 from 1797, and Southey dedicated <title>Madoc</title>
							(1805) to him.</gloss>
					</item>
				</list>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
