<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Tables of Contents: Ordering the Commonplace Book Poems (DCMS 120)
                    
                </title>
                
                
                <!-- DW will be the author for the "reading texts" because she is a historical figure, change role to "primary" -->
                
                <author role="secondary">
                    <name>Michelle Levy</name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor">Michelle Levy</editor> 
                
                
                <funder>Brigham Young University College of Humanities</funder>
                <principal>Paul Westover</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>T. J. McLemore</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- TJ AND JESSICA CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE PAUL'S NAMING CONVENTIONS IN THE "toc_file_names_for_links" DOC THAT IS LINKED TO THE SLACK CHANNEL-->
                <idno type="edition">editions.2022.DW.Poems-contents</idno>
                <idno type="resource">DW</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Table of Contents: Ordering the Commonplace Book Poems (DCMS 120)
                        </title>
                        <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE THE NAMING DOC -->
                        <ptr target="editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.Poems-contents"/>
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Dorothy Wordworth's Lake District</title>
                        <title level="s">Editions</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- JESS AND TJ CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">aging</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">childhood</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">disability</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">environment</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">memory</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">mobility</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">walking</term>
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  PUT YOUR NAME HERE. AND ADD THE CODING DATE  -->
                <name>Lavender Earnest</name>
                <date>2022-14-11</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head>Table of Contents: Ordering the Commonplace Book Poems (DCMS 120)</head>
                    <byline>Edited by Michelle Levy, Nicholas Mason, and Paul Westover</byline>
                
                <div type="section">   
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Editor&#8217;s note:</hi> Given the enduring norm in editions such as this of
                        presenting a writer&#8217;s works chronologically, Dorothy Wordsworth&#8217;s commonplace book
                        poems pose a challenge. Not only is it impossible to know whether the order in which the poems
                        appear in DCMS 120 corresponds with their order of composition, but we also have no means to
                        ascertain the precise temporal relationship between material copied into the opposite ends of the
                        notebook. Therefore, rather than attempt to order the poems by date or impose any single
                        organizational scheme upon a notebook that was never intended to reach the public, we
                        present here two models for working through the poems:</p>
                    
                    <list type="unordered">
                      <item>
                          <hi rend="bold">Table of contents 1</hi> shows how, like the typical commonplace book,
                          DCMS 120 intermingles the author&#8217;s own creative work or personal reflections with
                          miscellaneous quotations, recipes, and extracts. This table therefore captures a core
                          feature of this notebook that gets obscured in our <ref target="editions.2022.DW.Poems.xml">
                          reading text</ref>, which transcribes only Dorothy&#8217;s original poems. It also highlights
                          the fact that this notebook is an ambigraph&#8212;or a book that begins on either end (see 
                          <ref target="editions.2020.DW.Poems-intro.xml">this section&#8217;s introduction</ref>)&#8212;by
                          dividing its contents into two parts. <hi rend="bold">Table 1A</hi> lists texts that appear
                          right-side up when one reads from the front cover. Conversely, <hi rend="bold">Table 1B</hi> 
                          lists those written in the other direction, and hence read by flipping the book over and 
                          beginning from the back cover.
                      </item>
                        <lb/>
                      <item>
                          <hi rend="bold">Table of contents 2</hi> instead lists just the poems, clustering together
                          different versions of the same text but otherwise presenting them in their order of appearance
                          in DCMS 120. Studying alternate versions of her poems offers a clearer understanding of both
                          the nature of Dorothy&#8217;s revisions and the types of poems she repeatedly reworked. While, for
                          ease in referencing, we have labeled variant texts according to their sequence in DCMS 120
                          (e.g., Version A, Version B, etc.), we caution against assuming earlier versions of poems
                          appear earlier in the notebook. Readers should also be aware that a degree of editorial
                          judgment has gone into grouping together texts, as some poems appearing under a single
                          title contain major variants. For example, <title level="a">Lines intended for my Niece&#8217;s Album</title> (12, 
                          13)&#8212;a poem Dorothy wrote for her namesake, Dora&#8212;was drafted or copied first into DCMS
                          120. It appears in both a 5-stanza and a 12-stanza version (with considerable differences
                          between the shared stanzas). These two versions exist because Dorothy marks the first
                          seven stanzas in the 12-stanza version (see fig. 6B.1) as &#8220;Not to be put in this album,&#8221;
                          a puzzling note in a poem that has been written explicitly for that purpose, especially
                          since the rejected stanzas contain no obviously unacceptable material. A similar gesture
                          is found in <title level="a">Lines intended for Edith Southey&#8217;s album,</title> in which
                          &#8220;Not intended for the Album&#8221; is penciled at the top of the second page of the poem.
                          What these notes about excisions suggest is that Dorothy was highly cognizant of the need to
                          modify her poems for different audiences, as her concern may have been that the poems would
                          have a wider circulation when copied in her niece&#8217;s and Edith&#8217;s albums. It also
                          suggests that she exercised control over who saw this manuscript notebook. We also find Dorothy
                          returning to some poems, especially <title level="a">Grasmere&#8212;A Fragment</title> (four
                          versions), <title level="a">Lines written (rather say begun)</title> (seven versions), and
                          <title level="a">Loving &amp; Liking</title> (three versions), repeatedly, revising 
                          various sections, sometimes only individual stanzas or lines. To say therefore that they are
                          &#8220;versions&#8221; of the same poem may, in some cases, be overstating the case. 
                      </item>
                    </list>
                    
                    
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="PLACEHOLDER" width="00px" rend="inline"/>
                        <figDesc><title level="a">Figure 6B.1: Lines intended for my Niece&#8217;s Album.</title> (Courtesy: The Wordsworth Trust)</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="underline">Explanation of column headers</hi>
                        </head>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item><hi rend="bold">Foliation:</hi> the text&#8217;s place in DCMS 120, numbered consecutively from the start
                            and with <hi rend="italic">r</hi> and <hi rend="italic">v</hi> indicating whether it appears on the recto (the front of an unbound sheet, or
                            the right-hand page of a codex) or verso side (the back of a sheet, or left-hand page when bound)
                            of the notebook.</item>
                        <item><hi rend="bold">Text at Top of Page:</hi> either the title of the text at the head of the page or,
                            when it continues from the previous page, its opening phrase.</item>
                        <item><hi rend="bold">Poems &#35;:</hi> the poem&#8217;s number (based on the sequence of DCMS 120) in 
                            <ref target="editions.2022.DW.Poems.xml">this edition&#8217;s transcription</ref>. Each separate
                            instance of a poem as it appears in DCMS 120 is numbered sequentially.</item>
                        <item><hi rend="bold">Version:</hi> poems that appear in multiple versions are also named as separate
                            versions, with Version A, Version B, and so on indicating their sequential appearance in DCMS 120.</item>
                        <item><hi rend="bold">Poem Title:</hi> Each poem is given a name. In cases in which there is only one
                            version, it is Dorothy&#8217;s title or, for untitled poems, the first line in quotation marks and square
                            brackets. If there are multiple versions of a poem, we treat the title first used in DCMS 120 as the
                            standard.</item>
                        <item><hi rend="total">Hand:</hi> the person in whose hand the text has been written (DW = <ref target="editions.2022.DW.bios.xml">Dorothy
                            Wordsworth, Dora = Dora Wordsworth, SH = Sara Hutchinson, JH = Joanna Hutchinson, EH = Elizabeth
                            Hutchinson).</ref></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head>
                        Note on Inserts/Patches:
                    </head>
                    <p>We use the insert numbers assigned by the Wordsworth Trust. These capture most of the separate sheets pasted
                        into the notebook, and some but not all of the patches Dorothy added to her poems while revising. As a
                        result, inserts and patches are sometimes denoted by insert numbers, and sometimes are described only
                        as inserts/patches with the relevant folio given to describe where they are added and, usually, how they
                        are attached. In the transcription document, all patches have been separately transcribed, where possible,
                        showing what is written on the original page and what has been pasted on top.</p>
                </div>
    
    <div type="section">
        <head>Table of Contents 1A: Starting from Front Cover</head>
        
    </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
