<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title> 
                
                <title level="a">Version C of <title level="a">Scawfell Excursion</title>: Wordsworth's <title level="m">Guide to the Lakes</title></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>William Wordsworth</name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor">Paul Westover</editor> 
                
                <funder>Brigham Young University College of Humanities</funder>
                <principal>Paul Westover</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>T. J. McLemore</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                    </p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                
                <idno type="edition">editions.2022.DW.SP-C</idno>
                <idno type="resource">DW</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        
                        <title level="a" type="main">Version C of <title level="a">Scawfell Excursion</title>: Wordsworth's <title level="m">Guide to the Lakes</title></title>
                        <ptr target="editions.2022.DW.SP-C.html"/>
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                        <title level="s">Editions</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  PUT YOUR NAME HERE. AND CHANGE THE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION  -->
                <name>Lavender Earnest</name>
                <date>2022-10-04</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                          
            <head>Version C of <title level="a">Scawfell Excursion</title>: Wordsworth&#8217;s <title level="m">Guide to the Lakes</title> (1822)</head>
                
                <div type="paratext">
                    
             <p><hi rend="bold">[Editor&#8217;s note:</hi> The following abridgment of Dorothy Wordsworth&#8217;s <title level="a">Excursion up
                Scawfell Pike</title> became the earliest version to appear in print when her brother
                included it in the 1822 third edition of his <title level="m">Guide to the Lakes.</title> 
                William needed fresh material to expand what had previously been a supplementary essay 
                into a stand-alone guidebook.<note place="foot" resp="editors">Known today as editions of 
                WW&#8217;s <title level="m">Guide to the Lakes</title>, the work&#8217;s stand-alone third (1822) and
                fourth (1823) incarnations were both entitled <title level="m">A Description of the Scenery
                of the Lakes in the North of England.</title> For details on the minor revisions made to 
                    <title level="a">Scawfell Excursion</title> between 1822 and the <title level="m">Guide</title>&#8217;s <!--How can I shorten this URL? Cut off right before /editions? also, add in an anchor to wherever this leads!-->
                fifth and final edition of 1835, see the <ref target="https://romantic-circles.org/sites/default/files/imported/editions/guide_lakes/parallel_text_chart.pdf">
                parallel-text comparison table</ref> in Mason, Stimpson, and Westover&#8217;s Romantic Circles 
                edition of the <title level="m">Guide</title>.</note> In subsequent editions, 
                <title level="a">Scawfell Excursion</title> would be joined by Dorothy&#8217;s 
                <title level="a">Ullswater Excursion</title> and, later, by two of William&#8217;s topographic
                poems in the <title level="m">Guide</title>&#8217;s climactic section. None of these editions,
                however, acknowledged Dorothy&#8217;s authorship, and <title level="a">Scawfell Excursion</title>
                would never be published under her name until 1941.]</p>
                </div>
                
                <lb/><milestone unit="paratext"/><lb/>         
             
             <div type="section">
                 
            <head><title level="m">A Description of the Scenery of the Lakes in the North of England</title> (1822), pp. 129&#8211;36</head>
                 
            <p>It was my intention, several years ago, to describe a regular tour through this
                country, taking the different scenes in the most favourable order; but after some
                progress had been made in the work it was abandoned from a conviction, that, if well
                executed, it would lessen the pleasure of the Traveller by anticipation, and, if the
                contrary, it would only mislead him. The Reader may not however be displeased with
                the following extract from a letter to a Friend, giving an account of a visit to a
                summit of one <span change="brown">[page break]</span> of the highest of these
                mountains; of which I am reminded by the observations of Mr. West, and by reviewing
                what has been said of this district in comparison with the Alps.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">This introductory paragraph is entirely new for the 
                <title level="m">Guide</title>. DW&#8217;s narrative voice takes over at &#8220;Having left Rossthwaite 
                in Borrowdale.&#8221;</note>
            </p>
                 
            <p>Having left Rossthwaite in Borrowdale, on a bright morning in the first week of
                October, we ascended from Seathwaite to the top of the ridge, called Ash-course, and
                thence beheld three distinct views. On one side, the continuous Vale of Borrowdale,
                Keswick, and Bassenthwaite,&#8212;with Skiddaw, Helvellyn, Saddleback, and numerous other
                mountains,&#8212;and, in the distance, the Solway Frith and the Mountains of Scotland. On
                the other side, and below us, the Langdale Pikes&#8212;their own vale below <hi
                rend="italic">them</hi>; &#8212;Windermere, &#8212; and, far beyond Windermere, Ingleborough
                in Yorkshire. But how shall I speak of the deliciousness of the third prospect! At
                this time, <hi rend="italic">that</hi> was most favoured by sunshine and shade. The
                green Vale of Esk&#8212;deep and green, with its glittering serpent stream, was below us;
                and, on we looked to the Mountains near the Sea &#8212;Black Comb pre-eminent,&#8212;and, still
                beyond, to the Sea itself in dazzling brightness. Turning round
                <span change="color">[page break]</span> we saw the Mountains
                of Wastdale in tumult; to our right, Great Gavel, the loftiest, a distinct, and <hi
                rend="italic">huge</hi> form, though the middle of the mountain was, to our
                eyes, as its base.
            </p>
                 
            <p>We had attained the object of this journey; but our ambition now mounted higher. We
                saw the summit of Scaw-fell, apparently very near to us; and we shaped our course
                towards it; but, discovering that it could not be reached without first making a
                considerable descent, we resolved, instead, to aim at another point of the same
                mountain, called the <hi rend="italic">Pikes</hi>, which I have since found has been
                estimated as higher than the summit bearing the name of Scawfell Head,
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">DCMS 51 has &#8220;Scaw Fell&#8221; here, but WW seems eager
                to distinguish more carefully between neighboring Scafell (&#8220;Scawfell Head&#8221;) and the
                slightly higher Scafell Pike.</note> where the Stone Man is built.</p>
                 
            <p>The sun had never once been overshadowed by a cloud during the whole of our progress
                from the centre of Borrowdale: &#8212; on the summit of the Pike, which we gained after
                much toil though without difficulty, there was not a breath of air to stir even the
                papers containing our refreshment, as they lay spread out upon a rock. The stillness
                seemed to be not of this world: &#8212; we paused, and kept silence to listen; and no
                sound could be heard: the Scawfell <span change="brown">[page break]</span> 
                Cataracts were voiceless to us; and there was not an insect to hum in the air. The
                vales which we had seen from Ash-course lay yet in view; and, side by side with
                Eskdale, we now saw the sister Vale of Donnerdale terminated by the Duddon Sands.
                But the majesty of the mountains below, and close to us, is not to be conceived. We
                now beheld the whole mass of Great Gavel from its base,&#8212;the Den of Wastdale at our
                feet&#8212; a gulph immeasurable: Grasmire and the other mountains of Crummock&#8212; Ennerdale
                and its mountains; and the Sea beyond! Gladly<note place="foot" resp="editors">This passage 
                (from &#8220;Gladly&#8221; to &#8220;spotless snow,&#8221; the end of the paragraph) is WW&#8217;s, relocated from elsewhere
                in the <title level="m">Guide</title>. A version of it first appeared on p. 43 of 
                <title level="m">Select Views</title>, in a section describing the neighborhood of Great Gavel,
                Scafell Pike, and the Styhead Pass. It disappeared from the 1820 <title level="m">River Duddon</title>
                version of the text, only to return in this 1822 application.</note>
                would we have tempered our beverage (for there was no spring or well near us) with
                such a supply of delicious water as we might have procured, had we been on the rival
                summit of Great Gavel; for on its highest point is a small triangular receptacle of
                water in the native rock, which, the shepherds say, is never dry. There, we might
                have slaked our thirst plenteously with a pure and celestial beverage, for the cup
                or basin, it appears, has no other feeder than the dews of heaven, the showers, the
                vapours, the hoar frost, and the spotless snow. <span change="brown">[page break]</span> 
            </p>
                 
            <p>While we were gazing around, &#8220;Look,&#8221; I exclaimed, &#8220;at yon ship upon the glittering
                sea!&#8221; &#8220;Is it a Ship?&#8221; replied our Shepherd-guide. &#8220;It can be nothing else,&#8221;
                interposed my companion; &#8220;I cannot be mistaken, I am so accustomed to the appearance
                of Ships at sea.&#8221; The Guide dropped the argument; but, before a minute was gone, he
                quietly said, &#8220;Now look at your Ship; it is changed into a Horse.&#8221; So indeed it
                was,&#8212;a horse with a gallant neck and head. We laughed heartily; and, I hope, when
                again inclined to be positive, I may remember the Ship and the Horse upon the
                glittering Sea; and the calm confidence, yet submissiveness, of our wise Man of the
                Mountains, who certainly had more knowledge of clouds than we, whatever might be our
                knowledge of ships.
            </p>
                 
            <p>I know not how long we might have remained on the summit of the Pike, without a
                thought of moving, had not our guide warned us that we must not linger; for a storm
                was coming. We looked in vain to espy the signs of it. Mountains, vales, and sea
                were touched with the clear light of the sun. &#8220;It is <span change="brown">[page break]</span>
                there,&#8221; he said, pointing to the sea beyond Whitehaven, and there we
                perceived a light vapour unnoticeable but by a Shepherd accustomed to watch all
                mountain bodings. We gazed around again, and yet again, unwilling to lose the
                remembrance of what lay before us in that lofty solitude; and then prepared to
                depart. Meanwhile the air changed to cold, and we saw that tiny vapour swelled into
                mighty masses of cloud which came boiling over the mountains. Great Gavel,
                Helvellyn, and Skiddaw, were wrapped in storm; yet Langdale, and the mountains in
                that quarter, remained all bright in sunshine. Soon the storm reached us; we
                sheltered under a crag; and almost as rapidly as it had come it passed away, and
                left us free to observe the struggles of gloom and sunshine in other quarters.
                Langdale now had its share, and the Pikes of Langdale were decorated by two splendid
                Rainbows; Skiddaw also had its own Rainbows. Before we again reached Ash-course
                every cloud had vanished from every summit.
            </p>
                 
            <p>I ought to have mentioned that round the top of Scawfell PIKE not a blade of grass is
                to <span change="brown">[page break]</span> be seen. A few cushions or tufts of     
                moss, parched and brown, appear between the huge blocks and stones that lie in heaps
                on all sides to a great distance, like skeletons or bones of the earth not needed at
                the creation, and there left to be covered with never-dying lichens, which the
                clouds and dews nourish; and adorn with colours of vivid and exquisite beauty.
                Flowers, the most brilliant feathers,<note place="foot" resp="editors">The comparison 
                to &#8220;brilliant feathers&#8221; appears to be one of WW’s innovations. It appears
                in none of the manuscript sources, though DW does write of the colors that &#8220;no
                gems or flowers can surpass&#8221; in DCMS 51.</note>
                and even gems, scarcely surpass in colouring some of those masses of stone, which no
                human eye beholds, except the Shepherd or Traveller be led thither by curiosity: and
                how seldom must this happen! For the other Eminence is the one visited by the
                adventurous Traveller; and the Shepherd has no inducement to ascend the PIKE in
                quest of his Sheep; for no food is <hi rend="italic">there</hi> to tempt them. 
            </p>
                 
            <p>We certainly were singularly favoured in the weather; for when we were seated on the
                summit, our Conductor, turning his eyes thoughtfully round, said, &#8220;I do not know
                that in my whole life, I was ever, at any season of the year, so high upon the
                mountains on so calm a day.&#8221; (It was the 7th of October.) Afterwards we had the
                storm, which exhibited the grandeur of <span change="brown">[page break]</span>
                the earth and heavens commingled; yet without terror. We knew that it would pass
                away; &#8212; for so our prophetic Guide had assured us.
            </p>
                 
            <p>Before we reached Seathwaite in Borrowdale, a few stars had appeared, and we pursued
                our way down the Vale, to Rossthwaite, by moonlight.
            </p>
             </div>
             </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
