<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Wordsworth on the Greens</title>
                               
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>William Wordsworth</name>
                </author>
                
                <author role="secondary">
                    <name>Michelle Levy</name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor">Michelle Levy</editor> 
                
                
                <funder>Brigham Young University College of Humanities</funder>
                <principal>Paul Westover</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>T. J. McLemore</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- TJ AND JESSICA CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE PAUL'S NAMING CONVENTIONS IN THE "toc_file_names_for_links" DOC THAT IS LINKED TO THE SLACK CHANNEL-->
                <idno type="edition">editions.2022.DW.Greens-WW</idno>
                <idno type="resource">DW</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Wordsworth on the Greens
                        </title>
                        <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE THE NAMING DOC -->
                        <ptr target="editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.Greens-WW"/>
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Dorothy Wordworth's Lake District</title>
                        <title level="s">Editions</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- JESS AND TJ CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">charity</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">childhood</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">community</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">death</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">poverty</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">rural</term>
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <name>Lavender Earnest</name>
                <date>2022-10-29</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>   
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">               
                <head>William Wordsworth on the Greens</head>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>1. From a letter to Francis Wrangham (17 April 1808)
                        <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">Letters</title>, 2:213&#8211;14. Writing to STC two days later, WW explained the origins of this account:
                        &#8220;Within a day or two after my return home, when my mind was easier than it has been since, in passing through the churchyard I stopped at the grave of
                         the poor Sufferers and immediately afterwards composed the following stanzas; <hi rend="italic">composed</hi> I have said, I ought rather to have said effused,
                         for it is the mere pouring out of my own feeling; but if you can turn these verses to any profit for the poor Orphans in any way, either by reciting, 
                         circulating in manuscript, or publishing them, either with or without the name of the Author, pray do so&#8220; (2:219&#8211;220).</note>
                </head>
                
            <p>George Green and Sarah his Wife, Inhabitants of the Vale of Grasmere, having gone to
                Langdale on the morning of Saturday the 19th of March last, set off to return to
                their own house a lonely Dwelling on the same eve[n]ing, intending to cross over the
                mountain. They had left a Daughter at home, eleven years of age, with the care of
                five other children younger than herself, the youngest an infant at the breast. On
                Monday afternoon, one of the Boys went to the nearest house to borrow a Cloak for
                his Sister, who (he said) was going to Langdale to seek their Father and Mother, who
                had not returned as they had expected, on Saturday. Immediately the alarm was
                spread, and continual search was made, as long as daylight lasted, on that day, and
                the day following, and till Wednesday afternoon, when the Bodies of the unfortunate
                Persons were found. It is supposed they had been bewildered by the snow and mist;
                and they perished by falling over the rocks, they were buried in one Grave on the
                Friday afternoon. 
            </p>
                
            <p>The unhappy Fate of this Pair, and the forlorn condition in which the children are
                left, have excited much compassion; which has been more deeply felt in their own
                neighbourhood because the Deceased were much respected for their good morals and
                decent manners, for their frugality and industry, and for the constant cheerfulness
                and independence of mind, with which, without any assistance from the parish, they
                supported their Family under the burthen of extreme poverty. This compassion has
                naturally been accompanied with a general desire that more than ordinary exertions
                should be made to befriend and protect the orphan children. It is therefore thought
                proper to draw up a brief statement of the condition of the Family, for the
                information of such persons as may be disposed to promote this benevolent design.
                </p><pb/>
                
            <p>George Green had been twice married, and has left one Son and three Daughters by his
                first wife who do not stand in need of assistance. By her who died with him, he has
                left four Sons and four Daughters: the eldest of these, a Girl fifteen years of age,
                is at present in Service; the second, a girl likewise, is with a Family who will
                take care of her and fit her out, when she also is fit, for Service. One of the Boys
                will be maintained by his Father&#8217;s eldest Son, who will breed him up to his own
                business; so that there remain five children to be provided for.
            </p>
                
            <p>The Father has left a small Estate which is deeply mortgaged, and it is probable that
                <hi rend="italic">after it is sold,</hi> little or nothing will remain for his
                children. The Parish have therefore agreed to allow, to each of these five children,
                two shillings per week till they are fit to go to Service or to be apprenticed. The
                object then of those Persons who interest themselves on this occasion, is to raise a
                Sum to make an addition to the weekly allowance of the Parish, by means of which the
                children may be placed in a respectable Family or Families: it is also intended to
                send them to School, and what money remains to be employed in setting them forward
                as Servants or Apprentices.
            </p>
                
            <p>It is conceived that it will be grateful to benevolent Persons to promote a
                subscription for the above purpose: first, as a natural tribute of human Sympathy
                upon so melancholy an occasion; secondly, as a testimony of respect for the honesty,
                industry, patient and even cheerful endurance of extreme poverty by which the
                Deceased were distinguished: and lastly, and above all, that there may be a better
                hope that the children may go forward in that course of innocence and virtue in
                which their Parents have thus far conducted them. 
            </p>
         </div>
                
         <lb/><milestone unit="section"/><lb/>
                
         <div type="poetry">
            <head><title level="a">2. Elegiac Stanzas composed in the Churchyard of Grasmere, Westmorland, a few
                    days after the Interment there of a Man and his Wife, Inhabitants of the Vale,
                    who were lost upon the neighbouring Mountains, on the night of the nineteenth of
                    March last</title> (19 April 1808)
             <note place="foot" resp="editors">DW copied this poem into WW&#8217;s 19 April 1808 letter to STC (see n1). It remained unpublished until 1839, when De Quincey printed
                 a substantially revised version in <title level="m">Tait&#8217;s Edinburgh Magazine</title> (see n3).</note>
            </head>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Who weeps for Strangers? &#8212; Many wept</l>
            <l>For George and Sarah Green; </l>
            <l>Wept for that Pair&#8217;s unhappy end, </l>
            <l>Whose grave may here be seen. </l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>By night upon these stormy Heights </l>
            <l>Did Wife and Husband roam; </l>
            <l>Six little-ones the Pair had left </l>
            <l>And could not find their Home. </l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza"> 
            <l>For any Dwelling-place of men </l>
            <l>As vainly did they seek. &#8212; </l>
            <l>He perish&#8217;d; and a voice was heard </l>
            <l>The Widow&#8217;s lonely shriek. </l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Down the dark precipice he fell, </l>
            <l>And she was left alone, </l>
            <l>Not long to think of Children dear, </l>
            <l>Not long to pray or groan! </l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>A few wild steps &#8212; she too was left </l>
            <l>A Body without life! </l>
            <l>The chain of but a few wild steps </l>
            <l>To the Husband bound the Wife. </l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Now lodge they in one Grave, this Grave </l>
            <l>A House with two-fold Roof, </l>
            <l>Two Hillocks but one Grave, their own, </l>
            <l>A covert tempest-proof.</l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>And from all agony of mind </l>
            <l>It keeps them safe and far; </l>
            <l>From fear, and from all need of hope. </l>
            <l>From sun, or guiding Star. </l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Our peace is of the immortal Soul, </l>
            <l>Our anguish is of clay; </l>
            <l>Such bounty is in Heaven, so pass </l>
            <l>The bitterest pangs away. </l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Three days did teach the Mother&#8217;s Babe </l>
            <l>Forgetfully to rest </l>
            <l>In reconcilement how serene! </l>
            <l>Upon another&#8217;s breast </l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>The trouble of the elder Brood </l>
            <l>I know not that it stay&#8217;d </l>
            <l>So long &#8212; they seiz&#8217;d their joy, and they </l>
            <l>Have sung, and danc&#8217;d, and play&#8217;d. </l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Now do those sternly-featur’d Hills </l>
            <l>Look gently on this Grave, </l>
            <l>And quiet now is the depth of air </l>
            <l>As a sea without a wave. </l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>But deeper lies the heart of peace </l>
            <l>In shelter more profound; </l>
            <l>The heart of quietness is here, </l>
            <l>Within this Church-yard ground. </l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>O Darkness of the Grave! how calm </l>
            <l>After that living night, </l>
            <l>That last and dreary living one</l>
            <l>Of sorrow and affright! </l>
            </lg>
             
            <lg type="stanza">
            <l>O sacred Marriage-bed of Death </l>
            <l>That holds them side by side. </l>
            <l>In bond of love, in bond of God, </l>
            <l>Which may not be untied! </l>
            </lg>
                    
      </div>
                <lb/><milestone unit="poetry"/><lb/>  
              
      <div type="poetry">
                    
          <head><title level="a">3. Who Weeps for strangers (1839)</title>
               <note place="foot" resp="editors">This poem, along with WW&#8217;s <title level="a">Elegiac Stanzas</title> on the Greens (see n2), first appeared in Thomas
                   De Quincey&#8217;s <title level="a">Sketches of Life and Manners; from the Autobiography of an English Opium Eater</title> (<title level="m">Tait&#8217;s
                   Edinburgh Magazine</title>, Sept. 1839, 573). Upon republishing this essay in his <title level="m">Recollections of the Lakes and the Lake Poets</title>,
                   De Quincey added a lengthy account of the Greens&#8217; tragic deaths (see <ref target="editions.2022.DW.Greens-intro.xml">introduction to this section</ref>
                   for further details).</note>
           </head>

          <lg type="stanza">
          <l>Who weeps for strangers? Many wept</l>
          <l>For George and Sarah Green;</l>
          <l>Wept for that pair&#8217;s unhappy fate,</l>
          <l>Whose grave may here be seen.</l>
          </lg>
          
          <lg type="stanza">
          <l>By night, upon these stormy fells,</l>
          <l>Did wife and husband roam;</l>
          <l>Six little ones at home had left,</l>
          <l>And could not find that home.</l>
          </lg>
          
          <lg type="stanza">
          <l>For <hi rend="italic">any</hi> dwelling-place of man</l>
          <l>As vainly did they seek.</l>
          <l><hi rend="italic">He</hi> perish&#8217;d; and a voice was heard—</l>
          <l>The widow&#8217;s lonely shriek.</l>
          </lg>
          
          <lg type="stanza">
          <l>Not many steps, and she was left</l>
          <l>A body without life&#8212;</l>
          <l>A few short steps were the chain that bound</l>
          <l>The husband to the wife.</l>
          </lg>
          
          <lg type="stanza">
          <l><hi rend="italic">Now</hi> do those sternly-featured hills</l>
          <l>Look gently on this grave;</l>
          <l>And quiet <hi rend="italic">now</hi> are the depths of air,</l>
          <l>As a sea without a wave.</l>
          </lg>
          
          <lg type="stanza">
          <l>But deeper lies the heart of peace</l>
          <l>In quiet more profound;</l>
          <l>The heart of quietness is here</l>
          <l>Within this churchyard bound.</l>
          </lg>
          
          <lg type="stanza">
          <l>And from all agony of mind</l>
          <l>It keeps them safe, and far</l>
          <l>From fear and grief, and from all need</l>
          <l>Of sun or guiding star.</l>
          </lg>
          
          <lg type="stanza">
          <l>O darkness of the grave! how deep,</l>
          <l>After that living night&#8212;</l>
          <l>That last and dreary living one</l>
          <l>Of sorrow and affright?</l>
          </lg>
          
          <lg type="stanza">
          <l>O sacred marriage-bed of death!</l>
          <l>That keeps them side by side</l>
          <l>In bond of peace, in bond of love,</l>
          <l>That may not be untied!</l>
          </lg>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
