<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Introduction to &#8216;Excursion up Scawfell Pike&#8217; (1818)                   
                </title>
  
                <!-- DW will be the author for the "reading texts" because she is a historical figure, change role to "primary" -->
                
                <author role="secondary">
                    <name>Paul Westover</name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor">Paul Westover</editor> 
                             
                <funder>Brigham Young University College of Humanities</funder>
                <principal>Paul Westover</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>T. J. McLemore</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- TJ AND JESSICA CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE PAUL'S NAMING CONVENTIONS IN THE "toc_file_names_for_links" DOC THAT IS LINKED TO THE SLACK CHANNEL-->
                <idno type="edition">editions.2022.DW.SP-intro</idno>
                <idno type="resource">DW</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Introduction to &#8216;Excursion up Scawfell Pike&#8217;
                        </title>
                        <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE THE NAMING DOC -->
                        <ptr target="editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.SP-intro"/>
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Dorothy Wordworth's Lake District</title>
                        <title level="s">Editions</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- JESS AND TJ CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">Lake District</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">landscape</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">mapping</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">travel</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">walking</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">women writers</term>
                    
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  PUT YOUR NAME HERE. AND ADD THE CODING DATE  -->
                <name>Lavender Earnest</name>
                <date>2022-09-21</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="paratext">
                
            <head><title level="m">5. Introduction to <title level="a">Excursion up Scawfell Pike</title> (1818)</title></head>
            <div type="section"><head>Paul Westover</head></div>
          <!--Am I doing this subtext right-->
                
            <div type="section"><head>I. Contexts</head>
            <list rend="numbered">
                <item><ref target="Overview">Overview</ref></item>
                <item><ref target="Background">Background Story</ref></item>
                <item><ref target="Afterlives">Afterlives: Dorothy’s Mark on the Mountains</ref></item>
            </list>
            </div>        
                
            <div type="section"><head>II. Textual and Editorial Issues</head>
            <list rend="numbered">
                <item><ref target="MSS">Manuscript Witnesses and Related Primary Sources</ref></item>
                <item><ref target="Editorial">Editorial Principles</ref></item>
                <item><ref target="DWandWW">Dorothy’s Account vs. William's Guide to the Lakes</ref></item>
                <item><ref target="Editions">Post-Guide Editions of the Text</ref></item>
            </list></div>
                
            <div type="section"> <!--how do i differentiate different sections within a section? with the essay tag?-->
                <div type="section">
                    <head>I. Contexts</head>
                </div>
                
            <div type="section">
                <head>A. <anchor xml:id="Overview"/>Overview</head>
            </div>
            
            <div type="essay">
                <p>This section of our edition features Dorothy Wordsworth’s account of climbing Scafell Pike,<note place="foot" resp="editors">&#8220;Scaw Fell&#8221; and &#8220;Scawfell&#8221; were common spellings in DW’s time, but today the accepted form is &#8220;Scafell Pike.&#8221;</note> England’s highest mountain, in 1818. A revised and abbreviated version of the text appeared under her brother William’s name in his <title level="m">Description of the Scenery of the Lakes in the North of England</title> (1822), the first stand-alone edition of the work, now commonly known as Wordsworth’s <title level="m">Guide to the Lakes</title> (figs. 5.1 and 5.2). <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">A Description of the Scenery of the Lakes in the North of England</title> (1822) was the third printing of WW’s essay but the first in the form of a guidebook. On the textual history of Wordsworth’s <title level="m">Guide</title>, see the 2015<ref target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/guide_lakes"> Romantic Circles digital critical edition</ref>, ed. Mason, Westover, and Stimpson.</note> Since subsequent editions of William’s <title level="m">Guide</title> continued to present her description of the ascent as his, Dorothy’s authorship was not broadly acknowledged until 1941, when Ernest de Sélincourt included the full text in his important edition of her journals.<note place="foot" resp="editors"> <title level="a">Excursion up Scawfell Pike</title> is the final item in De Sélincourt’s <title level="m">DWJ</title>, vol. 1 (423&#8211;30). De Sélincourt had earlier described and quoted from <title level="a">Excursion</title> in his 1933 DWB (313&#8211;16), but this was the first time the text was presented in full.</note></p>
                
                <p>In the <title level="a">Guide</title>, William introduced Dorothy’s narrative as an &#8220;extract from a letter to a Friend.&#8221;<note place="foot" resp="editors">WW’s &#8220;extract from a letter&#8221; explanation first appeared in the <ref target="https://www.romantic-circles.org/editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.SP-C">1822 Guide (129)</ref>.</note> While this attribution was technically accurate, as Dorothy did send the account in a letter to their mutual friend, the Reverend William Johnson, William never mentioned that the source was his sister’s letter, leaving readers to assume that he was its author. Later writers of travel books, drawing on the <title level="m">Guide</title>, enthusiastically quoted Dorothy’s language as if it were William’s and supposed that he had made the climb. For over a century, then, devotees of the poet intent on emulating his ascent remained unaware that it was, in fact, Dorothy’s footsteps that they were retracing.</p>
            
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1001" width="5.278783333333333cm" height="9.263769444444444cm" url="media/image1.jpeg" rend="inline"/>
                    <graphic n="1002" width="9.776047222222223cm" height="4.499783333333333cm" url="media/image2.jpeg" rend="inline"/>
                        <head>Figures 5.1 and 5.2:</head>
                    <figDesc>(Left) Title page from William Wordsworth’s <title level="m">Description of the Scenery of the Lakes in the North of England</title>. (Right) Selection 
                      from the book’s table of contents, showing &#8220;Ascent to the Top of Scawfell.&#8221; (Courtesy: Brigham Young University, Harold B. Lee Library)</figDesc> 
                </figure>               
                <!--Should the above "Ascent" be double curly quotations or title level="a"? Same question below for "Excursion"-->
                           
                <p>Dorothy’s description of her ascent, which De Sélincourt called &#8220;Excursion up Scawfell Pike,&#8221; is remarkable for at least two related reasons. First, it is a landmark in the history of British mountaineering&#8212;one of the earliest reports of a recreational climb of Scafell Pike (3,209 ft., or 978 m) and the first by a woman.<note place="foot" resp="editors">DW’s account of climbing Scafell Pike was not quite the first. In <title level="m">The Tourist’s New Guide</title> (1819), William Green described summiting the mountain with Jonathan Otley in September 1816 and noted that Otley had already done so with Edward Birkett in June 1815 (2:318&#8211;26). If, as Green claims, he began writing his book in late 1816 and printing it in 1817 (1:vii), his account predated DW’s. It was certainly first in print, as DW’s did not appear until 1822.</note> Second, it captures an aspect of Dorothy’s life that has sometimes been overlooked. Dorothy Wordsworth was a prodigious walker—this fact is well known&#8212;but her pioneering achievements as a mountaineer have insufficiently shaped the public’s memory of her.<note place="foot" resp="editors">Happily, recent scholarship has helped bring DW’s mountaineering into view. See especially Simon Bainbridge’s <title level="m">Mountaineering and British Romanticism</title>, chapter 7.</note> &#8220;Excursion&#8221; helps us reimagine Dorothy on the fells, representing one of her most dramatic walks in the vibrant prose for which she is famous.</p>
                
                <p>Of course, recovering Dorothy’s place in mountaineering history requires bringing her &#8220;Excursion&#8221; out of the shadow of her brother’s writing. One admirer subtly pointed this out in 1855, the year of Dorothy’s death. In a letter to the editor of the <title level="m">Kendal Mercury</title>, venerable mountain guide Jonathan Otley hinted that there was more to tell about the now-famous Scafell Pike adventure: &#8220;The story of the ascent of Scawfell, in Wordsworth’s Guide, said in some former editions to be extracted from a letter to a friend; and in the last edition from a letter by a friend, is well told, and is good as far as it goes; but it might have been improved by a prefatory introduction, and extended by an appendix.&#8221;<note place="foot" resp="editors"> Appearing in the 26 May 1855 issue under the anagrammatic pen name &#8220;Anthony Loajet,&#8221; Otley’s</hi> <title level="m">Kendal Mercury</title> letter was occasioned by the recent publication of Harriet Martineau’s <title level="m">Complete Guide to the English Lakes</title>. Although he did not say so, he must have known that DW (recently deceased) was the letter-writing &#8220;friend.&#8220; The textual change he mentions occurred in the second and third editions of Hudson’s <title level="m">A Complete Guide to the Lakes</title> (1843, 1846), which incorporated WW’s <title level="m">Guide</title> but added supplementary materials.</note> Our introduction and editorial apparatus should perform the record-expanding services that Otley imagined, restoring a historic experience and its documentation to the rightful owner: Dorothy Wordsworth.</p>
          </div>     
            
          <div type="section">           
            <head>
                <anchor xml:id="Background"/>B. Background Story</head>
              <p>On Wednesday, 7 October 1818, Dorothy Wordsworth (age 46) and her friend Mary Barker (age 44) climbed Scafell Pike, the highest mountain in England. They were joined by a shepherd-guide (John Allison, Barker’s neighbor), a porter, and Barker’s maid (Agnes)&#8212;none of whom were named in Dorothy’s account of the adventure.<note place="foot" resp="editors">We owe the names of John Allison (1787&#8211;1855) and Agnes to Otley, who includes them in the <title level="m">Kendal Mercury</title> letter previously cited. Otley was unreliable in some details, but he knew the people concerned and was sound in his basic recollections. While the names of the maid and guide do not appear in DW’s narrative, we include them in part to counteract the tendency to mythologize writer-mountaineers while overlooking those who accompanied them and helped make their accomplishments possible. Agnes was obviously a fit and trusted companion for Mary Barker, though we know little more about her. Perhaps John Allison was no Tenzing Norgay, but he deserves honorable mention in the history of British mountaineering alongside other shepherd-guides of the early days. About the unnamed porter, unfortunately, we know nothing at all. <p>Regarding Agnes, see various letters of SH and DW’s own <title level="m">Journal of a Tour on the Continent</title> (1820), in which she reports on visiting Mary Barker at Boulogne. At this reunion, the party &#8220;had Borrowdale Agnes to wait upon us, a little frenchified in exterior, it is true, but retaining her good Cumberland speech&#8221; (<title level="m">DWJ</title>, 2:331). John Allison’s life is otherwise documented. His grave marker survives at St. Andrew’s Churchyard, Stonethwaite. Fittingly, given his occupation, the stone features a ram and ewe with their lambs and the inscription &#8220;Jesus Saith Feed My Sheep.&#8221; A brief obituary appeared in the <title level="m">Carlisle Patriot</title> for 27 January: &#8220;At Rosthwaite, in Borrowdale, John Allison, on the 22nd inst., Mr. John Allison, yeoman, aged 68.&#8221; Given that Allison and DW passed away within three days of each other in January 1855, Otley’s May letter can perhaps be understood as a tribute to both.</p></note> They walked an ambitious nine-mile loop that took the better part of a day: Dorothy reports setting out in the morning and finishing as the first stars appeared over Borrowdale.</p>
              
              <p>For Dorothy, this hike was the culmination of a season spent among brilliant associates. Her old acquaintance William Wilberforce, the statesman and abolitionist, had arrived in the Lake District with his family in late August 1818 and spent most of September at Rydal to be near the Wordsworths. Sir George and Lady Beaumont, dear friends and prominent art patrons, also visited Rydal in September.<note place="foot" resp="editors">Prior to this, the Beaumonts had been visiting mutual friends, the Marshalls, at Hallsteads on Ullswater&#8212;perhaps one reason why DW wrote to Jane Marshall on 14 October to report on recent adventures.</note> In early October, the Wilberforces decamped to nearby Keswick, where Dorothy and the Beaumonts soon joined them. (William Wordsworth, meanwhile, was occupied with political business.)<note place="end" resp="m">WW missed out on several opportunities that year due to absorption in the Westmorland election and its aftermath. In late June, John Keats tried to visit him at Rydal Mount and lamented that the older poet was out canvassing for the Lowther interest. Famously, several writers of the younger generation condemned his active engagement in Tory politics. DW, for her part, supported WW’s efforts. For accounts of DW’s Scafell Pike walk set against the context of late 1818, see <title level="m">DWB</title>, chapter 16 and <title level="m">Gittings</title>, chapter 15.  </note>Learning of this gathering in Keswick, Mary Barker invited the whole group to dine at her new home in Rosthwaite, Borrowdale, six miles to the south (fig. 5.3).</p>
            
              <figure>
                <graphic n="1003" width="10.287080555555555cm" height="6.855852777777778cm" url="media/image3.jpeg" rend="inline"/>
                <head>Figure 5.3:</head>
                  <figDesc>The Scafell Hotel in scenic Rosthwaite, Borrowdale, originally the home of Mary Barker. It has long been a launching point for walks in the mountains.
                      (Photo: Paul Westover, October 2018)</figDesc>  
            </figure>
 
              <p>A writer, artist, and music teacher, Mary Barker had lived next door to the Robert Southey family in Keswick between 1812 and 1817. She soon became intimate with the larger &#8220;Lake Poet&#8221; circle, and in 1814, Dorothy described her to Catherine Clarkson as the epitome of &#8220;Generosity, Frankness, Sincerity, and perfect disinterestedness.&#8221;<note place="foot" resp="editors">In her letter to Caroline Clarkson, 24 April 1814, DW takes Barker’s part in a dispute with the Southey and Coleridge women next door. She and Barker had been nursing Basil Montagu junior together for several weeks, and this had been an important season for the solidification of their friendship (<title level="m">Letters</title>, 3:137&#8211;44).</note> Dorothy also mentioned her friend’s &#8220;warm temper&#8221; and &#8220;disdain [for concealing] her opinions.&#8221; Barker was passionate, funny, and independent.<note place="foot" resp="editors">Barker’s nicknames included &#8220;The Senhora,&#8221; &#8220;The Colonel,&#8221; and &#8220;The Major.&#8221; Gittings characterizes Barker as a &#8220;rollicking spinster&#8221; (215), and Susan Wolfson as a &#8220;gender-fluid personality&#8221; (<title level="a">Two Wordsworths,</title> 69). The most thorough biographical treatment of Barker is David Bradbury’s <title level="m">Senhora Small Fry: Mary Barker and the Lake Poets</title> (2003). Barker is a major presence in Southey’s correspondence, and she sometimes appears in footnotes to literary history as the author of a 1798 novel, <title level="m">A Welsh Story</title>; as the &#8220;Bhow Begum&#8221; of Southey’s <title level="m">The Doctor</title>; or as the writer of the satirical <title level="a">Lines Addressed to a Noble Lord [Lord Byron] by one of the Small Fry of the Lakes.</title></note>
                  
              <p>Though impractical,<note place="foot" resp="editors">Southey dubbed Barker’s new home &#8220;Barker’s Folly,&#8221; in part because it overtaxed her income (see letter <ref target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2854.html">2584</ref>in <title level="m">Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>). Sara Coleridge offered details in a 4 June 1819 letter: &#8220;Our friend, Miss Barker . . . [,] with an annuity of 400 a year, and 1200 pounds in money . . . [,] is obliged to leave us, and a house in Borrowdale half finished (the foolish building of which, has caused this temporary ruin) and retire to France to live in her Uncle’s house, at Boulogne until her annuity can pay her debts. This is the precious fruits of having <hi rend="italic">a taste for magnificence</hi>. We are sorry to part with her, and so are the Wordsworths, for she was lively, sensible, and accomplished” (Potter, <title level="m">Minnow among Tritons</title>, 76). Because Barker moved to Boulogne in 1819 and never returned to England, the October 1818 walk was one of the last chances for her and DW to make such a memory.</note> relatively isolated, and built alongside a flood-prone branch of the River Derwent, Mary Barker’s new home was nonetheless ideal for hosting friends who shared her taste for mountain scenery.<note place="foot" resp="editors">William Green mentioned Barker’s new home and its setting in his <title level="m">Tourist’s New Guide</title> (1819): &#8220;On the banks of the Stonethwaite arm of the Derwent, there has recently been erected, by Miss Barker, an excellent house, commanding a fine view over the river. . . . There is scarcely amongst these northern vallies, a place, in which an equally valuable collection of painters’ studies may be so speedily collected, as from the environs of Rosthwaite&#8221; (2:136).</note> Dorothy went there on the morning of 5 October, possibly to help with preparations for the dinner. Then, on 6 October, the Wilberforce entourage and the Beaumonts made their way into Borrowdale &#8220;with store of provisions,&#8221; while Barker &#8220;provided vegetables, etc.&#8221;<note place="end" resp="editors">These details appear in DW’s letter to Jane Marshall, 14 October 1818 (<title level="m">Letters</title>, 3:494&#8211;97).</note> In a period famous for its &#8220;immortal&#8221; dinners, this was a gathering worthy of remembrance.</p>
                  
              <p>In the course of conversation, the Wilberforces expressed their intent to ride up Skiddaw (3,054 ft., 931 m), the far-famed mountain overlooking Keswick, on the following morning, and the Beaumonts pledged to accompany them. Wilberforce would be revisiting an ascent he made years earlier while touring the Lakes as a young man. Accordingly, most of the visitors returned to Keswick for the night, looking forward to their outing, but Dorothy stayed at Rosthwaite. She and her host settled on their own hiking plan. Thus, as Dorothy reports, she and Mary Barker summited Scafell Pike on the same day their friends explored Skiddaw, 14 miles to the north. The Skiddaw excursion was less ambitious than the Scafell Pike ascent; still, as Wilberforce was in his late 50s and the Beaumonts in their 60s, none of them in perfect health, we should admire the spirit of this group as well—not least because they got a good wetting in the rain. <note place="end" resp="editors">The Skiddaw ascent must have been a challenge for at least some of the group. William Green, who coincidentally met with the party on the mountain, left a humorous journal entry in which he described Sir George Beaumont as &#8220;Sir George Breadth&#8221; (original owned by Lakeland Arts in Kendal). Green himself was now in his late 50s but was still an enthusiastic walker of the fells.</note>Meanwhile, from high in the mountains above Borrowdale, Dorothy and Mary, enjoying comparatively mild weather themselves, saw rainbows over Skiddaw and felt grateful that the weather had eventually cleared for their friends. </p>
            
             <p>Dorothy and Mary Barker did not at first aim to climb Scafell Pike—their original goal was to ascend Esk Hause (2,490 ft.), a high pass that on a clear day would afford excellent views of the surrounding peaks and valleys. Barker, of late &#8220;an active climber of the hills,&#8221; had recently been to Esk Hause and was eager to share the &#8220;magnificent prospect.&#8221;<note place="foot" resp="editors">We are indebted to Otley for this knowledge, though DW hints at it by mentioning that Barker confidently promised her fantastic views from Esk Hause. On the earlier occasion, Otley reports, &#8220;Miss B. was so enraptured with the prospect that it was not till her maid reminded her that the sun was going down, that she could think of leaving the place; vowing that she would visit it again ere long.&#8221; She and Agnes had to find their own way down into Borrowdale, having been abandoned by their guide. At Seathwaite, they happened to meet John Allison, who promised to &#8220;direct [Miss Barker] by a better route than the one by which she had descended.&#8221; Later, when DW visited, &#8220;[the friends] fixed upon an excursion, and called upon Mr. Allinson [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] to redeem his promise&#8221; (<title level="m">Kendal Mercury</title>, 26 May 1855, 6).</note> However, when the friends arrived at the pass, they decided to press on. As Dorothy reports, their &#8220;spirit of enterprise&#8221; did not fail, and they climbed where, so far as we can tell, few other recreational walkers had been. </p>
            
             <p>Because it was a fine day, they could see for miles in every direction. Heart-stopping views like this were relatively uncommon in an age unfamiliar with air travel and satellite imagery. However, Dorothy characteristically noticed close-range features as well as the vast panorama. She observed, for instance, that the rocks were &#8220;covered with never-dying lichens . . . adorn[ed] with colours of the most vivid and exquisite beauty.&#8221; She also observed the extreme silence of the summit, having had the sound of mountain streams in her ears for much of the ascent.</p>
                  
             <p>Despite her emphasis on accurate description, Dorothy explored the limits of her perceptions. Looking out from the mountain to the sea (over 12 miles away), she supposed she saw a ship. &#8220;<hi rend="italic">Is</hi> it a ship?&#8221; her smiling guide asked. Barker quickly supported Dorothy’s conclusion: &#8220;A ship, yes, it can be nothing else.&#8221; However, a moment later, the &#8220;ship&#8221; had become a horse, for in fact the friends had been watching a cloud. Dorothy enjoyed this joke on herself, resolving to remember it when she was &#8220;again inclined to positiveness.&#8221; Like many great Romantic texts, Dorothy’s <title level="a">Excursion</title> reminds us that what we see depends to some extent on prior experience, perspective, and imagination./p>
                      
             <p>Reading Dorothy’s account, one gets the impression that she was pleased with herself, and rightly so. She remarks upon the “continuance of that vigour of body, which enabled me to climb the high mountain, as in the days of my youth” and reports that she and Barker each dashed off a triumphant letter to Sara Hutchinson<hi rend="foot" resp="editors">SH was of course the sister of WW’s wife, Mary, close to DW, and a friend also to Mary Barker. A keen mountaineer in her own right, she was an integral part of the Wordsworth circle, perhaps most famous now for being the longtime object of STC’s passion. She may be the most important shadow character in the history of DW’s Scafell Pike ascent and the writing that emerged from it. On this subject, see our speculations in paragraph [X—insert link when body paragraphs are numbered] on DW’s memory of STC’s 1802 Scafell ascent and also our appendix on the Kenyon Transcript [insert link].</note> from the summit. (It is remarkable to think of them carrying pens, paper, and ink, if not also something to write on—no wonder they secured the help of a porter!) A week later, Dorothy wrote briefly about the experience to her old friend Jane Marshall,<note place="foot" resp="editors"><persName ref type="a" target="hyperlink-to-index-entry"><!--how do I do this linking stuff again?-->Jane Marshall (née Pollard)</persName> and DW had been friends since their childhood days in Halifax. Jane was married to John Marshall, a wealthy linen manufacturer and politician from Leeds, and now lived at Hallsteads, a fine house on the shore of Ullswater near Watermillock.</note> and a week after that she composed the longer, more circumstantial letter to William Johnson that forms (indirectly, as explained in our textual and editorial section) the basis of our edited text, speaking of the &#8220;feat&#8221; she and Barker had performed and aptly calling it an &#8220;uncommon performance.&#8221; Then, before mailing the letter, she copied it into one of her notebooks for preservation. She and her companion had broken with social convention and done something worth remembering and sharing. Part of their enjoyment, clearly, was writing about it.</p>
            </div> 
                
            <div type="section">
                <head>
                    C. <anchor xml:id="Afterlives"/>Afterlives: Dorothy’s Mark on the Mountains</p>
                </head>            
              <p>When Dorothy Wordsworth climbed Scafell Pike, this mountain&#8212;which had been proven to be England’s highest peak by Joseph Banks’s Trigonometrical Survey in 1790 <note place="foot" resp="editors">Though the Trigonometrical Survey had confirmed the preeminence of Scafell Pike, it appears that the news was not yet universally accepted. DW and Mary Barker thought that neighboring Scafell was the higher peak and found out otherwise only after their ascent. Then, in the <title level="m">Guide</title>, WW introduced DW’s account by saying that it recorded &#8220;a visit to a summit of one of the highest of these mountains,&#8221; as if he were not certain of its claim to be<hi rend="italic">the</hi> highest (<title level="m">A Description of the Scenery of the Lakes</title> [1822], 130 &#8212;or <ref target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/guide_lakes/editions.2020.guide_lakes.1835.html#:~:text=BANKS%20OF%20ULSWATER.-,117,-.%C2%A0%C2%A0%C2%A0%C2%A0%C2%A0%C2%A0%C2%A0%C2%A0It%20was%20my">para. 117 in the 1835</ref><title level="m">Guide</title> text).</note>&#8212;was not yet on the beaten tourist trail. While highland walking had increased in popularity in recent years, the vast majority of Lake District pedestrians tended to stick to well-established routes around the central valleys.<note place="foot" resp="editors">WW makes this point himself in <title level="m">Select Views</title>: &#8220;But it must be observed that the visits of travellers are for the most part confined to the Vales of Coniston, Winandermere with the intermediate country between Ambleside and Keswick, the Vale of Keswick itself, Buttermere, and Ulswater, which are the most easy of access, and indeed from their several characters most likely to repay general curiosity&#8221; (iii&#8212;<ref                              target="https://romantic-circles.org/editions/guide_lakes/editions.2020.guide_lakes.1810.html#:~:text=of%20the%20wheel.-,4.%C2%A0,-Such%2C%20concisely%20given">para. 4</ref> in RC <title level="m">Select Views edition</title>). In short, Romantic-era visitors normally looked <hi rend="italic">up</hi> at the Lake District’s mountains, and when (increasingly) they did seek out the high places, they usually climbed Skiddaw or the more challenging Helvellyn.</note> Maps of the mountains included limited detail, and those enterprising tourists who did explore them generally depended on local guides. In subsequent decades, of course, mountain walks became common practice and guidebook staples. Scafell Pike in particular became a rite of passage for Lakeland peak-baggers. Dorothy and her friends played a part in bringing about this shift, though relatively few people knew this. </p>
            
              <p>The perennial challenge in studies of Dorothy Wordsworth has been her tendency to disappear, a propensity abetted by William’s habit of absorbing her work and by models of literary history that have undervalued the kinds of writing she did and the methods she used to share it. Readers often locate her influence indirectly, in poems of William’s that rework her journal entries, in letters that reveal her collaboration, and so forth, but except on occasions when William mentions her directly or includes her verses in his collections, it is often difficult to say, &#8220;There it is&#8212;there’s Dorothy’s mark.&#8221;</p>
                
            <p>Yet Dorothy’s mark is visible on England’s highest mountain, where walkers have unwittingly followed her footsteps for two centuries now. Almost literally, you find those footsteps inscribed on the landscape in the form of trails (fig. 5.4). To be sure, many aspects of trail-making are determined by practical factors unrelated to literary history, but Dorothy’s Scafell Pike route has endured partly because of her writing’s intersection with the nineteenth century’s multiplication of maps and guidebooks.</p>
                
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1004" width="10.181319444444444cm" height="9.54086388888889cm" url="media/image4.png" rend="inline"/>
                <head>Figure 5.4:</head>
                <figDesc>The route taken by Dorothy Wordsworth, Mary Barker, and their companions
                    on 7 October 1818, ascending from Seathwaite via Grains Gill and returning by way of
                    Sty Head. This loop remains easily traceable on maps today. (Created by Paul
                    Westover and Teresa Gomez, Brigham Young University)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            
                <p>Dorothy observed of Scafell Pike’s rocky summit, &#8220;No gems or flowers can surpass in colouring the beauty of some of these masses of stone which no human eye beholds except the shepherd led thither by chance or traveler by curiosity; and how seldom this must happen!”&#8221;&#8212;seldom because, as she noted, sheep would find little in the rocks to eat, and because recreational fell-walking there was still in its early days. However, once Dorothy’s letter found its way into William’s <title level="m">Guide</title>, a transformative process began. By incorporating Dorothy’s ascent narrative (not far removed in genre from accounts that would later appear in Alfred Wainwright’s books and on trekking websites), the <title level="m">Guide</title> made it a permanent part of the tourist literature and encouraged readers to imagine and undertake their own mountain ascents./p>
            
                    <p>Just as importantly, William’s <title level="m">Guide</title> provided material that would be recycled by other travel writers. Numerous Lakeland guidebooks of the Victorian era, including Harriet Martineau’s famous <title level="m">Complete Guide</title> (fig.5.5), lingered on the <title level="m">Guide</title>’s description of climbing Scafell hike. Normally, writers attributed the description to William, if they attributed it at all, but in doing so they enshrined Dorothy’s descriptive language and itinerary.<note place="foot" resp="editors">At times, DW’s text was (mis-)cited with comical results. Consider Henry S. Salt’s <title level="m">On Cambrian and Cumbrian Hills: Pilgrimages to Snowdon and Scawfell</title> (1908). Salt praises certain descriptions by poets like WW and Walter Scott but gripes that &#8220;on the whole . . . the poets have written about mountains as if they had never set foot on them, but had been content to take the panoramic &#8216;views&#8217; of them from afar&#8221; (46). As evidence, he cites WW’s <title level="m">Guide</title>: &#8220;Even Wordsworth’s prose account of his ascent from Seathwaite &#8216;to the top of the ridge, called Ash Course,&#8217; makes one suspect that his real acquaintance with the hills was very slight; indeed his corruption of the guide’s pronunciation of &#8216;Esk Hause&#8217; . . . into the absurdity of &#8216;Ash Course,&#8217; shows that he had but little sympathetic knowledge either of the nomenclature of the hills or of the dialect of the hillmen&#8217; (46). This sort of thing can happen when you publish your sister’s work as your own; by compressing her account, you make it less nuanced. DW mentions that &#8220;Ash Course&#8221; must be a corruption of &#8220;Esk Hause&#8221; and even provides the etymology for <hi rend="italic">Hause</hi>, the normal word for a mountain saddle in the region. WW’s <title level="m">Guide</title> cuts out her chatty and interesting explanation, leaving Salt, the latter-day man of the mountains, to conclude that the poet was ignorant.</note></p>
                    
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1005" width="8.275241666666666cm" height="6.2064361111111115cm" url="media/image5.jpeg" rend="inline"/>
                <head>Figure 5.5:</head>
                <figDesc>The Scafell Pike section of Martineau’s <title level="m">Complete Guide
                    to the English Lakes</title> (1855 pocket edition), which quotes extensively from
                    Dorothy’s account by way of William’s <title level="m">Guide</title>. Note the imprint
                    from a pressed flower, which suggests that this was once a favorite section of the
                    volume’s owner. On the following page, Martineau writes, &#8220;As far as what is seen
                    from [the peak], the best service to the stranger is still to copy portions of that
                    &#8216;Letter to a friend&#8217; which Mr. Wordsworth published many years ago, and which is the
                    best account we have of the greatest mountain excursion in England&#8221; (138).
                    (Courtesy: Brigham Young University, Harold B. Lee Library)</figDesc>
            </figure>
     
            <p>The transmission process continued across many decades, as Dorothy’s (unacknowledged) observations were reprinted, quoted, and remembered by authors of various publications. Their influence reverberated even as far as Wainwright, the patron saint of latter-day Lakeland fell-walkers, who offered his own endorsement of Dorothy’s path in 1960: &#8220;Of the many routes of approach to Scafell Pike,&#8221; he wrote, &#8220;this, from Borrowdale via Esk Hause, is the finest.&#8221;<note place="foot" resp="editors">Wainwright, <title level="m">Pictorial Guide to the Lakeland Fells</title>, 4: Scafell Pike 18.</note>A few pages earlier, he specifically recommended the loop Dorothy and her friends followed&#8212;ascent via Grains Gill, descent via Sty Head. He might have done this coincidentally, but probably not; he knew Wordsworth’s <title level="m">Guide</title>.</p>
                    
                    <p>Hardwicke Rawnsley, writing in <title level="m">Literary Associations of the English Lakes</title> (1894), captured both the reach and the essential irony of the reception history of Dorothy’s <title level="a">Excursion.</title> Having quoted approvingly from the Scafell Pike section of the <title level="m">Guide</title> and smiled over its observation (by then quaint) that few travelers summit that mountain, he concluded, &#8220;It may well be that never shall we witness such storm-grandeur as it was Wordsworth’s lot to witness when, having climbed hither on a still autumn day, he was bade by his shepherd guide not to linger, for a storm was coming.&#8221;<note place="foot" resp="editors">Rawnsley, <title level="m">Literary Associations of the English Lakes</title>, 1:159&#8211;60.</note> Of course, <hi rend="italic">William</hi> Wordsworth never did witness that storm-grandeur—in fact, he never climbed Scafell Pike at all, so far as records can tell. Rawnsley, like many others, assumed that he had, and his aim was to emphasize that modern pilgrims might stand where the poet had stood. After all, as Rawnsley said, &#8220;the wanderer up Borrowdale and the mountains in its vicinity&#8221; will always &#8220;move&#8221; in &#8220;the company of chosen spirits.&#8221; But which spirits? In the minds of many, the company has always worn trousers, but we hope our edition helps readers correctly imagine skirts and bonnets in the party.</p>
                    
            <p>The 2018 bicentennial of Dorothy’s Scafell Pike adventure offered a unique occasion
                to promote awareness of the “Excursion” and its place in history. A cluster of
                commemorative projects, including an award-nominated exhibition at the Wordsworth
                Museum in Grasmere, <hi rend="italic">This Girl Did: Dorothy Wordsworth and Women
                    Mountaineers</hi>; a series of related lectures, magazine articles, and
                interviews; reenactments of the Scafell Pike and Skiddaw ascents; and a documentary
                film, combined to make this text more visible than perhaps it has ever been.<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Videos associated with the bicentennial may be viewed at the </hi><ref
                                target="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLJvHjPhm4PEZBsk5MuJHSeGI5Jf9cpllY"
                                    ><hi style="font-family:PT Sans;font-size:11pt">Wordsworth
                                    Grasmere YouTube
                                channel</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">. Interviews are available for streaming </hi><ref
                                target="https://www.bbc.co.uk/sounds/play/m00013tt"><hi
                                    style="font-family:PT Sans;font-size:11pt"
                                >here</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> and </hi><ref
                                target="https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/m0002r6p"><hi
                                    style="font-family:PT Sans;font-size:11pt"
                                >here</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> from BBC Radio 4 and from </hi><ref
                                target="https://www.byuradio.org/c9fe31b6-b491-4f5b-afed-e06f2cfa58b0"
                                    ><hi style="font-family:PT Sans;font-size:11pt">BYU
                                Radio</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">. Jo Taylor’s talk at the opening of the Wordsworth Museum’s </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">This Girl
                                Did</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> exhibit is available </hi><ref
                                target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=reVa4SOAZa0"><hi
                                    style="font-family:PT Sans;font-size:11pt"
                                >here</hi></ref><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">. See also Simon Bainbridge’s related December 2018 talk, “’Active Climbers of the Hills’: </hi><ref
                                target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PSdbk5uvHeA"><hi
                                    style="font-family:PT Sans;font-size:11pt">Women in the
                                    Mountains</hi></ref><hi rend="Hyperlink"><seg
                                    style="font-size:11pt"
                                >,</seg></hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">” and his </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Mountaineering and British
                                Romanticism</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> (Oxford UP, 2020), which both details and contextualizes DW’s mountain-climbing career.</hi></p></note></hi>
                This digital edition further aids in this effort, not only by celebrating Dorothy’s
                descriptive prose but also by providing illustrations that will help readers
                visualize the route she and Mary Barker took on 7 October 1818. In particular, we
                recommend visiting our Story Map, a <ref target="https://arcg.is/1C01Lv">multimodal
                    reconstruction of
                    that</ref><ref target="https://arcg.is/1C01Lv" xml:space="preserve"> day</ref><ref
                    target="https://arcg.is/1C01Lv">,</ref> complete with a 3D map, photographs, and
                videos. We trust that these resources help restore “Excursion up Scawfell Pike” to
                the honorable place it deserves in the canon of Dorothy’s writings—and in the
                tradition of ascent narratives generally. </p></div>
                
       <!--Section 2-->         
                
            <p> II. Textual and Editorial Issues</p>
            <p>A. <anchor xml:id="MSS"/>Manuscript Witnesses and Related Primary Sources</p>
            <p>Although De Sélincourt categorized Dorothy’s Scafell Pike account with her journals,
                it is not a diary entry per se. This genre question deserves consideration, for some
                of the text’s character depends on its material forms, its circulation, and its
                audiences. </p>
            <p>In conception, Dorothy’s account emerged from a cluster of letters—including, we
                presume, the lost one she wrote to Sara Hutchinson on top of the mountain. The
                earliest surviving record of her ascent is her letter to Jane Marshall, dated 14
                October 1818, which reads like a seed draft for the expanded report she would pen a
                week later. Dorothy expresses continued admiration for William Wilberforce (“There
                never lived on earth, I am sure, a man of sweeter temper”) and recaps the lively 6
                October dinner at Rosthwaite. “The next day,” she continues, “which was one of the
                finest of the year, I ascended Scaw Fell from Seathwaite with Miss Barker—and never
                before did I behold so sublime a mountain prospect.” Grateful for the weather they
                enjoyed, she reports, “Our Guide, who is a Shepherd of Borrowdale, turning his eyes
                thoughtfully round when we were on the pinnacle of Scaw Fell, said ‘I do not know
                that ever in the whole course of my life, I was at any season so high upon the
                mountains on so calm a day.’ There was not a breath of wind to stir the very papers
                which we spread out with our food, when we ate our dinners on that commanding
                eminence.” Some of this language would reappear almost verbatim in Dorothy’s final
                treatment of the subject.</p>
            <p>The experience of climbing the mountain obviously remained vivid in Dorothy’s mind.
                Eager to share it at length, she wrote on 21 October to the Reverend William
                Johnson, former curate and schoolmaster in Grasmere (1811–1812), who had since taken
                up an important teaching post in London. The original of her letter has been lost.
                Fortunately, two copies survive, and these are our manuscript authorities for
                “Excursion up Scawfell Pike.” </p>
            <p>The most complete extant manuscript is Dorothy’s own backup copy: as noted
                previously, she transcribed her letter to Johnson into a hand-sewn notebook, which
                is now catalogued as Dove Cottage Manuscript (DCMS) 51 (fig. 5.6). Similar to DCMS
                120, which preserves Dorothy’s poetry [link to that section of the edition], DCMS 51
                collects literary efforts that she valued. “Excursion up Scawfell Pike” is its final
                item (fig. 5.7). It features both Dorothy’s edits in ink and various pencil marks,
                possibly by William, which move the text in the direction of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Guide</hi>.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="endnote text"
                            ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Some of the pencil marks on DCMS 51 are literal scribbles—cancellations, insertion marks, and the like—while others suggest verbal revisions. It is difficult to determine who made the marks or when, though many of them do advance reshaping for the </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Guide </hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">project, and it is likely that there are multiple layers. Possibly DW herself undertook adjustments at WW’s request, so we have to take care when assigning intention and responsibility. </hi></p></note></hi>
                Besides the obvious merit of being written in Dorothy’s own hand, this manuscript
                also includes two important notes at the bottom of the last page: “October 21st
                1818” (confirming the composition date of the Johnson letter) and “Went up Scaw Fell
                on Wednesday the 7th October-1818.” </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1006" width="6.01655cm" height="7.982938888888889cm"
                    url="media/image6.jpeg" rend="inline"/>
                <graphic n="1007" width="6.2815916666666665cm" height="8.094938888888889cm"
                    url="media/image7.jpeg" rend="inline"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Figures 5.6 and 5.7: (Left) The cover of DCMS 51, the notebook that contains
                Dorothy’s copy of the Johnson letter. The cover inscription reads
                “Dorothy/Wordsworth/Rydal Mount.” (Right) The beginning of Dorothy’s “Scawfell”
                account.</p>
            <p>The second surviving manuscript, described hereafter as the Kenyon Transcript, is
                written in an attractive, unknown hand on paper watermarked 1817 (fig. 5.8). At once
                a letter in its own right (addressed to “Miss Hutchinson” in Wales) but otherwise
                businesslike, with no conventional gestures of greeting or conclusion, it is
                actually an incomplete copy of Dorothy’s letter to Johnson. It is dated “October,
                1818” and bracketed entirely within quotation marks. It begins, “I must inform you
                of a feat that Miss Barker and I performed on Wednesday the 7th of this month.” In
                short, it omits material that takes up more than a page of Dorothy’s notebook
                version, including her introduction of Mary Barker and her description of the dinner
                at Barker’s home. As Simon Bainbridge summarizes, it “edits out the first part of
                the original letter to focus on the ascent narrative.”<hi rend="endnote_reference"
                        ><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Bainbridge, </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Mountaineering and British
                                Romanticism</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt">,
                    239.</hi></p></note></hi></p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1008" width="6.602133333333334cm" height="10.434594444444445cm"
                    url="media/image8.jpeg" rend="inline"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Figure 5.8: The first page of the Kenyon Transcript, written in an unknown hand.
                (Courtesy: The Wordsworth Trust)</p>
            <p>While DCMS 51 is longer and arguably more authoritative than the Kenyon Transcript,
                much of its final page has been torn out and lost (fig. 5.9). Therefore, at least
                for the closing section of Dorothy’s account, the Kenyon Transcript is essential. </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1009" width="12.066694444444444cm" height="7.688647222222222cm"
                    url="media/image9.jpg" rend="inline"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Figure 5.9: The final two pages of DCMS 51. (Courtesy: The Wordsworth Trust)</p>
            <p>Furthermore, the Kenyon Transcript may match the original Johnson letter more closely
                than the DCMS 51 copy in some respects. We suggest this because DCMS 51 shows edits
                for style and economy that the Kenyon Transcript does not include. Derived directly
                from the Johnson letter (or from yet another copy that has not survived), the Kenyon
                Transcript likely retains many original readings, despite errors in copying.
                Additionally, the transcript includes a final paragraph that Dorothy omits in DCMS
                51: “I believe that you are not much acquainted with the Scenery of this Country,
                except in the Neighbourhood of Grasmere, your duties when you were a resident here,
                having confined you so much to that one Vale; I hope, however, that my long Story
                will not be very dull; and even I am not without a further hope, that it may awaken
                in you a desire to spend a long holiday among the Mountains, and explore their
                recesses.” No doubt this invitation was part of the original letter to Johnson, but
                Dorothy saw no reason to copy it for her own records. </p>
            <p>The Kenyon Transcript complicates the view that Dorothy’s text was never published
                except as part of William’s <hi rend="italic">Guide to the Lakes</hi>. True,
                “Excursion up Scawfell Pike” was never <hi rend="italic">printed</hi> as Dorothy’s
                during her lifetime, but it seems to have enjoyed a lively public (or at least
                semipublic) existence in handwritten forms, moving among family, friends, and
                    associates.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="Times NR 10 footnote"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Considering “Excursion Up Scafell Pike” as a manuscript publication naturally prompts us to ask if still more copies were made. This question may be unanswerable. However, minor variants in De Sélincourt’s edition (</hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">DWJ</hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">) that reflect neither DCMS 51 nor the Kenyon
                                Transcript suggest that an additional copy, now lost, might have
                                been available to him. Owen and Smyser speculate on this point
                                (</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Prose </hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">2:367). Unfortunately, De Sélincourt says nothing about his manuscript sources. </hi></p></note></hi>
                Dorothy did write for an audience. By revealing some of her circuits of
                communication, the Kenyon Transcript helps us guess at the significance of
                “Excursion” for both its writer and her friends and admirers. For more on the Kenyon
                Transcript, please see the appendix to our diplomatic transcription [link]. </p>
            <p>In addition to the missing Johnson letter, the lost letters Dorothy and Mary Barker
                wrote to Sara Hutchinson from Scafell Pike would surely round out our understanding
                of 7 October 1818. Did these summit posts recall another famous “Scawfell letter,”
                written to the same Sara by Samuel Taylor Coleridge 16 years before on the
                neighboring peak?<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="Times NR 10 footnote"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> STC’s exuberant journal-letter to SH has become a classic of mountain literature. He is often said to have been the first nonlocal to climb Scafell and also, accidentally, England’s first rock climber, as he got himself in a tight pinch while descending. From 5 August 1802, we have this self-dramatizing passage: “On a nice Stone Table am I now at this moment writing to you—between 2 and 3 o’clock as I guess, surely the first Letter ever written from the Top of Sca’ Fell!” He adds, “You shall call this Letter when it passes before you the Sca’Fell Letter.” See Griggs, </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Collected
                            Letters</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, 2:834–51. As Bainbridge notes, STC’s letter would be for the Wordsworth circle the “best-known of all descriptions of mountain peril” (235). </hi>
                        </p></note></hi> We can only speculate, but it is not hard to imagine
                Dorothy recalling Coleridge’s exploit. Her “gift for drawing into the present all
                the wealth of past memories” surely applies to this text as it does to others.<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> This description of DW’s tendency to saturate present experience with memory comes from </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt"
                            >DWB</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, 151. </hi></p></note></hi>
                If the missing on-the-spot letters ever surface, we may have more details to enrich
                our story and help us better understand why the Kenyon Transcript was mailed to
                “Miss Hutchinson.” </p>
            <p><anchor xml:id="Editorial"/>B. Editorial Principles</p>
            <p>Our annotated and illustrated reading text [link] is based primarily on DCMS 51, with
                minor emendations indicated in notes and the shift to the Kenyon Transcript (where
                DCMS 51 is torn) clearly indicated. Our emendations reflect the fact that certain
                conventions that today’s readers take for granted were not fully standardized in the
                early nineteenth century. Like other editors of Romantic-era writing, we have tried
                to balance reading convenience with preserving our text’s historical character.<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="Times NR 10 footnote"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Our approach largely corresponds with that of William Knight, who wrote in his preface to </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Letters of the Wordsworth Family </hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">(1907), “I have not retained the punctuation
                                adopted by Wordsworth—sometimes there was none—nor the capital
                                letters, which were both numerous, and very arbitrary. . . .</hi>
                            <hi style="font-size:11pt">It might have been interesting, from a
                                linguistic point of view, to preserve all the archaisms of spelling
                                and punctuation (even when the dashes took the place alike of
                                semicolons, colons, and periods); but the Wordsworth family were so
                                arbitrary and casual in their letter-writing—and even careless at
                                times—that it would have been unjust to them, as well as disturbing
                                to their readers, to have done so” (1:xi).</hi></p></note></hi>
                Insofar as possible, we preserve Dorothy’s paragraphing, though her indentations
                vary and her intentions can be hard to discern. Dorothy’s underlined words are set
                in italics. Her ampersands are converted to <hi rend="italic">and</hi>, and her
                occasional abbreviations are expanded—for example, “Sir G. and &amp; Lady B.” to
                “Sir George and Lady Beaumont.” Capitalization is largely standardized, though we
                retain some instances in which Dorothy seems to capitalize common nouns for
                emphasis. We also retain Dorothy’s spelling. </p>
            <p>Admittedly, any regularization may obscure important ambiguities or idiosyncrasies in
                the text. Some readers may wish to consult the original manuscripts to study
                Dorothy’s frequent and varied uses of dashes, as such marks either disappear in our
                reading text or appear uniformly as em dashes. Others may simply crave more
                antiquarian flavor. Fortunately, our digital edition includes page images of the two
                manuscript sources [links] as well as diplomatic transcriptions [links], allowing
                readers to make their own judgments. In today’s “versioning” culture of editing,
                made convenient by technology, readers can generate their own ideal texts. </p>
            <p>C. <anchor xml:id="DWandWW"/>Dorothy’s Account vs. William’s <hi rend="italic">Guide
                    to the Lakes</hi></p>
            <p>Though based on DCMS 51, the version of “Excursion” that appears in William’s 1822
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Guide </hi>simplifies Dorothy’s textual
                chronology and removes all dates, as if aiming to make the account timeless. It
                introduces various minor revisions.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="endnote text"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> The </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Guide </hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">version changes “Scaw Fell” to “Scawfell Head,” presumably to better distinguish that eminence from Scafell Pike; adds a passage (relocated from a different section of the </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Guide</hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">) about “celestial” drinking water on
                                neighboring Great Gavel; inserts a comparison between the colors of
                                Scafell Pike’s lichen-painted stones and “brilliant feathers”; and
                                so
                                forth.</hi><hi rend="annotation_reference" xml:space="preserve"> </hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">However, these are minor features; the
                                principal transformation comes from removing contextual framing and
                                the participants’ names.</hi></p></note></hi> However, the most
                obvious difference between Dorothy’s manuscript and the adaptation is the latter’s
                reduced length. William’s version includes approximately 1,205 words, whereas
                Dorothy’s original runs over 2,500. Unsurprisingly, Dorothy’s text is richer. The
                    <hi rend="italic">Guide</hi>’s main editorial tendency is to make Dorothy’s
                narrative less personal. In the manuscript, Dorothy begins by recording the visits
                of the Beaumonts and Wilberforces and by introducing Mary Barker—that is, by
                assembling her cast of characters. All of this social context disappears in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Guide</hi>. Thus, when the <hi rend="italic">Guide</hi> reports,
                “Having left Rossthwaite [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] in Borrowdale . . . we
                ascended,” readers have little sense of who “we” might be. In Dorothy’s manuscript,
                readers find friendship, personality, wonder, and humor, all shaping an expedition
                organized by two intrepid women. In William’s abridgment, readers mainly encounter
                landscape visions that might be comparable with those afforded by the Alps.<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="Times NR 10 footnote"
                            ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> WW’s 1822 title page promises “illustrative remarks upon the Scenery of the Alps,” and his attempt to “reconcile a Briton to the scenery of his own country” (120) has included an argument that, although the Lakeland fells cannot compare with the Alps in absolute height and grandeur, they compare favorably in their proportions and combinations. Accordingly, WW introduces DW’s account in this way: “The Reader may not however be displeased with the following extract from a letter to a Friend, giving an account of a visit to a summit of one of the highest of these mountains; of which I am reminded by the observations of Mr. West, and by reviewing what has been said of this district in comparison with the Alps” (129–30). He has already quoted West saying that Britons who intend to tour the Continent should begin in the Lake District “as it will give, in miniature, an idea of what they are to meet with there” (128). He and DW had recently undertaken this sort of comparison, exploring the Alps during their 1820 Continental tour. </hi></p></note></hi>
                After reading William’s version, one knows nothing of the occasion that prompted the
                mountain walk and finds no sign that any women were involved. </p>
            <p>What might Dorothy’s feelings have been about supplying this text for William’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Guide</hi>? We have a few key facts to consider. First, Dorothy
                was part of the project from the start. Back at the time of <hi rend="italic">Select
                    Views</hi> (1810), the first version of what became the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Guide</hi>, William asked Dorothy to finish some of the writing when the work
                became “irksome” to him.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="Times NR 10 footnote"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Letter to Catherine Clarkson, 12 November 1810 (</hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Letters</hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">, 2:449).</hi>
                        </p></note></hi> Meanwhile, Dorothy opined that William might repurpose <hi
                    rend="italic">Select Views</hi>, create his own guide to the Lake District, and
                find the product more lucrative than his “higher [poetic] labours.”<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="Times NR 10 footnote"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Letter to Catherine Clarkson, 18 November 1809 (</hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Letters</hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">, 2:372).</hi>
                        </p></note></hi> William eventually took her advice by including
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Select Views </hi>material in his 1820
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">River Duddon </hi>volume. This experiment
                resulted in encouraging sales and reviews, so issuing a stand-alone guidebook seemed
                like a logical next step. However, for this purpose, William likely sensed that his
                text needed some padding out.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="Times NR 10 footnote"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> In </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">The River
                                Duddon</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, the “Topographical Description of the Country of the Lakes in the North of England” ran to approximately 108 pages (213–321), or about a third of the total volume and some 40 percent of the total word count. The 1822 </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt"
                            >Guide</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> added ten thousand words and came to 156 pages. </hi></p></note></hi>
                Happily, he had promising material on hand in the form of Dorothy’s notebook and its
                copy of the Scafell Pike letter. Dorothy was fond of this autobiographical piece,
                which she had bound with other specimens of her best work (DCMS 51). She was
                probably willing—perhaps even pleased—to see it in print, even if it would appear in
                truncated form. Perhaps William transformed it for his own ends, but we should keep
                in mind the likelihood that Dorothy wanted him to use it and even preferred that he
                remove personal details about her and her friends. Indeed, she may have assisted
                with the edits.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> Compare revisions DW made to </hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Recollections of a Tour Made in Scotland, A.D. 1803 </hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">(described well in </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt"
                            >DWB</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, 411–12) when preparing a copy for possible publication; also, consider her rationale for refusing to print her “Narrative Concerning George and Sarah Green,” discussed elsewhere in this edition [link]. Tact and privacy were important to her. </hi>
                        </p></note></hi> The <hi rend="italic">Guide</hi> was an important effort in
                favor of the family economy, and Dorothy supported this endeavor as she had so many
                others. </p>
            <p>Readers must decide for themselves about the ethics of William’s borrowing, an issue
                that has been addressed repeatedly in studies of the Wordsworths but perhaps not
                sufficiently with respect to “Excursion up Scawfell Pike.” This instance of
                appropriation seems unique in scale and significance, as William tacitly takes
                credit not only for Dorothy’s writing but also for her physical accomplishment.
                Might it not have been a simple matter for William to describe the account as “an
                extract from <hi rend="italic">my sister’s</hi> letter to a friend”? Nonetheless, we
                have no evidence that Dorothy objected to his editorial sleight of hand. Lucy
                Newlyn’s observation, offered in a different context, may apply in this situation:
                “Dorothy’s preference was always for an anonymous role in their collaboration, but
                this need not be read as a sign that she believed herself inferior. . . . Her labour
                was not alienated, and she knew her gifts to be greatly valued.”<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt"
                            >Newlyn</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, 238. </hi></p></note></hi></p>
            <p>In any case, the <hi rend="italic">Guide</hi>’s incorporation of Dorothy’s Scafell
                Pike ascent must have been thought a success by all concerned. The 1822 <hi
                    rend="italic">Guide</hi> sold well, and then, in the 1823 edition, another gem
                from Dorothy’s notebook (DCMS 51) was added: her account of an 1805 walking tour
                around Ullswater [link to Ullswater section of the edition]. This meant that
                Dorothy’s presence in the <hi rend="italic">Guide</hi> grew as the project evolved.
                We do not know precisely how many words she contributed in 1810 or 1820,<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="Times NR 10 footnote"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> For conjectures on this point, see </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Prose </hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">2</hi><hi rend="italic"
                                style="font-size:11pt"
                            >:</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">126, 143. One substantial 1810 passage Owen and Smyser conclude to be DW’s, written in her hand, comes to 452 words. Unfortunately, handwriting in the surviving </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Guide </hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">manuscripts is no sure evidence of authorship, since DW, WW, MW, and SH all took turns writing. </hi></p></note></hi>
                but in 1822, she generated at least 1,200 words out of the total 29,800 (about 4
                percent), and in 1823, at least 4,446 words of 35,300 (13 percent). The placement of
                her offerings was also important, since her two “excursions” became the final,
                climactic section of the book.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="endnote text">
                            <hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">As Mary Ellen Bellanca argues, DW’s writing reached readers mostly “by means of William’s poetic reputation and in context ancillary to it,” but it </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt"
                                >did</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> find readers, and indeed it “helped to </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt"
                                >make</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> [WW’s] reputation”; therefore, “it is well past time to discard the notion of Dorothy Wordsworth as an unpublished, or only posthumously published, writer” (</hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Daybooks</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, 138). Along this line, it is noteworthy that enthusiastic readers of the </hi>
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Guide </hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">often singled out DW’s contributions. See,
                                for instance, one of the earliest reviews, which quoted the Scafell
                                Pike narrative at length (“Wordsworth’s Scenery of the Lakes,”
                                494–95).</hi></p></note></hi>
            </p>
            <p>D. <anchor xml:id="Editions"/>Post-<hi rend="italic">Guide</hi> Editions of the
                Text</p>
            <p>For over a century, the survival of Dorothy’s “Excursion” in print depended on the
                popularity of William’s <hi rend="italic">Guide</hi>. William Angus Knight did not
                include it in his 1897 edition of Dorothy’s journals or his 1907 <hi rend="italic"
                    >Letters of the Wordsworth Family</hi>. Consequently, as noted previously, its
                full public introduction had to wait for the appearance of De Sélincourt’s 1941
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Journals </hi>(vol. 1).<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> De Sélincourt had not included the text in his (first) edition of WW and DW’s correspondence, published 1935–39, possibly because the original letter was missing. However, he did include the related letter to Jane Marshall and mention in a footnote that DW’s account of climbing Scafell Pike could be found (revised) in WW’s </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Guide</hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">.</hi></p></note></hi> De Sélincourt’s
                edition, with its brief but valuable introduction, remained the standard for
                years.</p>
            <p>In 1970, the text appeared in the revised Oxford
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Letters of William and Dorothy Wordsworth </hi>(vol.
                3, <hi rend="italic">Middle Years II, 1812–1820</hi>). This resource correctly
                reframed the text as a letter (“D. W. to William Johnson”); however, some
                information it provided was misleading. The editors of that volume, Mary Moorman and
                Alan G. Hill, cited as their manuscript authority “<hi rend="italic">WL transcript
                    [possibly in John Carter’s hand]</hi>.”<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                        place="end"><p rend="endnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt"
                            >Letters</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, 3:499. </hi></p></note></hi>
                Either that document has been lost or, more likely, the editors meant to describe
                what our edition calls the Kenyon Transcript, which is definitely not in John
                Carter’s hand. Moreover, the editors did not faithfully follow that source. Instead,
                they largely adopted De Sélincourt’s text from <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>,
                though they did add one sentence, Dorothy’s final invitation to come explore the
                mountains. </p>
            <p>A few years later, W. J. B. Owen and Jane Worthington Smyser provided a more reliable
                and thoroughly annotated version of the Scafell Pike “Excursion” as an appendix to
                    <hi rend="italic">The Prose Works of William Wordsworth</hi>, vol. 2 (1974),
                aiming to illuminate the origins of the <hi rend="italic">Guide to the Lakes</hi>.
                Unfortunately, <hi rend="italic">Prose Works</hi> is out of print, expensive to
                purchase on the used market, and available mainly in research libraries. It remains
                an essential source for scholars aiming to trace textual variants; however, it is
                neither easily obtained nor especially friendly for the general reader, and it
                places Dorothy Wordsworth in a secondary role.</p>
            <p>“Excursion up Scawfell Pike” was occasionally mentioned in scholarship of the 1980s
                and 90s; for instance, Susan M. Levin discussed it in her <hi rend="italic">Dorothy
                    Wordsworth and Romanticism</hi> (1987). Surprisingly, however, Levin chose to
                omit it from her own anthology, <hi rend="italic">Dorothy Wordsworth, A Longman
                    Cultural Edition</hi> (2009). Susan Wolfson chose in 1999 to include most of
                Dorothy’s “Excursion” in <hi rend="italic">The Longman Anthology of British
                    Literature</hi>, making the text available to student readers for the first
                    time.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="Times NR 10 footnote"
                                ><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve"> The text appeared in all five editions of the </hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">Longman Anthology of British Literature </hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">(1999 forward), specifically in </hi><hi
                                rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">Volume 2A, The Romantics and
                                Their
                            Contemporaries</hi><hi style="font-size:11pt" xml:space="preserve">, coedited by Susan Wolfson and Peter Manning. Wolfson has been one of the text’s most prominent recent champions. See also her “Two Wordsworths,” 61–82. </hi></p></note></hi>
                A few respected critics have discussed the text more recently. Still, it seems safe
                to say that the text remains an underappreciated part of Dorothy’s oeuvre. We trust
                that this digital edition makes “Excursion up Scawfell Pike” available to a broader
                audience while also providing a vital and up-to-date resource to scholars. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
