<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Introduction to First Notebook of the Grasmere Journal
                </title>
                
                
                <!-- DW will be the author for the "reading texts" because she is a historical figure, change role to "primary" -->
                <author role="secondary">
                    <name>Michelle Levy</name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor">Michelle Levy</editor> 
                
                
                <funder>Brigham Young University College of Humanities</funder>
                <principal>Paul Westover</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>T. J. McLemore</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- TJ AND JESSICA CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE PAUL'S NAMING CONVENTIONS IN THE "toc_file_names_for_links" DOC THAT IS LINKED TO THE SLACK CHANNEL-->
                <idno type="edition">editions.2022.DW.GJ-intro</idno>
                <idno type="resource">DW</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Introduction to First Notebook of the Grasmere Journal
                        </title>
                        <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE THE NAMING DOC -->
                        <ptr target="editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.GJ-intro"/>
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Dorothy Wordworth's Lake District</title>
                        <title level="s">Editions</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- JESS AND TJ CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">Lake District</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">landscape</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">mapping</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">travel</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">walking</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">women writers</term>
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  PUT YOUR NAME HERE. AND ADD THE CODING DATE  -->
                <name>Emily Stephens</name>
                <date>2022-10-20</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    
    
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head>2. Introduction to First Notebook of the Grasmere Journal</head>
                <head type="subhead">(DCMS 20, 14 May&#8211;22 December 1800</head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Michelle Levy</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>Furman University</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
                <div type="paratext">
                    <p rend="large">I: Contexts</p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item><ref target="#Return">A. Return to the Lakes </ref></item>
                        <item><ref target="#Walking">B. Walking in the Lakes</ref></item>
                        <item><ref target="#Writing">C. Writing the Journals</ref></item>
                        <item><ref target="#Publication">D. Publication and Reception History of the Journals</ref></item>
                    </list>     
                    
                    <p rend="large">II: Textual and Editorial Issues</p>    
                </div>
                <lb/><milestone unit="paratext"/><lb/> 
    
        <div type="section">
            <head>I. Contexts</head>
            
            <p>In this section, we present the entirety of Dorothy Wordsworth’s first Grasmere
                journal notebook, DCMS 20. This notebook includes entries for 172 days, from 14 May
                to 22 December 1800, as well as other miscellaneous material Dorothy copied into the
                pages. The contents of this single notebook are reproduced through diplomatic
                transcription, meaning that we record as closely as possible the appearance of the
                text in the original manuscript. Thus, we preserve all of Dorothy’s original
                spellings and abbreviations and her marks of revision (corrections, cancellations,
                substitutions) as well as, where possible, other nonlinguistic marks (such as lines
                she draws between some journal entries), in addition to her line and page breaks.
                There are multiple reasons for keeping editorial intervention to a minimum. By
                copying Dorothy’s words and punctuation as they appear on the page, we make her
                compositional processes more available to interpretation—processes that are often
                obscured in regularized edited versions of the journal. For example, her use of
                contractions, abbreviations, and ampersands suggests that she wrote in haste. For
                similar reasons, we include all of her journal entries rather than editorial
                selections. By reviewing each entry, it is possible to follow her daily routines as
                she recorded them, over a six-month period, without focusing on exceptional entries
                or events. The preservation of line breaks reminds readers of the diplomatic
                transcription of the small size of the notebook Dorothy used and the short nature of
                the entries themselves. In sum, this straightforward presentation supports
                understanding of the material practices and structures within which Dorothy wrote
                all four notebooks of her now-famous Grasmere journals.
            </p>
        </div>
            
        <div type="section">
                <head type="subhead">
                    <anchor xml:id="Return"/>A. Return to the Lakes
                </head>
            
            
            <p>Dorothy and William Wordsworth were born (in 1771 and 1770, respectively) in
                Cockermouth, Cumberland (now Cumbria), about 25 miles northwest of Grasmere. They
                and their three brothers were separated after the death of their mother in 1778:
                Dorothy was sent to live with her mother’s cousin in Halifax, West Yorkshire (and
                later with other relatives), while William was sent with his brother Richard to
                Hawkshead Grammar School, six miles due south of Grasmere (see fig. 2.3). William
                and Dorothy did not see each other again for nine years. They were together briefly
                in 1787, before William went to Cambridge, and ultimately, they lived together in
                various residences from 1795 onward, first in Racedown, Dorsetshire, and then in
                Alfoxden, Somerset, southwest of Bristol. On 17 December 1799 (after a cold winter
                spent in Goslar, Germany), brother and sister moved to Town End, Grasmere, adopting
                the home now known as Dove Cottage. They would live in Grasmere and the nearby
                village of Rydal (see fig. 2.3) for the rest of their lives. The first surviving
                journal of their time after returning to live in the Lakes, Dorothy’s first Grasmere
                journal was begun on 14 May 1800, in a very small notebook (at 15 x 9.5 cm, it is
                only slightly larger than an iPhone 8), now known as DCMS 20.
            </p>
            
            <p>The entries in this journal notebook therefore offer the first glimpses into the
                siblings’ lives after returning to the Lake District, covering the second half of
                their first year in Grasmere and tracing Dorothy’s activities as they set up their
                own household and began, for the first time, to live on their own terms. It was an
                important period for the Wordsworths, a moment that combined a sense of homecoming
                with experiences of dislocation and itinerancy. At least in this first year, they
                were not quite locals, though they were not quite tourists either. Upon moving to
                Grasmere, Dorothy and William began the practical labor of creating a home for
                themselves, as they improved their cottage and garden; made new friendships,
                particularly with two families resident nearby, the Simpsons and the Lloyds;
                nourished old intimacies, especially with the Coleridges and the Hutchinsons;
                reacquainted themselves with Lakeland ways; and walked everywhere, having no other
                means of transportation and being devoted to pedestrianism as a form of recreation
                and exploration. The journal also reports on an essential period of their shared
                literary life, as William composed poetry for the second volume of the second
                edition of <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title> (1800) and as brother and sister
                prepared the volume for the press.
            </p>
            
            <p>The opening entry in the journal (see fig. 2.1 for its first page and fig. 2.2 for
                pages 4 and 5) is dramatic. In it, Dorothy takes up her pen after the departure of
                her two brothers, John and William, to visit Mary, Sara, and Tom Hutchinson in their
                new home in Yorkshire. John, a sailor, had come to live with Dorothy and William in
                January 1800, after an eight-year separation. William and Dorothy knew the
                Hutchinsons from Penrith, where Dorothy had gone to live with her maternal
                grandparents as a 16-year-old. William met the Hutchinsons during school holidays;
                and he would later marry Mary Hutchinson, in October 1802. All of this context
                informs our reading of this first entry, which begins with an emotional intensity
                that is not often repeated. Dorothy finds herself overwhelmed upon saying goodbye to
                William (“My heart was so full that I could hardly speak to W when I gave him a
                farewell kiss”); she describes the “flood of tears” that follows and ends the entry
                with a wish for a letter from her brother (“Oh! that I had a letter from William!”),
                even though he has only just left. The entry is also remarkable for its length (at
                450 words, it is the longest entry that does not involve Dorothy trying to catch up
                on multiple days) and because, in it, Dorothy describes herself in the present
                moment of journal writing (“It is nine o’clock, I shall soon go to bed.”). Normally,
                her journal is retrospective, but in key instances Dorothy writes to the moment.
            </p>
            
            <figure>
                <graphic url="PLACEHOLDER" width="400px" rend="inline"/>
                <head>Figure 3.3:</head>
                <figDesc>The first page of Dorothy’s journal entries in DCMS 20.
                    Some of the stubs from the six excised pages at the beginning of the notebook
                    are visible, as are figures scribbled at the top of this page, demonstrating
                    previous uses of the notebook. (Courtesy: The Wordsworth Trust)
                </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
    
            <p>In this entry, Dorothy reflects, directly for the first and only time in the
                surviving journals, on her purpose for keeping one:
            </p>
        </div>
                
        <div type="poetry">
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>Sate down very often – tho’ </l>
                <l>it was cold – I resolved to write </l>
                <l>a journal of the time </l>
                <l>till W &amp; J return – &amp; I </l>
                <l>set about keeping my re=</l>
                <l>=solve because I will not quar=</l>
                <l>=rel with <del rend="strike">my</del> myself &amp; because </l>
                <l>I shall give W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Pleasure by </l>
                <l>it when he [illegible deleted word] comes home </l>
                <l>again.</l>
            </lg>
        </div>
                
        <div type="section">
            <p>To be sure, she would discover additional uses for the journal over time (just
                as she had prior uses, as is evidenced in the sums found at the top of fig. 2.1),
                but here she frames her resolution to keep it primarily as a means of consoling
                herself for the grief she feels at the departure of her brothers (“because I will
                not quarrel with myself”) and as a gift for William upon his return, presumably
                because it will allow him to share in her daily activities, thoughts, and
                encounters. The speed with which Dorothy wrote this and most of her other entries is
                apparent in pages 4 and 5 of her first journal entry (fig. 2.2). Notice, for
                instance, her use of abbreviations (W and W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> for
                William, J for John); in the cancellation of “my,” possibly because it was written
                too close to the previous word, followed by her rewriting “myself”; and in the
                deleted and undecipherable word in the middle of page 4. The minuteness of the
                notebook is also apparent in the very short lines (most have only five to seven
                words) and in the formation of letters, which though legible are often far from
                neat.</p>
            
            <figure>
                <graphic url="PLACEHOLDER" width="400px" rend="inline"/>
                <head>Figure 2.2:</head>
                <figDesc>The fourth and fifth pages of the journal (DCMS 20),
                    showing the notebook open. A ruled line at the end of page 5 indicates how
                    Dorothy usually denotes a break between days. (Courtesy: The Wordsworth
                    Trust)
                </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
           
            
            <p>Within this first entry, we see how Dorothy’s stated aims coalesce. The act of
                recording her daily activities offers her solace for her loneliness and allows her
                to reflect on the productive nature of her days, spent working in the house and
                garden, reading and writing, visiting with friends, and walking. These activities
                follow the daily rhythms of life: the chores necessary to run a household, such as
                washing and mending, as well as those tasks she seems to have taken special pleasure
                in, such as gathering plants and flowers for her garden. At the end of the first
                entry, for example, Dorothy reports, “Arrived at home with a bad head-ach – set some
                slips of privett. The evening cold – had a fire – my face now flame-coloured.” This
                entry offers a foretaste of the descriptions to come, as she enumerates her daily
                household chores, all undertaken with a bad headache on a cold May day, after a long
                and emotionally draining walk. Throughout this notebook, we learn that Dorothy had
                help with some chores, as she mentions her neighbors from the cottage across the
                road, John Fisher; his wife, Aggy (Agnes); and his sister Molly (Mary) Fisher.
                Pamela Woof notes that Molly was paid two shillings a week “to clean, light fires,
                wash dishes, prepare vegetables, do the weekly small clothes wash, and the 5-weekly
                ‘great wash.’”
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">GJ</title>, 165.</note>
            </p>
            
            <p>Still, Dorothy had “a good deal” to do (in her own oft-repeated phrase)—ironing,
                baking, weeding—work that was physically demanding and time-consuming but that also
                represented more acceptable forms of labor for a middle-class woman. The kitchen
                garden was an important source of food, such as peas and turnips, and it is evident
                that much effort was needed to grow and harvest these crops, as it was more
                generally to manage a home at the beginning of the nineteenth century, in one of the
                wettest parts of England, with minimal help from servants. She also engaged in
                shoemaking, wallpapering, and mattress making, with one mattress being sent to the
                Coleridges in Keswick. Dorothy took delight and pride in her pleasure garden, and
                she transplanted the mosses, plants, and flowers that she gathered on her walks or
                bought from others. When William returned on 7 June, they stayed up until 4:00 a.m.
                “so he had an opportunity of seeing [their] improvements” when the sun came up, and
                she expressed satisfaction two days later when a party in “a coronetted Landau [a
                luxury carriage bearing an insignia of the nobility] . . . (evidently tourists)
                turned an eye of interest upon [their] little garden &amp; cottage.”
            </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">    
            <head type="subhead">
                <anchor xml:id="Walking"/>B. Walking in the Lakes
            </head>
            
            <p>Dorothy’s encounter with tourists traveling by landau contrasts strongly with her own
                pedestrianism. The Wordsworths had no horse or carriage in their early Grasmere days
                and got around on foot. Indeed, perhaps most striking to the modern reader of DCMS
                20 is the centrality of walking to Dorothy’s daily life, an activity that brought
                her into close contact with a landscape she loved, with friends and family (with and
                to whom she often walked), and with the local farmers and shepherds, beggars, and
                itinerant laborers who also traversed the neighborhood. Indeed, walking emerges as
                an organizing feature of her (and her brother’s) daily life. She repeatedly speaks
                about going out for “[her] walk,” suggesting that it is the walk itself—the physical
                activity and the opportunity it allows for experiencing her natural
                surroundings—that serves as the prime motivator for the activity. She rambles
                through almost all weather, in all seasons, in rain and snow, by moon and starlight,
                often not returning home until late in the evening. Dorothy was proud of her skill
                and endurance as a walker. On 18 May, she notes, “I was overtaken by 2 Cumberland
                people on the other side of Rydale who complimented me upon my walking.” In most
                entries, Dorothy takes care to describe all of these activities: whether and where
                she has walked, her household chores, her engagement in sociable activities, and her
                participation in intellectual and literary work such as reading, copying, writing
                letters, and, of course, keeping her journal. As the record of an indefatigable
                pedestrian and a young, single woman interested in the lives and livelihood of
                others of all ages and social classes, the journal provides its readers with a tour,
                informal and unplotted as it is, as well as with commentary on the Lake District’s
                topography and ecology, and on the life—social, economic, intellectual, creative—of
                those who live there.
            </p>
            
            <p>Within the lengthy first entry for 14 May 1800, Dorothy records the walk she takes
                (after parting with her brothers at the shores of Lake Windermere), including the
                route she took and her observations along the way. She describes three encounters
                with individuals as she walks along the public roads: with a blind man driving
                bulls, with a poor woman from Rydal who begs a half penny, and with a young woman
                from Manchester who has buried three children and a husband in a pauper’s grave.
                Walking thus affords Dorothy opportunities for encountering both nature and human
                nature, and these experiences weave throughout the journal. (Some of them, famously,
                reappear in William’s poems.) The Rydal woman tells Dorothy that she has never
                begged before but has been forced to do so because of these “hard times.” The
                representation of poor men, women, and children, many of whom are homeless and
                itinerant and forced to beg, whom she meets on her walks and at her door (Dove
                Cottage was then on the main road, so it was a usual place for those passing through
                to stop and beg for money or food), attest to the economic dislocations of
                industrialization and war affecting England at the start of the new century.
            </p>
            
            <p>Dorothy’s record of and response to the speech, appearance, and actions of these
                distressed people form an important aspect of her journal. She often reflects on the
                residents of the vale and how they too are adversely affected by the “hard times.”
                On 18 May, she quotes her neighbor, John Fisher, who expresses concern “about the
                alteration in the times,” observing “that in a short time there would be only two
                ranks of people, the very rich &amp; the very poor, for those who have small estates
                says he are forced to sell, &amp; all the land goes into one hand.” Several years
                later, she would address the dire circumstances of small landowners in 
                <ref target="/editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.Greens-intro><title level="m">
                A Narrative concerning George &amp; Sarah Green of the Parish of
                Grasmere addressed to a Friend</title>(1808) </ref>. In her journal entries and 
                elsewhere, we find Dorothy expressing her
                awareness of and sympathy for the suffering of those around her, as well as her
                desire to voice their concerns. Indeed, her walking could itself be seen as an act
                of solidarity with the poor.
            </p>
            
            <p>Rarely is there an entry in this notebook that does not mention walking. Even when
                she does not walk, an explanation is usually given for why it has not been possible
                to do so (the reasons are illness, visitors, or severe weather). Of the 172 days
                recorded in the journal, Dorothy reports walking on 125, or 73 percent of the total.
                On 37 of these days, she reports walking two or three times. Some of these walks are
                left unspecified, such as on 23 November, when we are simply told, “Sarah &amp; I
                walked after dinner.” However, on many if not most days, it is possible to have a
                much more precise sense of where she goes. Many of Dorothy’s walks are solitary
                rambles, but, as noted previously, few days go by without Dorothy visiting or being
                visited by her friends.
            </p>
            
            <p>The 1818 map detailed in figure 2.3, with Grasmere in the near center (and Dove
                Cottage marked by the rectangle on the road to east of the lake), enables us to
                better visualize her daily walks, which moved in every direction from her home. One
                frequent destination was the town of Ambleside, to the south, where mail was
                delivered and picked up, a distance of about four miles each way. Often, she
                describes taking the route to Ambleside via Clappersgate. In November 1800, Charles
                Lloyd; his wife, Mary; his sister Priscilla; and their children moved to Old
                Brathay, southwest of Ambleside (denoted as “Brathay” on the map), and Dorothy
                visited them frequently. Clappersgate and Brathay are at the head of Lake
                Windermere, and it was just south of there, at Low Wood on the eastern shore, that
                Dorothy parted from William and John as reported in her first journal entry.
            </p>
            
            
            <figure>
                <graphic url="PLACEHOLDER" width="400px" rend="inline"/>
                <head>Figure 2.3:</head>
                <figDesc><title level="m">Detail from New Map of the District of the Lakes, in
                    Westmorland, Cumberland, and Lancashire</title>, scale
                    bout 4 miles to 1 inch, by Jonathan Otley, engraved by J. and G. Menzies,
                        Edinburgh. The map dates from 1817 to 1818. This copy appears in Otley’s 
                        <title level="m">A Concise Description of the English
                        Lakes</title>, 5th ed. (Keswick, 1834). (Courtesy: SFU
                        Library, Special Collections and Rare Books)
                </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            
            <p>More westerly is Langdale, the neighboring vale, under the mountains known as the
                Langdale Pikes. Dorothy reports walking to Langdale on three occasions (16 and 23
                June and 7 September): on 16 June she mentions visiting Collath (Colwith) and
                Skelleth (Skelwith), also visible on the map, and on 23 June she describes seeing
                Elterwater. She “peeps” into Langdale valley, by climbing around Loughrigg, one of
                the fells to the south of Grasmere, another two times (30 August and 4 December). To
                the south and east and closer to home are the neighboring village of Rydal and lake
                of the same name; and there are also the hills behind Dove Cottage, where Dorothy
                acquires mosses and plants.
            </p>
            
            <p>Figure 2.4, from the same map, takes a wider view to include the area north of
                Grasmere. In July 1800, Samuel Taylor Coleridge had moved to Keswick, to be nearer
                to the Wordsworths, his new home at Greta Hall being about 13 miles northeast of
                Grasmere (along what was known as the Keswick Road, which passed over Dunmail Raise,
                denoted as “Raise” on the map but spelled as “Rays” by Dorothy). Dorothy walked to
                Keswick at least three times in the six-month period described in this notebook, in
                August, November, and finally in December, when her journal entry mentions “snow
                upon the ground.” On 17 November 1800, she records the time it took for her to walk
                from Dove Cottage to Keswick for this second trip of the year: “Set off at 5 minutes
                past 10, &amp; arrived at ½ past 2.” Thus, she covers about three miles per hour,
                walking uphill much of the way. Much closer to Grasmere but along the same road is
                the village of Wythburn, a common turning-around point for Dorothy when she
                accompanies William on the first part of his journeys to Keswick. Dorothy also
                frequently walks to Wythburn, the home of Miss Elizabeth Jane Simpson and her
                father, the Reverend Joseph Simpson, vicar of the village’s small church.
                <note place="end" resp="editors"> Wythburn Church still stands, but most of the small 
                    community it served was destroyed when the Thirlmere Reservoir was created in 1894.
                </note>
                Elizabeth was near in age to Dorothy (Dorothy was 29,
                Elizabeth about 33, in 1800), and the distance between their homes was about 1.5
                miles. To the northwest, even closer to home, is the Easedale valley, often referred
                to by the Wordsworths as the “Black Quarter”—a favorite place for their walks; one
                can also see “Helm [Crag]” on the map, the iconic local fell that looks over
                Grasmere and Easedale, mentioned frequently in the journal along with other
                surrounding hills. </p>
            
            <figure>
                <graphic url="PLACEHOLDER" width="400px" rend="inline"/>
                <head>Figure 2.4:</head>
                <figDesc>Second detail from Otley’s <title level="m">New Map of the District of the Lakes, in
                        Westmorland, Cumberland, and Lancashire.</title>
                </figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            
            <p>To some extent, Dorothy’s walking habits depend on who is at Dove Cottage with her.
                After William’s return from his visit to Penrith, her routine changes slightly; she
                describes less wandering and more fishing on the lake. When she has company, such as
                during the extended, 3½-week visit with the Coleridges in July or Coleridge’s visit
                alone in December, she stops writing in her journal, so we learn less about her
                walking during those periods (see figure 2.6). When Coleridge comes, Dorothy appears
                to be excluded from some longer and more arduous walks undertaken by the men—for
                instance, Coleridge, brother John, and William climb Helvellyn (England’s
                third-highest mountain), Seat Sandal, and the path to Stickle Tarn (Langdale)
                without her. All three destinations may be seen in figure 2.4. It is not clear why
                Dorothy did not accompany the men on these 1800 walks. She would not be left out for
                long. By late 1801, she had attempted Fairfield and reached the summit of Helvellyn.
                We know from <title level="m">A Narrative concerning George &amp; Sarah Green</title> that
                by 1808 she had been to Stickle Tarn. In short, Dorothy would make these ascents
                (and many others) in the years to come.
                <note place="end" resp="editors"> On DW’s evolution as a fell walker, see Bainbridge, 
                    <title level="m">Mountaineering and British Romanticism</title>, chapter 7. DW became
                    increasingly active in mountain excursions and related writing, as
                    emphasized in our section on her 1818 <ref target="/editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.SP-intro">
                    <title level="a">Excursion up Scawfell Pike</title></ref>. In reporting to 
                    Catherine Clarkson about her 1820 tour of
                    the Continent, DW remarked with forgivable pride, “Let no one speak
                    of fatigue in crossing the Alps who has climbed Helvellyn. It is
                    nothing in point of exertion to that ascent” (<title level="m">Letters</title>,
                    :640, 3 September 1820).
                </note>
            </p>
            
            <p>Examining and closely reading a single notebook allows us to understand the
                centrality of walking to Dorothy Wordsworth. Walking was important for her physical
                and mental health. Certainly, it invested her with a strong sense of independence
                and personal worth. Many of Dorothy’s later travel narratives also describe her mode
                of travel as chiefly pedestrian, reflecting the profound importance that walking had
                for her writing. Furthermore, Dorothy’s inability to walk later in life, when beset
                by illness, became the subject of one her most celebrated poems, “Thoughts on my
                sickbed” <ref target="PLACEHOLDER">(see Section 7 of this edition)</ref>. <!--WHERE IS THIS POEM??-->
            </p>
        </div>
        
        <div type="section">
            <head type="subhead">
                <anchor xml:id="Writing"/>C. Writing the Journals
            </head>
            
            <p>Like most diarists, Dorothy sometimes gets behind, and she writes at highly variable
                levels of detail. Sometimes she composes retrospectively, and at other times she
                writes to the moment. In the first entry, as we have seen, she writes in the
                present, and also on 3 September: “– writing my journal now at 8 o clock.” On 19
                October, we seem to catch her writing in installments within a single entry: “We are
                not to dine till 4 o clock ––– Dined at ½ past 5.” Additionally, there are many
                indications, both direct and indirect, that Dorothy did not consistently write her
                entries on the day she describes. In an undated entry after 13 September, she notes,
                “Here I have long neglected my Journal” and inserts a compensatory entry covering
                the period from 19 to 30 September. An earlier example appears between 25 June and
                26 July. Beneath the entry for 25 June, Dorothy reports that the Coleridges arrived
                on Sunday, 29 June and stayed for over three weeks, departing on Thursday, 24 July
                (Dorothy mistakes this date as 23 July). In other words, we have a gap of five days.
                Moreover, in this catch-up entry, Dorothy provides an extremely truncated account of
                the Coleridges’ visit. All we learn about this 26-day period (Sunday, June 29 to
                Thursday, July 24) is that on the Friday before her friends’ departure, the group
                took tea on the island (in Grasmere); that on the Sunday before they had tea in
                Bainriggs with the Simpsons, Dorothy accompanied Sara Coleridge to Wythburn; and
                that the weather was hot. We see a similar brevity at play when Coleridge visits in
                December (there is a gap between 4 and 15 December; see fig. 2.6) and when Dorothy
                travels to Keswick, between 9–16 August and 10–14 December. Sometimes, we conclude,
                she was just too busy to write.
            </p>
            
            <p>The <title level="m">Grasmere Journals</title> have long been read for the way they
                illuminate the literary labors pursued by, and often shared between, brother and
                sister. Within the pages of DCMS 20, Dorothy regularly mentions the time she spends
                reading (sometimes out of doors), writing letters, writing new verse from dictation
                or copying poetry (such as on 17 December, when she is “Writing all the morning for
                William”), and of course composing the journal entries themselves. At times, we see
                such activities overlapping, as when Dorothy copies unpublished stanzas drafted for
                <title level="a">Complaint of the Forsaken Indian Woman,</title> a poem first published in <title level="m">
                Lyrical Ballads</title> (1798), at the end of the notebook. The
                journal documents a shared life and shared work.
            </p>
            
            <p>A careful reading of DCMS 20 also enables us to piece together how Dorothy’s journal
                entries might have been shared with her brother and how William often took
                inspiration and even phrases from Dorothy’s journals for use in his poems. On 10
                June 1800, just a few days after William’s return home on the 7th, Dorothy includes
                a long narrative recollecting her encounter with a tall beggar woman and her family
                from more than two weeks prior. In this case, Dorothy reaches back to record a past
                event, possibly because after William returned home and Dorothy had told him about
                it, he asked her to describe it in her journal, their common memory device. In a
                journal entry from 13 March 1802, we find a precise description of how William
                returned to this 1800 entry nearly two years later:
                
                <quote>William finished <title level="m">Alice Fell</title>, &amp; then he wrote the poem of
                the Beggar woman, taken from a Woman whom I had seen in May–(now nearly 2 years ago)
                when John &amp; he were at Gallow Hill – – I sate with him at Intervals all the
                morning, took down his stanzas, &amp;c — . . . . After tea I read to William that
                account of the little Boys belonging to the tall woman &amp; an unlucky thing it was
                for he could not escape from those very words, &amp; so he could not write the poem,
                he left it unfinished &amp; went tired to Bed.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">GJ</title>,
                            77.
                    </note>
                </quote>
            
            <p>Also within DCMS 20 we find Dorothy’s lengthy description of a leech gatherer (in an
                entry for 3 October 1800), which was later used to shape <title level="a">Resolution and
                Independence,</title> drafted between 4 May and 4 July 1802. Perhaps one of the reasons for
                the careful preservation of this (and other notebooks) is that the use of the
                journal entries could be delayed by many years. In some cases, however, the uptake
                was more immediate: on 11 October 1800, Dorothy describes walking to an abandoned
                sheepfold in Greenhead Ghyll (the mountain stream that runs to the northeast of the
                Swan in fig. 2.3), capturing thoughts and images central to William’s poem
                <title level="a">Michael,</title> which is already being drafted at the time.
            </p>
            
            <p>Dorothy’s entry of 13 March 1802, discussing William’s vexed attempt to write a poem
                about the tall beggar woman, suggests that William could feel stimulated but also
                trapped by Dorothy’s words. It is not known whether the “very words” she uses
                confine him because he feels obligated not to use them or because—as seems more
                likely—they dominate his mind, seem impossible to surpass, or do not fit the meter
                or mode of poetic composition he is attempting. Dorothy seems sympathetic to the
                writer’s block she has induced (“unlucky thing it was”), though perhaps she takes
                some pleasure in knowing her words have impact.
            </p>
            
            <p>The journal’s descriptions of collaboration, whether smooth or frustrated, raise
                ethical questions about William’s use of Dorothy’s writing. Such questions have long
                been a source of interest and concern to feminist scholars who, since the 1980s,
                have raised claims that William appropriated Dorothy’s work and stifled her
                creativity, preventing her from becoming “more than half a poet.”
                <note place="foot">In an oft-cited journal entry for 18 March 1802,
                            DW describes how viewing Rydal Lake at moonlight “made [her] more than
                            half a poet” (<title level="m">GJ</title>, 81).
                </note> 
                As Patricia Comitini has noted, most “scholarship has focused
                primarily on [Dorothy’s] failure to realize herself, develop her talent, or
                establish her own home,” and William’s uncredited use of her writing is often blamed
                for this.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">Comitini, <title level="a">ʻMore Than Half a Poet,’</title>
                        307.
                </note> 
                Ultimately, however, Dorothy’s fate was tied to that of
                her brother, and his ability to produce marketable poems was indispensable to the
                family economy. Lucy Newlyn has written eloquently about the siblings’ relationship,
                understanding that their literary, affective, and economic lives were inevitably
                intertwined.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">See <title level="m">Newlyn</title>.</note> 
                It should also be remembered that Dorothy’s economic
                dependency, as a single woman without property, meant that, practically speaking,
                she <emph>was</emph> unable to assert intellectual
                property in her “very words.”
            </p>
        </div>
                
        <div type="section">
            <head type="subhead">
                <anchor xml:id="Publication"/>D. Publication and Reception History of the Journals
            </head>
            
            <p>It is unknown the extent to which Dorothy’s journal notebooks may have been read by
                others besides William during the period in which they were being written and
                subsequently during the remaining 55 years that she lived. We do know that William’s
                nephew, Christopher Wordsworth, learned of their existence and, in his 1851 
                <title level="m">Memoirs of William Wordsworth</title>, included over 50 pages from
                the four Grasmere journal notebooks and Dorothy’s unpublished <title level="m">
                Recollections of a Tour Made in Scotland</title>. According to Mary Ellen
                Bellanca, the “avowed purpose for excerpting her texts [was] to furnish contexts for
                the poems,”
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Bellanca, <title level="a">After-Life-Writing,</title> 
                    204.
                </note> 
                and Christopher directly stated
                that the “materials” like Dorothy’s journals and letters were to be considered
                “subordinate and ministerial to the Poems, and illustrative of them.”
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">Memoirs</title>, 1:3.</note> 
                Nevertheless, as Bellanca
                explains, many of Christopher’s selections “bear little relation to the poetry or
                even significant incidents” but were included for their intrinsic merit, and in
                particular as a means of presenting Dorothy “in effect, as a nature writer.”
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Bellanca, <title level="a">After-Life-Writing,</title> 
                    208, 204.
                </note>
                Here we find a blueprint for the reception of Dorothy’s writing that to a large
                extent continues today, in which the <title level="m">Grasmere Journals</title> are
                understood to be central to her reputation, their value conceived as depending on
                their descriptions of natural scenery and the context they provide for her brother’s
                life and poems.
            </p>
            
            <p>Dorothy’s Grasmere-period journals were first presented to the public in a more
                complete form than the 1851 <title level="m">Memoirs</title> allowed in William
                Knight’s
                <title level="m">Journals of Dorothy Wordsworth</title> of 1897.
                In his introduction, he notes, albeit with some concern, that “many sentences in the
                Journal present a curious resemblance to words and phrases which occur in the
                    poems.”
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">KJ</title>, xviii–xix.</note>
                His edition
                offers special praise for the Grasmere journal (“To many readers this will be by far
                the most interesting section of all Dorothy Wordsworth’s writings”) and describes
                their importance in terms nearly identical to those articulated by Christopher
                Wordsworth:
            
                <quote>[The journal] not only contains exquisite descriptions of Grasmere and its district—a
                most felicitous record of the changes of the seasons and the progress of the year,
                details as flower and tree, bird and beast, mountain and lake—but it casts a flood
                of light on the circumstances under which her brother’s poems were composed.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">KJ</title>, ix–x.</note>
                </quote>
            
                Knight enhances this “flood of light” by including footnotes referencing passages in
                the journal that are echoed in William’s poems, a practice that was continued by her
                next editor, Ernest de Sélincourt, in 1941.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">DWJ</title>, 1:37–189.</note>
                Fortunately, De Selincourt restored many of the passages Knight saw fit to censor in
                his edition: chiefly, Knight cut Dorothy’s descriptions of laborious housework,
                bodily functions, and physical illnesses, as well as her commentary about some
                members of the community (such as drunken priests and battered wives), which he
                presumably thought were indelicate to bring before his Victorian readers.
            </p>
            
            <p>The <title level="m">Grasmere Journals</title> were first initiated into the canon of
                Romantic literature for the reasons identified by Christopher Wordsworth and William
                Knight. Brief selections from the journals were the first writing by a woman of the
                Romantic period to be included in the
                <title level="m">Norton Anthology of English Literature</title> (in
                the third edition of 1974), chiefly because they could be used to illuminate
                William’s poetry.
                <note place="end" resp="editors">Abrams, ed., <title level="m">Norton Anthology of English
                    Literature</title>, 3rd ed., 2:263&#8211;83.
                </note>
                Notwithstanding significant shifts in how Dorothy’s writing
                is understood today, nearly 50 years after her first appearance in the <title level="m">Norton</title>, 
                student anthologies continue to emphasize entries
                that speak to her brother’s poetry, illuminate their shared domestic and emotional
                life, or (in keeping with the vision of Romanticism as inspired nature writing)
                foreground Dorothy’s perspicacious observations on her surroundings. For example,
                the 2000 (7th) edition of the
                <title level="m">Norton Anthology of English Literature</title> includes
                only four entries from this first notebook, all of which directly relate to William
                and his poetry: 
            </p>
        </div>
        <div type="paratext">
            
            <list type="ordered">
                <item>14 May 1800 (the first entry);</item>
                <item>3 October 1800 (on the leech gatherer);</item>
                <item>11 October 1800 (on the sheepfold); and </item>
                <item>12 October 1800 (which includes descriptions of William composing and Dorothy
                    copying poems and a description of autumnal foliage). </item>
            </list>
        </div>
                
        <div type="section">
            <p>The second edition of the <title level="m">Broadview Anthology of Literature</title>
                (2006) includes the same first three entries (14 May, 3 and 11 October 1800), and
                many similar examples might be cited. These anthologizing practices arguably distort
                the content of the journals, selected because they illuminate William’s creative
                processes and surroundings. One of our chief aims in representing this first
                notebook in its entirety (as opposed to making selections from all four Grasmere
                journal notebooks) has been to focus attention on the richness and diversity of
                Dorothy’s writing about her life in Grasmere and also to provoke us to understand
                that while her brother and his poetry were important elements of her life, they were
                not centrally or exclusively what the journal was about.
            </p>
            
            <p>Additionally, many print sources ignore the materiality of the originals and the
                obvious facts that the entries were handwritten, seemingly quickly, in very small
                notebooks, often many days after the scenes and events described. Selections such as
                we find in modern anthologies often provide a false impression of the journal
                entries as carefully wrought vignettes, products of a reflective, sedate life. This
                edition counters these impressions by reproducing, as precisely as possibly,
                Dorothy’s words in a diplomatic transcription. In addition, facsimiles of several
                notebook pages have been provided to help the reader to understand the appearance
                and dimensions of the notebook, the entry system Dorothy used, and the handwriting
                within it. By these means, we can trace how Dorothy missed or misdated days, made
                strikethroughs and emendations, and generally wrote in haste, in moments snatched at
                the end of what appear to have been very full and tiring days. We can observe
                Dorothy including references to individuals and places without providing explanation
                or context, as it was unnecessary for her to do so given her imagined (and actual)
                audience of her brother. The next section provides more detail about the material
                nature of the notebook and our edition of it.
            </p>
        </div>
                
        <div type="section">
            
            <head>
                II. Textual and Editorial Issues
            </head>
            
            <p>Unlike the writings by Dorothy included in most other sections of this edition, no
                one, including Dorothy, recopied the first Grasmere journal notebook. It exists in a
                single manuscript, DCMS 20. As we have seen, Dorothy was prompted to begin the
                journal because of the departure of her brothers on a trip to Yorkshire.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">Journaling itself was not new to DW. Her
                       first known diary, kept between 20 January and 22 May 1798, is known
                       as the Alfoxden Journal (named after the home where she and WW lived
                       in Somerset). This manuscript was edited, perhaps heavily, by
                       William Knight, who published it along with the Grasmere-period
                       journals in 1897. Unfortunately, the manuscript has not survived; it
                       may have been lost or destroyed by Knight himself. DW also kept a
                       journal during the early part of her visit, with WW, to Hamburg and
                       Goslar, Germany, from 14 September to 1 October 1798. This journal
                       was also included by Knight.
                </note> 
                Three other notebooks (DCMS 25, 10 October 1801 to 14
                February 1802; DCMS 19, 14 February to 2 May 1802; and DCMS 31, 4 May 1802 to 16
                January 1803) make up the remainder of what are now called the 
                <title level="m">Grasmere Journals</title>, though there is a gap between the first notebook and
                the second. The last entry in DCMS 20 is dated 22 December 1800, and it ends
                midsentence. In another notebook, now missing, Dorothy likely continued this
                sentence; and she continued that journal in the next surviving Grasmere notebook
                (DCMS 25), which begins at 10 October 1801, more than nine months after DCMS 20
                abruptly ends. Dorothy would continue to write journals, across multiple notebooks,
                for most of her life. We include selections from the <ref target="/editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.RJ-overview">Rydal notebooks</ref> in this edition.
            </p>
            
            <p>As mentioned previously, DCMS 20 is small, measuring just 15 x 9.5 cm, with mottled
                brown paper covers. It was not unused when Dorothy came to it in May 1800. Remaining
                stubs of cut-out pages have discernible writing on them, as do the endpapers. As
                Pamela Woof explains, the stray figures, accounts (see fig. 2.1), lists, and German
                words indicate that the notebook had been used during the Wordsworths’ visit to
                Germany in 1798–1799.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="endnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">GJ</hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">, 159–60.</hi></p></note></hi> The notebook
                as we have it now begins in one direction with the first journal entry; however,
                before that, it had apparently been used the other way round. From the other end,
                following the five cut-out pages, Dorothy copied down four epitaphs from her visit
                to Durham in the early summer of 1799.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"
                            ><p rend="endnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:11pt">GJ</hi><hi
                                style="font-size:11pt">, 159–60.</hi></p></note></hi> The epigraphs
                are followed by five unpublished stanzas of William’s “Complaint of the Forsaken
                Indian Woman,” a poem first published in <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads</hi>
                (1798). These verses end halfway down a page, with the final journal entries for
                December 1800 meeting them but being written with the book rotated 180 degrees (see
                fig. 2.5). Transcriptions of the epitaphs and William’s poem are included in our
                edition to demonstrate the heterogeneous nature of the notebook’s contents. They
                also remind us of the thrift involved in writing within the Wordsworths’ household;
                as a partially used notebook, with many pages remaining, it was available for reuse.
                Paper was an expensive commodity during the period, and making the most of a small
                notebook was another way to practice economy. As a notebook, moreover, DCMS 20 could
                be easily transported: we know Dorothy had it in Germany, and it is also possible
                she brought the notebook with her when she went to visit the Coleridges in Keswick,
                though if she did, she used it sparingly. </p>
            <figure>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1005" width="7.0220416666666665cm" height="11.260666666666667cm"
                        url="media/image5.tiff" rend="block">
                        <desc>Text, letter Description automatically generated</desc>
                    </graphic>
                </figure>
                <figure>
                    <graphic n="1006" width="6.955013888888889cm" height="11.153069444444444cm"
                        url="media/image5.tiff" rend="block">
                        <desc>Text, letter Description automatically generated</desc>
                    </graphic>
                </figure>
            </figure>
            <p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10.5pt">Figure
                2.5:</hi><hi style="font-size:10.5pt" xml:space="preserve"> The last page of DCMS 20, shown to the left, with the final journal entry, to the right, including lines of William’s “Complaint of a Forsaken Indian Woman.” (Courtesy: The Wordsworth Trust)</hi></p>
            <p>Dorothy left no room, in the top or bottom or side margins, or between the lines, for
                additions, once again demonstrating thrift in using all available space (see fig.
                2.5) and suggesting no intention to revise the journal entries. She did on occasion
                cancel a word or two, and in those cases where a deleted word (or two or three)
                cannot be made out, it is noted (as “[illegible deleted word]”) in the
                transcription. Many of the changes were made in the first instance of writing, as a
                word was crossed out and immediately replaced in the same line. Dorothy does appear
                to have returned to the manuscript after the entries had been made, however, and
                made some changes, particularly to correct dates, which she had frequently
                mistaken.</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1007" width="12.457041666666667cm" height="9.944005555555556cm"
                    url="media/image6.tiff" rend="inline">
                    <desc>Text, letter Description automatically generated</desc>
                </graphic>
            </figure>
            <p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10.5pt">Figure
                2.6:</hi><hi style="font-size:10.5pt" xml:space="preserve"> Entries for Wednesday and Thursday, 3 and 4 December, and Friday, 15 December, in DCMS 20. The entries do not register the gap of 11 days during Coleridge’s visit. (Courtesy: The Wordsworth Trust)</hi></p>
            <p>The handwriting throughout the notebook is legible but variable in size and far from
                tidy. It is quite different from the careful, even hand we see on display in her
                fair copies (such as the hand that appears in her <hi rend="italic">Journal of a
                    Tour of the Continent</hi>, DCMS 90—fig. 2.7) but more like the writing of her
                informal letters. Her punctuation is erratic. Indeed, often there is no punctuation
                at all, and when there is, her dashes, periods, and commas are often
                indistinguishable. We have not edited her writing to include additional punctuation,
                and we have tried to reproduce her marks as they appear, though doing so often
                presents a challenge (as in marks appearing in unexpected or indeterminate places or
                the many canceled words that are impossible to decipher). In addition to her
                handwriting and mistakes in dating, the lack of punctuation reinforces the
                conclusion that Dorothy usually wrote quickly. In keeping with the journal form, she
                dates her entries (though again, often erroneously and irregularly) and uses ruled
                lines to signify breaks between them. Discernible changes in the ink and handwriting
                between the entries are rare.</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic n="1008" width="7.805347222222222cm" height="10.175875cm"
                    url="media/image7.tiff" rend="inline">
                    <desc>Text, letter Description automatically generated</desc>
                </graphic>
            </figure>
            <p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10.5pt">Figure
                    2.7:</hi><hi style="font-size:10.5pt" xml:space="preserve"> DCMS 90, 52, </hi><hi
                    rend="italic" style="font-size:10.5pt">Journal of a Tour on the
                    Continent</hi><hi style="font-size:10.5pt">. (Courtesy: The Wordsworth
                    Trust)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Readers interested in the remaining three journal notebooks are urged to consult
                Pamela Woof’s Oxford World’s Classics edition of
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Grasmere and Alfoxden Journals </hi>(2002).</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
