<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title> 
                <title level="m">Introduction to Poems from the Commonplace Book (DCMS 120)</title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Dorothy Wordsworth</name>
                </author>
                
                <author role="secondary">
                    <name>Michelle Levy</name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor">Michelle Levy</editor> 
                
                
                <funder>Brigham Young University College of Humanities</funder>
                <principal>Paul Westover</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>T. J. McLemore</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- TJ AND JESSICA CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="edition">editions.2022.DW.Poems-intro</idno>
                <idno type="resource">DW</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title level="m" type="main">Introduction to Poems from the Commonplace Book (DCMS 120)
                        </title>
                        <ptr target="editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.Poems-intro"/>
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Dorothy Wordworth's Lake District</title>
                        <title level="s">Editions</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- JESS AND TJ CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">charity</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">childhood</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">community</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">death</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">poverty</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">rural</term>
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  PUT YOUR NAME HERE. AND ADD THE CODING DATE  -->
                <name>Emily Stephens</name>
                <date>2022-11-7</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
            <head>6. Introduction to Poems from the Commonplace Book (DCMS 120)</head>
                   <byline>
                            <docAuthor>Michelle Levy</docAuthor>
                            <affiliation>Furman University</affiliation>
                   </byline>
                        
                        <div type="paratext">
                            <p rend="large">I: Contexts</p>
                            <list type="unordered">
                                <item><ref target="#Brief">A. Brief Introduction to Dorothy Wordsworth&#8217;s Poetry and DCMS 120</ref></item>
                                <item><ref target="#Poetry">B. Poetry In (and Out of) the Commonplace Book</ref></item>
                                <item><ref target="#Arrangement">C. The Arrangement, Presentation, and Reception of the Poems</ref></item>
                                <item><ref target="#D.">D. &#8220;D. Wordsworth: Old Poetess&#8221;</ref></item>
                                <item><ref target="#Poems">D. Poems of Memory and Consolation: <title type="a">I trod the hills again</title></ref></item>
                            </list>     
                            
                            <p rend="large"><ref target="#Textual">II: Textual and Editorial Issues</ref></p>    
                        </div>
                        <lb/><milestone unit="paratext"/><lb/> 
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>I. Contexts</head>
                    <head type="subhead">
                        <anchor xml:id="brief"/>A. Brief Introduction to Dorothy Wordsworth&#8217;s Poetry and DCMS 120
                    </head>
            
            <p>While individual poems by Dorothy Wordsworth appeared in nineteenth-century
                collections of her brother&#8217;s verse and twentieth-century teaching anthologies, the
                first comprehensive presentation of her poems didn&#8217;t appear until 1987, when Susan
                Levin published them as the appendix to her critical study <title level="m">Dorothy
                Wordsworth and Romanticism</title>, an effort she later amplified with her
                important teaching edition, <title level="m">Dorothy Wordsworth: A Longman Cultural 
                Edition</title>, in 2009. These were milestone
                events, as Levin&#8217;s editorial work introduced the poems to a broad academic audience
                and sparked a wave in which scholars such as Pamela Woof, Rachel Feder, Lucy Newlyn,
                and Levin herself published thoughtful readings of Dorothy&#8217;s verse. Since their
                first appearance in Levin&#8217;s monograph in 1987, several of Dorothy&#8217;s poems have been
                anthologized, frequently appearing alongside selections from the Grasmere journal
                notebooks. Two notable poems, <title level="a">Thoughts on my Sickbed</title> and 
                <title level="a">Grasmere&#8212;A Fragment,</title>
                have also been included in recent editions of the
                <title level="m">Norton Anthology of English Literature</title> and
                the <title level="m">Broadview Anthology of British Literature</title>. Interestingly,
                the poems currently featured in teaching anthologies are not among the five that
                were published in Dorothy&#8217;s lifetime. Even <title level="a">Floating Island at Hawkshead,</title> perhaps
                her best-known and finest poem, has been omitted. But the anthologized examples are,
                arguably, those that may be considered her most &#8220;Wordsworthian,&#8221; insofar as they
                elaborate themes also found in her brother&#8217;s poetry, such as the wonderment and
                healing powers of nature and the imagination. Furthermore, they converse overtly
                with William&#8217;s poems, offering useful comparisons for the classroom, though also
                implying through the selection process that what matters most in Dorothy&#8217;s verse are
                these resonances.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">The Longman Anthology of English
                    Literature</title> (now sadly out of print) includes the fullest representation of DW&#8217;s 
                    poems in any major teaching anthology. It includes, in its fifth edition, 
                    <title level="a">Grasmere&#8212;A Fragment</title> 
                    and <title level="a">Thoughts on my Sick-Bed</title> as well as <title level="a">Floating Island,</title> 
                    <title level="a">Address to a Child,</title> <title level="a">Irregular Verses,</title> 
                    <title level="a">Lines intended for my Niece&#8217;s Album,</title> the very short 
                    <title level="a">[When Shall I Tread Your Garden Path?],</title> and <title level="a">Lines written (rather say begun).</title>
                </note>
            </p>
            
                <p>This electronic edition applies a different theory of inclusion, as we neither
                collect all of Dorothy&#8217;s known poems, as edited by Levin and pulled from various
                print and manuscript sources, nor present a selection based on connections with
                William&#8217;s work or subjective judgments on aesthetic value or biographical relevance.
                Instead, we offer a substantial (and arguably representative) sample based on the
                material practices of Dorothy&#8217;s writing and grounded in a single manuscript: Dove
                Cottage Manuscript (DCMS) 120, commonly referred to as the &#8220;commonplace book&#8221; (fig.
                6.1). In this battered notebook with paper boards, purchased in November 1820,
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">DCMS 120&#8217;s label survives to provide details
                       about where it was purchased: GRISET FILS AINÉ, a shop in
                       Boulogne-Sur-Mer that DW, WW, and MW visited in November 1820 near the
                       end of their Continental tour. A detailed description of the notebook
                       appears in the section <title level="a">Textual and Editorial Issues</title>.
                    </note> 
                Dorothy collected most of the poems she wrote during her lifetime,
                often in multiple versions. In most cases, she revised while collecting and copying,
                as is evident by edits on the notebook&#8217;s pages, though some poems were copied fair.
                In total, the notebook&#8217;s 89 leaves contain 22 poems in 38 versions. Most of these
                poems were composed and entered in the notebook between 1826 and 1832, though new
                entries appeared until 1840.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"> As Levin has done the most extensive work 
                        in dating the poems, her dates are used in this edition (<title level="m">
                            Levin</title>, 176&#8211;77).
                    </note> 
                Rather than seek to
                identify (or create) fixed versions of her poems through the editorial process, this
                section of the edition represents the multiple and unsettled versions of her poetry
                in this one artifact, wherein it becomes possible to observe Dorothy returning to
                her poems over time as she rereads, revises, and recopies them.
                </p>
            
            <figure>
                <graphic url="PLACEHOLDER" width="400px" rend="inline"/>
                    <head>Figure 6.1:</head>
                    <desc>Front cover of DCMS 120, with partial stationer&#8217;s label marked &#8220;GRISET FILS AINÉ&#8221; visible. The notebook measures 
                        276 mm (height) x 215 mm (width). (Courtesy: The Wordsworth Trust)
                    </desc>
            </figure>
            
            <p>DCMS 120 also contains a considerable quantity of other material, copied from
                newspapers and from other manuscripts as well as some print clippings. The
                miscellaneous nature of the notebook&#8217;s contents may be seen in the 
                <ref target="/editions.2022.poems-contents">first
                table of contents created for this edition</ref>. Included
                are all of Dorothy&#8217;s poems written to or about members of her domestic circle,
                alongside recipes, epitaphs, and other snippets of poetry and prose. Interestingly,
                Dorothy also incorporates fair copies of her poems handwritten by others,
                demonstrating that her poetry (like the notebook itself) was shared with a group.
                She annotates her own handwritten poems with emphatic markings, often in
                pencil—adding another stratum to their textual archaeology. While our emphasis is on
                the poetry within DCMS 120, we also wish to call attention, through the complete
                table of contents, to the interplay of her poetry with the other material she copies
                or pastes into the notebook.
            </p>
                
            <p>It should be noted as well that many of the poems included here are also preserved in
                other documents outside of DCMS 120—in notebooks, letters, and separate sheets, as
                copies Dorothy gifted to others. Nonetheless, we find that focusing on this one
                notebook and the history of its making and use allows us to reanimate Dorothy&#8217;s
                poetry within the period&#8217;s thriving manuscript culture. Though in many ways Dorothy
                drafted, revised, shared, and preserved her writing as a professional author might,
                her verse was rarely if ever intended for a print audience. Nonetheless, she had
                readers. This notebook did not directly serve her brother&#8217;s professional literary
                career, as arguably did the Grasmere journal notebooks and other manuscripts
                discussed in this edition, but this does not mean that Dorothy did not share her
                poetry or intend it to be read and enjoyed by others. Rather, DCMS 120 reflects both
                the social activities of composing, gifting, exchanging, and collecting, as well as
                Dorothy&#8217;s possibly more private processes, particularly with poetry, of recopying,
                rereading, and rewriting.
            </p>
                
            <p>A commonplace book is traditionally understood to be a handmade collection of
                edifying or inspiring quotations that reflect upon the collector&#8217;s reading. Although
                the term has developed a more capacious meaning, partly because commonplacing became
                less systematized in the nineteenth century, it is nevertheless somewhat misapplied
                to Dorothy&#8217;s notebook, which is only in part an account of her reading. DCMS 120
                might more accurately be called a manuscript miscellany, exemplifying a traditional
                method of curation that thrived in the eighteenth century, particularly for poetry;
                the miscellany can also be, as it is in this case, a space for drafting, collecting,
                and preserving heterogeneous material. As noted previously, one of DCMS 120&#8217;s most
                important functions was to gather both drafts and fair copies of nearly all of
                Dorothy&#8217;s poems. However, it also included poetry and prose authored by others, in a
                variety of forms. Dorothy preserved this material both through the act of directly
                copying onto pages in the notebook and by pasting loose sheets into the notebook
                pages. The manuscript miscellany gathers contributions from various sources and
                people into a single (if somewhat chaotic) space, both representing and embodying a
                literary community.
            </p>
                
            <p>One advantage of studying and editing a single notebook, then, is that it provides
                access to the messy and complex nature of manuscript writing and literary exchange.
                One disadvantage is that approaching such a collection can feel unfamiliar and even
                alienating. DCMS 120 defies many expectations of today&#8217;s readers, who are used to
                encountering regularized print. Like DCMS 20, it starts at both ends, a feature that
                Margaret Ezell describes as &#8220;a doubling of the matter in an inverted format,&#8221;
                resulting in &#8220;a practice alien to print technology . . . and disorienting for modern
                    readers.&#8221;
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Ezell, <title level="a">Invisible Books,</title> 60.</note>
                As in other draft manuscripts, corrections, revisions, and errors remain visible in
                layers, as Dorothy works and reworks her lines. Time is thus encoded on the pages in
                a way that is distinctive to the scribal medium. Meanwhile, white space within the
                manuscript is unevenly distributed, with some pages left entirely blank, some barely
                written on, and others crammed with writing. There are pages cut or torn or patched,
                all contributing to a lack of uniformity that is indicative of the book being filled
                over time, without a predetermined plan. Text appears at multiple angles and
                cross-written; there are sheets pasted in horizontally that must be folded out, and
                the entire book must be manipulated and rotated throughout for proper reading. There
                are essentially no navigational tools—no tables of contents, indices, signatures,
                attributions, or page numbers, and very few titles. Legibility, regularity, and
                re-usability are all compromised. In many ways, then, the notebook is impenetrable
                to us—undecipherable in places, with missing pages, unknown hands, and unidentified
                scraps copied and clipped from print and manuscript sources. It is a book in which
                we struggle to find a single or clear narrative except of use and ongoing
                engagement. Nonetheless, its tolerance of variation and indeed messiness—the
                willingness to allow for corrections and variants to remain visible, with draft and
                fair copies remaining side by side—enables a revisiting of past versions and past
                selves, very much a Wordsworthian theme at the core of Dorothy&#8217;s as well as her
                brother&#8217;s poetics.
            </p>
            
                <p>A complicated manuscript like DCMS 120 presents special challenges to editors, but
                the digital platform of Romantic Circles makes it possible for us to convey a sense
                of the poems&#8217; material environment. Figure 6.2 suggests the many kinds of activities
                and artifacts in DCMS 120. On the verso appear the last two stanzas of &#8220;Irregular
                Stanzas / Holiday at Gwerndovennant May 1826,&#8221; with sums visible at the bottom left,
                demonstrating a thrifty (and very common) use of blank space. On the recto is the
                final page of a tipped-in fair copy version, on lavender wove paper, of <title level="a">Grasmere—A
                Fragment</title> (insert 2), a poem of unknown date that appears in four versions in the
                notebook.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">The Wordsworth Trust has labeled all added pages as inserts. This is insert 2.</note>
                Viewing the open notebook, we also observe the multidirectionality of the writing,
                which here occurs in three orientations.
                </p>
            
            <figure>
                <graphic url="PLACEHOLDER" width="400px" rend="inline"/>
                    <head>Figure 6.2:</head>
                    <desc>The manuscript for <title level="a">Irregular Stanzas / Holiday at
                        Gwerndovennant</title> in DCMS 120. (Courtesy: The Wordsworth Trust)</desc>
            </figure>
            
                <p>Looking more closely at the recto page featured in figure 6.2, we may notice
                additional details. Figure 6.3 reproduces and enlarges the page&#8217;s penultimate
                stanza. Here, Dorothy recopies, twice, in pencil, the expression &#8220;Trust me&#8221; from the
                stanza&#8217;s first line, strongly emphasizing its message on the passage of time: &#8220;Too
                soon your hearts shall own / The past is all that is your own.&#8221; Thus, the manuscript
                carries a sting—a poignant indication of the poet&#8217;s feeling in later life.
                </p>
                
            <figure>
                <graphic url="PLACEHOLDER" width="400px" rend="inline"/>
                    <head>Figure 6.3:</head>
                    <desc>Detail from final page of <title level="a">Irregular Stanzas / Holiday
                        at Gwerndovennant</title> in DCMS 120. &#8220;Trust me&#8221; appears twice, in faded pencil, on
                        the left. (Courtesy: The Wordsworth Trust)</desc>
            </figure>
            
            <p>Sharon Cameron has observed of Emily Dickinson&#8217;s manuscript variants that many appear
                to place her both within and &#8220;outside the ostensible boundaries of the poem.&#8221;
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Cameron, <title level="m">Choosing Not Choosing</title>, 24.</note> 
                Dorothy Wordsworth occupies
                the same double or multiple positionality, as an older self often encircles a
                younger one in poems that themselves thematize the passage of time. In this way,
                throughout DCMS 120, we observe traces of Dorothy rereading and reworking her own
                life. Often her revisions are less about altering the meaning and more about
                accentuating and perhaps even, in the act of rewriting, re-experiencing feelings. As
                Pamela Woof perceptively observes, &#8220;The constant return to lines and snatches from
                the poems provides for her a way to investigate her own mind.&#8221;
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Woof, <title level="m">Dorothy Wordsworth</title>, 139&#8211;41.</note> 
                In penciled additions
                to <title level="a">Lines intended for my Niece&#8217;s Album,</title> Dorothy underlines the phrase &#8220;no longer
                young&#8221; apparently to add emphasis and to mark the additional passage of time since
                the poem was originally written, or both.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Dora Wordsworth&#8217;s Album is held at the Wordsworth Trust, DCMS 122.</note>
                She also uses penciled marginal notes to adjust the pronouns: in ink, she refers to
                the time &#8220;when the cold earth covers her,&#8221; but in her penciled markings—more variant
                readings than revisions—she returns the poem to the more intimate, if morbid, first
                person, imagining the moment when &#8220;the cold earth covers me.&#8221; By preserving this
                adjustment, which directly invokes the poet&#8217;s mortality, the manuscript reveals acts
                of rereading and reengagement that personalize and renew the poetry&#8217;s meaning.
            </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
                
            <head>
                <anchor xml:id="Poetry"/>B. Poetry In (and Out of) the Commonplace Book
            </head>
            
                <p>Of the 30 Dorothy Wordsworth poems that survive in manuscript form, five were
                published anonymously during her lifetime in collections of her brother William&#8217;s
                works. Three of these, dating to 1805–1807—<title level="a">An address to a Child in a high wind,</title>
                <title level="a">The Mother&#8217;s Return,</title> and <title level="a">To my niece Dorothy, a sleepless Baby</title>
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"> These poem titles are taken from Levin, 
                        who uses as her copytexts the fair copies in the Coleorton Commonplace Book, 
                        now held by the Morgan Library and Museum (<title level="m">Levin,</title> 177).
                    </note>
                    —appeared as the &#8220;work of a Female Friend&#8221; of the author in
                <title level="m">Poems by William Wordsworth</title> (1815).
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">DW&#8217;s poems appeared in vol. 1 of <title level="m">
                        Poems of William Wordsworth</title> (1815) as <title level="a">An Address to a Child, 
                        During a boisterous Winter Evening</title> (pp. 8&#8211;10), <title level="a">The Mother&#8217;s Return</title> 
                        (pp. 11&#8211;13), and <title level="a">The Cottager to Her Infant</title> (p. 160). In his famous 
                        <title level="a">Preface</title> to this collection, WW noted, &#8220;Three short pieces (now first 
                        published) are the work of a Female Friend; and the Reader, to whom they may be acceptable, 
                        is indebted to me for his pleasure; if any one regard them with dislike, or be disposed to 
                        condemn them, let the censure fall upon him, who, trusting in his own sense of their merit and 
                        their fitness for the place which they occupy, <emph>extorted</emph> them from the Authoress&#8221; (xli). 
                        For the siblings&#8217; longtime friend Charles Lamb and his sister Mary, however, this was
                        overly coy. In a 7 April 1815 letter to WW, Charles Lamb remarks, &#8220;We
                        were glad to see the poems by a female friend. The one of the wind is
                        masterly, but not new to us. Being only three, perhaps you might have
                        clapt a D. at the corner and let it have past as a printer&#8217;s mark to the
                        uninitiated, as a delightful hint to the better-instructed. As it is,
                        Expect a formal criticism on the Poems of your female friend, and she
                        must expect it&#8221; (<title level="m">Letters of Charles and Mary Lamb</title>, 
                        1:141). WW did eventually accept this advice, including DW&#8217;s initials in 
                        some later editions.
                    </note> 
                Several decades later, two additional poems, <title level="a">Loving &amp; Liking</title>
                and <title level="a">Floating Island at Hawkshead,</title> were included semi-anonymously 
                in the 1836 and 1842 editions, respectively, of William&#8217;s collected works.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"> See <title level="a">Loving &amp; Liking,</title> 
                        1:249&#8211;51; and <title level="a">Floating Island,</title> 230&#8211;31.
                    </note> 
                While these latter two poems and 20 others by Dorothy appear in DCMS
                120, the three poems published in 1815 do not. Given that she did not purchase the
                notebook until five years after these poems&#8217; first appearance in print, she
                apparently saw no reason to recopy and collect them. This theory is supported by the
                fact that DCMS 120 does include several versions of <title level="a">Loving &amp; 
                Liking</title> and <title level="a">Floating Island,</title> which were not published 
                until long after she obtained the notebook.
                </p>
                
            <p>Beyond the 22 poems in DCMS 120 and the three early printed poems, Dorothy wrote an
                additional five poems, which survive in letters, loose sheets, or volumes of her 
                <ref target="editions.2022.DW.RJ-15">Rydal Journals</ref>.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"> These additional six poems, all reprinted in Levin, 
                    are <title level="a">Innocent were the lives they led</title> (1828), <title level="a">
                    No more the Pastor with his Flock</title> (1828), <title level="a">To Rotha Quillinan</title> 
                    (unknown date), <title level="a">Miss B. Southey</title> (1836), and <title level="a">To 
                    Christopher Rennison</title> (unknown date).
                </note>
                These five are relatively short (the longest is 20 lines), and four are clearly
                addressed to members of her social circle. Evidence that nearly all of her poems
                circulated in manuscript during her lifetime comes in surviving copies included in
                her correspondence and written in the hands of family or friends. Though this
                introduction primarily addresses the poems contained in DCMS 120 and the practices
                of drafting, revision, collection, and sharing revealed within its pages, it is
                important to acknowledge the notebook&#8217;s place within a larger set of surviving
                documents that demonstrate Dorothy writing and sharing her verses.
            </p>
                
            <p>While many of the poems are hard to date with precision, most seem to have been
                written in the 1820s and 1830s, when Dorothy was in her 50s and 60s and living at
                Rydal Mount with William and his family. As a result, the poems trace themes that
                are somewhat different from those that dominate her earlier writing, for example, in
                the first Grasmere journal notebook, before William had a wife and children. The
                passage of time and its effects on the body and her familial and social
                relationships are constant themes of the poems, as Dorothy reflects on both her
                younger and older selves. A few poems do return to quite early times; for instance,
                <title level="a">Grasmere&#8212;A Fragment</title> recounts the Wordsworths&#8217; arrival in Grasmere in late 1799.
                Nevertheless, most of the poems differ from the descriptions of daily life and local
                scenes that are found in the <title level="m">Grasmere Journals</title>, being more
                centrally focused on her anxiety about writing poetry (an insecurity not much
                expressed in her other writing) and her reflections on aging and the fragility of
                the body.
            </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
            <head>
                <anchor xml:id="Arrangement"/>C. The Arrangement, Presentation, and Reception of the Poems
            </head>
            
            <p>While most poems in DCMS 120—15 in number—are presented in only one version, seven
                appear in multiple revisions. One poem, <title level="a">Lines written (rather say 
                begun),</title> appears in seven distinct versions. As is to be expected with a working 
                notebook that is filled over years, the poems are not organized or arranged in any 
                prescribed or logical order. Moreover, as previously noted, DCMS 120 is an amigraph&#8212;a 
                book filled from both ends. How, then, to number the pages? The stationer&#8217;s label on the cover
                determines the orientation we designate as the front, and indeed the notebook is
                largely filled from that end.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Working from the front, we find that certain leaves or pages 
                    are blank (7v, 23, 25v, 26r, 33v, 35&#8211;36r, 41r, 42, 43r, 45v, 48v, 50, 51v, 57v, 59v, 61&#8211;78) 
                    and that some folios are stubs&#8212;that is, pages that have been cut or torn out (27, 30, 34, 46, 
                    46, 60). The last written entry appears on 59r. When opening the book from the other direction, 
                    the last piece of writing appears on 15v, with no blanks and one stub, on folio 8. No observable 
                    pattern distinguishes material entered at either end, as both have DW&#8217;s own poems along with 
                    copied material. Twelve inserts&#8212;that is, materials extraneous to the notebook&#8212;have been pasted 
                    in. These include complete poems (by DW and others, usually written out by others) as well as 
                    patches added to correct poems.
                </note> 
                It is possible that Dorothy began to fill the notebook from
                the front first, as the first dated entry is from 1830, and then began to use the
                book from the rear cover, chiefly to attach copies of her poems made by others, with
                the first copy pasted in being <title level="a">Lines to Dora</title> and dated 1835. 
                After 1835, she likely used the book from both ends. An amigraph is a difficult object 
                to replicate outside of a physical facsimile, as it is arguably even more difficult to flip a
                screen than it is a book. As displayed by this edition&#8217;s
                <ref target="editions.2022.DW.poems-contents">Alternative Tables of Contents</ref> and
                explained at length in its headnote, we have attempted to present this aspect of the
                notebook as transparently as possible.
            </p>
            
            <p>Dorothy frequently expressed anxiety about her poetic abilities, and her
                self-deprecating statements have shaped the reception of her poetry, which has
                received less attention and far less praise than the journals and her travel
                writing. When, in 1806, her friend and quasi-patron Lady Beaumont encouraged her to
                try verse, Dorothy responded with a detailed history of her efforts in the genre
                that is worth quoting at length:
            
            <quote>Believe me, since I received your letter I have made several attempts (could I do
                less as you request that I would <emph>for your sake</emph>?) and have
                been obliged to give it up in despair; and looking into my mind I find nothing
                there, even if I had the gift of language and numbers, that I could have the vanity
                to suppose could be of any use beyond our own fireside, or to please, as in your
                case, a few partial friends; but I have no command of language, no power of
                expressing my ideas, and no one was ever more inapt at molding words into regular
                metre. I have often tried when I have been walking alone (muttering to myself as is
                my Brother&#8217;s custom) to express my feelings in verse; feelings, and ideas such as
                they were, I have never wanted at those times; but prose and rhyme and blank verse
                were jumbled together and nothing ever came of it.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">Letters</title>, 2:24&#8211;25.</note>
            </quote>
            </p>
                
            <p>Family members sometimes repeated this narrative of Dorothy struggling with formal
                verse. In 1832, for instance, Dora enclosed some of her aunt&#8217;s verses in a letter to
                Edward Quillinan, remarking, &#8220;You must excuse limping measure. Aunt cannot write
                regular metre.&#8221;
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">DW to Edward Quillinan, 25 May 1832, reproduced
                    in <title level="m">DWB</title>, 387&#8211;90.
                </note>
            </p>
            
                <p>Partly due to such assessments, Dorothy&#8217;s poems have been regarded as categorically
                inferior to her prose works, even by sympathetic readers. The preeminent early
                twentieth-century Wordsworth scholar Ernest de Sélincourt, for one, concluded that
                her poems &#8220;have little intrinsic merit,&#8221; opining that &#8220;only rarely are they lit up
                by that alertness of vision and felicity of phrasing of which to the last her prose
                was capable.&#8221;
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">DWB</title>, 388.</note> 
                At the opposite end of the twentieth century,
                the pioneering editor of her works, Susan Levin, summed up the enduring consensus
                that &#8220;uneven in quality, Dorothy&#8217;s poetry sometimes has the effect of making us more
                appreciative of her talents as a prose writer.&#8221;
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">Levin</title>, 109.</note>
            </p>
            
                <p>In the aforementioned letter to Lady Beaumont, Dorothy claims to have no expressive
                power or metrical ability; however, she was in a singularly challenging position in
                attempting to compose poetry alongside her brother, particularly in 1806, when
                William was writing some of the finest poetry of his life. Levin describes this
                &#8220;anxiety of influence&#8221; making it &#8220;difficult for Dorothy to write poetry.&#8221; In this
                reading, Dorothy&#8217;s habitual self-denigration is everywhere evident as she sets her
                poems against his.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">Levin</title>, 113.</note> 
                Some evidence supports
                this view. Even two decades later, in &#8220;To Julia Marshall—A Fragment,&#8221; a poem dated
                to 1827 and addressed to her goddaughter, whose mother, Jane Pollard Marshall, was
                Dorothy&#8217;s lifelong friend, she explores her fraught relationship with poetry. She
                returns to her childhood and explains that, even though she &#8220;reverenced the Poets&#8217;
                skill,&#8221; 
            
             <quote>
                <div type="poetry"><!--all of the following errors are related to these same div tags that I do....but I don't know how to else to do it-->
                    <lg type="poetry">
                        <l>And <hi rend="underline">might have</hi> nursed the wish &amp; will</l>
                        <l>To imitate the tender lays</l>
                        <l>Of them who sang in Nature&#8217;s praise</l>
                        <l>But bashfulness, a struggling shame,</l>
                        <l>A fear that elder heads might blame</l>
                        <l>— Or something worse – a touch of pride,</l>
                        <l>Whispering [her] playmates would deride,
                            <note place="foot" resp="editors">Above this line, DW writes in pencil a variant: &#8220;A dream least 
                                playmates should deride.&#8221;
                            </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Stifled ambition, check&#8217;d the aim</l>
                        <l>If e&#8217;er by chance &#8220;the numbers came&#8221;</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
            </quote>
            
            In an apparent allusion to Alexander Pope&#8217;s <title level="a">Epistle to Dr. Arbuthnot,</title> where Pope
            peaks about how easily versification came to him&#8212;&#8220;I
            lisp&#8217;d in numbers, for the numbers came&#8221;&#8212;Dorothy explains the fear of
            humiliation that prevented her from pursuing poetry. Writing these lines in 1827,
            she had not yet forgotten the unnamed &#8220;elder heads&#8221; and &#8220;playmates&#8221; who &#8220;stifle[d]&#8221;
            her poetic ambition as a child, many decades earlier.
            </p>
            
            <p>Rather than amplify this narrative of constraint and discouragement, however, we
                prefer to frame our approach to Dorothy&#8217;s poetry by asking, to paraphrase Margaret
                Ezell, &#8220;‘What is this author attempting to do?&#8217;&#8221;
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Ezell, <title level="m">Social Authorship</title>, 23.</note> 
                Unlike her brother, Dorothy
                did not regularly compose poetry with print publication in mind. Instead, she
                usually addressed her poems to specific individuals, or to commemorate specific
                experiences or events. As she explains in the 1806 letter to Lady Beaumont, she
                wrote primarily for friends and family, rarely imagining an audience that extended
                &#8220;beyond [their] own fireside.&#8221; She also appears to have found it difficult to write
                upon command, as her friends&#8217; requests for verse often languished. For the most
                part, Dorothy seems to have written when inspired, to reflect on stirring moments,
                or to express special friendship. Though she preserved only a small number of poems,
                she returned to many of these, reworking and copying them for friends and family.
                Some of the poems, of course, found enthusiastic readers, as when Charles and Mary
                Lamb praised &#8220;Address to a Child&#8221; as &#8220;masterly.&#8221;
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Letter from Charles Lamb to WW, 7 April 1815.</note>
                But Dorothy&#8217;s body of poetry illustrates an understanding of herself as primarily a
                manuscript poet, writing for a select few but also rewriting and rereading for
                herself.
            </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>
                    <anchor xml:id="D."/>D. &#8220;D. Wordsworth: Old Poetess&#8221;
                </head>
            
            <p>In several poems, Dorothy writes as a fixture in her brother&#8217;s home and loving aunt
                to his children. As Levin has observed, &#8220;Many of Dorothy&#8217;s poems are written in the
                voice of a woman who considers her life and her past in relation to the children or
                younger women around her.&#8221;
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">Levin</title>, 110.</note> 
                Importantly, of the five
                Dorothy poems published with William&#8217;s during her lifetime, four of them explicitly
                position her as a maiden aunt or caregiver, casting her into a role of helpmate that
                continues to shape understandings of her and her writing. The titles of the three
                early poems published in 1815 describe her helping to rear Dora (born in 1804),
                Thomas (1806), Catherine (1808), and Willy (1810). By contrast, among the later
                poems included in DCMS 120, only <title level="a">Loving &amp; Liking</title> addresses a young child,
                gently admonishing its addressee for claiming to love roasted fowl. The speaker of
                the poem instructs the child that animals can be loved only in their natural
                environments, not when they have been made to serve human needs or tastes.
                </p>
            
            <p>By the 1820s and 1830s, the children have grown up. Two poems from 1832,
                respectively, address Edith Southey, daughter of Robert, and Dora, intimate friends
                for whom Dorothy had been something of a surrogate mother. Both had turned 28 in
                1832, and, as is apparent from her titles&#8212;<title level="a">Lines intended 
                for my Niece&#8217;s Album</title> (12, 13) and <title level="a">Lines intended for 
                Edith Southey&#8217;s album</title> (14)&#8212;Dorothy intended these poems, along with 
                <title level="a">Lines to Dora</title> (35, 36) from 1835, for the young women&#8217;s personal
                album collections. Especially popular among young British ladies of the 1820s and
                1830s, albums were blank notebooks or scrapbooks that gathered autographs and
                poetry, often solicited as were the lines from Dorothy. In her album verses, we find
                Dorothy contemplating the nature of the subgenre, the difficulties encountered in
                attempting to write on command (the title describes <title level="a">Lines intended for Edith
                Southey&#8217;s album</title> as responding to &#8220;a request made by her some years ago, &amp; of my
                own promise till now unfulfilled&#8221;) and, more broadly, her struggle to write poetry
                at all.
            </p>
            
            <p>In &#8220;Lines intended for my Niece&#8217;s Album,&#8221; Dorothy asks, &#8220;But why should I inscribe my
                name, / No Poet I — no longer young?&#8221; In such verses, Dorothy associates poetry with
                youth, expressing amusement and perhaps discomfort with being a sexagenarian
                generator of keepsakes. Some months later, she signs herself, in a poem addressed to
                Edith&#8217;s sister, &#8220;Miss Bertha Southey,&#8221; as &#8220;D. Wordsworth Old Poetess. Oct. 7th
                1836.&#8221; Most of her surviving poems were composed in her 50s and 60s, and in them she
                regularly plays the role of the &#8220;aged Friend,&#8221; as she puts it in &#8220;Lines intended for
                my Niece&#8217;s Album.&#8221; Levin observes that poems to the younger generation afforded
                Dorothy an opportunity to meditate upon her own past and present:             
                
                <quote>
                In certain of her poems, an older, sickly, &#8220;enfeebled&#8221; speaker addresses a young
                woman who serves as both her contrast and complement. The writing of the poems
                establishes a series of oppositions such as youth/age, health/sickness, freedom in
                nature/sickroom as prison. Setting out these positions in composing the poem, the
                narrator encounters her own youthful energies mirrored in the young women she
                addresses.
                </quote>
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">Levin,</title> 111.</note>
            </p>
            
            <p>Other poems where Dorothy employs such doubling include <title level="a">Lines Addressed to Joanna
                H.,</title> which reflects on the difference between the poet&#8217;s and subject&#8217;s younger
                selves; <title level="a">Irregular Stanzas / Holiday at Gwerndovennant May 1826,</title> in which,
                addressing a group of children surrounding the adults, she considers, &#8220;Forty years
                have roll&#8217;d away / Since we were young as you&#8221;; and <title level="a">Irregular Verses,</title> another poem
                to Julia Marshall, in which she addresses the separation between the two women and
                the difference in their lots in life, as Jane Marshall has gone on to have 10
                children. But most memorably she uses this trope in her album verses for Dora and
                Edith, the latter of which offers a noteworthy celebration of the bonds between the
                generations: 
                
            <quote>
                <div type="poetry">
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>But <add rend="sup">let</add> this page a record stand</l>
                        <l>Of <del rend="strike">my</del> <hi rend="underline"><del rend="strike">deep</del></hi>
                            <add rend="sup"><hi rend="underline">tender</hi></add> <hi rend="underline">love</hi> which may not die,</l>
                        <l>Friendship betwixt the Old and Young,</l>
                        <l>The growth of faithful sympathy.</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
            </quote>
            </p>
            </div>
                
            <div type="section">
                <head>
                    <anchor xml:id="Poems"/>E. Poems of Memory and Consolation: <title level="a">I trod the hills again</title>
                </head>
                
            <p>Memory obviously plays a key role in many of the poems in DCMS 120, uniting the
                older, infirm, and relatively immobile Dorothy with the younger, spirited, and
                active one. As she notes in <title level="a">Lines Addressed to Joanna H.</title>: 
            
               <quote>
                   <div type="poetry">
                       <lg type="stanza">
                            <l>But in the workings of my heart</l>
                            <l>Doth memory act a busy part;</l>
                            <l>That jocund April Morn lives there,</l>
                            <l><del rend="strike">Its cheering sounds,<add rend="sup">sounds</add></del> its hues so fair </l>
                       </lg>
                   </div>
               </quote>
            </p>
                
            <p>In the poignant <title level="a">Thoughts on my Sick-Bed,</title> it is memory 
                that rescues Dorothy from the captivity of illness. The poem is dated to the 
                early spring of 1832, after her first extended period of confinement that began 
                in 1830. Much like Coleridge&#8217;s 1797 poem <title level="a">This Lime Tree Bower, 
                my Prison,</title> in which Coleridge laments being unable to join
                his friends on a ramble due to a recent injury, <title level="a">Thoughts on my 
                Sick-Bed,</title> depicts Dorothy imprisoned in her room at Rydal Mount. 
                The speaker, for whom walking outdoors has been such an important part of 
                life, now finds herself disabled. But, like Coleridge, she rejoices in the 
                creative powers that allow her to imagine that she is not confined, and 
                she ultimately refutes her entrapment. &#8220;I thought of Nature&#8217;s loveliest 
                scenes,&#8221; she concludes, &#8220;And with Memory I was there.&#8221; In &#8220;This
                Lime Tree Bower, my Prison,&#8221; Coleridge finds that neither nature nor his friends
                have deserted him, as he enjoys the capacity to traverse space in his mind&#8217;s eye,
                providing him much to delight and soothe him. For Dorothy, a gift of spring flowers,
                brought by friends, spurs the powers of her imagination and transports her beyond
                the four walls of her room: 
                
            <quote>
                <div tyep="poetry">
                    <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>It bore me to the Terrace walk</l>
                        <l>I trod the hills again; —</l>
                        <l>No prisoner in this lonely room,</l>
                        <l>I saw the green banks of the Wye,</l>
                        <l>Recalling thy prophetic words,
                            <note place="foot" resp="editors">
                            The &#8220;prophetic words&#8221; occur in the final
                            section of WW&#8217;s <title level="a">Tintern Abbey,</title> 
                            especially in lines 137–59, which
                            imagine DW&#8217;s &#8220;after years&#8221; and predict that memories will bring her
                            joy and consolation.
                            </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Bard, Brother, Friend from infancy!</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
            </quote>
            </p>
                
            <p>Invoking one of her brother&#8217;s most famous poems, <title level="a">Lines written a few miles above
                Tintern Abbey,</title> Dorothy&#8217;s poem shares with it and Coleridge&#8217;s <title level="a">This Lime Tree Bower</title>
                a faith in the restorative powers of the imagination. As in <title level="a">Tintern Abbey,</title> Dorothy
                claims in &#8220;Thoughts on my Sick-Bed&#8221; that there has been what her brother termed
                &#8220;abundant recompense&#8221; for what has been lost:
                
           <quote>
               <div type="poetry">
                   <lg type="stanza">
                       <l>Yet⟩
                        <del rend="strike">But</del> never in those careless days,</l>
                        <l>When spring-time in rock, field, or bower</l>
                        <l>Was <del rend="strike">but as a</del> <add rend="sup">but a</add> fountain of <del rend="strike">hope</del> earthly hope</l>
                        <l>A promise of fruits &amp; the <hi rend="underline">splendid</hi> flower.</l>
                   </lg>
                   
                   <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>No! then I never felt a bliss </l>
                        <l>That might with <hi rend="underline">that</hi> compare</l>
                        <l>Which, piercing to my couch of rest,</l>
                        <l>Came on the vernal air,</l>
                   </lg>
                   
                   <lg type="stanza">
                        <l>When loving Friends an offering brought,</l>
                        <l>The first flowers of the year,</l>
                        <l>Culled from the precincts of our home,</l>
                        <l>From nooks to Memory dear.</l>
                   </lg>
               </div>
           </quote>
            </p>
                
            <p>In short, <title level="a">Thoughts on My Sick-Bed,</title> one of her most personal and meditative poems,
                is also arguably one of her best. It is also highly allusive, as it gestures toward
                her brother&#8217;s and Coleridge&#8217;s poems in order to underscore the fundamental shared
                argument about the powers of friendship, memory, and the imagination, and to draw
                the poems, and the poets, together.
            </p>
            
                <p>Perhaps the memory-poem most indebted to her brother and most grounded in their
                common life in the Lakes is <title level="a">Grasmere&#8212;A Fragment,</title> an undated poem that reflects on
                the siblings&#8217; arrival in the village in December 1799. It is a poem that, like her
                brother&#8217;s <title level="a">Home at Grasmere</title> (1800), reflects both on their return to the Lake
                District to establish a home and on the meaning of home itself. Four versions of
                <title level="a">Grasmere&#8212;A Fragment,</title> all with revisions, are included in DCMS 120, suggesting it
                was important to Dorothy and part of a family dialogue about the meaning of their
                shared life. The poem describes a sense of deep satisfaction upon viewing Dove
                Cottage, which, &#8220;with its clustering trees / Summons [her] heart.&#8221; Although it is
                little more than a &#8220;shed,&#8221; modest in comparison to some neighboring homes, with no
                fertile fields but a rocky steep that rises behind, she declares, &#8220;I love that house
                because it is / The very mountains&#8217; child.&#8221;
                </p>
                
            <p>The poem proceeds to describe the &#8220;lovely winter&#8217;s day&#8221; when the Wordsworths moved
                into Dove Cottage. Soon after arriving, Dorothy writes: 
            
                <quote>
                    <div type="poetry">
                        <lg type="stanza">
                            <l>I left my sole companion-friend</l>
                            <l>To wander out alone —</l>
                            <l>Lured by a little winding path,</l>
                            <l>I quitted soon the public road,</l>
                            <l>A smooth and tempting path it was,</l>
                            <l>By sheep and shepherds trod —</l>
                            <l>Eastwards towards the lofty hills</l>
                            <l>That pathway led me on</l>
                        </lg>
                    </div>
                </quote>
            </p>
                
            <p>This scene, in which Dorothy leaves her brother behind &#8220;to wander out alone,&#8221;
                reflects her newfound autonomy, whereas the actual &#8220;little winding path&#8221; that leads
                her up the hills hints at the opportunities for walking and exploration soon to
                come. The poem also addresses the delight she finds in the wintery scenes on
                display:
           
                <quote>
                    <div type="poetry">
                        <lg type="stanza">
                            <l>&#8220;Thou wear&#8217;st,&#8221; said I, &#8220;a splendid garb,</l>
                            <l>Here winter keeps his revelry —</l></lg>
                        
                        <lg type="poetry">
                            <l>Full long a dweller on the Plains,</l>
                            <l>I grieved when summer days were gone,</l>
                            <l>No more I&#8217;ll grieve, for Winter here</l>
                            <l>Hath pleasure gardens of his own.</l></lg>
                        
                        <lg type="peotry">
                            <l>What need of flowers? the splendid moss</l>
                            <l>Is gayer than an April mead</l>
                            <l>More rich its hues of various green,</l>
                            <l>Orange, &amp; gold, and glittering red—&#8221;</l>
                        </lg>
                    </div>
                </quote>
            </p>
                
            <p>It concludes with a sense of gratitude for this long-awaited homecoming:
            
                <quote>
                    <div type="poetry">
                        <lg type="stanza">
                            <l>My youthful wishes all fulfill&#8217;d</l>
                            <l>Wishes matured by thoughtful choice,</l>
                            <l>I stood an <hi rend="underline">Inmate</hi> of this Vale,</l>
                            <l>How <hi rend="underline">could</hi> I but rejoice?</l>
                        </lg>
                    </div>
                </quote>
            </p>
                
            <p><title level="a">Grasmere&#8212;A Fragment</title> describes Dove Cottage and its environs in idealized terms, as
                sheltered, verdant, and brimming with life and as the realization of her &#8220;youthful
                wishes.&#8221;
            </p>
                
            <p>Reflections on those early wishes also appear in Dorothy&#8217;s <title level="a">Irregular Verses.</title> She
                recalls that she had imagined sharing a home with her friend Jane Pollard as well as
                with William.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">In a series of exuberant letters from 1793, DW explores her desire to 
                    create a home with Jane Pollard and her brother. For example, on 10 and 12 July 1793, she writes, 
                    
                    <quote>
                        But oh how imperfect is my pleasure! I am <emph>alone</emph>; why are not you seated with me? and 
                        my dear William why is not he here also? I could almost fancy that I see you both near me. I have 
                        chosen a bank where I have room to spare for a resting-place for each of you. I hear <emph>you</emph> 
                        point out a spot where, if we could erect a little cottage and call it <emph>our own</emph> we should 
                        be the happiest of human beings. I see my Brother fired with the idea of leading his sister to such a 
                        retreat as Fancy ever ready at our call hastens to assist us in painting; our parlor is in a moment 
                        furnished; our garden is adorned by magic; the roses and honeysuckles spring at our command, the wood 
                        behind the house lifts at once its head and furnishes us with a winter&#8217;s shelter, and a summer&#8217;s noon-day 
                        shade. My dear friend I trust that ere long you will be, without the aid of imagination, the companion 
                        of my walks. (<title level="m">Letters</title>, 1:97&#8211;104, 97. See also letters from 5 June
                        793, 1:91&#8211;92; 30 August 1793, 1:107&#8211;11; and spring 1795, 1:141&#8211;44.)
                    </quote>
                </note>
                This ideal, however, did not materialize, as Jane married and had her own family: 
                
                <quote>
                    <div type="poetry">
                        <lg type="stanza">
                            <l>Such was the spot I fondly framed</l>
                            <l>When life was new, and hope untamed:</l>
                            <l>There with my one dear Friend would dwell,</l>
                            <l>Nor wish for aught beyond the dell.</l>
                            <l>Alas! the cottage fled in air,</l>
                            <l>The streamlet never flowed:</l>
                        </lg>
                    </div>
                </quote>
            </p>
                
            <p>Dorothy did, of course, establish a household with her brother, and many of her poems
                celebrate visions of their home, at Dove Cottage until 1808 and at other residences
                until 1813, when they moved to Rydal Mount, where they would remain until their
                deaths.
            </p>
            
                <p>In sum, readers of this edition will be confronted with many poems that describe the
                long life Dorothy enjoyed with her brother in Grasmere and Rydal; they will
                encounter multiple versions of many of these poems, and often variant readings
                within these versions. Our presentation reflects the textually indeterminate state
                of Dorothy&#8217;s writing and attempts to remain faithful to the nature and purpose of
                her poetic expression. We believe that her poems reward careful reading, both for
                what they can tell us about her life and for their own sake. They enhance and
                supplement our understanding of her prose writing. Above all, they give us a picture
                of an older woman of letters seeking to process her experiences in poetic forms.
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>
                    <anchor xml:id="Textual"/>II. Textual and Editorial Issues
                </head>
                
            <p>DCMS 120 is a hardcover book with mottled brown paper boards, containing 89 leaves
                and measuring 276 mm (height) x 215 mm (width). As discussed previously, Dorothy
                enters most of the contents of the notebook from the front of the book, with the
                front being determined by the cover with a stationer&#8217;s label, and the last entry
                written on 59r. When opened and read in this direction, certain leaves or pages are
                blank (7v, 23, 25v, 26r, 33v, 35&#8211;36r, 41r, 42, 43r, 45v, 48v, 50, 51v, 57v, 59v,
                61&#8211;78), and some folios are stubs—that is, pages that have been cut or torn out (27,
                30, 34, 46, 46, 60). When opening the book from the other direction, the last piece
                of writing appears on 15v, with no blanks and one stub, on folio 8. There is no
                observable pattern that distinguishes material entered at either end, as both have
                Dorothy&#8217;s own poems along with copied material. There are 12 inserts&#8212;that is,
                materials extraneous to the notebook that have been pasted in. These inserts are
                both complete poems (by Dorothy and others, usually written out by others) as well
                as patches added to provide correct poems.
            </p>
                
            <p>As noted, DCMS 120&#8217;s label (see fig. 6.1) survives to provide details about where it
                was purchased. It indicates that the book was bought at GRISET FILS AINÉ, a shop in
                Boulogne-Sur-Mer that Dorothy, William, and Mary Wordsworth visited in November 1820
                near the end of a Continental tour.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">In Boulogne, they were visiting DW&#8217;s friend Mary Barker, 
                    who two years earlier had been her climbing companion on Scafell Pike. On Barker, see 
                    <ref target="editions.2022.DW.SP-intro">our introduction</ref> to DW&#8217;s account of that 
                    excursion.
                </note>
                Part workbook for her verse, part poetic miscellany, part commonplace book, and part
                scrapbook, the notebook embodies what Margaret Ezell terms &#8220;messy&#8221; manuscript
                volumes, domestic literary artifacts that have been largely invisible to modern
                scholars precisely because of their refusal to conform to print norms.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Ezell, <title level="a">Invisible Books,</title> 55.</note>
            </p>
            </div>
        </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
