<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Version C: Guide to the lakes (1823)
                </title>
                
                
                <!-- DW will be the author for the "reading texts" because she is a historical figure, change role to "primary" -->
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Dorothy Wordsworth</name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor">Paul Westover</editor> 
                
                
                <funder>Brigham Young University College of Humanities</funder>
                <principal>Paul Westover</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>T. J. McLemore</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- TJ AND JESSICA CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE PAUL'S NAMING CONVENTIONS IN THE "toc_file_names_for_links" DOC THAT IS LINKED TO THE SLACK CHANNEL-->
                <idno type="edition">editions.2022.DW.Ulls-C</idno>
                <idno type="resource">DW</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Version C: Guide to the Lakes (1823)
                        </title>
                        <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE THE NAMING DOC -->
                        <ptr target="editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.Ulls-C"/>
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Dorothy Wordworth's Lake District</title>
                        <title level="s">Editions</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- JESS AND TJ CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">Lake District</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">landscape</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">mapping</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">travel</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">walking</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">women writers</term>
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  PUT YOUR NAME HERE. AND ADD THE CODING DATE  -->
                <name>Emily Stephens</name>
                <date>2022-09-09</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="paratext">
            <head>Version C of <title level="a">Ullswater Excursion</title>: <title level="m">Guide to the
                Lakes</title> (1823)</head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Paul Westover</docAuthor><!--not sure if this stays the same because Paul is the editor-->
                    <affiliation>Brigham Young University</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
             <p><hi rend="bold">[Editor&#8217;s note:</hi> This, the earliest
                published version of Dorothy Wordsworth’s <title level="a">Ullswater Excursion,</title> appeared in 1823 in
                the fourth edition of her brother’s <title level="m">Guide to the Lakes</title>.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">Although now commonly known as the fourth edition of WW&#8217; <title level="m">Guide</title>, this book, like the 
                third edition of 1822, was titled <title level="m">A Description of the Scenery of the Lakes in the North of England</title>. 
                    <title level="a">Ullswater Excursion</title> appears from pp. 117&#8211;29.
                </note>
                As the only printed version through the late nineteenth century, the
                <title level="m">Guide</title> text is crucial for the text&#8217;s
                reception history. Labeled <title level="a">Excursion on the Banks of Ulswater,</title> it was appended,
                without a header or section break, to Dorothy&#8217;s <title level="a">Excursion to the Top of Scawfell,</title>
                which a year earlier William had included in the third edition of his <title level="m">Guide</title>. Dorothy&#8217;s authorship of these narratives was
                acknowledged neither in their original printings nor in the definitive 1835 edition
                of the <title level="m">Guide</title>, where they were flanked by two poems by
                William.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">The minor differences between the versions of <title level="a">Ullswater Excursion</title> published in the 1823 
                    and 1835 editions can be seen in the 
                    <ref target="/editions/guide_lakes/parallel_text_chart.pdf">parallel-text <!--Add anchor wherever this leads-->
                    comparison table</ref> in Mason, Stimpson, and Westover&#8217;s Romantic Circles edition of the <title level="m">Guide</title>.
                </note>
                The manuscript draft in DCMS 51 that closely corresponds with the printed text of 1823 features revisions in both Dorothy&#8217;s and William&#8217;s 
                hands, suggesting that preparing <title level="a">Ullswater Excursion</title> for publication was a collaborative endeavor.
                <note place="foot" resp="editors">For details on DW&#8217;s unacknowledged contributions to the <title level="m">Guide</title> and the differences 
                between her manuscript versions and those that appeared in print, see the introductions to <title level="a">
                <ref target="editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.SP-intro">Excursion up Scawfell Pike</ref></title> and     
                <title level="a"><ref target="editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.Ulls-intro">Excursion on the Banks of Ullswater.</ref></title>
                </note>]
            </p>
            </div>
                
            <lb/><milestone unit="paratext"/><lb/>
            <div type="section">
            
            <p>Having said so much of a point of view to which few are likely to ascend, I am
                induced to subjoin an account of a short excursion through more accessible parts of
                the country, made at a time when it is seldom seen but by the inhabitants. As the
                journal was written for one acquainted with the general features of the country,
                only those effects and appearances are dwelt upon, which are produced by the
                changeableness of the atmosphere, or belong to the season when the excursion was
                made.
            </p>
                
             <p>A.D. 1805.&#8212;On the 7th of November, on a damp and gloomy morning, we left Grasmere
                Vale, intending to pass a few days on the banks of Ulswater. A mild and dry autumn
                had been unusually favourable to the preservation and beauty of foliage; and, far
                advanced as the season was, the trees on the larger Island of Rydal-mere retained a
                splendour which did not need the heightening of sunshine. We noticed, as we passed,
                that the line of the grey rocky shore of that island, shaggy with variegated bushes
                and shrubs, and spotted and striped with purplish brown heath, indistinguishably
                blending with its image reflected in the still water, produced a curious
                resemblance, both in form and colour, to a richly-coated caterpillar, as it might
                appear through a magnifying glass of extraordinary power. The mists gathered as we
                went along: but, when we reached the top of Kirkstone, we were glad we had not been
                discouraged by the apprehension of bad weather. Though not able to see a hundred
                yards before us, we were more than contented. At such a time, and in such a place,
                every scattered stone the size of one&#8212;s head becomes a companion. Near the top of
                the pass is the remnant of an old wall, which (magnified, though obscured, by the
                vapour) might have been taken for a fragment of some monument of ancient
                grandeur,&#8212;yet that same pile of stones we had never before even observed. This
                situation, it must be allowed, is not favourable to gaiety; but a pleasing hurry of
                spirits accompanies the surprize occasioned by objects transformed, dilated, or
                distorted, as they are when seen through such a medium. Many of the fragments of
                rock on the top and slopes of Kirkstone, and of similar places are fantastic enough
                in themselves; but the full effect of such impressions can only be had in a state of
                weather when they are not likely to be <emph>sought</emph> for. It was not
                till we had descended considerably that the fields of Hartshope were seen, like a
                lake tinged by the reflection of sunny clouds: I mistook them for Brothers-water,
                but, soon after, we saw that Lake gleaming faintly with a steelly brightness,&#8212;then,
                as we continued to descend, appeared the brown oaks, and the birches of lively
                yellow&#8212;and the cottages&#8212;and the lowly Hall of Hartshope, with its long roof and
                ancient chimneys. During great part of our way to Patterdale, we had rain, or rather
                drizzling vapour; for there was never a drop upon our hair or clothes larger than
                the smallest pearls upon a lady&#8217;s ring.
            </p>
                
            <p>The following morning, incessant rain till 11 o&#8217;clock, when the sky began to clear,
                and we walked along the eastern shore of Ulswater towards the farm of Blowick. The
                wind blew strong, and drove the clouds forward, on the side of the mountain above
                our heads;&#8212;two storm-stiffened black yew-trees fixed our notice, seen through, or
                under the edge of, the flying mists,&#8212;four or five goats were bounding among the
                rocks;&#8212;the sheep moved about more quietly, or cowered beneath their sheltering
                places. This is the only part of the country where goats are now found
                <note place="foot" resp="editors"> WW&#8217;s note: &#8220;A. D. 1805. These also have disappeared.&#8221;
                </note>
                ; but this morning, before we had seen these, I was reminded of
                that picturesque animal by two rams of mountain breed, both with Ammonian horns, and
                with beards majestic as that which Michael Angelo has given to his statue of
                Moses.&#8212;&#8212;But to return; when our path had brought us to that part of the naked common
                which overlooks the woods and bush-besprinkled fields of Blowick, the lake, clouds,
                and mists were all in motion to the sound of sweeping winds; &#8212;the church and
                cottages of Patterdale scarcely visible, or seen only by fits between the shifting
                vapours. To the northward the scene was less visionary;&#8212;Place Fell steady and
                bold;&#8212;the whole lake driving onward like a great river&#8212;waves dancing round the small
                islands. The house at Blowick was the boundary of our walk; and we returned,
                lamenting to see a decaying and uncomfortable dwelling in a place where sublimity
                and beauty seemed to contend with each other. But these regrets were dispelled by a
                glance on the woods that clothe the opposite steeps of the lake. How exquisite was
                the mixture of sober and splendid hues! The general colouring of the trees was
                brown&#8212;rather that of ripe hazel nuts: but towards the water, there were yet beds of
                green, and in the highest parts of the wood, was abundance of yellow foliage, which,
                gleaming through a vapoury lustre, reminded us of masses of clouds, as you see them
                gathered together in the west, and touched with the golden light of the setting
                sun.
            </p>
                
            <p>After dinner we walked up the Vale: I had never had an idea of its extent and width
                in passing along the public road on the other side. We followed the path that leads
                from house to house; two or three times it took us through some of those copses or
                groves that cover the little hillocks in the middle of the vale, making an intricate
                and pleasing intermixture of lawn and wood. Our fancies could not resist the
                temptation; and we fixed upon a spot for a cottage, which we began to build: and
                finished as easily as castles are raised in the air.&#8212;Visited the same spot in the
                evening. I shall say nothing of the moonlight aspect of the situation which had
                charmed us so much in the afternoon; but I wish you had been with us when, in
                returning to our friend&#8217;s house, we espied his lady&#8217;s large white dog, lying in the
                moonshine upon the round knoll under the old yew-tree in the garden, a romantic
                image&#8212;the dark tree and its dark shadow&#8212;and the elegant creature, as fair as a
                spirit! The torrents murmured softly: the mountains down which they were falling did
                not, to my sight furnish a back-ground for this Ossianic picture; but I had a
                consciousness of the depth of the seclusion, and that mountains were embracing us on
                all sides; &#8220;I saw not, but I <emph>felt</emph> that they were there.&#8221;
            </p>
                
            <p>Friday, November 9th.&#8212;Rain, as yesterday, till 10 o&#8217;clock , when we took a boat to
                row down the lake. The day improved,&#8212;clouds and sunny gleams on the mountains. In
                the large bay under Place Fell, three fishermen were dragging a net, a picturesque
                group beneath the high and bare crags! A raven was seen aloft; not hovering like the
                kite, for that is not the habit of the bird; but passing on with a straight-forward
                perseverance, and timing the motion of its wings to its own croaking. The waters
                were agitated; and the iron tone of the raven&#8217;s voice, which strikes upon the ear at
                all times as the more dolorous from its regularity, was in fine keeping with the
                wild scene before our eyes. This carnivorous fowl is a great enemy to the lambs of
                these solitudes; I recollect frequently seeing, when a boy, bunches of unfledged
                ravens suspended from the churchyard gates of H&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212; for which a reward of 
                <emph>so</emph> much a head was given to the adventurous destroyer.&#8212;The
                fishermen drew their net ashore, and hundreds of fish were leaping in their prison.
                They were all of the kind called skellies, a sort of fresh-water herring, shoals of
                which may sometimes be seen dimpling or rippling the surface of the lake in calm
                weather. This species is not found, I believe, in any other of these lakes; nor, as
                far as I know, is the chevin, that <emph>spiritless</emph> fish, (though I
                am loth to call it so, for it was a prime favourite with Isaac Walton,) which must
                frequent Ulswater, as I have seen a large shoal passing into the lake from the river
                Emont. <emph>Here</emph> are no pike, and the char are smaller than
                those of the other lakes, and of inferior quality; but the grey trout attains a very
                large size, sometimes weighing above twenty pounds. This lordly creature seems to
                know that &#8220;retiredness is a piece of majesty&#8221;; for it is scarcely ever caught, or
                even seen, except when it quits the depths of the lake in the spawning season, and
                runs up into the streams, where it is too often destroyed in disregard of the law of
                the land and of nature.
            </p>
                
            <p>Quitted the boat in the bay of Sandwyke, and pursued our way towards Martindale along
                a pleasant path&#8212;at first through a coppice, bordering the lake, then through green
                fields&#8212;and came to the village, (if village it may be called, for the houses are
                few, and separated from each other,) a sequestered spot, shut out from the view of
                the lake. Crossed the one-arched bridge, below the chapel, with its &#8220;bare ring of
                mossy wall,&#8221; and single yew-tree. At the last house in the dale we were greeted by
                the master, who was sitting at his door, with a flock of sheep collected round him,
                for the purpose of smearing them with tar (according to the custom of the season)
                for protection against the winter&#8217;s cold. He invited us to enter, and view a room
                built by Mr. Hasell for the accommodation of his friends at the annual chase of red
                deer in his forests at the head of these dales. The room is fitted up in the
                sportsman&#8217;s style, with a cupboard for bottles and glasses, with strong chairs, and
                a dining-table; and ornamented with the horns of the stags caught at these hunts for
                a succession of years&#8212;the length of the last race each had run being recorded under
                his spreading antlers. The good woman treated us with oaten cake, new and crisp; and
                after this welcome refreshment and rest, we proceeded on our return to Patterdale by
                a short cut over the mountains. On leaving the fields of Sandwyke, while ascending
                by a gentle slope along the valley of Martindale, we had occasion to observe that in
                thinly-peopled glens of this character the general want of wood gives a peculiar
                interest to the scattered cottages embowered in sycamore. Towards its head, this
                valley splits into two parts; and in one of these (that to the left) there is no
                house, nor any building to be seen but a cattle-shed on the side of a hill, which is
                sprinkled over with trees, evidently the remains of an extensive forest. Near the
                entrance of the other division stands the house where we were entertained, and
                beyond the enclosures of that farm there are no other. A few old trees remain,
                relics of the forest, a little stream hastens, though with serpentine windings,
                through the uncultivated hollow, where many cattle were pasturing. The cattle of
                this country are generally white, or light-coloured; but these were dark brown, or
                black, which heightened the resemblance this scene bears to many parts of the
                Highlands of Scotland.&#8212;While we paused to rest upon the hill-side, though well
                contented with the quiet every-day sounds&#8212;the lowing of cattle, bleating of sheep,
                and the very gentle murmuring of the valley stream, we could not but think what a
                grand effect the music of the bugle-horn would have among these mountains. It is
                still heard once every year, at the chase I have spoken of; a day of festivity for
                the inhabitants of this district except the poor deer, the most ancient of them all.
                Our ascent even to the top was very easy; when it was accomplished we had
                exceedingly fine views, some of the lofty Fells being resplendent with sunshine, and
                others partly shrouded by clouds. Ulswater, bordered by black steeps, was of
                dazzling brightness: the plain beyond Penrith smooth and bright, or rather gleamy,
                as the sea or sea sands. Looked down into Boardale, which, like Stybarrow, has been
                named from the wild swine that formerly abounded here; but it has now no sylvan
                covert, being smooth and bare, a long, narrow, deep, cradle-shaped glen, lying so
                sheltered that one would be pleased to see it planted by human hands, there being a
                sufficiency of soil; and the trees would be sheltered almost like shrubs in a
                green-house.&#8212;After having walked some way along the top of the hill, came in view of
                Glenriddin and the mountains at the head of Grisdale.&#8212;Before we began to descend,
                turned aside to a small ruin, called at this day the chapel, where it is said the
                inhabitants of Martindale and Patterdale were accustomed to assemble for worship.
                There are now no traces from which you could infer for what use the building had
                been erected; the loose stones and the few which yet continue piled up resemble
                those which lie elsewhere on the mountain; but the shape of the building having been
                oblong, its remains differ from those of a common sheep-fold; and it has stood east
                and west. Scarcely did the Druids, when they fled to these fastnesses, perform their
                rites in any situation more exposed to disturbance from the elements. One cannot
                pass by without being reminded that the rustic psalmody must have had the
                accompaniment of many a wildly-whistling blast; and what dismal storms must have
                often drowned the voice of the preacher! As we descend Patterdale opens upon the eye
                in grand simplicity, skreened by mountains, and proceeding from two heads, Deepdale
                and Hartshope, where lies the little lake of Brotherswater, named in old maps
                Broaderwater, and probably rightly so; for Bassenthwaite Mere at this day, is
                familiarly called Broadwater; but the change in the appellation of this small lake
                or pool (if it be a corruption) may have been assisted by some melancholy accident
                similar to what happened about twenty years ago, when two brothers were drowned
                there, having gone out to take their holiday pleasure upon the ice on a new-year&#8217;s
                day.
            </p>
                
             <p>A rough and precipitous peat track brought us down to our friend&#8217;s house.&#8212;Another
                fine moonlight night; but a thick fog rising from the neighbouring river, enveloped
                the rocky and wood-crested knoll on which our fancy-cottage had been erected; and,
                under the damp cast upon my feelings, I consoled myself with moralising on the folly
                of hasty decisions in matters of importance, and the necessity of having at least
                one year&#8217;s knowledge of a place before you realise airy suggestions in solid
                stone.
            </p>
                
            <p>Saturday, November 10th. At the breakfast-table tidings reached us of the death of
                Lord Nelson, and of the victory at Trafalgar. Sequestered as we were from the
                sympathy of a crowd, we were shocked to hear that the bells had been ringing
                joyously at Penrith to celebrate the triumph. In the rebellion of the year 1745,
                people fled with their valuables from the open country to Patterdale, as a place of
                refuge secure from the incursions of strangers. At that time, news such as we had
                heard might have been long in penetrating so far into the recesses of the mountains;
                but now, as you know, the approach is easy, and the communication, in summer time,
                almost hourly: nor is this strange, for travellers after pleasure are become not
                less active, and more numerous than those who formerly left their homes for purposes
                of gain. The priest on the banks of the remotest stream of Lapland will talk
                familiarly of Buonaparte&#8217;s last conquests, and discuss the progress of the French
                revolution, having acquired much of his information from adventurers impelled by
                curiosity alone.
            </p>
                
             <p>The morning was clear and cheerful after a night of sharp frost. At 10 o&#8217;clock we
                took our way on foot towards Pooley Bridge, on the same side of the lake we had
                coasted in a boat the day before.&#8212;Looked backwards to the south from our favourite
                station above Blowick. The dazzling sunbeams striking upon the church and village,
                while the earth was steaming with exhalations not traceable in other quarters,
                rendered their forms even more indistinct than the partial and flitting veil of
                unillumined vapour had done two days before. The grass on which we trod, and the
                trees in every thicket were dripping with melted hoar-frost. We observed the
                lemon-coloured leaves of the birches, as the breeze turned them to the sun, sparkle,
                or rather <emph>flash</emph>, like diamonds, and the leafless purple twigs
                were tipped with globes of shining crystal.
            </p>
                
            <p>The day continued delightful, and unclouded to the end. I will not describe the
                country which we slowly travelled through, nor relate our adventures; and will only
                add, that on the afternoon of the 13th we returned along the banks of Ulswater by
                the usual road. The lake was in deep repose after the agitations of a wet and stormy
                morning. The trees in Gowbarrow park were in that state when what is gained by the
                disclosure of their bark and branches compensates, almost, for the loss of foliage,
                exhibiting the variety which characterises the point of time between autumn and
                winter. The hawthorns were leafless; their round heads covered with rich red
                berries, and adorned with arches of green brambles, and eglantines hung with glossy
                hips; and the grey trunks of some of the ancient oaks, which in the summer season
                might have been regarded only for their venerable majesty, now attracted notice by a
                pretty embellishment of green mosses and fern intermixed with russet leaves retained
                by those slender outstarting twigs which the veteran tree would not have tolerated
                in his strength. The smooth silver branches of the ashes were bare; most of the
                alders as green as the Devonshire cottage-myrtle that weathers the snows of
                Christmas.&#8212;Will you accept it as some apology for my having dwelt so long on the
                woodland ornaments of these scenes&#8212;that artists speak of the trees on the banks of
                Ulswater, and especially along the bays of Stybarrow crags, as having a peculiar
                character of picturesque intricacy in their stems and branches, which their rocky
                stations and the mountain winds have combined to give them?
            </p>
                
            <p>At the end of Gowbarrow park a large herd of deer were either moving slowly or
                standing still among the fern. I was sorry when a chance companion, who had joined
                us by the way, startled them with a whistle, disturbing an image of grave simplicity
                and thoughtful enjoyment; for I could have fancied that those natives of this wild
                and beautiful region were partaking with us a sensation of the solemnity of the
                closing day. The sun had been set some time; and we could perceive that the light
                was fading away from the coves of Helvellyn, but the lake under a luminous sky, was
                more brilliant than before.
            </p>
                
             <p>After tea at Patterdale, set out again:&#8212; a fine evening; the seven stars close to the
                mountain-top; all the stars seemed brighter than usual. The steeps were reflected in
                Brotherswater, and, above the lake, appeared like enormous black perpendicular
                walls. The Kirkstone torrents had been swoln by the rains, and now filled the
                mountain pass with their roaring, which added greatly to the solemnity of our walk.
                Behind us, when we had climbed to a great height, we saw one light, very distinct,
                in the vale, like a large red star&#8212;a solitary one in the gloomy region. The
                cheerfulness of the scene was in the sky above us.
            </p>
                
            <p>Reached home a little before midnight.</p>
           
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
