<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  CHANGE TITLE, AUTHOR NAME, AND EDITOR NAME(S)  -->
                <title type="main">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                <title type="subordinate">"A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition"</title>
                <!-- Subtitle will change based on site section; 
for Editions, "A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition" 
for Praxis, "A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume" 
for Pedagogies, "A Romantic Circles Pedagogies Commons Volume" -->
                <title level="a">Editorial Philosophies and Guidelines</title>
                <!-- If author is a contemporary critic (secondary) -->
                <author role="secondary">
                    <name>Michelle Levy</name>
                    <name>Nicholas Mason</name>
                    <name>Paul Westover</name>
                </author>
                <!-- Remove the above if not contemporary author -->
                <editor role="editor">VOLUME/EDITION EDITOR(S)
                    <name>Michelle Levy</name>
                    <name>Nicholas Mason</name>
                    <name>Paul Westover</name></editor>
                <!-- Repeat the above line in the case of multiple editors -->
                <!-- If external funding was used in production, include the following section -->
                <funder>Brigham Young University</funder>
                <principal>Paul Westover</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <!-- Remove above "funder" section if not relevant -->
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                <!-- In the following, keep only the relevant section editor(s) -->
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                <!-- Choose section editor from above -->
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>T. J. McLemore</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado
                    Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                        or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                        purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                        use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                        are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                        with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                        permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                        requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/ editor(s) and
                        advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization
                        should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                        conditions: <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                        them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                        have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                        Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                        continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                        generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                        a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                        use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- CHANGE IDNO; ENSURE THAT THE "EDITION" LINE EXACTLY MATCHES THE FILE NAME -->
                <idno type="edition">editions.2022.DW.intro-editorial</idno>
                <idno type="resource">DW</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Editorial Philosophies and Guidelines</title>
                        <ptr target="SECTION/VOL-ABBREV/SECTION.YEAR.VOL-ABBREV.AUTHORLAST.html"/>
                    </analytic>
                    <!-- CHANGE TITLES -->
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Dorothy Wordsworth's Lake District</title>
                        <title level="s">Editorial Philosophies and Guidelines</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of
                                Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2023-08-02">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " to &#8220; or
                        &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed except in the case of
                        diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                        keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
                        such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
                        been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                    12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">KEYWORD</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  PUT YOUR NAME HERE. AND CHANGE THE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION  -->
                <name>Emily Stephens</name>
                <date>2023-08-02</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- End of Header -->
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head>Editorial Philosophies and Guidelines<lb/>
                <title level="m"><hi rend="small">Dorothy Wordsworth&#8217;s Lake District: A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</hi></title>
                </head>
                
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Paul Westover</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>Brigham Young University</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
             <div type="section">
                <head><span change="blue"><hi rend="small">Romantic-Era Women and the Scholarly Edition</hi></span></head>
            
                <p>In 1995, when &#8220;electronic edition&#8221; still had a futuristic ring and even the most
                inclusive of syllabi were constrained by which noncanonical texts were readily
                available in print, Marilyn Butler issued a call for scholars and publishers to
                prioritize producing high-quality yet affordable editions of important works by
                women. &#8220;We must have true scholarly editions of a significant body of women&#8217;s
                writing,&#8221; she argued, &#8220;not only to grasp the internal dynamics of an individual
                career, but to understand its group dynamics, its inter-relations with society and
                history.&#8221; Merely reprinting an old poem, play, or novel wasn&#8217;t enough, as &#8220;we
                mustn&#8217;t underrate how much a good edition adds to a &#8216;raw&#8217; text—far more, indeed, if
                it&#8217;s discreetly presented than most readers retain much consciousness of.&#8221; Even a
                rudimentary critical apparatus, Butler suggested, tends to make us take a text more
                seriously, as there is an inherent aura to a work that comes shrouded in a &#8220;penumbra
                of knowledge, biographical, textual, intertextual and extra-textual.&#8221;
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">Butler, <title level="a">Editing Women,</title> 274&#8211;75.
                    </note>
                </p>
            
                <p>Around the time of Butler&#8217;s appeal, many important new editions of Romantic women&#8217;s
                writing did, in fact, appear in print. Since then digital publication has emerged as
                a key avenue for publishing women&#8217;s writing of the period, with the web offering key
                advantages over print for representing full-color, high-quality images of
                manuscripts and also for rendering diplomatic transcriptions. In the present
                instance, publishing on Romantic Circles offers a stable, open-access, and
                peer-reviewed platform that adheres to the editorial standards of the best print
                series while also facilitating web-specific features like hypertext links and
                high-resolution galleries of illustrations and manuscript pages.
                </p>
            
                <p>Whether publishing in print or online, editors of Romantic-era women writers face
                particular challenges. Researchers studying most women writers lack the trove of
                archived manuscripts, letters, and notebooks that have been used to make modern
                editions of male Romantic writers the gold standard for exhaustively researched,
                copiously annotated, theoretically informed, and editorially inventive critical
                texts. Thus, while the trailblazing textual scholarship of Romanticists like Neil
                Fraistat, Jerome McGann, Donald Reiman, Charles Robinson, and Jack Stillinger has
                reinvigorated the field of scholarly editing, their weighty volumes have sometimes
                left editors of the period&#8217;s women writers uncertain how to follow suit.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">Other influential modern editors of the 
                        male Romantics include contributors to the monumental Cornell edition 
                        of WW, the Princeton edition of Coleridge, and the 
                        <title level="m">William Blake Archive</title>.
                    </note> 
                As Daniel Robinson has observed in relation to his own edition of the writing of Mary
                Robinson, &#8220;the relationship of the previously neglected woman writer to the canon may 
                be forever tenuous due to the nature of the archive, and this determines the work an 
                editor can do. The quality of an edition, therefore, is contingent upon, in effect, 
                the quality of the archive.&#8221;
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">Robinson, &#8220;Mary Robinson&#8217;s Poetry,&#8221; 53.</note> 
                For many women of the period, the archive consists mainly or exclusively of print editions.
                Therefore, with a few notable exceptions, those producing editions of women Romantic
                writers lack primary resources. This is true even for those working on writers like
                the prolific Ann Radcliffe or ultra-canonical Jane Austen, for whom we have only one
                manuscript fragment from her six printed novels.
                </p>
             </div>
                
             <div type="section">
                <head><span change="blue"><hi rend="small">From &#8220;The Poet&#8217;s Sister&#8221; to Major Author</hi></span></head>
            
                <p>With Dorothy Wordsworth, however, the opposite is true. She is a writer who published
                little in her lifetime, especially under her own name, but who left behind a wealth
                of manuscripts. Several of her works survive in multiple manuscript versions, almost
                all of which are conveniently archived at the Wordsworth Trust and, since 2012,
                available digitally through Adam Matthew&#8217;s <title level="m">Romanticism: Life,
                Literature, and Landscape</title> database. Moreover, unlike most of her female
                contemporaries&#8217;, Dorothy&#8217;s writing has, since the Victorian age, been admired,
                edited, and even re-edited by a series of leading scholars.
                </p>
            
                <p>Four years before Dorothy&#8217;s death, excerpts from her
                <title level="m">Grasmere Journals</title> first appeared under
                her name in <title level="m">Memoirs of William Wordsworth</title>, the biography her
                nephew Christopher Wordsworth Jr. published in the wake of the poet&#8217;s death.
                Twenty-three years later, Principal J. C. Shairp&#8217;s 1874 edition of her 
                <title level="m">Recollections of a Tour Made in Scotland A.D. 1803</title> proved so
                popular that it went into a third edition within a year. Then, in 1889, the
                preeminent Wordsworthian of late-Victorian England, William Knight, published the
                most extensive selections from Dorothy&#8217;s Alfoxden, Hamburg, and Grasmere journals to
                date in his eleven-volume <title level="m">Life of William Wordsworth</title> (1889).
                Knight soon republished these excerpts, along with several more from her travel
                narratives and &#8220;mountain rambles,&#8221; in his landmark two-volume 
                <title level="m">Journals of Dorothy Wordsworth</title> (1897). This was the standard Dorothy
                Wordsworth edition until 1941, when Ernest de Sélincourt, the great Wordsworth
                editor of the early twentieth century, released his own two-volume edition of her
                journals. (De Sélincourt, like Knight before him, began by working on William&#8217;s
                writings but soon became one of Dorothy&#8217;s champions.) Although only minimally
                contextualized and annotated, and devoid of any detailed analysis of conflicting
                versions and other textual concerns, De Sélincourt&#8217;s <title level="m">Journals of
                Dorothy Wordsworth</title> remains in many respects the closest thing to a proper
                scholarly edition of Dorothy&#8217;s prose works.
                </p>
            
                <p>Another breakthrough moment for the study of Dorothy Wordsworth, and arguably for
                Romantic women writers more broadly, came in 1974, when the Romanticism section in
                the third edition of the <title level="m">Norton Anthology of English
                Literature</title>, edited by M. H. Abrams, admitted her into what had previously
                been an all-male club. Yet, even while introducing excerpts from the 
                <title level="m">Grasmere Journals</title>, the anthology signaled that Dorothy&#8217;s
                inclusion had less to do with the intrinsic merits of her writing than with the
                light they shed on the domestic and writing life of her famous poet-brother.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"> This enduring sense of DW&#8217;s writings being 
                        more useful as secondary than primary sources partly explains the early, 
                        persistent, and, at times, exclusive focus on those passages from her 
                        <title level="m">Grasmere Journals</title> that capture peak moments in 
                        WW&#8217;s and Coleridge&#8217;s poetic careers.
                    </note> 
                 Of course, the <title level="m">Norton Anthology</title> was hardly the first to treat 
                 her journals as, above all, a study aid for the masterpieces composed by men of the 
                 &#8220;Wordsworth circle.&#8221; Knight, for instance, notoriously justified abridging her journals 
                 by explaining that they &#8220;contain numerous trivial details&#8221; and contending, &#8220;there is no 
                 need to record all the cases in which the sister wrote, &#8216;Today I mended William&#8217;s shirts,&#8217; 
                 or &#8216;William gathered sticks,&#8217; or &#8216;I went in search of eggs,&#8217; etc. etc.&#8221; He preferred 
                 passages that would cast &#8220;a flood of light on the circumstances under which her brother&#8217;s
                 poems were composed.&#8221;
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">KJ</title>, 1:vii&#8211;viii, x.</note> 
                 And while De Sélincourt was well ahead of his time when he declared that &#8220;Dorothy Wordsworth is
                 probably the most remarkable and the most distinguished of English writers who never
                 wrote a line for the general public,&#8221;
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">DWJ</title>, 1:v.</note>
                the critical apparatus to his edition of her journals perpetuated the tradition of
                placing heaviest emphasis on moments when her writings might illuminate William&#8217;s
                life and works. Furthermore, his claim that Dorothy never wrote for the public
                demands some scrutiny, for although she rarely wrote with publication directly in
                view, she knew that much of what she wrote would be absorbed by William and
                published by him.
                </p>
            
                 <p>With the late twentieth-century feminist turn in literary studies, however, scholars
                began to be newly attuned to Dorothy&#8217;s distinctive gifts, and to the audience that
                her writing garnered, even in her lifetime. Susan Levin&#8217;s <title level="m">Dorothy
                Wordsworth and Romanticism</title> (1987) was a breakthrough moment in this
                respect, as it at once made a persuasive case for revaluing Dorothy&#8217;s life and work
                and, in its latter half, offered the first anthology of her poems. Likewise,
                successive Oxford World&#8217;s Classics versions of <title level="m">The Grasmere and
                Alfoxden Journals</title>, beginning with Helen Darbishire&#8217;s pocket-sized edition
                of 1958 and culminating in Pamela Woof&#8217;s masterful edition of 2001, treated
                Dorothy&#8217;s diaries as &#8220;classics&#8221; worthy of meticulous presentation and generous
                annotation. When the 2001 edition appeared, Nicola Trott rightfully celebrated how
                Woof &#8220;establishes the full independence of Dorothy Wordsworth as a writer&#8221; and
                &#8220;makes it abundantly clear that Dorothy&#8217;s writing was not merely fodder for his
                [William&#8217;s] own, nor indeed was it about him, except in so far as he entered a
                narrative already crowded with incident and observation.&#8221;
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Trott, &#8220;Review,&#8221; 213.</note>
                 </p>
             </div>
                
             <div type="section">
                <head><span change="blue"><hi rend="small">The Digital Dorothy Wordsworth</hi></span></head>
            
                 <p>As in Woof&#8217;s edition, Dorothy is the undisputed protagonist of this Romantic Circles
                electronic edition of her writings on the Lake District. To a degree matched only by
                Levin&#8217;s 2009 Longman Cultural Edition, our 
                <ref target="/editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.contents.html">table of contents</ref> strays
                from the beaten path in including a range of lesser-known and even previously
                unpublished works demonstrating her abilities in multiple genres and stages of life.
                Moreover, excepting Woof, no previous editors have contextualized and annotated
                Dorothy&#8217;s works as thoroughly as we have here, and we pay unprecedented attention to
                the material forms of her texts and what they can teach us about the nature of her
                writing process, literary sociability, and intended audiences.
                 </p>
            
                 <p>At a moment of belt-tightening in academic publishing in the humanities, a 
                 scholarly edition with this level of breadth and detail is increasingly 
                 imaginable only in the digital realm, where editors face fewer 
                 constraints in matters of length, layout, and illustration. Since the 
                 earliest online editions appeared in the mid-1990s, the best examples 
                 of the genre have appreciated and capitalized on the distinctive advantages 
                 of this new medium. As a case in point, the digital version of Charles Robinson&#8217;s 
                 <ref target="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/contents/frankenstein/">
                 <title level="m">Frankenstein</title> Notebooks</ref> published two decades ago 
                 in the Shelley-Godwin Archive remains an essential resource. On a platform 
                 available to anyone with an internet connection, it offers high-resolution 
                 images of Mary Shelley&#8217;s manuscripts and scrupulous transcriptions, which 
                 combine to present the material contexts of this novel&#8217;s production and 
                 circulation in an entirely new light. Similarly, the
                 <ref target="https://www.edickinson.org/">Emily Dickinson Archive</ref> 
                 deploys digital tools to re-present a manuscript writer 
                 whose poetry has consistently been distorted by print mediations.
                 </p>
            
                 <p>Following in the footsteps of leading digital editors, we have designed 
                 this edition to showcase the challenges of rendering Dorothy&#8217;s manuscripts 
                 into typographic characters. Thanks to the Wordsworth Trust&#8217;s generosity, 
                 we provide dozens of scans of the original manuscripts, providing many 
                 opportunities to compare them to our transcriptions. As the digitized pages 
                 from her notebooks make readily apparent, Dorothy often wrote to the moment, 
                 particularly when journaling, and did not always come back to revise or create 
                 fair copies. When necessary, she wrote in a neat, legible hand; otherwise, as 
                 readers of her letters know, she usually preferred to apologize for her 
                 &#8220;bad habit of scrawling&#8221; rather than labor over every word.
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">Letters</title>,
                         4:293&#8211;94.
                     </note> 
                 Consequently, merely transcribing some of her more private texts, like her 
                 <ref target="/editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.RJ-1-intro.html">Rydal
                 Journals</ref>, presents countless editorial dilemmas.
                 </p>
            
                 <p>Dorothy&#8217;s poems pose different challenges, as many survive in multiple 
                 drafts that are rife with variants. Since she published only a handful 
                 of these poems and did not regularly identify or collect final versions, 
                 no one manuscript can be said to have authority over another. Still 
                 other texts, like <ref target="/editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.Greens-intro.html">
                 &#8220;A Narrative Concerning George &amp; Sarah Green&#8221;</ref> and 
                 <ref target="/editions/DW/editions.2022.DW.Ulls-intro.html">&#8220;Excursion on the Banks of
                 Ullswater,&#8221;</ref> survive in multiple copies made for various purposes and audiences, 
                 some with substantial corrections and revisions.
                 </p>
            
                 <p>Given such variations, we have been ecumenical in our editorial approach. As detailed
                in our introductions to specific sections, we have tried to tailor our digital
                presentation and editorial methodology to the distinctive features of individual
                texts and manuscripts. For instance, recognizing the challenges of engaging with the
                fragmentary and allusive <title level="m">Rydal Journals</title> without a familiarity
                with Dorothy&#8217;s world ca. 1825&#8211;1835, we supplement our transcriptions with detailed
                contextual introductions, indexes of key people and places, and hundreds of
                hyperlinked endnotes. In contrast, with Woof and others having already thoroughly
                annotated the <title level="m">Grasmere Journals</title>, we instead opt to provide a
                diplomatic transcription of the first of the four notebooks, emphasizing Dorothy&#8217;s
                revisions and the manuscript&#8217;s physical characteristics. And for her Lakeland
                &#8220;excursions,&#8221; we include interactive maps and dozens of illustrations to create a
                stronger sense of geography and material circumstances. In sum, we trust that
                editorial flexibility reflects Dorothy Wordsworth&#8217;s own flexibility and variety as a
                writer.
                 </p>
            
                 <p>Just as we have tried to adopt best practices from earlier digital editions, we have
                followed the lead of pioneering editors of women&#8217;s writing in questioning the
                conventional belief that, as W. W. Greg put it in 1954, the editor&#8217;s task is &#8220;to
                present the text, so far as the available evidence permits, in the form in which we
                may suppose that it would have stood in a fair copy, made by the author himself, of
                the work as he finally intended it.&#8221;
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors">Greg, Editorial Problem, x.</note>
                Authorial intention is a notoriously vexed subject in critical theory—&#8220;final
                intention&#8221; perhaps even more so, not least because it depends on the often shaky
                assumption that &#8220;final&#8221; versions exist. Further, as McGann has argued, this
                traditional focus on final intentions rests upon notions of &#8220;the autonomy of the
                isolated author,&#8221; an arguably masculine construction that &#8220;has the effect of
                desocializing our historical view of the literary work.&#8221;
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors">McGann, <title level="m">Critique</title>, 8, 121.</note> 
                And Dorothy is an exemplary
                social writer, frequently customizing her texts for different readers and occasions
                and often writing in close collaboration with others. She frequently customized her
                texts for different readers and occasions. She also tended to leave multiple versions of
                texts side by side in her notebooks, making it all but impossible in many cases to
                determine her &#8220;final intentions.&#8221; The same facts make it impossible to adopt
                the tenets of an opposing philosophy of textual editing—one perhaps most famously
                embraced by the Cornell Wordsworth editors—that consistently privileges the earliest
                completed version. Even where the sequence of versions can be reconstructed in
                Dorothy&#8217;s notebooks&#8212;and usually it cannot&#8212;it is impossible to say that one version
                is better, more authoritative, or more important than another.
                 </p>
            
                 <p>Fortunately, the nature of this digital edition allows us in several cases to offer
                multiple versions of a text, leaving readers to interpret each on its own terms. In
                such instances, we apply principles from the modern &#8220;versioning&#8221; school of textual
                editing, which has perhaps been most effectively modeled by editors such as Mays and
                Stillinger, who have taken pains to reproduce multiple versions of poems by
                Coleridge and Keats. As Amy Culley and Anna F. Fitzer have suggested, this approach
                treats writing &#8220;as a collaborative and social product&#8221; and discerning authorial
                intent as &#8220;just one in a sequence of textual negotiations.&#8221;
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Culley and Fitzer, 
                         <title level="a">Introduction: Editing Women&#8217;s Writing,</title> 7.
                     </note> 
                In its attempts to foreground the material, social, and geographical contexts of
                Dorothy&#8217;s writing, this edition also adopts key tenets of &#8220;the new textualism.&#8221; This
                approach, as described by Ann Hollinshead Hurley and Chanita Goodblatt, &#8220;focuses on
                the material properties of the manuscript or book, its print or performance history,
                and records of its dissemination.&#8221;
                     <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Hurley and Goodblatt, <title level="a">Preface,</title> xi.</note>
                Such an approach is necessary given the sociable contexts in which Dorothy wrote and
                circulated her writing.
                 </p>
             </div>
                
             <div type="section">
                <head><span change="blue"><hi rend="small">General Editorial Practices</hi></span></head>
            
                 <p>While our editorial approach may vary from text to text, all sections of this edition
                adhere to the following practices:
                 </p>
            <list rend="unordered">
                <item><hi rend="bold">References to the author</hi>: We default
                    to the somewhat familiar &#8220;Dorothy&#8221; as an imperfect alternative to the
                    potentially confusing &#8220;Wordsworth&#8221; (which still tends to connote the brother) or
                    the clumsy repetition of both writers&#8217; first and last names. Likewise, where
                    William Wordsworth appears in our apparatus, he becomes &#8220;William.&#8221; For the sake
                    of brevity, our endnotes use initials for Dorothy (DW), William (WW), and Mary
                    Wordsworth (MW), Sara Hutchinson (SH), and Samuel Taylor Coleridge (STC).
                    Endnotes reference William and Mary&#8217;s three surviving children (John, Dora, and
                    Willy) by first names only (see the list of <ref>Abbreviations of Commonly 
                    Used Names</ref><!--link to where this is-->).
                </item>
            
                <item><hi rend="bold">References to the region</hi>: To avoid
                    overusing any one toponym, we use &#8220;the Lakes,&#8221; &#8220;the Lake District,&#8221; &#8220;Lakeland,&#8221;
                    and &#8220;Cumbria&#8221; interchangeably. In doing so, we are cognizant that the
                    Wordsworths would have considered themselves residents of &#8220;the Lakes&#8221; and
                    Westmorland but perhaps not of &#8220;the Lake District&#8221; (which, first gaining
                    traction in the 1820s, would have seemed a neologism) or &#8220;Cumbria&#8221; (which had
                    grown archaic). These latter labels became normative only in the latter half of
                    the twentieth century, after the formations of the &#8220;Lake District National Park&#8221;
                    in 1951 and County of Cumbria (encompassing the traditional counties of
                    Westmoreland and Cumberland and slivers of Lancashire and Yorkshire) in 1974.
                    <note place="foot" resp="editors"> Note, however, that the popularity of 
                        the &#8220;Lake District,&#8221; both as a concept and as a toponym, was probably 
                        helped along by William Wordsworth&#8217;s <title level="m">Guide to the Lakes</title>, 
                        which from its 1835 edition forward had &#8220;District of the Lakes&#8221; in its title.
                    </note>
                </item>
            
                <item><hi rend="bold">Spelling and punctuation</hi>: All
                    transcriptions strive to replicate Dorothy&#8217;s spelling and punctuation precisely.
                    When unconventional, inaccurate, or omitted punctuation in the manuscript might
                    produce confusion, we provide punctuation marks inside editorial brackets (e.g.,
                    [,]). While our reading texts preserve Dorothy&#8217;s variant or archaic renderings
                    of place names (e.g., &#8220;Ulswater&#8221; and &#8220;Scawfell&#8221;), our editorial apparatus
                    generally privileges modern spellings (e.g., &#8220;Ullswater&#8221; and &#8220;Scafell&#8221;).
                </item>
            
                <item><hi rend="bold">Citations</hi>: As per general Romantic
                    Circles guidelines, all citations follow the short-form rules dictated in the
                    <title level="m">Chicago Manual of Style</title> (17th
                    edition). See also our list of <ref>Abbreviations for
                    Commonly Used Sources.</ref><!--link to where this is-->
                </item>
            
                <item><hi rend="bold">Titles</hi>: When Dorothy provided a
                    title for a text, we reproduce it. In many cases, however, she saw no need for
                    titles. For her unnamed poems, we have resisted the urge to offer standardized
                    titles, adopting instead the first line and placing it within brackets. For her
                    journals, also untitled, for ease of reference we use names commonly used by
                    scholars—that is, <title level="m">Grasmere Journals</title> and 
                    <title level="m">Rydal Journals</title>. This practice adheres to the norm of formatting
                    references to posthumously constructed texts (e.g.,
                    <title level="m">The Prelude</title> of 1805) identically to
                    those for lifetime editions (e.g.,
                    <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title> of 1798). But when
                    referring to the physical manuscripts or to specific journal entries we use the
                    term &#8220;Grasmere journal notebooks&#8221; in acknowledgement of the fact that DW never
                    appears to have considered the four notebooks now known as the 
                    <title level="m">Grasmere Journals</title> a unified work. The fact that many teaching editions
                    extract her Grasmere entries from notebooks that also contain other materials
                    reminds us that &#8220;journals&#8221; are not necessarily identical with the manuscripts in
                    which they are found. Especially when referencing these early journals, then, we
                    attempt to distinguish between the text and its material instantiation on paper.
                </item>
                
                <item>For Dorothy&#8217;s two &#8220;excursion&#8221; narratives, we adopt titles supplied for them in
                    William&#8217;s <title level="m">Guide to the Lakes</title> and retained by later
                    editors, as these serviceably describe their contents.
                </item>
            </list>
             </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
