<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Untitled Document</title>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2021-12-18T23:40:00</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>no publication statement available</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Written by OpenOffice</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><name>Amelia Worsley</name><date>2021-12-18T23:40:00</date></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p rend="center"><hi rend="bold"><lb/>Afterthoughts on a Pedagogy of Dehiscence</hi></p>
            <p>Black studies is a dehiscence at the heart of the institution and at its edge; its
                broken, coded documents sanction walking in another world while passing through this
                one, graphically disordering the administered scarcity from which black studies
                flows as wealth. The cultivated nature of this situated volatility, this emergent
                poetics of the emergency in which the poor trouble the proper, is our open
                secret.</p>
            <p rend="end">— Fred Moten, “Black Op” (2008a)</p>
            <p>In the spring semester of 2014, eighteen months prior to the course I describe in
                this essay, I had begun to study Afropessimism during a graduate seminar on global
                modernism. The following summer—when officers of the New York Police Department
                killed Eric Garner; when police officer Darren Wilson killed Michael Brown; when a
                highly militarized police force intensified its occupation of Ferguson, Missouri;
                when Claudia Rankine published <hi rend="italic">Citizen; </hi>when Black feminist
                activists founded the Movement for Black Lives; and Sandra Bland died in prison
                after her arrest following a pretextual traffic stop—Afropessimism offered an
                analytically rigorous and unflinching account of the paradigm of “ontological
                terror” in which these events had occurred, as well as a framework for reevaluating
                my fledgling pedagogical practices (Warren 2018). Emerging in part from the
                acknowledgment of a continuum that links racial slavery to the anti-Blackness of
                whiteness, policing, and the state, Afropessimism challenges conventional accounts
                of civic reason and historical progress and produces a conceptual break to think
                through the paradigmatic anti-Blackness of global modernity in “the afterlife of
                slavery” (Hartman 2006).</p>
            <p>In Afropessimism, the paradigm of anti-Blackness explains the performance of
                anti-Black racism in higher education as much as it explains the performance of
                anti-Black policing. As context for the discussion on pedagogy that follows, I will
                briefly describe a spate of anti-Black violence on the campus of University of
                Massachusetts Amherst that took place in the fall of 2014. Content warning: though I
                describe some of the language as it appeared on campus that fall, my purpose in
                doing so is not to transgress the suffering of African Americans and other people of
                color, but to refuse a practice so common to neoliberal institutionality by which
                systemic racism and structural violence are hushed in the service of a recommitment
                to the institution. At the time, the anti-Black language I reference here led to the
                organization of somber events about “standing together against racism,” to
                sanctimonious acts of “reflection,” to repetitious commitments to “diversity and
                tolerance,” and to administrative calls to “work together to reaffirm our values of
                inclusion and respect for all.”<hi rend="sup"><note xml:id="ftn1" place="foot" n="1"
                        > An event called “Standing Together Against Racism: A Week of Reflection, A
                        Day of Solidarity” was organized by The Anti-Racism Committee of English
                        Students and Faculty and featured a full-day “Solidarity Read-In” that I
                        participated in on November 4, 2014. The phrase “work together to reaffirm
                        our values of inclusion and respect for all“ was published in a
                        university-wide email by Chancellor Kumble Subbaswamy, “Incidents of Racist
                        Vandalism,” on October 14, 2014.</note></hi> There was little institutional
                recognition, however, of the well-documented history of anti-Black violence as a
                longstanding tenet of the University at large, little space or outlet for the
                expression of Black anger, suffering, or rage, and no answer as to why incidents of
                anti-Black violence should lead the “community” to <hi rend="italic">come
                    together</hi> as opposed to <hi rend="italic">coming apart</hi>. Christina
                Sharpe comments on how often “the note of a more perfect union, the note of
                unhearable Black suffering” is struck by leaders on the occasion of anti-Black
                violence: a striking note that “sutures Black suffering to romance and redemption”
                (Sharpe 2016). It is a practice far too common that seeks by way of anti-Black
                institutions solutions to the very problems they give rise to. I therefore refer to
                the following language in the spirit of anti-romance and an anti-redemptive
                abolitionism. in the service of an imperfect union.</p>
            <p>In October 2014, amidst the cries and lamentations of protestors, a statement calling
                for the killing of two Black students in Harambee (a defined residential community
                for African and African American students) was written on their front door with a
                racial slur. One of the students directly targeted, an undergraduate, had recently
                returned from Ferguson, Missouri, where he had taken part in Ferguson October, a
                coalition-building social movement later known as Ferguson Action. It was written on
                his door during the fatefully named “Columbus Day” weekend (“#WrongDoor”). That same
                weekend, someone else had also written a racist message calling for the death of
                Hispanic students because of perceived linguistic otherness on the door of another
                dorm room, and the following week, several additional students were targeted by a
                person later identified as Devin Ayres, who was charged with property damage in the
                Eastern Hampshire District Court, thereby leaving a public record of his hate-speech
                (Vidales). According to testimony quoted in reports, Ayres wrote the n-word on the
                door of one student because he knew her to be African American, and used it a second
                time on the door of two white students because he knew one of them to be dating an
                African American man (“UMass student charged”). Viewed through an Afropessimist
                lens, the performance of anti-Black sexual racism is neither aberrant nor anomalous,
                but as banal and procedural as Ayres’s court testimony. In a university context,
                furthermore, the excuse of white ignorance should not be allowed its ordinarily
                stabilizing effect for a multicultural society where education is purported to be
                the antidote to (rather than the cause of) anti-Black racism. There was nothing
                unknowing or unintentional about these acts of violence. Their effect appears to
                have been to restore the order of institutional power.</p>
            <p>A year later, in the fall of 2015, I taught an introductory Ethnic American
                Literature course oriented toward transatlantic (anti)slavery literature whose
                emphasis on <hi rend="italic">legacies </hi>engaged constructions of race, gender,
                and minoritization in narratives of slavery, colonialism, emancipation, and
                political awakening in a campus climate antagonized by anti-Black violence. Some of
                the texts, like Olaudah Equiano’s <hi rend="italic">Interesting Narrative
                </hi>(1789) and Edgar Allan Poe’s <hi rend="italic">Narrative of Arthur Gordon
                    Pym</hi> (1838), were drawn from the era of Romanticism properly speaking, and
                animated our discussions of freedom, slavery, persuasion, and unselfpossessed gothic
                subjectivity. Most of them, however, were contemporary texts that take up
                Romantic-era concepts in a “speculative” framework, like Mat Johnson’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Pym </hi>(2011), Celu Amberstone’s “Refugees” (2004), Octavia
                Butler’s <hi rend="italic">Bloodchild and Other Stories </hi>(1995/2005), and Samuel
                Delany’s <hi rend="italic">Empire Star </hi>(1966) — all texts that engage with
                race, racialization, and the rule of dominance in contemporary (anti)slavery. The
                course I was assigned to teach, “Ethnic American Literature,” is defined by the
                University of Massachusetts Amherst English Department as “American literature
                written by and about ethnic minorities, from the earliest immigrants through the
                cultural representations in modern American writing.” The course is traditionally
                taught as an introduction to immigrant literature, focusing either on historical
                breadth or on a particular literary tradition (e.g. Jewish American literature or
                Asian American literature). I decided to create a version of the course that would
                reckon with the apparent incompatibility of racial slavery with the “immigrant”
                experience. Thus two other themes drove my choice of the “sci-fi” texts on the
                syllabus, namely (time) travel and consciousness. The course aimed to provoke
                commentary on race and (anti)slavery through <hi rend="italic">bildungsroman</hi>
                about characters who awaken to the realities of colonialism, conquest, and
                displacement by placing these texts in conversation with both (Critical) Ethnic
                Studies and Black Studies. Though the course I taught was not envisioned a course on
                Romanticism, then, I hope it will be useful to colleagues wishing to experiment with
                the dialogue between Romantic texts and more recent speculative fiction. </p>
            <p>In the initial course design, Afropessimism provided a framework for understanding
                the wave of anti-Black terror as a brief moment of disequilibrium in the hegemony of
                everyday violence held over from slavery, rather than some shocking set of events
                unrelated to the political structure of the University. I wanted students to engage
                with this continuum, to question their assumptions about the “pastness” of slavery,
                the progressiveness of liberal democracy, and the postracialism of the contemporary.
                I wanted them to feel authorized to use the space of the classroom to acknowledge
                the profound suffering on campus and to partake of the unspeakable rage of its
                injustice. In the epigraphs above, Fred Moten speaks to a “dehiscence at the heart
                of the institution,” seizing on the ambiguity of that term to indicate how Black
                Studies attends to the structural vulnerability of critical thought in the
                University, where Black Studies is constantly vulnerable to regulation, defunding,
                and marginalization. A (wound) dehiscence is an opening in a plant that allows seeds
                to disperse as well as a gaping incision in a body (politic) prone to infection. I
                did not at the time conceive of my pedagogy as a “dehiscent” one, but upon
                reflection, I see how teaching (in) the epistemic and psychosocial wounds of slavery
                pushed my class toward shared vulnerability rather than inviolable strength, and how
                this shifted the goals of student learning from individual mastery of the subject
                toward “unthinking mastery” through expressions of humility, collectivity, and
                selflessness (Singh).</p>
            <p>As we moved from Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Pym</hi> to the text it annotates (Poe’s
                    <hi rend="italic">The Narrative of Arthur Gordon Pym</hi>), the first half of
                the course addressed what Johnson calls “the pathology of Whiteness,” a subject that
                animated a wide spectrum of student responses ranging from sheer delight and
                selfless auto-critique to reactionary defensiveness and other performances of tacit
                white supremacy. By producing a class that was vulnerable and conflicted, wounded
                and antagonistic, the prick and provocation of simply naming whiteness led us into
                the second half of the course, which focused on “<hi rend="italic">the Slave grammar
                    of suffering</hi>,” a phrase I adopt from the work of Frank B. Wilderson III. As
                I will go on to explain, “the Slave grammar of suffering” disrupts fantasies of
                social wholeness and historical redress from the vantage point of the enslaved
                subject within a field of structural antagonisms. Making a distinction between the
                oppression of subaltern positions and the suffering of “the Slave,” Wilderson’s
                political ontology induces unsettling disquiet and anger rather than sentimentality,
                positivity, or solution-oriented saviorism. Seizing on the double meaning of
                dehiscence as diaspora and wound, the essay then concludes with some afterthoughts
                on pedagogy: what do students learn and unlearn when asked to bear witness to the
                collective and enduring traumas of slavery?</p>
            <p rend="center"><hi rend="bold">The Pathology of Whiteness</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Pym</hi>, Mat Johnson’s third novel, follows protagonist Chris
                Jaynes, an Assistant Professor of African American Literature, whose desire to
                uncover “how the pathology of Whiteness was constructed” shapes his obsessive
                inquiry into the work of Edgar Allan Poe, particularly <hi rend="italic">The
                    Narrative of </hi><hi rend="italic">Arthur Gordon Pym of Nantucket</hi>, Poe’s
                Antarctic expedition tale. Chris is the only Black professor at a small liberal arts
                college in Manhattan, and as the only professor who specializes in African American
                literature, he is denied tenure because in teaching courses like “Dancing with the
                Darkies: Whiteness in the Literary Mind” (an allusion to Toni Morrison’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Playing in the Dark: Whiteness in the Literary Imagination</hi>),
                he refuses to play the part of “Professional Negro” (7). “You were hired to teach
                African American literature,” explains the college President during a heated
                exchange. “Not just American literature. You fought that. Simple” (13).
                Foregrounding the racial politics of literary interpretation from the outset, <hi
                    rend="italic">Pym</hi> pits the institutional demand for minority representation
                (“We are a large literature faculty, they can handle the majority of literature. You
                were retained to purvey the minority perspective” [13]) against Chris’s heroic
                ambition to “[cure] America’s racial pathology,” which “like all diseases… had to be
                analyzed at a microscopic level” (8).</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Pym </hi>staged a series of questions for us to consider at the
                outset of the course. Why does the College President say “<hi rend="italic">Not
                    just</hi> American Literature”? Is African American Literature (or Ethnic
                American Literature) <hi rend="italic">not</hi> American Literature, per se? And if
                the latter category is in fact so specific as to include these others, then why is
                it unmarked and unraced? Why not refer to it as <hi rend="italic">White
                </hi>American Literature? As the novel pursues such questions through a satirical
                travel narrative that takes Chris and an ad hoc “Creole crew” to Antarctica in
                search of the fabled island of Tsalal, that “great undiscovered African Diaspora
                homeland” referred to in Poe’s text (“uncorrupted by Whiteness”) it also begins to
                answer them (39). Whiteness is a “pathology and a mindset,” Chris thinks, not an
                “ethnic nomenclature” (33, 31). It is “metaphorical” (30), an “ideology” (30), and a
                “strategy” (31). Above all, “Whiteness isn’t about being something, it is about
                being no thing, nothing, an erasure” (225), a claim that is confirmed symbolically
                when Chris and his crew are enslaved by a “race” of culture-less “snow honkies”
                called Tekelians who rule the white, windswept landscape of the South Pole (160).
                When their captivity among the Tekelians appears to be inescapable, Chris’s uncle,
                Captain Booker Jaynes, tells him, “You can’t run from Whiteness. You have to stand
                and engage it” (209). For Chris, though, whiteness is not something “to stand.” From
                New York to Antarctica, whiteness is the inescapable background of his every
                movement.</p>
            <p>To facilitate conversation between and among students, I assigned everyone to a
                small, three- to four-person online writing group where they submitted short essays
                and reading responses and provided each other with written feedback. In addition to
                my notes about in-class presentations that were also required of every student, this
                online archive of the course is where, with permission, I’ve drawn the direct
                quotations and paraphrased commentary that appear throughout this essay.</p>
            <p>As disturbing as it is to see Chris denied tenure as a result of the racist
                institutional politics that lead to his firing, students writing about <hi
                    rend="italic">Pym</hi> were, predictably, much more profoundly pained by his
                subsequent enslavement, and by the gratuitous violence used by the Tekelians to
                maintain control over their captives. One non-Black student of color wrote that they
                were saddened by the apparent “hopelessness” of the novel, which seemed to suggest
                that “no matter how hard they [the crew] try, whiteness cannot be escaped.” Yet
                several students, perhaps feeling uncomfortable sharing this viewpoint with the
                whole class so early in the semester, confided that they were refreshed by the
                novel’s reorientation of the “normal” routes of desire, as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pym</hi> made the sniveling, nail-biting, blubber-eating white Tekelians
                repulsive, and the Black Creole crew attractive. Indeed many students became more
                comfortable analyzing whiteness while reading <hi rend="italic">Pym</hi>; and after
                also reading Poe’s <hi rend="italic">Narrative of Arthur Gordon Pym</hi>, one
                student concluded that whiteness is an “idea of unity that, in the case of this
                novel and perhaps in reality, only succeeds in destroying than bringing together. It
                swallows only the ideas that perpetuate its image as salvation, purity, and
                goodness, and erases all that would tarnish its brilliant color.” However, the
                criticism of whiteness engendered by these books also led to reactionary
                defensiveness. In a response essay submitted to an online writing group, one student
                wrote that Chris’s reference to the indistinguishability of the Tekelians (“they all
                pretty much looked the same to me” [131]) was effectively a form of reverse racism.
                This was addressed and, I think, adequately corrected both in their peer group and
                in the classroom, where we explained that an observer who is enslaved, and who
                therefore has no institutional power, cannot be <hi rend="italic">racist</hi>, even
                if that same observer can be provocative. To support the student’s understanding, I
                shared Ruth Wilson Gilmore’s definition of racism as “the state-sanctioned or
                extralegal production and exploitation of group-differentiated vulnerabilities to
                premature death” (Gilmore 2007). In <hi rend="italic">Pym</hi>, the impossibility of
                reverse racism is made clear: Chris, a captive subject to the institutional and
                interpersonal violence of the Tekelians, cannot possibly return the same threat.</p>
            <p>The satirical tone and allegorical humor of <hi rend="italic">Pym</hi> makes it an
                accessible index for critiquing whiteness and engendering generous if sometimes
                painful (auto)critique. Having read it prior to Poe’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Narrative</hi>, and along with excerpts from Morrison’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Playing in the Dark</hi>, students are presented with a persuasive case to
                study whiteness as what Johnson terms a “pathology,” “strategy,” and “ideology.”
                What is additionally generative about these texts is that although they are
                sometimes misrecognized as saying that “race” is a biological signifier, they also
                prompt students to think about the evaluative symbolism of “color.” Early on in <hi
                    rend="italic">Pym</hi>, Chris comments on a passage of Poe’s novel where the
                narrator observes a river on the island of Tsalal “made up of a number of distinct
                veins, each of a distinct hue; [whose] cohesion was perfect in regard to their own
                particles among themselves, and imperfect in regard to neighboring veins” (29).
                Chris suggests that the description resembles the “racial fantasy” of Booker T.
                Washington’s “Atlanta Compromise,” a fantasy, in other words, of functional
                segregation (29). I taught Poe’s imagery as an anti-Black fantasy of (social)
                control over the distribution of color, however, pointing out that this fantasy is
                represented repeatedly in both novels.</p>
            <p>In <hi rend="italic">Pym</hi>, for instance, there is Poe’s fictional “hybrid” Dirk
                Peters’ great-great-granddaughter, Mahalia Mathis, who despite appearing to Chris as
                phenotypically Black, refuses African heritage. Mathis heads the Native American
                Ancestry Collective of Gary, Indiana (NAACG), a group that uses DNA testing to prove
                that their genes have “no kind of Africa”:</p>
            <p>I got lots of Indian in me. I got Irish and I got a little French too. I got some
                German, or so I’m told. I even got a little Chinese in me, on my mother’s side.
                Matter of fact, I’m sure I got more bloods in me that I knows. But I do knows this:
                I ain’t got no kind of Africa in these bones. (49)</p>
            <p>This anti-Black fantasy, which plays itself out in the self-recognition of several
                “colors” ostensibly excluding the color “black,” also plays out in the color
                symbolism of Chris’s Antarctic expedition. After he and his best friend Garth escape
                their captivity among the Tekelians, they flee to an Antarctic BioDome owned by the
                painter Thomas Karvel (a parody of Thomas Kinkade), who provides them shelter while
                they work a small plantation. True to his moniker, “the Master of Light” is a
                sovereign of <hi rend="italic">color</hi>, a monarch over of a Disney-like “fantasy
                of Whiteness” marked by the monochromatic oversaturation of the BioDome, where the
                animals are too-white, the grass too-green, the river too-blue, but where nothing is
                Black except Chris and Garth, the ostensible interlopers (185). Indeed, Chris
                complains to Garth that Karvel’s paintings never have Black people in them; even
                worse, he suspects that in Karvel’s work, “black people couldn’t exist, so thorough
                was its European romanticization” (184).</p>
            <p>In “The Case of the Blackness,” Fred Moten writes that “the cultural and political
                discourse on black pathology has been so pervasive that it could be said to
                constitute the background against which all representations of blacks, blackness, or
                (the color) black take place,” arguing in sum that “blackness has been associated
                with a certain sense of decay, even when that decay is invoked in the name of a
                certain (fetishization of) vitality” (Moten 2008b). As if throwing their hands up,
                one student recognized “the absurdity in our world’s thought process that anything,
                even things of the same nature such as mice and birds, can be separated and
                classified into greater and lesser categories just because of color.” But Johnson’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Pym </hi>and Poe’s <hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi> suggest a
                politics of chroma that goes beyond irrational absurdity. For if Black is
                theoretically every color, and white is theoretically no-color, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pym</hi> suggests that “the pathology of Whiteness” lies precisely in Karvel’s
                desire to <hi rend="italic">master</hi> color itself. Whiteness is an ideology and a
                strategy because it is an operation that speciates every-color into veins of a river
                that do not “commingle,” turning inward into monochromatic oversaturation or
                dividing up into “ethnic” varieties of American literature. If blackness is the
                chromatic equivalent of refusing this violent speciation through absorption,
                whiteness is by definition antagonistic to such a politics: the refusal of
                every-color.</p>
            <p rend="center"><hi rend="bold">The “Slave Grammar of Suffering”</hi></p>
            <p>In the anti-Black environment in which my students took this course, I was not
                surprised that some would perform whiteness by being defensive or by making
                discreditable claims of “reverse racism.” I was heartened, however, that for the
                most part, white and non-Black students of color in the course allied themselves
                with the interests of their Black peers (which is to say, with Blackness) and
                seriously committed themselves to diagnosing “America’s racial pathology.”
                Questioning the existential basis of one’s relationship to whiteness can produce
                existential crises that overflow what a normative classroom is able to hold, putting
                students in a position that may be analogous to the one occupied by the person who
                asked Frank Wilderson, in an online interview, what a white person could do to
                interpolate Afropessimism without succumbing to a form of reasoning that would lead
                them to commit suicide: “As a white person who feels bad about all my race does,
                what can I do to help besides killing myself?” Wilderson’s answer was swift and to
                the point. Rather than “kill yourself,” the questioner should get angry and “undo
                yourself.” Moreover, the questioner should develop “ways and means for your speech
                and action to be authorized by a Black/slave grammar of suffering rather than the
                grammar of suffering of subalterns.” Wilderson concluded the answer by remarking on
                the radical potential of the questioner’s “undoing”: “<hi
                    rend="background-color(#ffffff)">You are far more dangerous by being committed
                    in this long, protracted struggle than you are or would be if you just check
                    out.” </hi>Thus, in the second half of the course, I aimed to give students
                space to take up “the Slave grammar of suffering” as a pedagogy of “speech and
                action” oriented toward “undoing” the pathology of whiteness<hi rend="italic"
                >.</hi></p>
            <p>What is the difference between the subaltern grammar of suffering and the Slave
                grammar of suffering, and what does it mean to be “authorized” by the latter?
                Wilderson defines grammar as “the structure through which the labor of speech is
                possible,” arguing that scripts which view “social turmoil through the rubric of
                conflict (i.e. a rubric of problems that can be posed and conceptually solved)”
                represent a subaltern grammar of suffering in which grievances are submitted and
                solutions proposed to return aggrieved parties to a condition of prior wholeness. On
                the other hand, scripts that view social turmoil through a “rubric of antagonism (an
                irreconcilable struggle between entities, or positions, the resolution of which is
                not dialectical but entails the obliteration of one of the positions)” represent a
                Slave grammar of suffering that disrupts the dream of repair. Thus one of the
                primary distinctions between a Slave grammar of suffering and a grammar of subaltern
                suffering concerns a text’s relationship to resolution. From the vantage point of
                the Slave, whose exclusion from civil society is fundamental to the freedom enjoyed
                by citizens (Wilderson’s terminology includes “Humans,” “Whites,” and “Settlers”),
                inclusion is a form of “obliteration.” Being authorized by the Slave grammar of
                suffering therefore begins with refusing the “prescriptive gesture” of
                reconciliation. For Wilderson, it continues (through Fanon via Cesaire) with “the
                end of the world… the only thing… worth the effort of starting” (337).</p>
            <p>As literary texts, Celu Amberstone’s “Refugees,” Octavia Butler’s “Amnesty” and
                “Bloodchild,” Samuel Delany’s <hi rend="italic">Empire Star</hi>, and Equiano’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi> are all available to interpretation
                through the grammar of suffering: “Refugees” through a colonizer/colonized dynamic
                on the fictional planet of Tallav’Wahir; “Amnesty” and “Bloodchild” through the lens
                of captivity on earth and on the Tlic planet, respectively; <hi rend="italic">Empire
                    Star</hi> through its plot to emancipate the enslaved Lll; and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi> through its autobiographical narrative
                of enslavement. Yet as a story about people relocated from a post-apocalyptic earth,
                “Refugees” seems to engage the suffering of the colonized or the migrant subject
                struggling to reestablish the customs of their homeland; it does not engage the
                Slave grammar of suffering, since through “natal alienation” such resolution is
                ultimately unavailable to the enslaved person (Patterson 1982). Similarly, by
                focusing on a human protagonist who translates between human beings and an
                extraterrestrial lifeform that has colonized earth, Butler’s “Amnesty” is more about
                structural adjustment and human de-exceptionalism than it is about slavery.
                “Bloodchild” certainly <hi rend="italic">appears</hi> to be about slavery, and many
                students were certain it was; they were therefore puzzled that Butler herself
                disagreed, writing, “It amazes me that some people have seen ‘Bloodchild’ as a story
                of slavery” (30). However, as one student observed about the gender and reproductive
                politics of the story, Butler was probably right to call her narrative about the
                implantation of a male human named Gan with Tlic larvae her “pregnant man story,”
                and a “love story,” rather than a “slave narrative”: </p>
            <p>It is interesting that in a society where women get pregnant and have children all
                the time, it is often called love, but when it is a man being impregnated in almost
                the same exact way, it can be seen as slavery. Perhaps this happens because sci-fi
                novels are seen as so drastically different in their own imagined worlds that it is
                hard to see their similarity to the reality of life on Earth, or it is because of
                the patriarchal views that have been instilled in the reader that affect how
                ‘Bloodchild’ is read.</p>
            <p>Prompted by such articulate student writing, I wonder, then, when I thought I was
                teaching about slavery several years ago, if I was not, perhaps, teaching about
                something else. Recognizing that not all of these texts are engaged with the grammar
                of Slave suffering places pressure on how I would teach Romantic antislavery
                literature and its legacies in the future, especially when the topic is “the slave
                narrative” (See Matthew and Chander 2018).</p>
            <p>Of all the texts we read together, Samuel Delany’s <hi rend="italic">Empire Star
                </hi>gets nearest to representing what Wilderson calls “the suffering of the Slave,”
                as it were, grammatically. At the center of the novella about slavery and
                emancipation in a far-off galaxy is “the suffering of the Lll,” a race of
                world-building beings whose emancipation is seemingly dependent on the delivery of a
                message to Empire Star by the young Comet Jo. As students began to notice, however,
                the Lll never speak. They are always described collectively, never individually. And
                their enslavement seems to be constituted as much by their silence as through the
                garrulous verbosity of everyone else with something to say about why the Lll should
                be or should not be emancipated, which is to say, every other “free” character.
                “Their place in the book is the un-speaking point of conflict,” wrote one student;
                indeed, “they <hi rend="italic">are</hi> conflict, not <hi rend="italic"
                    >character</hi>, not <hi rend="italic">being</hi>. And while they might achieve
                ‘emancipation,’ they are not free, but remain enslaved to others with a voice.” The
                world of <hi rend="italic">Empire Star</hi> clearly depends upon the slavery of the
                Lll, making their emancipation a political farce, their suffering an antagonism with
                no redress, pessimistic conclusions frankly confirmed by <hi rend="italic">Empire
                    Star</hi>’s circular, spiral, and “retrocausal” form (Shepard 2019). Treating
                the continuum of slavery and emancipation as a formal element of the text, the
                novella ends exactly where it began, with Comet Jo realizing he has been tasked with
                Lll emancipation perhaps many times before.</p>
            <p>By contrast, Equiano’s <hi rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi> appears to end on
                a somewhat hopeful, solution-oriented note based on free market liberalism, the
                British state’s capacity for “justice,” and the good will of “every man of
                sentiment” (176). Yet if this prescriptive gesture lends itself to an interpretation
                as a grammar of subaltern suffering, yet the book is undoubtedly a narrative that
                grapples with exposing the grammar, or structure, of “Black/slave” suffering, in
                Wilderson’s terms. In one class discussion of Equiano’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Interesting Narrative</hi>, a conversation that continued in our online
                discussion forum, I introduced students to the evidence compiled by Vincent Carretta
                suggesting that Equiano may have been born in Carolina, even though his
                autobiography tells us he was born in Africa, that he was captured as a child, and
                that he suffered the Middle Passage (Carretta 2005, Youngquist 2016). I explained
                that Carretta’s evidence included the ship’s log for Equiano’s Arctic voyage as well
                as the record of his baptism, both of which identified Carolina as his place of
                birth. I also explained that Carretta’s intention was not to cast doubt on Equiano’s
                narrative but to understand what literary and political concerns may have motivated
                the decision, if it were indeed true — an intention I therefore posed to the class
                as a question. Why would Equiano fabricate aspects of his autobiography?</p>
            <p>Having posed the question, the ensuing conversation more or less followed Carretta’s
                own conclusions: Equiano’s political motivation was to abolish slavery, and an
                account of his capture and Middle Passage journey was the most likely way to provoke
                what one non-Black student referred to as a “drama-driven English audience.”
                Elaborating on a now-foundational connection between the liberal anti-slavery
                movement and spectacular representations of Black suffering (Hartman 1997), some
                students were therefore content to understand autobiography as a genre with certain
                formal needs and capabilities, including “literary devices.” Abolition by any means
                necessary. Others went so far as to suggest that it was “natural and unavoidable to
                lie when selling a story,” and that lying “is practically part of the social
                contract” between writers and readers.</p>
            <p>This conversation was enormously productive for nuancing the understanding of at
                least one non-Black student, who wrote online that before the full unfolding of our
                class discussion he viewed Equiano’s potential fabrication as a way to disguise his
                status as an otherwise “privileged slave” who was able to read, write, and build
                relationships with free whites. “I thought that it seemed a bit ridiculous that he
                would make things up and make [a narrative of his capture and the Middle Passage]
                sound like his own life to rouse sympathy in the readers,” wrote the student, whose
                classmates were quick to jump on the notion of “privilege” at play. One non-Black
                peer wrote that they would “hesitate to call a[n enslaved person] privileged,
                especially since it is clear from the text that Equiano does not define himself this
                way and consistently refers to any good luck that comes his way as an aberration
                from a system that is built to deny him any good fortune. He certainly considers
                himself blessed, mainly in retrospect after being freed, but his narrative is
                demonstrating how the institution of slavery blocks privilege based on race.” A good
                point — although it was ultimately not the purpose of the first student to pursue
                the idea of “privilege.” Rather, in examining why Equiano would fabricate aspects of
                his autobiography, the student had become interested in whether it was Equiano’s
                intention “to voice stories of other [enslaved people] that do not have the
                opportunity to.” In other words, was Equiano’s narrative more of a social history
                than an autobiography?</p>
            <p>In <hi rend="italic">The Intimacies of Four Continents</hi>, Lisa Lowe demonstrates
                how Equiano’s narrative, given voice through a genre of liberalism (“In a sense,
                autobiography is the liberal genre par excellence” [46]), reveals a connection
                between slavery, subjugation, and “the singular life” (71). In thinking of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi> as a kind of polyvocal performance of
                himself and “other [enslaved people],” then, my student was perhaps moving toward a
                critique of autobiography: Olaudah Equiano was not only Equiano, he was also
                Gustavus Vassa, and he was born in multiple places. In attempting to find a grammar
                requisite to the suffering of the enslaved, Equiano/Vassa had to call the genre of
                the autobiography, the narrative of the singular life, into profound question. Even
                though the <hi rend="italic">Interesting Narrative </hi>concludes with a predictable
                form of prescriptive redress, much of it nevertheless strives toward a collective
                articulation of dispersed suffering and rather than a selfish, self-made, or
                individual suffering. The internal differentiation of Equiano’s narrative into that
                of Gustavus Vassa <hi rend="italic">as well as </hi>“[enslaved people] that do not
                have the opportunity” leads us to think and imagine antislavery everywhere.</p>
            <p rend="center"><hi rend="bold">Toward a Pedagogy of Dehiscence</hi></p>
            <p>In recent years, the field of Black Studies has become, perhaps more consciously than
                ever before, an interdisciplinary mode, a fugitive method, and an intellectual
                itinerary inseparable but nevertheless distinguishable from the disciplinary study
                of the color black, Black people, or Black arts and culture — where the emphasis may
                fall on either the first or the second term. While there are many descriptions of
                what Black study is and does, I have adopted Fred Moten’s description of it as “a
                dehiscence at the heart of the institution and at its edge.” This definition has
                animated these afterthoughts on the pedagogy of dehiscence in and as a form of
                wounding that is also a plan of and for dispersal. Dehiscence is a recurring concept
                in Moten’s work, where he mobilizes uses of the phrase from Derrida, Levinas, and
                Lacan with a difference — as in “Refuge, Refuse, Refrain,” an essay on Adrian Piper,
                where he further elaborates on dehiscence as a “motif of selflessness” against the
                longstanding association of subjectivity with the inviolability of the possessive
                individual, which echoes with questions, raised above, about the singularity of
                autobiography: “To disagree with Piper’s account of herself and her work is to
                depend upon the dehiscence of and within herself and her work, the gravity of which
                is a matter of the field they occupy rather than fiction of their particularity. In
                this dehsicence, this break, this differential inseparability, other motives emerge;
                what emerges is another motif of selflessness” (Moten 2018, 118). My understanding
                of dehiscence as a marginal if animating premise and practice of Black Studies
                postdates the Ethnic American Literature course I have described. However, in our
                attention to the <hi rend="italic">Slave grammar of suffering</hi> expressed in
                course materials, in the field of social relations, and on the UMass Amherst campus
                circa 2014-15 in particular, we were, I think, working toward a pedagogy of
                dehiscence — a learning environment that takes place in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >vulnus,</hi> or psychosocial wounds of Atlantic slavery; when that “wound” is
                understood as an atmosphere of violence which extends beyond the site of the
                original cut.</p>
            <p>My use of the word dehiscence to describe a method of teaching (anti)slavery
                literature and its legacies thus weaves together Black studies pedagogy with the
                intellectual and scholarly protocols of Afropessimism, which repeatedly express
                dissatisfaction with the state of academic knowledge production as civic engagement,
                politically acceptable modes of reform, and solution-oriented prescriptive gestures
                for addressing the continuum of anti-Black violence. In the introductory Ethnic
                American Literature course that I have described it was difficult to address <hi
                    rend="italic">the pathology of Whiteness</hi> and <hi rend="italic">the Slave
                    grammar of suffering</hi> in part because students are encouraged through
                education to think of themselves as becoming productive individuals, “engaged”
                citizens, and masters of intellectual property in a “meritocratic” context driven by
                competition against one another. Students are not so accustomed to viewing these
                aspects of their education as a part of the problem of racist institutions, or to
                    <hi rend="italic">undoing</hi> themselves through actions and speech authorized
                by suffering. There is nothing that excludes radical forms of care and compassion
                from a classroom informed by these practices. However, the feelings of woundedness
                and vulnerability in my class did not immediately lend themselves, nor should they
                have, to being neatly, cleanly sutured.</p>
            <p>In a well-known passage of <hi rend="italic">Teaching to Transgress: Education as the
                    Practice of Freedom</hi>, bell hooks shares an anecdote about the pain her
                students feel when they take her classes: “We take your class. We learn to look at
                the world from a critical standpoint, one that considers race, sex, and class. And
                we can’t enjoy life anymore” (42). hooks concludes the passage by suggesting that
                modeling mutual respect for that pain reveals its commonness among students “across
                race, sexual preference, and ethnicity,” and she writes that through sharing this
                pain her classes “build community.” In the Ethnic American Literature course I
                taught, students experienced similar feelings of pain, confusion, remorse, anger,
                and defensiveness when sitting with the violence of whiteness and the enduring
                suffering of slavery’s afterlives, and though I do not wish to disagree with hooks’
                optimistic comments about community-building, I do wish to question them. To my
                mind, a pedagogy of dehiscence does not (at least not at first) end in a reformed
                community. Instead, it opens up the possibility of ending “community.” Put another
                way, a pedagogy of dehiscence does not seek simply to undermine the hierarchical
                relations of the classroom and build community on disingenuous assertions of
                equality in the afterlife of slavery. Rather, a pedagogy of dehiscence acknowledges
                that the classroom continues to be structured by the social relations of conquest,
                colonialism, and slavery, and accepts that the wound this causes ought to cause one
                (one? many? who? us?) to pursue the abolitionist endeavor of ending <hi
                    rend="italic">this</hi> kind of world. </p>
            <p rend="center"><hi rend="bold">Works Cited</hi></p>
            <p>Butler, Octavia E. <hi rend="italic">Bloodchild and Other Stories.</hi> 1995. Seven
                Stories Press, 2005.</p>
            <p>Castro, Andres Fabian Henao. “Teaching to Transgress’ Death Drive, or bell hooks as
                Educator.” <hi rend="italic">La Deleuziana Online Journal of Philosophy</hi>, no. 6
                (2007): pp. 145-157.</p>
            <p>Carretta, Vincent, <hi rend="italic">Equiano, the African: Biography of a Self-Made
                    Man</hi>. U of Georgia P, 2005.</p>
            <p>Chander, Manu Samriti and Patricia A. Matthew. “Abolitionist Interruptions:
                Romanticism, Slavery, and Genre.” <hi rend="italic">Romantic Review</hi> 29.4<anchor
                    type="bookmark-start" xml:id="id__GoBack"/>(2018)<ptr type="bookmark-end"
                    target="#id__GoBack"/>: pp. 431-434.</p>
            <p>Delany, Samuel. <hi rend="italic">Babel-17/Empire Star</hi>. 1966. Vintage, 2001.</p>
            <p>Equiano, Olaudah. <hi rend="italic">The Interesting Narrative of Olaudah Equiano, or
                    Gustavus Vassa, an African, Written by Himself.</hi> 1789. W. W. Norton &amp;
                Company, 2001.</p>
            <p>Gilmore, Ruth Wilson. <hi rend="italic">Golden Gulag: Prisons, Surplus, Crisis, and
                    Opposition in Globalizing California</hi>. U of California P, 2007.</p>
            <p>Harney, Stefano and Fred Moten, <hi rend="italic">The Undercommons: Fugitive Planning
                    and Black Study</hi>. Minor Compositions, 2013.</p>
            <p>Hartman, Saidiya. <hi rend="italic">Lose Your Mother</hi>. Farrar, Straus and Giroux,
                2006.</p>
            <p>------. <hi rend="italic">Scenes of Subjection: Terror, Slavery and Self-Making in
                    Nineteenth-Century America</hi>. Oxford UP, 1997.</p>
            <p>hooks, bell. <hi rend="italic">Teaching to Transgress: Education as the Practice of
                    Freedom.</hi> Routledge, 1994.</p>
            <p>Johnson, Mat. <hi rend="italic">Pym.</hi> Spiegel and Grau, 2011.</p>
            <p>Lederman, Diane. “UMass student charged with racist messages must stay away from
                campus; police continue investigating other incidents.” MassLive, 20 Oct. 2014.
                https://www.masslive.com/news/2014/10/umass_student_charged_with_rac.html. Accessed
                6 March 2020.</p>
            <p>Lowe, Lisa. <hi rend="italic">The Intimacies of Four Continents</hi>. Duke UP,
                2015.</p>
            <p>Moten, Fred. “Black Op.” <hi rend="italic">PMLA</hi>, vol. 123, no. 5, 2008a, pp:
                1743-1747.</p>
            <p>------. “The Case of Blackness.” <hi rend="italic">Criticism</hi>, vol. 50, no. 2,
                2008b, pp: 177-218.</p>
            <p>------. <hi rend="italic">The Universal Machine</hi>. Duke UP, 2018.</p>
            <p>Odam, Josh. “#WrongDoor: Ethno-stress and racially charged attacks on the UMass
                campus.” <hi rend="italic">The Massachusetts Daily Collegian</hi>, 16 Oct. 2014.
                https://dailycollegian.com/2014/10/wrongdoor-ethno-stress-and-racially-charged-attacks-on-the-umass-campus/.
                Accessed 6 March 2020.</p>
            <p>Patterson, Orlando. <hi rend="italic">Slavery and Social Death: A Comparative
                    Study</hi>. Harvard UP, 1982.</p>
            <p>Poe, Edgar Allan. <hi rend="italic">The Narrative of Arthur Gordon Pym of
                    Nantucket.</hi> 1838. Melville House, 2013.</p>
            <p>Sexton, Jared. “People-of-Color-Blindness: Notes on the Afterlife of Slavery.” <hi
                    rend="italic">Social Text</hi>, vol. 28, no. 2, 2010, pp. 31–56.</p>
            <p>------. “The Social Life of Social Death: On Afro-Pessimism and Black Optimism.” <hi
                    rend="italic">InTensions</hi>, vol. 5, 2011.</p>
            <p>Shephard, W. Andrew. “‘All Is Always Now’: Slavery, Retrocausality, and Recidivistic
                Progress in Samuel R. Delany's <hi rend="italic">Empire Star</hi>.” <hi
                    rend="italic">CR: The New Centennial Review</hi> vol. 19, no. 2, 2019, pp
                1-20..</p>
            <p>Sharpe, Christina and Selmawit Terrefe. “What Exceeds the Hold?: An Interview with
                Christina Sharpe.” <hi rend="italic">Rhizomes: Cultural Studies in Emerging
                    Knowledge</hi> 29, 2016. https://doi.org/10.20415/rhiz/029.e06</p>
            <p>Vidales, Santiago. “‘Whose University? Our University:’ A Report on Racist Hate
                Crimes at UMass Amherst.” <hi rend="italic">Latino Rebels</hi>, 19 Oct. 2014.
                https://www.latinorebels.com/2014/10/19/whose-university-our-university-a-report-on-racist-hate-crimes-at-umass-amherst/.
                Accessed 6 March 2020. </p>
            <p>Singh, Julietta. <hi rend="italic">Unthinking Mastery: Dehumanism and Decolonial
                    Entanglements.</hi> Duke UP, 2018.</p>
            <p>Warren, Calvin. <hi rend="italic">Ontological Terror: Blackness, Nihilism, and
                    Emancipation</hi>. Duke UP, 2018.</p>
            <p>Wilderson, Frank. “I Am Frank Wilderson AMA.”
                https://www.reddit.com/r/Debate/comments/5al9pl/i_am_frank_wilderson_ama/</p>
            <p>------. <hi rend="italic">Red, White, &amp; Black: Cinema and the Structure of U.S.
                    Antagonisms.</hi> Duke UP, 2010.</p>
            <p>Youngquist, Paul. “The Afro Futurism of DJ Vassa.” <hi rend="italic">European
                    Romantic Review</hi> vol. 16, no. 2, 2005, pp. 181-192.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
