<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Introduction</title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Joselyn M. Almeida and Amelia Worsley</name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-11-22</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2024.race.almeida</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">race</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Romanticism and Anti-Slavery Literatures: Pedagogies and Contexts 
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Joselyn</forename>
                                <surname>Almeida</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Amelia</forename>
                                <surname>Worsley</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="praxis/contingent/praxis.2024.race.almeida"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/wellbeing/praxis.2024.wellbeing.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Anti-Slavery Literatures: Pedagogies and Contexts </title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-11-22">November 22, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>11.22.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
            <p>The initial impetus for the present volume emerges from a collective decision to make
                a written record of a roundtable on “Anti-Slavery Literature, Its Legacies, and the
                Future of Teaching,” organized by members of the Five College Faculty Seminar on
                Global Cultures of the Long Nineteenth Century in 2018.<note place="foot" resp="author"> 
                    A collaboration between the five colleges situated in the
                    Amherst área in Western Massachusetts, the <hi rend="italic">Global Cultures of
                        the Long Nineteenth Century</hi> seminar was founded in 2012 by Joselyn M.
                    Almeida (UMass), Gülru Çakmak (UMass) and Kate Singer (Mount Holyoke). Daniel
                    Block (Hampshire College) later became a co-organizer. By 2018, the seminar was
                    being led by Joselyn M. Almeida, Kate Singer, Lily Gurton-Wachter (Smith
                    College), and Amelia Worsley (Amherst College). See also <ref
                        target="https://k-saa.org/race_pedagogy_whiteness/"
                        >https://www.fivecolleges.edu/faculty/faculty-seminars</ref>: “Five College
                    Faculty Seminars bring together faculty members from three or more of the five
                    campuses to exchange ideas, discuss works-in-progress, and on occasion host
                    guest speakers.”</note> Since its inception in 2012, the seminar was conceived
                of as a venue in which faculty from five colleges in the Amherst area of Western
                Massachussets could collaborate with an interdisciplinary group of scholars
                “attentive to the intersections and tensions among the constellations of
                globalization, cosmopolitanism, migration, and border studies in the nineteenth
                    century.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> This quotation is taken from
                    the original funding request for the seminar.</note> Over the years, faculty
                from different colleges have met to share their work-in-progress, and have also
                hosted lectures from colleagues visiting from the surrounding area, which have
                illuminated the multiple intersections and tensions of colonialism and
                globalization, Atlantic Slavery, cosmopolitanism, migration, border studies, and the
                digital humanities.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Our conversation at the
                    panel in 2018 was shaped by seminars with Simon Gikandi, Manu Samriti Chander,
                    Grégory Pierrot, Laura Doyle, Ron Welburn, Roberto Marquez, Orrin Wang, Joel
                    Pace, Elizabeth Maddock Dillon, and Jared Hickman. (Nb.Since Five College
                    Funding is limited, we limited our invitations to colleagues located on the East
                    Coast of the US, or those travelling through the area.)</note></p>
                
            <p>The 2018 pedagogy roundtable, held at Mount Holyoke College<hi rend="italic">,</hi>
                built on these shared experiences and emerged from the community that these previous
                discussions had created. Our group’s decision to organize the event stemmed from a
                series of informal questions we had for each other during a seminar meeting in
                Amherst in January 2016, and later, from more formal questions that followed the
                seminar’s engagement with Brazilian scholar Paolo Freire's <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pedagogy of the Oppresed</hi> (1970, 2004) as we began to think more closely
                about pedagogy. In that winter meeting, we reflected on how national events in the
                previous eighteen months had impacted our classrooms. As Keeanga-Yamahtta Taylor
                describes that period of time: “Over the course of ten months, spanning from the
                summer and fall of 2014 into the winter and spring of 2015, the United States was
                rocked by mass protests, led by African Americans in response to the police murder
                of a young Black man, Michael Brown. In the summer heat of August, the people of
                Ferguson, Missouri, rose up and brought the world’s attention to the crisis of
                racist policing practices in the United States” (2). A year after the protests in
                Ferguson, in the fall of 2015, a series of student protests at the University of
                Missouri, including a “Racism Lives Here rally,” spurred on a wave of protests
                designed to open a dialogue about racism on university campuses across the country,
                including our own.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    https://www.cnn.com/2015/11/09/us/missouri-protest-timeline/index.html</note> At
                Amherst College, for instance, an event that began as an hour-long lunchtime protest
                in solidarity with students at Missouri and Yale spontaneously evolved into the
                “Amherst Uprising,” a multi-day occupation of the college library. Several months of
                critical dialogue within the Amherst College community, regarding the ways in which
                anti-Black racism impacted student life on campus, followed.<note
                    place="foot" resp="author"> The sit-in was organized by three Black Women of the Class of
                    2018, Katyana Dandrige, Lerato Teffo, and Sanyu Takirambudde. See
                    https://amherstuprising.org/</note> At UMass Amherst, too, a campus-wide
                reckoning with the effects of racism was taking place, in the wake of a series of
                racist incidents in 2014, which Sean Gordon describes in detail in his essay below,
                and which distressingly have become an almost yearly occurence despite the
                university’s effortsto redress them.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Racial
                    bias incidents are chronicled for the years 2016-8 and 2020 in the University of
                    Massachusetts at Amherst's <hi rend="italic">Annual Security Report</hi>. In
                    2021, the campus was again shaken when racist emails were sent to Black student
                    organizations in September. The investigation into the source of the emails is
                    ongoing. See Jesús Jimenez, "UMass Amherst Hires Cybersecurity Firm to
                    Investigate Racist Emails," <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, September 30,
                    2021, <ref target="https://www.fivecolleges.edu/faculty/faculty-seminars"
                        >https://www.nytimes.com/2021/09/30/education/umass-amherst-racist-emails.html</ref>
                </note></p>
                
            <p>In the wake of the Black Lives Matter movement and the
                    violence that prompted it, it was clear that the words “freedom” and
                “abolition,” so often found on the syllabi of classes on Romantic literature, were
                now resounding in universities with new connotations. Students walking straight from
                campus protests to our classes encountered anti-slavery texts on the syllabi of our
                surveys on Romantic literature with a new interest in exploring the relationship
                between the moment these texts were written and the moment in which we were reading
                    them. In a class on John Newton’s poem “Amazing
                Grace” that happened to be planned for the week following the Amherst Uprising, for
                instance, the atmosphere was understandably charged, since President Obama had only
                recently sung the hymn at Clementa Pinckney’s funeral, after he and eight members of
                the congregation at Emanuel African Methodist Episcopal Church were murdered by a
                white supremacist in June 2015. After watching a video of his rendition of the hymn,
                students debated what different lines in the poem might mean. Several students
                questioned Obama’s decision to sing the hymn after learning about how Newton, the
                author of the poem that became the hymn, had profited from the trade of enslaved
                persons before his conversion to Christianity. During this conversation, students
                became more and more intrigued by how context conjugates the polyvalence of words.
                One student insisted on the importance of the hymn to her and to her family in
                moments where tragedy had touched their lives, and taught the class about the
                importance of the hymn in the Baptist Church. As the class learned about the way
                that Obama was building on Martin Luther King’s engagement with the hymn during the
                Civil Rights movement, the debate about what the history of this poem might do to
                its meaning in the present, and <hi rend="italic">vice versa</hi>, intensified.</p>
                
            <p>Conversations in our classrooms that semester awakened a variety of emotions in
                students that we had not encountered as professors who had taught this material
                before. Or, at least, many affective responses to texts were on display in
                classrooms that semester, in a way that they hadn’t been before. In another class
                that centered on the sentimental tradition in abolitionist verse, students intuited
                for themselves Alan Richardson’s argument that “read less as literature than as
                political discourse or social commentary, the anti-slavery poems of the era still
                fail to move beyond vapid sentiment, stock description, stereotyped characters and
                    situation.”<note place="foot" resp="author">Alan Richardson
                        (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Slavery, Abolition and Emancipation: Writings in
                            the British Romantic Period, Vol 4: Verse</hi>. eds. Lee, Debbie, and
                        P.J. Kitson, London, England: Pickering &amp; Chatto, 1999, x.</note> 
                Some became viscerally angry at white Romantic abolitionist poets for the
                presumption they had shown in ventriloquizing the suffering of enslaved people, and
                others questioned the ethics of continuing to anthologize these poems. At other
                moments, professors became the targets of another kind of anger, motivated by a
                defensive form of white supremacy: one colleague in our seminar spoke about a
                student who had violently objected to “being made” to read <hi rend="italic">The
                    Interesting Narrative of Olaudah Equiano</hi>, which detonated many of the
                varied feelings of the pain that racism in the classroom can cause.<note
                   place="foot" resp="author"> For a helpful resource on student resistance,
                    see Abby Ferber, “Bringing Students into the Matrix: a Framework and Tools for
                    Teaching Race and Overcoming Student Resistance.” <hi rend="italic">Teaching
                        Race and Anti-Racism in Contemporary
                    America,</hi> edited by Kristin Haltinner, Springer, 2014, pp.
                    141-155.</note> As these conversations continued, students and teachers alike
                became increasingly aware that the pastness of Atlantic slavery does not translate
                into the pastness of racism.</p>
                
            <p>Our decision to think about how to teach anti-slavery literature within the broader
                purview of Romantic studies arose due to an organic synergy between the discussion
                of the Black Lives Matter movement and the discussions happening in our classrooms.
                Yet there are also structural reasons why the atmosphere in our classrooms was
                particularly charged in moments when we were discussing this particular body of
                texts. As Eric Williams revealed drawing on Marx, the system of Atlantic Slavery
                incubated Capitalism in generating surplus value from the labor of enslaved persons
                while European expansionism unfolded, and, like colonialism, is constitutive of the
                experience of modernity itself. Williams’ argument has been revisited by Immanuel
                Wallerstein, and Walter Mignolo alongside other historians, sociologists, and
                    economists.<note place="foot" resp="author">Eric Williams, <hi
                        rend="italic">Capitalism and Slavery,</hi> ed.Colin A. Palmer (Chapel Hill:
                    University of North Carolina Press, 1994); Immanuel Wallerstein, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Modern World System: Capitalist Agriculture and the
                        Origins of the Modern World System</hi> (Berkeley: University of California
                    Press, 2011); Walter Mignolo, The Idea of Latin America (Boston: Wiley,
                    2005).</note> Zakiyyah Iman Jackson writes, “Slavery and colonialism not only
                catalyzed the conscription of black people into hegemonically imperialist and
                racialized conceptions of ‘modernity’ and ‘universal humanity’ but also inaugurated
                Western modernity’s condition of possibility” (45). Simon Gikandi (who visited our
                    <hi rend="italic">Five College Global Cultures </hi>seminar in 2017) similarly
                argues, “The modern spirit seemed unable to incorporate the difference that it
                nevertheless needed to imagine its modernity, and hence authorized itself by
                inventing a hierarchical structure in which the whiteness of Europe would be
                refracted by the shadows cast by others” (10). Avery Gordon suggests that this
                heightens the urgency for action: “Slavery has ended, but something of it continues
                to live on in the social geography of where peoples reside... in the veins of the
                contradictory formation we call New World modernity, propelling, as it always has, a
                something to be done” (139). A new generation of abolitionist scholars also remind
                us that the symbolic afterlives of Atlantic Slavery must also be considered
                alongside political economy and other systems of forced labor, neoslavery, and
                exploitation that persist within the current permutation of capitalism.<note
                    place="foot" resp="author"> See Dennis Childs, <hi rend="italic">Slaves
                        of the State</hi> (Minnesota: Minnesota University Press, 2015); Van der
                    Linden, Marcel and Magaly Rodríguez García, <hi rend="italic">On Coerced Labor:
                        Work and Compulsion After Chattel Slavery</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 2016).
                </note></p>
                
            <p>We are keenly aware that our desire to make a record of a conversation at a
                particular moment in time is in tension with the way in which this conversation
                continues to evolve in real time as national and global events unfold. Since we held
                our panel in 2018—and even since the authors sent the revised versions of their
                essays in early 2020 to the respondents—the stakes of the conversation about the
                relationship between the Romantic period and the current moment continue to be
                amplified. The resurgence of Black Lives Matter protests after the murder of George
                Floyd in the summer of 2020, as well as the violent and militarized responses to
                them we witnessed, provided a salient reminder of the importance of Christina
                Sharpe’s injunction in <hi rend="italic">In the Wake: On Blackness and Being
                </hi>(2016) to imaginethe legacy of a “past that is not past” (13).<note
                    place="foot" resp="author"> For instance, Kerry Sinanan argues in “BLM
                    2020: Breathing, Resistance, and the War Against Enslavement,” responses to the
                    Black Lives Matter protests can be viewed as “part of the centuries-long
                    continuum of slave rebellion”: “As if to confirm this, on June 1, 2020,
                    President Trump threatened to invoke the 1807 Insurrection Act that would allow
                    him to ‘call forth the militia for the purpose of suppressing such
                    insurrection.’ This Act arose directly out of the threat posed by Haiti which
                    had declared its constitution in 1805, forming itself into a ‘free state,
                    sovereign and independent’” (para 1-2).</note> We edited final drafts of these
                essays in a year when the phrase “I can’t breathe” became, as Achille Mbembe put it,
                a rallying cry in a battle against “everything that fundamentally attacks the
                respiratory tract, everything that, in the long reign of capitalism, has constrained
                entire segments of the world population, entire races, to a difficult, panting
                breath and life of oppression” (“The Universal Right to Breathe”).</p>
                
            <p>Even as the political situation continues to evolve, however, questions that were
                being asked about teaching anti-slavery literature in 2016 still remain urgent in
                2021. As Patrisse Cullors, Alicia Garza and Opal Tometi, who founded the Black Lives
                Matter Movement in 2013, describe the movement, “We are committed to working for a
                world where Black lives are no longer systematically targeted for demise,” and “we
                affirm our humanity, our contributions to society, and our resilience in the face of
                deadly oppression.”<note place="foot" resp="author"><ref
                            target="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/09/30/education/umass-amherst-racist-emails.html"
                                >https://blacklivesmatter.com/about/</ref>, accessed October 2 2020.</note> For
                those who teach Romantic literature, it is necessary to continue to question not
                only how the era we teach contributed to a system in which Black lives became
                “targeted for demise,” but also to confront the question of how syllabi, classroom
                discussions and other spaces of pedagogical inquiry might better affirm the
                humanity, contributions and resilience of Black and Brown people, both in the
                nineteenth century and today.</p>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head>II. From roundtable to special issue</head>
            <p>Returning to 2016: as we examined events on local campuses with each other, we
                wondered what colleagues in other colleges and universities had been experiencing
                during this time of mourning and redress. Mindful of
                the inherent limitations in our positionalities, we sought to engage the collective
                wisdom of other colleages in a more formal and generative dialogue that would create
                different possibilities for the classrom. In dialogue with Kate Singer and Lily
                Gurton-Wachter, co-organizers of the seminar, we resolved to bring together four
                scholars of race and literature—Frances Botkin, Kimberly Juanita Brown, Sean Gordon,
                and Patricia A. Matthew—to create a safe and respectful space in which faculty and
                graduate student instructors could engage in dialogue with each other about how they
                were currently teaching anti-slavery texts from the Romantic period, and how we
                might imagine teaching them in the future. Two of our speakers were local, and two
                travelled from different East-Coast locations to be with us. The roundtable was
                transatlantic in scope, with scholars representing Caribbean, American and British
                literatures. In our invitation, we simply asked our colleagues to “speak about
                approaches to teaching eighteenth or nineteenth-century anti-slavery literature in
                the context of the Black Lives Matter Movement.” We asked them to share some moments
                from their own recent experiences in the classroom, and their subsequent reflections
                on them. We stressed that the emphasis would be on conversation with the audience,
                whom we imagined would also find it useful to have a space to share their
                reflections on classroom experience.</p>
            <p>An unusually large audience was in attendance at the pedagogy panel in
                Spring 2018: it was clear that this subject was of interest to students at both the
                graduate and undergraduate level, as well as to faculty members who more usually
                made up the audience of the <hi rend="italic">Global Cultures of the Long Nineteenth Century </hi>seminar.<note place="foot" resp="author"
                    > The panel was originally planned for February 17 2017, but a national
                    strike that day meant that we decided to cancel it in solidarity, meaning that
                    it had to be delayed until all the speakers could reconvene, in 2018. Yet the
                    topic only felt more urgent by that time.</note> Several different pedagogical
                approaches were offered, but the panelists all shared a desire to confront the
                violence contained in these eighteenth- and nineteenth-century texts and the
                silences of the past and to share epistemologies of social justice, speaking to the
                present with the future in mind. Though the speakers approached the task of teaching
                different anti-slavery texts with different methodologies, they each gave us an
                insight into classrooms where students are frequently invited to think about how to
                connect the past with the present moment. As our panelists discussed a range of
                approaches to teaching anti-slavery texts, the question of affect was clearly a
                central concern, as it had been in the discussion that led to the event. Students
                often have questions about the violence that these texts present them with, and in
                turn, teachers themselves had many questions for each other about how to frame that
                act of presentation. How do we support students through challenging readings, beyond
                giving content warnings or making the readings optional? How does one manage the
                affect—the emotions and feelings—that such triggering material is bound to bring
                into the room? How can we make space for conversation in the classroom about how
                different students might encounter anti-slavery literatures, because of the varied
                experiences they bring to these texts?</p>
                    
            <p>Several important questions about what it means to teach anti-slavery literature in
                the context of courses on Romanticism also emerged that day. We recall that Kimberly
                Juanita Brown played music over her own speech as she discussed the power of African
                American spirituals to invite students to connect to the “auditory dimensions” of
                the archive, a concept she also explores in her book, <hi rend="italic">The
                    Repeating Body: Slavery’s Visual Resonance in the Contemporary </hi>(140); and
                indeed, many of our panelists asked us to attune their ears to listen for
                multilayered channels of communication in anti-slavery texts. A central theme in our
                discussion was the question of how to bring to light the things that the texts do
                not say about the realities of slavery in the period, either because of the
                blindspots of the authors, or because of the constraints placed upon them. As
                Saidiya Hartman asks, where the archive is lacking, how can we “retrieve what
                remains dormant…without committing further acts of violence” in our own acts of
                narration (2)? </p>
                    
            <p>The essays that follow record various answers to these collective
                questions. Three of the original speakers at the panel (Frances Botkin, Sean Gordon
                and Patricia A. Matthew) have contributed essays to this collection. Although
                Kimberly Juanita Brown was not able to engage in this iteration of the conversation,
                the impact of her contributions to the panel in a talk on nonetheless remain. We are
                also pleased that the final collection contains essays by participants who were at
                different stages in their university careers at the time of the event: Sean Gordon
                was a graduate student at UMass Amherst at the time of his original contribution to
                the panel, and Nick Blaisdell, now an high-school teacher, adjunct professor, and
                activist, was an undergraduate when he attended our seminar. As the project
                continued, we also decided to gesture towards the shared frame of reference in the
                room that the <hi rend="italic">Global Cultures</hi> seminar had produced, by
                inviting other participants to join the conversation about pedagogy via the medium
                of print. Ivan Ortiz and Elizabeth Fay, who had spoken in our series, graciously
                accepted our invitation. We are also grateful to Debbie Lee and Alan Richardson for
                agreeing to offer responses to the collection. Eighteen years after they worked
                together on the pioneering anthology <hi rend="italic">Early Black British Writing
                </hi>(2003), Lee and Richardson not only offer a retrospective view of the shared
                insights of this collection, but also of the changes that have occurred in the field
                since 2003.</p>
                    
            <p>The genre of writing we asked contributors to engage in as their
                arguments took shape—something between argumentative prose, critical history,
                personal narrative, and a practical guide—is one that we are rarely asked to engage
                in as academics, and we thank the editors of the <hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles
                    Pedagogies</hi> for the room they have made within the field for this kind of
                reflection. Following the work of exemplary scholars and educators such as Paolo
                Freire, Stuart Hall, bell hooks, and Edward Said, we are humbled by the task of
                approaching alongside our contributors the question of how our teaching and
                scholarship can contribute to the advancement of restorative justice in a global
                community where division and injustice towards those structurally submitted to
                exclusionary regimes is increasing due to the fallout from Covid 19, economic
                agendas that put profit over people, climate change, and geopolitical conflict
                around the globe. As Hall sagely anticipated in his seminal “Teaching Race”
                (1980):
            <quote>The really crucial question is how do you begin to make that move away from the level
                of prejudice and belief? One needs to undermine the obvious. One has to show that
                these are social and historical processes and that they are not written in the
                stars, they are not handed down. They are deep conditions which are not going to
                change if we start tinkering around with them. We must not give our students that
                kind of illusion. We can however begin the process of questioning what the
                structures are and how they work. (127)</quote>
                
            This collection enters into the spirit of “beginning the process of questioning” with
                the awareness that there are many more questions to be asked than can be answered in
                one special issue, and the hopes that new work by colleagues and students will
                continue to urgently ask them. Because it has arisen out of a call for colleagues
                within a particular geographically-defined network to describe to us what they were
                already teaching, rather than from an open call for work about the future of our
                field at large, we cannot make claims for coverage. We regret that no essays address
                Romantic anti-slavery literatures from Latin America, Brazil, Africa, Asia, or
                Australia, or work with Indigenous literatures, translation or multilingualism. We
                also regret that there is no essay here that addresses in detail the question of how
                to teach the Haitian Revolution, which is clearly foundational in the study of
                anti-slavery in the Romantic period. As Nick Nessbit writes in his new work drawing
                on Marx, it brings labor to the forefront and its connection to Hegelian historical
                    realization.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See Nick Nesbitt, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Price of Slavery: Capitalism and Revolution in the
                        Caribbean, </hi>Virgina: University of Virginia Press, 2022. For a
                    consideration of labor in the current moment, see Toure Reed, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Toward Freedom: The Case Against Race Reductionism</hi>, London: Verso,
                    2020. </note> We wish to emphasize that this collection emerges from a request
                that our colleagues share with us what they had already been teaching in their
                classrooms in 2018, rather than a call to re-envision the field in 2021. It is our
                sincere hope that this reflective exercise, and the unanswered questions that the
                collection prompts, become springboards for further inquiry. As the discourse of
                anti-racist approaches to teaching literature of the Romantic period continues to
                broaden, we hope this collection—a record of one localized conversation—will be a
                prompt to further discussion.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>III. Beyond diversifying the canon</head>
            <p>Before we begin to describe in detail the interventions that the contributors to this
                collection make, a brief review of the texts available for teaching the topic of
                anti-slavery literature, as well as the history of its anthologization, may be
                useful to those planning to embark on teaching it for the first time, as well as to
                those wishing to think further about the relationship between how developments in
                research relate to those in their own pedagogy. Indeed, a commitment to the
                continued and critical self-examination of genealogies of primary and secondary
                texts about anti-slavery literature is one that the current moment necessitates.
                Scholars have long been engaged in the struggle to bring this material into
                classrooms. Thus, for example, Eva B. Dykes, whose work, as Bakary Diaby has pointed
                out, should be reasessed, was the earliest critic to call for an expansion of the
                Romantic canon to include anti-slavery writings (Diaby “Black Women”). Her
                groundbreaking <hi rend="italic">The Negro in English Romantic Thought: Or a Study
                    of Sympathy for the Oppressed </hi>(1942), written in the midst of the Harlem
                Renaissance and also at the height of Jim Crow segregation in the United States,
                drew attention to names such as Olaudah Equiano, Ignatius Sancho, Ottobah Cugoano,
                and Mary Prince, not yet present in any anthologies of Romantic-era literature. The
                reassessment of Dyke’s work seems particularly necessary when one notes that a
                forty-year silence passed between her study in 1942 and 1985, when Charles T. Davis
                and Henry Louis Gates Jr. published their pivotal anthology <hi rend="italic">The
                    Slave’s Narrative </hi>(1985), which printed excerpts from Equiano, Cugoano,
                Sancho and James Alberst Ukawsaw Gronniosaw, among others.</p>
                    
            <p>It was not until the 1990s that access to anti-slavery literature became more
                widespread. Inspired both by the historicist and postcolonial turn in Romantic-era
                scholarship, scholars in the United States and Britain worked to incorporate Black
                Atlantic authors into the Anglo-American canon throughout this period.<note
                    place="foot" resp="author"> In Romantic Studies of the 1990s, Alan
                    Richardson and Sonia Hofkosh’s <hi rend="italic">Romanticism, Race, and Imperial
                        Culture</hi> (1996) responded to the work of scholars such as Mary Louise
                    Pratt in <hi rend="italic">Imperial Eyes: Travel Writing and
                        Transculturation</hi> (1992), Moira Ferguson in <hi rend="italic">Subject to
                        Others: British Women Writers an Colonial Slavery: 1670-1834 </hi>(1992),
                    and Paul Gilroy’s <hi rend="italic">The Black Atlantic: Modernity and Double
                        Consciousness</hi> (1993), which exposed how colonialism, enslavement and
                    resistance to it were intimately bound with the modernity that writers imagined
                    in the wake of Said’s <hi rend="italic">Orientalism</hi> (1978).</note> Several
                classroom anthologies focusing on Black British writers appeared in this
                transformational decade, including <hi rend="italic">Black British Writers,</hi>
                1760-1890 (1991), eds. Paul Edwards and David Dabydeen; <hi rend="italic">Black
                    Atlantic Writers of the Eighteenth Century: Living the New Exodus in England and
                    the Americas</hi> (1995), eds. Adam Potkay and Sandra Burr; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Unchained Voices: An Anthology of Black Authors in the English-Speaking World
                    of the Eighteenth Century</hi>, ed. Vincent Caretta (1996); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pioneers of the Black Atlantic: Five Slave Narratives,</hi> 1772-1815, (1998),
                eds. Henry Louis Gates Jr. and William L. Andrews. Anne Mellor and Richard Matlak
                were the first editors of a broader anthology to grant a section to “Slavery, the
                Slave Trade, and Abolition in Britain” when they included it in their <hi
                    rend="italic">British Literature, 1780-1830</hi> (1996).</p>
                    
            <p>The scholarly recovery of Romanticism’s implication in the struggle
                for abolition and anti-slavery was also enormously facilitated by the publication of
                Pickering and Chatto’s seven-volume <hi rend="italic">Slavery, Abolition, and
                    Emancipation: Writings in the British Romantic Period,</hi> edited by Peter J.
                Kitson and Debbie Lee (1999). Following from this, James G. Basker’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Amazing Grace: An Anthology of Poems About Slavery, 1660-1810</hi>
                (2002), Marcus Wood’s <ref
                    target="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Poetry-Slavery-Anglo-American-Anthology-1764-1866/dp/0198187084/ref=sr_1_2?dchild=1&amp;keywords=marcus+wood+poems+slavery&amp;qid=1600531339&amp;s=books&amp;sr=1-2"
                        ><hi rend="italic">The Poetry of Slavery: An Anglo-American Anthology
                        1764-1866</hi></ref>(2003), <hi rend="italic">Early
                    Black British Writing</hi> (2003), eds. Debbie Lee and Alan Richardson, and <hi
                    rend="italic">Transatlantic Romanticism</hi> (2006), eds. Lance Newman, Joel
                Pace, and Chris Koenig-Woodward, also made anti-slavery texts more accessible than
                they had previously been. The republication of various novels that pertain to this
                topic has also changed students’ classroom experiences (for instance, many of our
                colleagues now use the Broadview edition of the anonymous <hi rend="italic">The
                    Woman of Colour</hi> (2008), ed Lyndon J. Dominique). Since it is not possible
                to anthologize novels in the same way as other texts, A.A. Markley’s overview of
                lesser-taught novels and plays is a useful resource for those wishing to teach
                novels that deal with the topic of slavery.<note place="foot" resp="author"> For instance, Markley suggests that Anna Maria
                        Mackenzie’s <hi rend="italic">Slavery: Or, The Times</hi> (1792) and Amelia
                        Opie’s <hi rend="italic">Adeline Mowbray</hi> (1804) offer “a rare view of
                        an African character’s experience of late eighteenth-century England” (para
                        15), and that Charlotte Smith’s “The Story of Henrietta,” in the second
                        volume of <hi rend="italic">The Letters of a Solitary Wanderer</hi>
                        (1800)...takes readers into the heart of plantation life in Jamaica and into
                        the midst of an uprising” (para. 22).</note> Following C.L.R. James’
                    <hi rend="italic">The Black Jacobins </hi>(1938), another foundational work for
                the study of anti-slavery literatures in the Romantic period, a growing body of
                scholarship on the Haitian Revolution and the revolutionary aesthetics of the period
                has also led to an increased access to classroom texts. We note, for example, the
                publication of Marcus Rainsford’s <hi rend="italic">An Historical Account of the
                    Black Empire of Hayti, </hi>eds. Paul Youngquist and Grégory Pierrot (Duke
                University Press, 2013),<note place="foot" resp="author"> For
                        more recent scholarship on the Haitian Revolution, see Scott (2004); Nesbitt
                        (2008); Morss (2009); Ferrer (2014), and Pierrot (2019).</note> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Poetry of Haitian Independence, </hi>eds Doris Kadish and Deborah
                Jensen (Yale University Press, 2015), which collects many neglected poems written
                between 1804 and the 1840s.<note place="foot" resp="author"> For a discussion
                    of many of these poems, see Martin Munro, “Listening to 19th-century Haitian
                    poetry” in <hi rend="italic">Sounds Senses, </hi>ed. yasser elhariry, Liverpool
                    University Press (2021).</note></p>
                    
            <p>The critical conversation has continued to grow alongside this editorial work, and
                has been nurtured by the interdisciplinary contact zones of Black Studies, African
                American Studies, Atlantic Studies, American Studies, Indigenous Studies, Caribbean
                Studies, History and Anthropology. We offer, in the bibliography to this
                introduction, a preliminary list of important contributions to this conversation, as
                an access point for further research and future pedagogical innovation.<note place="foot" resp="author"> In addition to Dykes, the
                        following texts, listed chronoglically, offer important contributions: David
                        (1975); Barker (1978); Fryer (1984); Costanzo (1986; 1987; 1993); Baum
                        (1994); Richardson and Hofkosh (1996); Doyle (1996); Caretta (1996, 2001);
                        Machow (1996); Thomas (1997); Aravamudan (1998); Makdisi (1998); Fulford and
                        Kitson (1998); Richardson (1999); Bewell (1999); Mellor (1999); Thomas
                        (2000); Linebaugh and Rediker (2000); Wood (2000; 2002); Sussman (2000);
                        McBride (2001); Colley (2002); Lee (2002); Ramey (2004); Coleman (2005);
                        Richardson and Lee (2003); Nussbaum (2003); Sharpe (2003); Carey, Ellis and
                        Salih (2004); Carey (2005); Coleman (2005); Baucom (2005); Fulford and
                        Kitson (2005); Carey, Kitson, and Wood (2007); Rezek (2007); Matthew (2008);
                        Fulford, Lee, Kitson (2010); Youngquist and Botkin (2011); Aljoe (2012;
                        2018); Younguist (2013; 2017); Ross (2013); Botkin (2017); Chander (2017;
                        2020); Sandler (2017; 2020); Chander and Matthew (2018); Hessell (2018);
                        Pierrot (2019); Bewell (2020); Pace (2020); Diaby (2019; 2020); Sinanan
                        (2020); Hanson (2020);Nielsen; 2020; Annette K. Joseph-Gabriel (2020),
                        Olivette Otele (2020).</note> Although there is not space here to give
                a full account of the scholarly literature in this period, we note that our
                respondents, Debbie Lee and Alan Richardson, not only played key scholarly roles in
                producing anthologies of these literatures, but also helped to define the critical
                conversation over the past two decades. Alan Richardson's seminal “Romantic Voodoo:
                Obeah and British Culture, 1797-1807” (1993) opened the field to Afro-British
                intertexts in the archive, those within textuality and beyond. Debbie Lee’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Slavery and the Romantic Imagination</hi> (2002) is a fundamental
                text in any survey of this corpus. When considering developments in the field, it is
                also important to note that, more recently, the “Bigger Six Collective” has been
                formed in order to resist the narrative that, as they put it, “diversification” or
                “going global” has done enough to change the field: instead, they have called for
                the need “to make our field in the image of those whose access to Romanticism has
                long been and continues to be actively restricted.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> See “Coda: From Coteries to Collectives” (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Symbiosis</hi> 23.1), 140. </note></p>
                    
            <p> Anti-slavery literatures—even aside from the larger and more neglected topic of race
                and Romanticism—still occupy a marginal position in the undergraduate curriculum.
                Despite the efforts of many scholars to join in the work of recovery and to redress
                the biases of twentieth-century criticism and editing of Romantic texts, the topic of “slavery and abolition” is still frequently
                framed as an additionto the anthologies that undergraduate
                    classes rely on, as well as in syllabi themselves.<note place="foot" resp="author"> James Basker calls abolitionist verse a “shadow canon,” in
                    the introduction to<hi rend="italic">Amazing Grace: An Anthology of Poems about
                        Slavery, 1660-1810 </hi>(2005). “In the latest
                    edition of <hi rend="italic">The Norton Anthology of Poetry,</hi> only six poems
                    coincide with those collected” in his anthology, he notes (xlii). </note>
                Digital searches of databases of online syllabi suggest that a handful of texts,
                especially in surveys of the period, are being asked to carry a heavy freight. Many
                and varied obstacles have been put in the way of affirming the contributions of
                Black and Brown writers from the period in the classroom. The presence of Mary Seacole and Ulawsaw Gronniosaw in anthologies of Black
                    British writers (for instance), does not guarantee them a place on syllabi;
                    neither do the names of African-American writers such as Jupiter Hammon or
                John Marrant, or Plácido and Juan Manzano from the Hispanophone Atlantic, appear
                very often on syllabi. In “Abolitionist Interruptions,” Patricia Matthew and Manu
                Samriti Chander note their “shared frustration with how Olaudah Equiano and his <hi
                    rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi> have served too long as the single
                abolitionist/anti-slavery text in Romanticism” (Chander and Matthew, 431); a
                discussion Matthew extends in her essay below. The tradition that has elided
                subjects who historically were denied ontological value, and who were silenced
                through enslavement and racism in the economic and geopolitical system that was
                Atlantic Slavery, can still be observed today in this disconnect between research
                and pedagogy.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head>IV. Contrapuntal Reading</head>
                    
            <p>Beyond simply adding texts to established syllabi, then, the contributors in this
                collection imagine many different ways to center the question of how to disrupt
                pedagogical traditions that have been handed down from past generations of
                scholars.These scholars invite readers to examine the degree to which their own
                pedagogy reflects transformations in the field, even as they push for further
                re-examination of the structures that pedagogical attitudes to teaching anti-slavery
                have previously been built on. Our contributors tend to agree that because Romantic
                era accounts of slavery were conditioned by the period in which they were written,
                it’s “not enough,” as Frances Botkin puts it, to ask them to speak on behalf of the
                enslaved without other sources to contextualize them. Dykes poignantly draws
                attention to this paradox at the center of Romantic anti-slavery literature in the
                opening pages of her text. “One of the salient features of the ‘Romantic Movement’
                of the latter eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries was the love of freedom”
                (1), she writes, paying tribute to Mary Prince’s famous line, “To be free is very
                sweet” (27). However, she then immediately notes that Romantic writers could also be
                “limited… by an adherence to traditional forms and conventions” (1), and notes that
                anti-slavery writings did not always depose the hierarchical structure and racism
                that authorized the triangular trade in the first place. Many scholars since Dykes
                have complicated any simple celebration of the expansion of the Romantic canon to
                include anti-slavery texts by exploring the capacity of these texts to sometimes
                “popularize and codify racial prejudice,” despite their ethical and civic
                commitments to breaking the Blakean “mind forg’d manacles” that sustained Atlantic
                Slavery (Lee and Richardson 7), and the contributors to this collection extend this
                project.</p>
                    
            <p>It has been intriguing for us to see that the authors in this collection have arrived
                at a shared methodology regarding how to approach teaching anti-slavery literatures
                today organically, without a prompt from us and without reading drafts of each
                others’ essays. Many of them reframe and resituate eighteenth- and nineteenth-century texts in new
                constellations, not only in relation to each other and to art and artefacts from the
                period, but also in relation to texts from Black Studies, and to twentieth and
                twenty-first works of fiction and critical fabulation that seek to address the
                silences of the past. In their commitment to this method, several contributors
                implicitly employ contrapuntal reading, a method that since Fernando Ortiz's <hi
                    rend="italic">Contrapunteo cubano del tabaco y el azúcar</hi> (1944) and Edward
                Said’s <hi rend="italic">Culture and Imperialism</hi> (1993), who independently of
                each other advanced the method, has influenced the work of writers like Cuban
                novelist Alejo Carpentier and critics such as Mary Louise Pratt and Simon
                Gikandi.</p>
                    
            <p> In the Anglo-American Academy, readers may be familiar with how Said theorizes the
                importance of reading “not univocally but contrapuntally, with an awareness both of
                the metropolitan history that is narrated and of those other histories against which
                (and together with which) the dominating discourse acts” (Said 51). Drawing on music
                to describe a form of attention to reading novels such as Austen’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mansfield Park</hi>, he writes:
                
            <quote>In the counterpoint of classical music, various themes play off one another, with
                only a provisional privilege being given to any particular one; yet in the resulting
                polyphony there is concert and order, an organized interplay that derives from the
                themes, not from a rigorous melodic or formal principle outside of the work. In the
                same way, I believe, we can read and interpret English novels, for example, whose
                engagement (usually suppressed for the most part) with the West Indies or India,
                say, is shaped and perhaps even determined by the specific history of colonization,
                resistance, and finally native nationalism. (51)</quote>
                
            While Said's archive was “English novels,” Fernando Ortiz applied “contrapunteo” in
                his anthropological analysis of sugar and tobacco written fifty years prior to
                Said’s work, and in which he coined the word “transculturación”— transculturation—by
                now familiar to critics through the work of Mary Louise Pratt. It should be noted
                that Ortiz and his generation, which included Lydia Cabrera, the renown scholar of
                    <hi rend="italic">santería</hi>, and Alejo Carpentier, who turned to the Haitian
                Revolution for inspiration, embarked on a reassessment of the contributions of
                AfroCuban and African cultures to Cuban identity. Ortiz emphasizes the musical roots
                of counterpoint at the same time that he undercores the AfroCuban experience, one
                that incorporates both music <hi rend="italic">and</hi> the orality of verse in call
                and response rituals between griot and the audience. “Recordemos en Cuba sus
                manifestaciones más floridas en las preces antifonarias de las liturgias, así de
                blancos como de negros, en la controvertida erótica y danzarina de la rumba, y en
                los contrapunteos versificados de la guajirada montuna y de la currería afrocubana"
                (F. Ortiz 18). [Let us remember the elaborate manifestations [of counterpoint] in
                Cuba, whether in the antiphonal liturgies of Blacks and whites, in the controversial
                erotics of the movement of the rumba, and in the versified counterpoints in country
                and Afrocuban peoples]. In his novel about the Haitian Revolution, <hi rend="italic"
                    >El siglo de las luces</hi> (1962), Carpentier develops the aesthetics of the
                    “<hi rend="italic">arbitrario contrapunto</hi>” (“the arbitrary counterpoint”)
                by considering the different, yet simultaneous unfolding of the lives of his
                protagonists (47), which shape and impact individual spheres of action as well as
                the grand récit of history. Carpentier later extends in his essay about "lo real
                maravilloso," the marvellous real, where he again returns to the Haitian Revolution,
                Henri Cristophe’s opposition to Napoleon, and Mackandal, "que hace creer a millares
                y millares de esclavos en Haití ... que puede transformarse en lo que quiera, y
                promueve con ellos una de las primeras revoluciones auténticas del Nuevo Mundo"
                [Mackandal, who convinces thousands and thousands of slaves in Haiti ... that he can
                turn into anything, and promotes with them one of the first authentic revolutions of
                the New World] (Carpentier 132).</p>
                    
            <p> Simon Gikandi further develops the contrapuntal method when he applies it to reading
                the archive of Atlantic slavery and anti-slavery in <hi rend="italic">Slavery and
                    the Culture of Taste </hi>(2011).<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    Gikandi, xiii.</note> Gikandi synchronizes the spatial, temporal, and interior
                dimensions of the lives of subjects as apparently disconnected as diarist Anna
                Larpent and Nealee, the enslaved woman in Mungo Park’s narrative. In other chapters,
                he considers texts by Francis Williams, Hume and Olaudah Equiano; Phillis Wheatley,
                William Beckford, and Thomas Jefferson (among others) in contrapuntal relationship
                to each other. Gikandi accounts for how “the criteria driving the aesthetic ideology
                in the eighteenth century—disinterest and virtue, among others—had come to be
                haunted by slavery” (Gikandi 144). The effect of this more deliberate counterpoint
                is to ensure “a dialectic between the visible subjects of modernity and its
                invisible actors” (70), as he writes. Exegesis as an act of resistance exposes the
                symbolic systems that mediate materiality, disturbing the cognitive and symbolic
                separations between the violent system of the plantation secured through empire, and
                the well-wrought tea set of the drawing room, holding actors accountable for their
                complicity with such violence.</p>
                    
            <p>Patricia A. Matthew draws attention to how her students themselves implicitly enacted
                a contrapuntal method when they responded to the suppressed context of William
                Blake’s “The Little Black Boy” in a class in 2006. Her essay offers a retrospective
                account of howthis moment offered an invitationto continue to explore, in several
                different settings (both undergraduate and graduate),the effects of centering the
                topic of race and slavery in the classroom. Matthew invites makers of syllabi to
                look beyond the question of which single texts to use in a self-contained “unit” of
                a syllabus on slavery, to instead imagine how Romanticism looks whenone centers
                “race, abolition and freedom” on the level of the syllabus as a whole. The essay
                criticizes the idea that one can simply add a single text about slavery to a
                syllabus and expect that the topic has been covered, as if a Romantic literature
                syllabus is a familiar recipe one can add a new ingredient to. Rather than
                focusing a discussion about Atlantic slavery on a single text in a syllabus, Matthew
                argues, it should be considered a relevant context in discussions of all Romantic
                texts, even in texts where it seems not to be present. Matthew describes two different courses
                which center anti-slavery literatures and texts about race, including detailed
                discussions ofteaching Blake’s poem, Hannah More and Eaglesfield Smith’s “The
                Sorrows of Yamba,” Amelia Opie’s “The Black Man’s Lament; or, How to Make Sugar,”
                Coleridge’s 1795 lecture “On the Slave Trade,” and the anonymous <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Woman of Colour, A Tale, A Novel</hi>(1808). Ivan
                Ortiz’ method can also be called contrapuntal, from several perspectives. Ortiz puts
                Said’s argument about the silences in Austen’s <hi rend="italic">Mansfield Park</hi>
                (1814) in dialogue with Lynn Festa’s argument that Austen is also asking readers to
                listen for “noise.” Ortiz begins by explaining how he uses this principle of
                “listening for noise” as a method to teach abolition poetry written by white
                authors. He positions this poetry in counterpoint with music, when he asks students
                to examine the complexity of a situation in which both Hannah More’s version of “The
                Sorrows of Yamba” and William Cowper’s “The Negro’s Complaint” were sung to the
                well-known ballad “Admiral Hosier’s Ghost,” a tune about white English sailors who
                had died at sea. He then turns to a text that could be called contrapuntal in
                itself; M. NourbeSe Philip’s <hi rend="italic">Zong!</hi> (2008), which is “composed
                entirely from the words of the case report, <hi rend="italic">Gregson vs.
                    Gilbert,</hi> related to the murder of Africans on board a slave ship at the end
                of the eighteenth century.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    <ref target="www.nourbese.com/poetry/zong-3">Zong 3</ref></note> As students center their attention on the
                silences that this text exposes, they are confronted with the question of “what the
                fragmentation of language accomplishes that a ballad narrative cannot.”</p>
                    
            <p>Sean Gordon also extends the contrapuntal method beyond the frame of synchronicity,
                to ask how twentieth-century narratives might also inform students’ understandings
                of nineteenth-century testimonies. He describes the project of “teaching
                contemporary texts that take up Romantic-era concepts in a speculative framework,”
                like Celu Amberstone’s “Refugees” (2004), Octavia Butler’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bloodchild and Other Stories </hi>(1995/2005), and Samuel Delany’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Empire Star </hi>(1966), in relation to Olaudah Equiano’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi>. To frame his discussion of what it
                meant to discuss these texts on a campus responding to a series of violently racist
                incidents in 2014, Gordon centers Fred Moten’s term “dehiscence” (which describes a
                form of structural vulnerability that allows for productive disordering), as well as
                the Afropessimism of Frank Wilderson, pointing toward another speculative future, in
                which a conversation between scholars of Black Studies and scholars of Romanticism
                will become more common. He also discusses how teaching Mat Johnson’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Pym</hi> (2011) in dialogue with Edgar Allan Poe’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Narrative of Arthur Gordon Pym</hi> (1838) allowed students to
                think through the issue of how structures of white privilege are implicit not only
                in the archive, but in the university itself.</p>
                    
            <p>Afrofuturism provides a site of conceptual resistance in several of the essays here.
                Leading sociologist Alondra Nelson defines Afrofuturism as a mode which uplifts
                “‘African American voices’ with ‘other stories to tell about culture, technology and
                things to come,’” and often concerns “sci-fi imagery, futurist themes, and
                technological innovation in the African diaspora” (9). Through her syllabus and
                classroom discussion, Elizabeth Fay stages an innovative conversation between
                Afrofuturism, Romanticism, and Atlantic Studies that juxtaposes past and present
                narratives of the legacies of enslavement, and challenges students to reinterpret
                Atlantic history by engaging “future history imagined” (13). When Fay asks students
                to compare Olaudah Equiano’s narrative with the film <hi rend="italic">Black Panther
                </hi>(2018), and contextualizes this question in relation to N.K. Jemisin’s
                introduction Afrofuturism in “How Long ’til Black Future Month?,” she extends the
                possibilities for the interpretation of “geographical space, conceptual space, and
                textual space” (Dillon 31) in Black Atlantic narratives.</p>
                    
            <p>In the broader sweep of her article, Fay emphasizes “the fluid movement of dynamic
                relationality among multiple, and variable subjects” as she explores various
                exercises designed to ask students to triangulate narratives of enslavement and
                post-enslavement. For instance, Fay asks students to consider how Mary Prince’s
                nineteenth-century rhetorics of suffering and resistance compare with those of
                Equiano, and then further complicates the question by asking them to read the
                rhetoric of Toussaint L’Ouverture’s letters in relation to C.L.R. James’ account of
                his life in <hi rend="italic">Black Jacobins</hi>. (Sylvia Wynter’s article on
                C.L.R. James, “Beyond the Categories of the Master Conception,” also offers students
                an argument about how James’ work helps to posit a theory of “becoming Black” which
                is relevant “whether the year is 1800 or 2021.”) In another unit of the syllabus,
                Fay triangulates Lenora Sansay’s <hi rend="italic">Secret History; or the Horrors of
                    St. Domingo </hi>(1808) and the anonymous <hi rend="italic">The Woman of Colour
                </hi>(1808) with Austen’s <hi rend="italic">Mansfield Park </hi>(1814), as she asks
                students to compare fictionalized accounts of women’s experience in the period, and
                further contextualizes this exercise with references to the work of Christina Sharpe
                and Sylvia Wynter.</p>
                    
            <p>Frances Botkin also offers many possibilities for students to read contrapuntally
                when she insists that Romantic-era narratives cannot be taught without a serious
                commitment to contextualization. Through a theorization of the practice of <hi
                    rend="italic">tunyuhan,</hi> Botkin uses what she terms an “undisciplined mode
                of assembly” to consider the value of generative improvisation in teaching, and how
                contemporary art, film, music and recordings of interviews with people in Jamaica
                “animate colonial textuality with the creative expressions of Afro-Caribbean culture
                that in revising the past, imagines and nourishes future worlds.” She describes, for
                instance, how she presents students with Lydia Maria Child’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Narrative of Joanna: An Emancipated Slave, of Suriname </hi>(1834) (a narrative
                extracted from John Gabriel Stedman’s <hi rend="italic">The Narrative of a Five
                    Years Expedition against the Revolted Negroes of Surinam</hi> [1796]), alongside
                John Earle’s <hi rend="italic">Obi; or the History of Three-Fingered Jack</hi>
                (1800), a painting of Three-Fingered Jack by the Jamaican painter Omari “Afrikan”
                Ra, and a documentary film by Roy Anderson called <hi rend="italic">Queen Nanny:
                    Legendary Maroon Chieftainess </hi>(2015); a constellation which allows students
                to see how “Child almost entirely excludes the Maroons with whom Joanna had family
                connections.” When she asks students to read Mary Prince’s <hi rend="italic">The
                    History of Mary Prince, A West Indian Slave </hi>(1831) alongside Marlon James’
                    <hi rend="italic">The Book of Night Women</hi> (2009), she puts further pressure
                on the question of what nineteenth-century writers do not say about the experiences
                of enslaved people, and particularly of enslaved women.</p>
                    
            <p>Another way in which the dialogic space can be transformed to create an anti-racist
                classroom is through the acknowledgment of the tension between writing and speech,
                foregrounding for students the incomplete nature of the anti-slavery archive. In her
                focus on “doing the work” of travelling to Jamaica in order to better understand
                Maroon history, Botkin brings centers the notion of orality in order to problematize
                the hierarchy of knowledge that privileges the archive. Her field work and
                connection to Maroon leader Gaa’ma Gloria Simms has enabled her to create a contact
                zone in the classroom where the oral histories of Afro-Caribbean descendants of
                Maroon communities expose asymmetries of power and the injustices encoded as silence
                in the written record. The conference in Jamaica which she co-organizes with Paul
                Youngquist reconfigure the spaces and possibilities of knowledge for Romanticists
                which brings the “archive” into conversation with living indigenous knowledge.</p>
                    
            <p>Nicholas Blaisdell elucidates how countepoint as exegesis
                awakens agency, as Carpentier also discovered in <hi rend="italic">El siglo de las
                    luces</hi>, when Sofía, one of his protagonists, urges, "¡Hay que hacer algo!"
                [Something must be done] (410). Blaisdell explores how anti-slavery writers like
                Cugoano indicte capitalism's use of enslaved labor in the 19th century as a global
                system, anticipating the system's accomodation of unfree labor through the present
                era. Drawing on Freire, he reflects on how study of anti-slavery texts, abolitionist
                networks, and Marx informed his development as a social justice activist and
                organizer of Black Lives Matter Protests in Peabody, Massachusetts, his work as a
                high school teacher and Adjunct Professor of education. His analysis illuminates how
                a Freirean pedagogy can translate into greater empowerment for students in
                educational and civic settings.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head>V. Some Future Directions</head>
              
            <p>The project of articulating linkages that connect the teaching praxis of Romanticists
                with histories of resistance, liberation, struggles against slavery, and the
                oppression of people of color, goes far beyond the purview of a single special
                issue, and so we wish to close by noting some of the areas for pedagogical inquiry
                that our contributors have opened vistas onto. We hope that the pedagogical
                experiments detailed in this collection will be useful in practical terms, as a
                guide for those teaching in universities in how to begin to redesign their own
                syllabi and classroom discussions. The larger aim, however, is for the collection to
                be useful in broader methodological terms, as a prompt for readers to imagine their
                own contrapuntal arrangements of texts and voices. The possibilities for new
                contrapuntal readings and new constellations of texts go far beyond the specific
                texts or arrangements listed in these case studies.</p>
                    
            <p> Many of our contributors use specific examples to describe a method that could be
                applied to various texts. The example Patricia A. Matthew gives, for example, of
                what it means to read Blake’s work in dialogue with anti-slavery literatures,
                encourages pedagogues to look more closely at how texts they have taught without
                reference to the history of slavery might change when this context is brought to
                bear. Similarly, Sean Gordon and Elizabeth Fay’s references to Afrofuturist texts
                invite readers to conduct their own research in this field, and to imagine their own
                conversations between the past and speculative futures. Another question that
                emerges from this focus on Afrofuturism is whether there might be room for more
                opportunites for students to encounter examples of Black resistance, humour, joy,
                and agency in the Romantic classroom. New possibilities for dialogue with
                contemporary texts will continue to arise as new works of critical fabulation appear
                (even during the time we have been editing this collection, for instance, many of
                our colleagues have begun to teach Honorée Fanonne Jeffers’ <hi rend="italic">The
                    Age of Phillis </hi>[2020,]).<note place="foot" resp="author"> In the
                    British Museum’s event “An Era of Reclamation | Beyond Bridgerton,” also
                    recorded online, participants questioned the effects of the erasure of the
                    history of slavery. 
                    (<ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=P_fqH2t0x1U">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=P_fqH2t0x1U"</ref>)</note></p>
                    
            <p>Our work on this collecton has prompted us to imagine several future topics for <hi
                    rend="italic">Romantic Circles Pedagogies </hi>collections on how to engage
                anti-slavery literatures in the classroom, which we would be pleased to see
                responses to. While our contributors engage the question of affect in passing, for
                instance, our field would benefit from a more sustained conversation about how to
                acknowledge the range of emotions that the learning process might bring up in
                classes that consider the history of slavery. From another perspective, both Botkin
                and Ortiz encourage attention to the aural dimension of textuality and its silences,
                which reveals how orality and the epistemologies it transmits is also major
                component of the anti-slavery archive which could also be engaged further. Becoming
                aware of the limitations that govern the textual archive<hi rend="italic">as
                    text</hi> with attention to the conditions of its production will allow for the
                introduction of approaches with which Romanticists are familiar, such historicist,
                post-structuralist, feminist, postcolonial, and neoformalist methodologies.</p>
                    
            <p>The essays here also enjoin readers to consider important questions that remain on
                the horizon of this collection, about how far discussions of anti-slavery texts have
                been made to stand in for larger discussions about race in the Romantic period, and
                how this tendency might be addressed in the future. This connects the work of the
                collection with Marlon B. Ross’s call to “shift the focus momentarily away from the
                important question of Romanticism’s self-conscious investment in or diversion from
                slavery and colonialism to consider <hi rend="italic">race</hi> itself as an economy
                of gut-instinctual, sensperceptual, socialpsychological, aesthetic-ideological, and
                geopolitical commitments” in his essay “The Race of/in Romanticism: Notes Toward a
                Critical Race Theory,” (26). As Bakary Diaby argues, “we must continue working on
                slavery, but we should not let it be our only engagement with, again, the deeply
                quotidian, socio-personal ordering of the world we inhabit and have inherited from
                the long Romantic period” (“Black Women” 252). Diaby himself offers a rare example
                of what it means to bring the topic of race to bear on texts that have not
                traditionally been grouped under the heading of texts that address the topic of race
                in the Romantic period in his reading of Wordworth's “We Are Seven” (“Counting the
                Bodies”). Although several of our authors encourage a more open dialogue between
                Black Studies and Romanticism, a more widespread and sustained dialogue between
                Romantic literature and critical race theory is clearly necessary in the field at
                large.</p>
                    
            <p>We also wish to note that several conversations on the subject of antiracist pedagogy
                have begun since we first edited these essays and drafted a version of this
                introduction in 2019, which multipy the possibilities for possible future
                pedagogical directions, as the relationship between a commitment to anti-racism and
                teaching anti-slavery texts is nuanced further. In Fall 2020, Tita Chico convened a
                series on “Antiracism: Research, Teaching, Public Engagement” which includes several
                talks by colleagues in our field. The series is ongoing, can be accessed online, and
                constitutes a rich pedagogical resource.<note place="foot" resp="author"> The
                    series is hosted by University of Maryland’s Center for Literary and Comparative
                    Studies: “<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10509585.2020.1747687"
                        >https://english.umd.edu/research-innovation/clcs/antiracism-series</ref></note>
                Shelby Johnson, Brigitte Fielder, and Kerry Sinanan, also spoke at a teach-in on
                “Race, Pedagogy and Whiteness in the Long 18C” that fall; a recording of this event
                is also available online.<note place="foot" resp="author"> The event was
                    sponsored by the Keats-Shelley Association, the University of Texas San Antonio
                    and Mills College: <ref
                        target="https://english.umd.edu/research-innovation/clcs/antiracism-series"
                        >https://k-saa.org/race_pedagogy_whiteness/</ref></note> Since many scholars
                who teach Romanticism also teach Victorian Studies, the recent call by Ronjaunee
                Chatterjee, Alicia J. Mireles Christoff and Amy Wong to “undiscipline” Victorian
                Studies also inflects the study of Romanticism.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See Ronjaunee Chatterjee, Alicia J. Mireles Christoff
                        and Amy Wong in “Undisciplining Victorian Studies,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Victorian Studies </hi>62.3.</note> In response, the Keats-Shelley
                Association of America posted online a virtual series of roundtables entitled
                “Toward an Anti-Racist, ‘Undisciplined’ Romanticism” (December 2020).<note
                     place="foot" resp="author">
                    <ref target="https://k-saa.org/k-saa-virtual-roundtable-toward-an-anti-racist-undisciplined-romanticism/">Virtual Roundtable</ref></note>
                These conversations both look toward this larger topic of race and romanticism, and
                aid the project of teaching anti-slavery literatures. In Spring 2021, Patricia A.
                Matthew hosted a series on Race, Blackness and Romanticism for the Boston Area
                Romantic Colloquium: we eagerly await the special issue she is editing on this topic
                for <hi rend="italic">Studies in Romanticism</hi>.
                <note place="foot" resp="author"><ref target="https://sites.bu.edu/barc/dialogues/">Dialogues</ref></note> 
                The Black Studies and Romanticism Virtual Conference held online in June 2021, organized by Kate Singer at
                Mount Holyoke College, was also a nexus for online exchange at a moment when
                in-person conversations were not possible.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    <ref target="https://commons.mtholyoke.edu/blsandr/">Holy Oke</ref></note></p>
                    
            <p> In an era when zoom makes possible new kinds of collaboration, geographical distance
                has become less of an obstacle to conversation since we began working on these
                questions, but the field of Romanticism, and especially studies of slavery in the
                Romantic period, still needs to do more to address the divisions it has historically
                instantiated between Anglophone texts and texts in other languages. The Anglophone
                focus of the authors examined throughout this collection points to multilingualism
                and Romanticism as a related area for future research as the plurilingual nature of
                the histories of African and indigenous resistance comes further into view. As
                Gillian Sankoff writes,
                
            <quote>It is difficult to conceive of another situation where people arrived with such a
                variety of native languages, where they were so cut off from their native language
                groups; where the size of no language group was enough to ensure its survival; where
                no second language was shared by enough people to serve as a useful vehicle of
                intercommunication; and where the legitimate [=official-RM] language was
                inaccessible to almost everyone. (qtd. in Mesthrie 230)</quote>
                
            For some of the writers in the archive of anti-slavery literatures, the process of
                translation into English and language acquisition was also a process of living
                through epistemic violence. Yet the governing assumption in Romantic era studies in
                approaching the anti-slavery archive is that the language of Black British authors
                is English (Almeida). A similar assumption governs the Indigenous archive, as Nikki
                Hessell shows in <hi rend="italic">Romantic Literature and the Colonised World:
                    Lessons from Indigenous Translations </hi>(2018). Hessell argues that Indigneous
                interpretations of canonical authors are more than “novelties, nor simple evidence
                of the global power and reach of Romantic literature” (229), but “simultaneous
                expressions of the value of Romantic literature and of the experience of
                colonization” (230). While some might respond that as scholars of British or
                American literature the field is Anglocentric by nature, this commitment to
                monolingualism out of habit robs the field of depth and breadth, since the African
                diaspora was not limited to English-speaking countries. During and even after the
                abolition of slavery in 1833, Britain continued to trade with the Global South, as
                scholars such as Rebecca Cole Heinowitz, Omar Miranda, César Soto, Juan Sánchez,
                Jesse Reeder, and Sara Medina Calzada show, while at the same time making greater
                imperial incursions in Africa and India. Even so, texts from this “second slavery,”
                as Dale Tomich has called it, have a belated entrance into Romanticism, such as Juan
                Manzano’s <hi rend="italic">The Life and Poems of a Cuban Slave</hi> (1840),
                translated by Richard Robert Madden, who also testified a trial that vindicated the
                rights of enslaved persons to rise up against their enslavers, and was one of the
                most international trials of its time: The Amistad. The
                    biography of the enslaved Brazilian, Mahommah Gardo Baquaqua (1848) is another
                    useful starting point for those wishing to expand their students’ reference
                    points beyond texts written in English (see Aljoe, “Testimonies” 111). Nicole
                    Aljoe also challenges “the marginal status of West Indian slave narratives
                within critical discourses of the slave narrative genre, Caribbean and Black
                Atlantic literary histories,” and reveals how Abolitionist groups in England, the
                United States, and the West Indies were in close contact with one another. <note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Nicole Aljoe,<hi rend="italic">Literary
                        Histories of the Early Anglophone Caribbean,</hi> 2.</note>
                 </p>
                    
            <p>Moreover, monolingualism, when assumed as a “natural state” prevents a true reckoning
                with how English functioned as a significant barrier for the millions of people who
                were deprived of access in British colonies, not only to literacy, but also to the
                judicial recognition of their oral testimony in colonial jurisdictions, further
                limiting access to “the legitimate language.”
                <note place="foot" resp="author"> In 1828, the law was ameliorated “to contemplate the
                        admission of the evidence of slaves, in those cases only in which they are
                        the actors or the sufferers, excluding their evidence in other cases.”
                            See<hi rend="italic">Slave Law of Jamaica,</hi> London: 1828
                        (216).</note> English in its oral and textual forms was therefore a
                second language for many formerly enslaved authors, from Phillis Wheatley to
                Ignatius Sancho and Cugoano. Acknowledging and considering that duality decenters
                the assumption of its naturality and the nationalist and imperialist underpinnings
                around the idea of English as the language of Romanticism, and disentangles it from
                the “metaphysical empires” of language that Ngũgĩ wa Thiong’o denounces
                (“Warscapes¨). The creolizations of English and other European languages in contact
                zones are also part of the Romantic aesthetic, as much as the standardization of
                these languages in this period.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See Andrew
                    Elfenbein, <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and the Rise of English.</hi> Stanford,
                    Stanford University Press, 2009.</note> In the United States, the question of
                accessibility is compounded by the disciplinary gateway of English as the privileged
                language of the corpus, for millions of its citizens speak languages other than
                English, which go unrecognized if Romanticism is configured as solely Anglocentric.
                As we reimagine community in the twenty-first century to create spaces of redress
                and also of transformation, Romanticist scholars must do more to invite students to
                imagine new contact zones, not only between canonical and non-canonical texts and
                between disciplines, but also between the past and the present; between history and
                historical fiction; between printed and living voices, and between linguistic
                communities whose ties between each other have been wilfully and violently
                erased.</p>
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Concluding Openly (or An Open Conclusion)</head>
               
            <p>The essays in this collection explore how recent history informs the way that
                students might currently receive Romantic texts, clearing a space for further
                discussion about how the conversation will continue to change the way that the
                Romantic texts signify. As scholars and teachers, becoming conscious of not only how
                pedagogical praxis might be shaped by developments in research and critical race
                theory, but also how events in the classroom might reshape research is more than a
                matter of good teaching or meeting the publish or perish expectations of the
                academy. Taken together, these essays encourage scholars to reflect on how both
                instructor and students must consider the relation between the classroom and the
                university, and its relationship to the imagined community at the national and
                planetary levels. As Matthew, Gordon, Richardson, and Lee elucidate, instructors and
                students have to grapple with how structures of white privilege are implicit in the
                university, the archive, and in the discipline so that together they can transform
                interpretation into a dialogic act of resistance as they deconstruct racialist and
                exclusionary discourses, thereby creating alternative spaces of true interrelational
                knowledge together. </p>
                    
            <p>The co-creation of knowledge is one of the paths towards the the liberatory potential
                of education that Paulo Freire, a major inspiration for the 2018 panel, describes.
                Arguing against the “banking concept” of education, a system in which students
                merely bank information they passively receive from their teacher, Freire challenges
                the asymmetry of power central to the subject/object dichotomy that is also at the
                core of the ontological negation racism relies on. As bell hooks writes in her
                meditation on how Freire’s pedagogy informs her own, “Freire’s work affirmed that
                education can only be liberatory when everyone claims knowledge as a field in which
                we all labor” (<hi rend="italic">Teaching to Transgress</hi> 14). Moments of first encounter are often formative: students
                    are coming to texts about slavery from a different historical perspective than
                    their teachers, and this means that students have the potential to teach their
                    teachers things they have not before seen, and which they may find hard to
                    see.</p>
                    
            <p>This conversation offers some specific practices in the attempt to create classroom
                environments to create a place of “where both [professors and students] are
                simultaneously teachers and students” while respecting the intersectionalities of
                race, gender, and class in our increasingly diverse student body (Freire 72), but it
                is by no means exhaustive. bell hooks also cautions that “teachers are often among
                that group most reluctant to acknowledge the extent to which white-supremacist
                thinking informs every aspect of our culture including the way we learn, the content
                of what we learn, and the manner in which we are taught” (<hi rend="italic">Teaching
                    Community </hi>25). With this in mind, the discussions here
                respectfully offer multiple ways to reflect on how we might more consciously
                acknowledge and evaluate how our own experiences inflect our pedagogical practices,
                and how to work with students to create spaces in our classrooms for this vital
                dialogue. At a time when events in the US have inspired civic action and debate in
                countries across the world, the present moment can no longer be kept outside the
                doors of a classroom in which Romantic literature is being read. As scholars, it is
                useful to consider not only how pedagogical praxis might be reshaped by developments
                in research, but also how events in the classroom might reshape research
                practices.</p>
                </div>
            
            <div type="citation">
                <head>Works Cited</head>
            <p>“About.” <hi rend="italic">Black Lives Matter</hi>, <ref
                    target="https://romanticcircles.org/praxis/circulations/index.html">https://blacklivesmatter.com/about/</ref>. Accessed 2 June 2020.</p>
            
            <p>Aljoe, Nicole N. <hi rend="italic">Creole Testimonies: Slave Narratives from the
                    British West Indies, 1709-1838</hi>. New York, Palgrave Macmillan, 2012.</p>
                
            <p> ———. “Testimonies of the Enslaved in the Caribbean Literary History.”<hi
                    rend="italic">Literary Histories of the Early Anglophone Caribbean: Islands in the
                    Stream</hi>, edited by Nicole N. Aljoe, Brycchan Carey, and Thomas W. Krise. New
                Caribbean Studies, Springer International Publishing, 2018, pp. 107-123.<ref
                    target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-71592-6_6">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-71592-6_6.</ref></p>
                
            <p>Almeida, Joselyn M. <hi rend="italic">Reimagining the Transatlantic, 1780–1890.
                </hi>2011. Routledge, 2016.</p>
                
            <p>———. “Translating a Slave's Life: Richard Robert Madden and the Post-Abolition
                Trafficking of Juan Manzano's <hi rend="italic">Poems by a Slave in the Island of Cuba</hi>.” <hi
                    rend="italic">Romanticism and the Black Atlantic,</hi> edited by Paul Youngquist and Frances Botkin, <hi
                    rend="italic">Romantic Circles Praxis,</hi> edited by Orrin N.C. Wang, 2011,<ref
                        target="https://romanticcircles.org/praxis/circulations/index.html">https://romanticcircles.org/praxis/circulations/index.html</ref>.</p>
                
            <p>Aravamudan, Srinivas. <hi rend="italic">Tropicopolitans: Colonialism and Agency,
                    1688-1804. </hi>North Carolina, Duke University Press, 1998.</p>
                
            <p>Barker, Anthony J. <hi rend="italic">The African Link: British Attitudes to the Negro
                    in the Era of the Atlantic Slave Trade, 1550-1807.</hi> London, Frank Cass, 1978.</p>
                
            <p>Basker, James G., editor. <hi rend="italic">Amazing Grace: An Anthology of Poems
                    about Slavery, 1660-1810</hi>. New Haven, Yale University Press, 2002</p>
                
            <p>Baucom, Ian. <hi rend="italic">Specters of the Atlantic: Finance Capital, Slavery,
                    and the Philosophy of History</hi>. Durham, Duke University Press, 2005.</p>
                
            <p>Baum, Joan. <hi rend="italic">Mind-Forg’d Manacles: Slavery and the English Romantic
                    Poets</hi>. Hamden, Archon, 1994.</p>
                
            <p>Bewell, Alan. <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and Colonial Disease. </hi>Baltimore,
                Johns Hopkins University Press, 1999.</p>
                
            <p>———. “The Stranger and the Exile Who Is in Our Land within Our Gates: Mary Prince
                as a Black British Immigrant.” <hi rend="italic">Modern Philology,</hi> vol. 118, no. 2,
                2020.</p>
                
            <p>Bhabha, Homi. <hi rend="italic">The Location of Culture</hi>. New York, Routledge,
                1994. </p>
                
            <p>Bigger Six Collective. “Coda: From Coteries to Collectives.”
                <hi rend="italic">Symbiosis: A Journal of Transatlantic Literary and Cultural Relations,</hi> vol. 23, no. 1,
                2019, pp. 139–40.</p>
                
            <p>Brown, Kimberly Juanita. <hi rend="italic">The Repeating Body: Slavery’s Visual
                    Resonance in the Contemporary</hi>. Durham, Duke University Press, 2015.</p>
                
            <p>Buck-Morss, Susan. <hi rend="italic">Hegel, Haiti and Universal History</hi>.
                Pittsburgh, University of Pittsburgh Press, 2009.</p>
                
            <p>Calzada, Sara Medina. <hi rend="italic">Britain and the Regeneration of the Hispanic
                    World: a Study of José Joaquín de Mora's Anglophilia</hi>, Doctoral Dissertation,
                University of Valladolid, Spain, 2017.</p>
                
            <p>Caretta,Vincent, editor. <hi rend="italic">Unchained Voices: An Anthology of Black
                    Authors in the English-Speaking World of the Eighteenth Century.</hi> Lexington,
                University Press of Kentucky, 1996.</p>
                
            <p>Caretta,Vincent and Philip Gould, editors. <hi rend="italic">Genius in Bondage:
                    Literature of the Early Black Atlantic</hi>. Lexington, University Press of Kentucky, 2001.</p>
                
            <p>Carpentier, Alejo. <hi rend="italic">El siglo de las luces.</hi> México: Siglo XXI
                Editores, 1984.</p>
                
            <p>———. "Conciencia e identidad de América." <hi rend="italic">La novela latinoamericana
                    en víspera de un nuevo siglo y otros ensayos.</hi> México: Siglo XXI Editores,
                1981.</p>
                
            <p>Chander, Manu Samriti. <hi rend="italic">Brown Romantics: Poetry and Nationalism in
                    the Global Nineteenth Century</hi>. Lewisburg, Bucknell University Press, 2017. </p>
                
            <p>———. “Romantic Diversitarianism: Problems and Promises.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >European Romantic Review,</hi> vol.31, no. 3, 2020, pp. 295–300.<ref
                    target="https://doi.org/10.1080/10509585.2020.1747687">https://doi.org/10.1080/10509585.2020.1747687</ref>.</p>
                
            <p>Chander, Manu Samriti, and Patricia A. Matthew. “Abolitionist Interruptions:
                Romanticism, Slavery, and Genre.” <hi rend="italic">European Romantic Review</hi>, vol. 29, no. 4,
                2018, pp. 431–97.</p>
                
            <p>Chatterjee, Ronjaunee, Alicia J. M. Christoff, and Amy Wong. “Undisciplining
                Victorian Studies.” <hi rend="italic">Victorian Studies,</hi> vol.62,
                no. 3, 2020.</p>
                
            <p>Coleman, Deirdre. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Colonization and British Anti-Slavery.
                </hi>Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 2005.</p>
                
            <p>Colley, Linda. <hi rend="italic">Captives: Britain, Empire and the World, 1600-1850.
                </hi>New York, Vintage 2002.</p>
                
            <p>Costanzo, Angelo. “Methods, Elements, and Effects of Early Black Autobiography.” <hi
                    rend="italic">A/B: Auto/Biography Studies</hi> 2.3 (fall 1986): 5–20.</p>
                
            <p>———. <hi rend="italic">Surprizing Narrative: Olaudah Equiano and the Beginnings of
                    Black Autobiography</hi>. Wesport, CT: Greenwood, 1987.</p>
                
            <p>———. “African-Caribbean Narrative of British America.” <hi rend="italic">American
                    Literary Study</hi> 19.2 (1993): 260–274.</p>
                
            <p>Cugoano, Ottobah. <hi rend="italic">Thoughts and Sentiments on the Evil and Wicked
                    Traffic of the Slavery and Commerce of the Human Species, Humbly Submitted to the Inhabitants
                    of Great Britain.</hi> London, 1787.<hi rend="italic">Eighteenth Century Collections Online</hi>.
                University of Michigan, 
                <ref target="https://quod.lib.umich.edu/e/eccodemo/K046227.0001.001/1:5?rgn=div1;view=fulltext">
                    https://quod.lib.umich.edu/e/eccodemo/K046227.0001.001/1:5?rgn=div1;view=fulltext</ref>
            Accessed 18 October, 2020.</p>
                
            <p>Davis, Charles T., and Henry Louis Gates Jr., editors. <hi rend="italic">The Slave’s
                    Narrative</hi>. Oxford University Press, 1985.</p>
                
            <p>Davis, David Brion. <hi rend="italic">The Problem of Slavery in the Age of
                    Revolution: 1770 –1823</hi>. Ithaca, Cornell University Press, 1975.</p>
                
            <p>Diaby, Bakary. “Black Women and/in the Shadow of Romanticism.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >European Romantic Review</hi>, vol. 30, no. 3, June 2019, pp. 249–254.</p>
                
            <p>———. “Counting the Bodies: Ferguson and Ferguson,” <hi rend="italic">Essays in
                    Romanticism</hi>, 27 (2), pp. 153-166.</p>
                
            <p>———. “The Signs of the Times.” Romantic Circles, Summer 2020.<ref
                    target="http://romantic-circles.org/blog_rc/signs-times">http://www.rc.umd.edu/pedagogies/commons/novel</ref>.</p>
                
            <p>Dillon, Elizabeth Maddock. “A Sea of Texts: The Atlantic World, Spatial Mapping
                and Equiano’s Narrative.” <hi rend="italic">Religion, Space, and the Atlantic World.</hi>
                Ed. John Corrigan. Columbia: University of South Carolina Press, 2017, pp. 25-54.</p>
                
            <p>Doyle, Laura. “The Racial Sublime.” <hi rend="italic">Romanticism, Race, and Imperial
                    Culture, 1780-1834</hi>, edited by Alan Richardson and Sonia Hofkosh. Bloomington,
                Indiana University Press, 1996, pp. 15-39.</p>
                
            <p>Dykes, Eva Beatrice. <hi rend="italic">The Negro in English Romantic Thought; Or, a
                    Study of Sympathy for the Oppressed</hi>. Washington, D.C., Associated Publishers,
                Incorporated, 1942.</p>
                
            <p>Edwards, Paul, and David Dabydeen, editors. <hi rend="italic">Black Writers in
                    Britain, 1760-1890</hi>. Edinburgh, Edinburgh University Press, 1991.</p>
                
            <p>Elfenbein, Andrew. <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and the Rise of English.</hi>
                Stanford, Stanford University Press, 2009.</p>
                
            <p>Fanon, Franz. <hi rend="italic">Black Skins, White Masks.</hi> Edited by Ziauddin
                Sardar and Homi K. Bhabha. London, Pluto Press, 2008.</p>
                
            <p>Ferber, Abby. “Bringing Students into the Matrix: a Framework and Tools for Teaching
                Race and Overcoming Student Resistance.”<hi rend="italic">Teaching Race and Anti-Racism
                    in Contemporary America,</hi> edited by Kristin Haltinner, Springer, 2014, pp.
                141-155.</p>
                
            <p>Ferguson, Moira. <hi rend="italic">Subject to Others: British Women Writers and
                    Colonial Slavery, 1670–1834</hi>. London, Routledge, 1992.</p>
                
            <p>Ferrer, Ada. <hi rend="italic">Cuba and Haiti in the Age of Revolution</hi>.
                Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 2014.</p>
                
            <p>Foreman, P. Gabrielle et al. “Writing about ‘Slavery’? This Might Help.” Accessed
                June 18, 2020.<ref
                    target="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1A4TEdDgYslX-hlKezLodMIM71My3KTN0zxRv0IQTOQs/mobilebasic?urp=gmail_link"
                    >https://docs.google.com/document/d/1A4TEdDgYslX-hlKezLodMIM71My3KTN0zxRv0IQTOQs/mobilebasic?urp=gmail_link</ref>.</p>
                
            <p>Fryer, Peter. <hi rend="italic">Staying Power: The History of Black People in
                    Britain</hi>, Pluto Press, 2010.</p>
                
            <p>Fulford, Tim and Peter J. Kitson, eds. <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and Colonialism:
                    Writing and Empire, 1780–1830</hi>. Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 1998.</p>
                
            <p>Fulford, Tim, Debbie Lee, and Peter J. Kitson. <hi rend="italic">Literature, Science
                    and Exploration in the Romantic Era: Bodies of Knowledge</hi>, Cambridge, Cambridge
                University Press, 2004. </p>
                
            <p>Gates Jr., Louis, and William L. Andrews, editors. <hi rend="italic">Pioneers of the
                    Black Atlantic: Five Slave Narratives 1772-1815</hi>, Washington D.C., Civitas Books,
                1998.</p>
                
            <p>Gerzina, Gretchen. <hi rend="italic">Britain’s Black Past</hi>, Liverpool University
                Press 2020.</p>
                
            <p>Gikandi, Simon. <hi rend="italic">Slavery and the Culture of Taste.</hi> Princeton,
                Princeton University Press, 2011.</p>
                
            <p>Gilroy, Paul. <hi rend="italic">The Black Atlantic: Modernity and Double
                    Consciousness</hi>. Cambridge, Harvard University Press, 1993.</p>
                
            <p>Gordon, Avery. <hi rend="italic">Ghostly Matters: Haunting and the Sociological
                    Imagination. </hi>Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2008.</p>
                
            <p>Hanson, Lenora. “Uprising, or ‘a Kind of Manna.’” <hi rend="italic">Romantic
                    Circles</hi>, Summer 2020.<ref target="http://romantic-circles.org/blog_rc/uprising-or-%E2%80%9C-kind-manna%E2%80%9D"
                >Uprising or Kind Manna</ref>.</p>
                
            <p>Hartman, Saidiya. “Venus in Two Acts.” <hi rend="italic">Small Axe: A Caribbean
                    Journal of Criticism</hi>, vol. 12, no. 2, 2008, pp. 1-14.</p>
                
            <p>Heinowitz, Rebecca Cole. <hi rend="italic">Spanish America and British Romanticism
                    1777-1826: Rewriting Conquest.</hi> Edinburgh, Edinburgh University Press, 2010.</p>
                
            <p>Hessell, Nikki. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Literature and the Colonised World:
                    Lessons from Indigenous Translations</hi>. London, Palgrave Macmillan, 2018.</p>
                
            <p>Hooks, Bell. <hi rend="italic">Teaching to Transgress: Education as the Practice of Freedom.</hi>New York, 
                Routledge, 1994.</p>
                
            <p>Jackson, Zakiyyah Iman. <hi rend="italic">Becoming Human: Matter and Meaning in an
                    Antiblack World. </hi> New York, New York University Press, 2020. </p>
                
            <p>James, C. L. R. <hi rend="italic">The Black Jacobins: Toussaint L’Ouverture and the
                    San Domingo Revolution</hi>. 3rd ed., London, Allison and Busby, 1980.</p>
                
            <p>Jeffers, Honorée Fanonne. <hi rend="italic">The Age of Phillis, </hi>Middletown CT:
                Wesleyan University Press, 2020.</p>
                
            <p>Joseph-Gabriel, Annette K. <hi rend="italic">Reimagining Liberation: How Black Women
                    Transformed</hi> Citizenship in the French Empire. The New Black Studies
                Series. Champaign, University of Illinois Press, 2020.</p>
                
            <p>Kadish, Doris and Deborah Jensen, eds., <hi rend="italic">Poetry of Haitian
                    Independence. </hi>(Yale University Press, 2015).</p>
                
            <p>Lee, Debbie. <hi rend="italic">Slavery and the Romantic Imagination</hi>.
                Philadelphia, University of Pennsylvania Press, 2002.</p>
                
            <p>———, and P.J. Kitson, editors. <hi rend="italic">Slavery, Abolition and Emancipation:
                    Writings in the British Romantic Period, Vols. 1-4</hi>. London, Pickering &amp; Chatto,
                1999.</p>
                
            <p>———, and Alan Richardson.<hi rend="italic"> Early Black British Writing</hi>. Boston,
                Houghton Mifflin, 2004.</p>
                
            <p>Linbaugh, Peter and Marcus Rediker. <hi rend="italic">The Many-Headed Hydra: Sailors,
                    Slaves, Commoners, and the Hidden History of the Revolutionary Atlantic. </hi>Boston,
                Beacon Press, 2000.</p>
                
            <p>Machow, Howard L. <hi rend="italic">Gothic Images of Race in Nineteenth-Century
                    Britain. </hi>Redwood City, Stanford University Press, 1996.</p>
                
            <p>Makdisi, Saree. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Imperialism: Universal Empire and the
                    Culture of Modernity.</hi> Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 1998.</p>
                
            <p>Markley, A.A. “Teaching Race and Racial Difference in Romantic Reformist
                Fiction.” <ref target="https://romantic-circles.org/pedagogies/commons/novel/index.html">Novel Prospects: Teaching Romantic-Era
                        Fiction</ref>, edited by Patricia A. Matthew and Miriam L. Wallace. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles Pedagogies,</hi> 2008.<ref
                    target="https://www.symbiosistransatlantic.com/">https://romantic-circles.org/pedagogies/commons/novel/markley.html</ref>.</p>
                
            <p>Matthew, Patricia A., and Miriam Wallace, editors. <hi rend="italic">Novel Prospects:
                    Teaching Romantic-Era Fiction</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles Pedagogies</hi>
                    2008<ref target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/pedagogies/commons/novel/">https://romantic-circles.org/pedagogies/commons/global
                   </ref>.</p>
                
            <p>Mbembe, Achille. “The Universal Right to Breathe.” 13 April 2020,
                    <ref target="https://critinq.wordpress.com/2020/04/13/the-universal-right-to-breathe/">The Universal Right to Breathe</ref>
                Accessed May 1, 2020.</p>
                
            <p>McBride, Dwight. <hi rend="italic">Truth, Abolitionism, and Slave Testimony. </hi>New
                York, New York University Press, 2001.</p>
                
            <p>Mellor, Anne K. “Romanticism, Difference and the Aesthetic.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pacific Coast Philology</hi>, vol. 34, no. 2, 1999, pp. 127–41. </p>
                
            <p>———, and Richard Matlak. “Slavery, the Slave Trade, and Abolition in Britain.” in
            <hi rend="italic">British Literature, 1780-1830</hi>, 1996.</p>
                
            <p>Mesthrie, Rajend. “Connecting with John Rickford's Language Contact Research.” <hi
                    rend="italic">The Routledge Companion to the Work of John Rickford</hi>, edited by
                Renée Blake and Isabelle Buchstaller, New York, Routledge, 2019.</p>
                
            <p>Mignolo, Walter. <hi rend="italic">Local Histories, Global Designs: Coloniality,
                    Subaltern Knowledges, and Border Thinking.</hi>Princeton, Princeton University Press,
                2012.</p>
                    
            <p>Miranda, Omar. “Romantic Celebrity and the Journal of Exile. <hi rend="italic">El
                    Colombiano</hi> and The Liberal.” <hi rend="italic">Symbiosis: A Journal of Transatlantic Literary and
                    Cultural Relations</hi>. Ed. Deanna Koretsky and Joel Pace. Special Issue on Transnational Romanticisms.
                (July 2019).<ref
                    target="https://ageofrevolutions.com/2020/06/10/blm-2020-breathing-resistance-and-the-war-against-enslavement/"
                    >https://www.symbiosistransatlantic.com/</ref></p>
                
            <p>Munro, Martin. “Listening to 19th-century Haitian poetry” in <hi rend="italic">Sounds
                    Senses, </hi>ed. Yasser Elhariry, Liverpool University Press (2021).</p>
                
            <p>Nesbitt, Nick. <hi rend="italic">Universal Emancipation: The Haitian Revolution and
                    the radical Enlightenment.</hi> Charlottesville, University of Virginia Press, 2008.</p>
                
            <p>Nelson, Alondra. "Introduction:
                    Future Texts." <hi rend="italic">Social Text</hi>, vol. 20 no. 2, 2002, p.
                1-15. <hi rend="italic">Project MUSE</hi><ref target="muse.jhu.edu/article/31931">muse.jhu.edu/article/31931</ref>
                    .</p>
                
            <p>Newman, Lance, Joel Pace, and Chris Koenig-Woodward. <hi rend="italic">Transatlantic
                    Romanticism</hi>: An Anthology of British, American, and Canadian Literature, 1767-1867.
               London, Longman, 2006.</p>
                
            <p>Nielsen, Wendy C, editor. “Introduction.” <hi rend="italic">Teaching Global
                    Romanticism.</hi>
                "Romantic Pedagogies", edited by Kate Singer and D.B. Rudderman, March 1, 2020. <ref target="https://romantic-circles.org/pedagogies/commons/global">https://romantic-circles.org/pedagogies/commons/global</ref>.</p>
            
            <p>Nussbaum, Felicity. <hi rend="italic">The Limits of the Human: Fictions of Anomaly,
                    Race, and Gender in the Long Eighteenth Century</hi>. Cambridge, Cambridge University
                Press, 2003.</p>
                
            <p>Ortiz, Fernando. <hi rend="italic">Contrapunto cubano del tabaco y el azúcar</hi>.
                Ed. Bronislaw Malinowski. Barcelona, Editorial Ariel, 1973.</p>
                
            <p>Otele, Olivette. <hi rend="italic">African Europeans: An Untold History</hi>. Hurst,
                2020.</p>
                
            <p>Pace, Joel. “#BlackLivesMatter: The Black Atlantic Matters.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Teaching Global Romanticism</hi>, edited by Wendy C. Nielsen, par. 1-24.</p>
                
            <p>Paquet, Sandra Pouchet. <hi rend="italic">Caribbean Autobiography: Cultural Identity
                    and Self-Representation</hi>. Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 2002.</p>
                
            <p>Pierrot, Grégory. <hi rend="italic">The Black Avenger in Atlantic Culture</hi>.
                Atlanta, University of Georgia Press, 2019.</p>
                
            <p>Potkay, Adam, and Sandra Burr, editors. <hi rend="italic">Black Atlantic Writers of
                    the Eighteenth Century: Living the New Exodus in England and the Americas</hi>, London,
                Palgrave Macmillan, 1995.</p>
                
            <p>Pratt, Mary Louise. <hi rend="italic">Imperial Eyes: Travel Writing and
                    Transculturation</hi>. New York, Routledge, 1992.</p>
                
            <p>Ramey, Lauri. <hi rend="italic">Black British Writing</hi>. Edited by R. Victoria
                Arana. New York, Palgrave Macmillan, 2004.</p>
                
            <p>Reeder, Jesse. <hi rend="italic">The Forms of Informal Empire: Britain, Latin
                    America, and Nineteenth Century Literature.</hi>Baltimore, Johns Hopkins University Press,
                2020.</p>
                
            <p>Rezek, Joseph. “Romanticism in the Atlantic World.” <hi rend="italic">Studies in
                    Romanticism </hi>vol. 55, no. 4, 2007, pp. 307-317. </p>
                
            <p>Richardson, Alan and Sonia Hofkosh, editors. <hi rend="italic">Romanticism, Race, and
                    Imperial Culture, 1780-1834</hi>. Bloomington, Indiana University Press, 1996.</p>
                
            <p>Richardson, Alan and Debbie Lee, editors.<hi rend="italic"> Early Black British
                    Writing</hi>. Boston, Houghton Mifflin, 2004.</p>
                
            <p>Richardson, Alan. “Romantic Voodoo: Obeah and British Culture.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Studies in Romanticism</hi>, vol. 32, no. 1 (Spring 1993): 3-28.</p>
                
            <p>———. “Slavery and Romantic Writing.” <hi rend="italic">A Companion to
                    Romanticism</hi>, edited by Duncan Wu, Hoboken, John Wiley and Sons Ltd, 1999.</p>
                
            <p>———. ed.,<hi rend="italic">Verse. </hi>vol. 4, <hi rend="italic">Slavery, Abolition,
                    and Emancipation: Writings in the British Romantic Period,</hi>edited by Debbie Lee and Peter Kitson,
                London, Routledge 1999.</p>
                
            <p>Ross, Marlon B. “The Race of/in Romanticism: Notes Toward a Critical Race
                Theory.” <hi rend="italic">Race, Romanticism, and the Atlantic</hi>, edited by Paul
                Youngquist. <hi rend="italic">Ashgate Series in Nineteenth-Century Transatlantic Studies.</hi> Farnham, Ashgate,
                2013, pp. 25–58.</p>
                
            <p>Said, Edward. <hi rend="italic">Orientalism. </hi>New York,<hi rend="italic"
                >Pantheon</hi>, 1978.</p>
                
            <p>———. <hi rend="italic">Cultural Imperialism. </hi>New York: Knopf, 1993.</p>
                
            <p>Sanchez, Juan. “Translating Revolution into Spanish: British Romanticism and The
                Spanish-Speaking World.”<hi rend="italic">Teaching Global Romanticism,</hi> edited by Wendy
                Nielsen, par. 1-19.</p>
                
            <p>Sandler, Matt. “Black Byronism.” <hi rend="italic">The Byron Journal</hi> vol. 45,
                no. 1, 2017, pp. 39–53.</p>
                
            <p>———. <hi rend="italic">The Black Romantic Revolution: Abolitionist Poets at the End
                    of Slavery. </hi>Verso, 2020.</p>
                
            <p>Scott, David. <hi rend="italic">Conscripts of Modernity: The Tragedy of Colonial
                    Enlightenment</hi>. Durham, Duke University Press, 2004.</p>
                
            <p>Sharpe, Christina Elizabeth. <hi rend="italic">In the Wake: On Blackness and
                    Being</hi>. Duke University Press, 2016.</p>
                
            <p>Sharpe, Jenny. <hi rend="italic">Immaterial Archives: An African Diaspora Poetics of
                    Loss</hi>. Evanston, Northwestern University Press, 2020.</p>
                
            <p>———. “What Use is the Imagination?” <hi rend="italic">PMLA</hi>
               vol. 129, no. 3, 2014, pp. 512–517.</p>
                
            <p>Sinanan, Kerry. “BLM 2020: Breathing, Resistance, and the War against Enslavement.”
                    <hi rend="italic">Age of Revolutions.</hi> June 10, 2020.<ref
                    target="https://ageofrevolutions.com/2020/06/10/blm-2020-breathing-resistance-and-the-war-against-enslavement/"
                        >https://blacklivesmatter.com/about</ref>.</p>
                
            <p>———. “Maroon Resistance, White Violence, and Romanticism’s Envy of Black Freedom.” Romantic Circles Unbound, <hi rend="italic">Breath, </hi>20.1 Summer
                    2020.<ref
                    target="http://romantic-circles.org/blog_rc/maroon-resistance-white-violence-and-romanticism%E2%80%99s-envy-black-freedom">Maroon Resistance, White Violence, and Romanticism</ref>
                    Accessed August 1, 2020.</p>
                
            <p>———. “The ‘Slave’ as Cultural Artifact: The Case of Mary Prince.” In <hi
                    rend="italic">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture</hi> 49, edited by Eve Tavor Bannet and
                Roxann Wheeler. Baltimore, Johns Hopkins University Press, 2020, pp. 65-83.</p>
                
            <p>Sussman, Charlotte. <hi rend="italic">Consuming Anxieties: Consumer Protest, Gender,
                    and British Slavery, 1713–1833</hi>. Redwood City: Stanford University Press, 2000.</p>
                
            <p>Taylor, Keeanga-Yamahtta. <hi rend="italic">From #BlackLivesMatter to Black
                    Liberation</hi>. Haymarket Books, 2016. “Teaching Global Romanticism.” <hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles,</hi> March 1, 2020.
                <ref target="https://blacklivesmatter.com/about/">https://romantic-circles.org/pedagogies/commons/global</ref>.</p>
                
            <p>Thiong'o, Ngũgĩ wa. “James Joyce and the English Metaphysical Empire.” Troy Lecture,
                4 April, 2016, University of Massachusetts, Amherst.</p>
                
            <p>Thomas, Helen. <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and Slave Narratives: Transatlantic
                    Testimonies. </hi>Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 2000.</p>
                
            <p>Thomas, Hugh.<hi rend="italic"> The Slave Trade: The History of the Atlantic Slave
                    Trade 1440–1870</hi>. London, Picador, 1997.</p>
                
            <p>Tomich, Dale. <hi rend="italic">Through the Prism of Slavery: Labor, Capital, and
                    World Economy</hi>. Maryland, Rowan &amp; Littlefield, 2004.</p>
                
            <p>Wallerstein, Immanuel. “Reading Fanon in the 21st Century.” <hi rend="italic">New
                    Left Review</hi>, vol. 57, 2009, pp. 117-25.</p>
                
            <p>Welburn, Rob. <hi rend="italic">Roanoke and Wampum: Topics in Native American
                    Heritage and Literatures, </hi>New York, Peter Lang, 2001.</p>
                
            <p>Williams, Eric. <hi rend="italic">Capitalism and Slavery</hi>. London, André Deutsch,
                1964.</p>
                
            <p>Wood, Marcus. <hi rend="italic">Blind Memory: Visual Representations of Slavery in
                    England and America, 1780–1865</hi>. Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2000. </p>
                
            <p>———. <hi rend="italic">Slavery, Empathy, and Pornography</hi>. Oxford, Oxford
                University Press, 2002.</p>
                
            <p>———. <hi rend="italic">The Poetry of Slavery: An Anglo-American Anthology, 1764-1865.
                </hi>Oxford, Oxford University Press, 2003. </p>
                
            <p>Youngquist, Paul, and Frances Botkin. “Introduction: Black Romanticism: Romantic Circulations.” 
                <hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles</hi>, 2011.</p>
                
            <p>Youngquist, Paul. editor. <hi rend="italic">Race, Romanticism, and the Atlantic</hi>.
                Ashgate Series in Nineteenth-Century Transatlantic Studies. Farnham, Ashgate, 2013.</p>
                
            <p>———. “Black Romanticism: A Manifesto.” <hi rend="italic">Studies in Romanticism</hi>,
                vol. 56, no. 1, 2017, pp. 3–14. </p>
            </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
