<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Triangulating (Textual) History: What Early Black British Narratives Teach Us about the Future To Come </title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Elizabeth Fay</name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-11-25</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2024.race.fay</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">race</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Triangulating (Textual) History: What Early Black British Narratives Teach Us about the Future To Come
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                                <surname>Fay</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        
                        
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="praxis/contingent/praxis.2024.race.fay"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/wellbeing/praxis.2024.wellbeing.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Anti-Slavery Literatures: Pedagogies and Contexts </title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-11-22">November 25, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>11.25.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="abstract">
               
            <p> I argue that a transatlantic perspective is not enough when we teach our students
                about the slave trade and the Abolition movement during the Romantic period. What is
                needed is an Atlantic studies perspective that involves the circum-Atlantic trade of
                goods and persons, disrupting a white Anglo-American dialogue of historical persons
                and texts with a more fluid set of networks and relationships. In order to situate
                an Atlanticist pedagogy, I enlist the historical nautical strategy of triangulation
                between Africa, the Caribbean, and Britain in its metaphorical sense: the
                triangulation of three narratives within contextual materials; the triangulation of
                literary interpretation with historical and current interpretive concepts and
                methods; the triangulation of Atlantic coasts and land entities; and the
                triangulation of the strategic terms “fluidity,” “circulation,” and “movement”
                borrowed from non-literary fields of study. I also introduce the way that the
                triadic relation between past, present and future is an important lens for student
                to read through: the slave trade’s prospective effects on the Black Lives Matter
                movement and the literary genre of Afrofuturism, or the impassioned rhetoric of
                corresponding texts from past, present and imagined future. Effectively, an Atlantic
                approach has the depth and breadth to put history, economic trade, political
                movements, and maritime realities in relation to rhetorical and figurative analysis
                of literary texts.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="essay">
            <p>Romantic Period studies has tended to focus on those literary and cultural concerns that apply to
                    Anglo-American relations in terms of a transatlanticism
                    belonging to a determinate timeframe. However, the Romantic Period was actually
                    an age of global capitalism, plundered resources, and
                    cross-contamination; therefore, enlarging the Anglo-American dialogue of public
                    voices and efficacious texts more expansively makes sense as Bernard Bailyn and Joselyn M.
                    Almeida have argued in separate contexts. <note place="foot"
                        resp="author"> See Bernard Bailyn, <hi rend="italic">Atlantic History: Concepts and
                            Contours, Cambridge: Harvard University Press,</hi> 2005, and Joselyn M.
                        Almeida, <hi rend="italic">Reimagining the Transatlantic</hi>, 1780-1890 New
                        York: Routledge, 2016).</note> Although I will be focusing
                    here on the triangular relation of Africa, Britain, and British holdings in the
                    Caribbean, folding into that relation the French colony of San Domingue and the
                    American city Philadelphia for two of the texts discussed, the same argument
                    holds for colonizers and the colonized, brutalized or enslaved peoples of other
                    territories belonging to panatlantic land masses. The point of engaging with
                    these histories, the ideologies that produced them, and the testimonies of
                    survivors is that the concerns of the Atlantic world remain central to the
                    concerns of today’s Atlantic and global reality. Historically, too, a more
                    expansive treatment of the Romantic-era Atlantic world could put the trading
                    circuits of the West Indies and the East Indies in dialogue; or one might make
                    the connection for students between the working of West Indian plantations and
                    the not-too different circumstances of the diamond mines today in mineral rich
                    countries like the Democratic Republic of the Congo, nations whose people see no
                    profit from the rapacious mining of their land by others. In terms of the
                    transatlantic, this more expanded perspective is the domain of Atlantic World
                    studies, which is interdisciplinary, and involves a deep sense of history from
                    plate changes in the ocean’s bottom to human geography
                    (which, for example, examines migration patterns over centuries, death tolls
                    amongst enslaved people, movement between Caribbean islands and plantations).</p>
                
            <p>The dilemma of what can be
                    crammed into a class discussion arises when the materials concerning the sites
                    of literary production and dissemination (important for emphasizing the
                    precarity of narratives
                    and testimonials of enslaved peoples) can be enriched by
                    contextualizing them with charity organizations and Parliamentary records of
                    Abolitionist and conservative documents. Yet I want to argue instead for a
                more engaged Atlanticist lens to broaden how we situate and affirm the complexities
                of Atlantic life for students, the malleable nature of Atlantic identity, and its
                opportunities for self-reinvention.<note place="foot" resp="author"> I also
                    want to caution against restricting ourselves to the British imperial when
                    teaching the Romantic period: the Black Atlantic intersects with the Red
                    Atlantic (the circulation, exchanges, and material productions of indigenous
                    peoples in the Atlantic and coastal regions of the Americas, as well as their
                    travels to Britain, Europe and Africa), and the Hispanic and Lusophone Atlantic
                    world whose historical importance loomed large in the period, as well as the
                    Francophone Atlantic, all of which extend our teaching about British empire
                    through these other circulations and imperial networks.</note> To think
                pedagogically using such a lens has allowed me to think more broadly geographically
                and temporally in order to situate the revolutionary aspects of Atlantic life in the
                Romantic period. My main strategy is one I adapted from the nautical strategy of
                triangulation to teach literary interpretation of narratives and testimonials of
                enslaved persons, historical texts or information, related texts and websites in
                groups of three, and to apply Atlantic studies concepts and methods in connection
                with literary analysis. The strategy of triangulation has been richly explored in
                the work of Bailyn, Jeremy Smith, Almeida, and others.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See also Aguirre, <hi rend="italic">Informal Empire</hi>;
                    Brown, <hi rend="italic">Informal Empire in Latin America</hi>; Heinowitz, <hi
                        rend="italic">Spanish America and British Romanticism</hi>; Robson, <hi
                        rend="italic">Britain, Portugal and South America in the Napoleonic
                        Wars</hi>; Tutino, ed.<hi rend="italic"> New Countries</hi>; and
                    Cañizares-Esguerra, ed.<hi rend="italic"> Entangled Empires.</hi></note> Against
                the Anglo-American oppositional model, triangulation is not just adding a middle
                term to create a dialectical engagement; rather, it involves the fluid movement of
                dynamic relationality among multiple, and variable subjects. In this way texts can
                be revisited several times in order to resee them, and the strategic terms
                “fluidity,” “circulation,” and “movement” help students approach the revisiting as
                necessary and deepening rather than repetitive. This strategy has helped me unpack
                with my students a vitally mobile and contingent arena in which texts embodying this
                dynamic can be read against those stemming from empire, against each other, and
                within a network of unstable conditions and circumstances.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See in particular Bailyn’s <hi rend="italic">Atlantic
                        History</hi> and Joselyn Almeida’s <hi rend="italic">Reimagining the
                        Transatlantic</hi>, esp. 69, 105-6, 197, 200, 325.</note></p>
                
            <p>Moreover, broadening the historical horizon from an Atlantic World perspective allows
                students to view the slave trade, Abolition, and radical politics during the
                Romantic period as conversant with our contemporary politics. The courageous voices
                of those enslaved during the Romantic period take on a new legitimacy for my most
                recent students, compared with the way in which earlier student cohorts had
                responded to such texts; current students can more readily hear and empathize with
                the outrage of those from so long ago. This outrage responds to the authority of
                lived experience. While students understand that the value of <hi rend="italic"
                    >this</hi> singular life made clear in individually voiced accounts was
                politically important to the Abolitionist cause, the personal and communal
                resilience such accounts express was necessary then, and comes across all these many
                years later to be heard in all its dignity. These voices, then, can be further
                complicated (rather than polarizing them against the claims of colonists and
                politicians), with the biographies of figures like Baron de Vastey, who Marlene
                    Daut has argued was signal for the development of a “[B]lack Atlantic humanism.”
                    In counterpoint to Toussaint L’Ouverture’s rhetorical promotion of brotherhood
                    across color lines, Vastey, a Haitian of biracial descent and Toussaint’s
                    contemporary, critiques colonial dependencies on slavery. The slave trade and
                    the high morbidity of slave labor, Vastey unceasingly argued, reveals that a
                    free-market economy is merely an ideological justification for the
                    inexcusability of racism.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See Daut, <hi rend="italic">Baron de Vastey.</hi></note></p>
                
            <p>Using material like Daut’s to set the triangle trade within cosmopolitan humanism, as
                well as other globalizing contextual materials (the competition between goods
                produced in the East Indies and the West Indies, for instance), expands the horizon
                of how we teach the transatlantic and the Atlantic World, but only if those singular
                voices are heard as integrated with larger contexts. Accounts of formerly enslaved
                persons are important for our students because, although mediated for a white
                audience, they make disclosures about lived experience that novels can only gesture
                to, especially for those students who resist the empathy necessarily involved in
                reading actual accounts, and worse, the documentation of abusive planter
                    practices.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See Helen Thomas’ excellent<hi
                        rend="italic">Romanticism and Slave Narratives, </hi>which has greatly
                    helped me in teaching Black British writing, as well as Nicole Aljoe’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Creole Testimonies, </hi>which distinguishes between the
                    testimonial and the narrative in terms of authorial voice and rhetorical
                    strategy. More recently, Patricia Matthew and Manu Chander’s discussion have
                    extended how to think about slave narrative and anti-slavery literature as a
                    genre in “Abolitionist Interruptions.”</note> While I rely on the arguments of
                Mark Salber Phillips for understanding historical distance through the narrative
                function, that gut-level pain is also interpretatively useful. To make connections
                between textual accounts in a way that makes for meaningful interpretation, I have
                found that starting with an emotionally rather than physically painful event can
                translate what students may be feeling into something we can discuss and then extend
                to other connections between the texts that are more politicized, and therefore more
                rhetorically inflected. For instance, in my recent course offering, I asked students
                to look at a similar event in Prince’s and Equiano’s narratives, and then to
                contrast it with Toussaint’s experience. Mary Prince’s account of the end of
                childhood, when her mistress sends her to work at another house, is charged with the
                distress of the twelve-year-old girl; but the moment when her mother has to take her
                and her sisters to the slave market to be sold after the death of her mistress,
                despite the distance of years at the time of writing, is suffused with emotional
                pain at confronting this final separation from family and home. Beginning with the
                day before, she writes:
                
            <quote>Oh dear! I cannot bear to think of that day,--it is too much.—It recalls the great
                grief that filled my heart, and the woeful thoughts that passed to and fro through
                my mind, whilst listening to the pitiful words of my poor mother, weeping for the
                loss of her children. (Prince, <hi rend="italic">History</hi> [1831], 3)</quote>
                
            In describing the next morning, Prince uses funereal language to depict the emotional
                death she and her mother feel at this moment: “The black morning at length came . .
                . whilst she was putting on us the new osnaburgs in we were to be sold, she said, in
                a sorrowful voice, (I shall never forget it!) ‘See, I am <hi rend="italic">shrouding
                </hi>my poor children; what a task for a mother!’” (<hi rend="italic">History</hi>,
                3). This chilling moment, in which the mother has to sell her own children at the
                slave market, is heart-rending in itself, while Prince’s use of language and word
                choice feels authentic rather than rhetorically distant (“I shall never forget
                it!”); the imagery of a funeral rather than a marketplace symbolizes the death of
                the subject-self that being sold is meant to create. But the exclamations and the
                never-forgotten emotion reveal, just as surely, that Prince has held onto her
                subjectivity in a way that students can now see is revealed throughout her
                narrative; Prince is a strong woman, one who can advocate through her story, and so
                providing a heroic model of fortitude in the face of extreme suffering. </p>
                
            <p> Equiano has a similar story to tell that usefully compares to Prince’s of the
                rending of the family. Although his begins with his sister’s and his abduction by
                African “slavers,” his parents never to be seen again, their strong sibling bond
                sustains them until the fatal moment when they are broken apart.<note place="foot" resp="author"> “Slavers” was the term commonly used in the period for those
                    engaged in capturing or gathering individuals for selling to others.</note> I
                ask students to closely compare the two scenes, Prince’s and Equiano’s, to compare
                the affective impact of their uses of rhetoric. 
                
                <quote>"One day . . . I saw one of those people come into the year of our next neighbor but
                one, to kidnap, there being many stout young people in it. Immediately on this I
                gave the alarm . . . But alas! Ere long it was my fate to be thus attached, and to
                be carried off, when none of the grown people were nigh . . . But alas! we were soon
                deprived of even the small comfort of weeping together . . . for my sister and I
                were then separated, while we lay clasped in each other’s arms." (Equiano,<hi
                    rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi> (1789, 62)</quote>
                
           Rhetorically, the “But, alas!” repetition has a lot of work to do, but for a modern
                reader, it can’t carry the weight of the experienced trauma in the way that Prince’s
                “Oh dear! I cannot bear to think of that day,--it is too much.—” still does. If
                Equiano’s response to the loss of his sister is different from Prince’s strikes the
                reader as pathos-filled rather than grief-stricken perhaps—so that students try to
                locate the difference in experienced pain contextually— I’ve found it helpful to
                shift their attention to seeing that the way the story is told can change the
                emotional register, and that the way emotion is being put to use should not
                influence us to value or devalue one person’s pain over another’s given our
                historical biases. Critical context thus informs students’ understanding ofthe
                disruptive force of the Atlantic trade during this period and the valuation of
                bodies in a marketplace that took no account of pain.<note place="foot" resp="author"> The Portuguese created a slave-trade category for the
                    standard measure in valuing Black lives, “pieza.” Drawing on James’s research,
                    Wynter explains in another article that a pieza “was a man of twenty-five years,
                    approximately, in good health, calculated to give a certain amount of physical
                    labor value against which all the others could be measure—with for example,
                    three teenagers equaling one pieza and older men and women thrown in a job lot
                    as refuse.” Qtd. in Walter D. Mignolo, “Sylvia Wynter: What Does It Mean to be
                    Human?,” 114.</note> Equiano openly states that his own father owned enslaved
                people, a repugnant fact for many students; he also explains the practice of African
                enslavers in terms of kidnapping and domestic servitude, and in opposition to the
                brutality of the triangle slave trade. This sometimes leads students to dismiss
                Equiano’s narrative. But by getting students to look for resemblance rather than
                difference, they can then see that like Prince, Equiano also tries to find a sense
                of home when he is with kinder people, and yet whereas she finds her real sense of
                “home” in her own strong sense of self, he continually remakes himself, transforming
                himself fluidly through the circulations of ship voyages he participates in. He
                makes himself into an Atlantic identity, so that he’s at home everywhere—on
                shipboard, in Philadelphia, in London, and so on—whereas we sense that she is never
                at home except within herself. And his rhetorical style is not just due to the
                temporal distance between the act of writing and biographical events; Equiano is
                becalmed as he writes his narrative, stilled by the land he now inhabits and the
                perhaps unyielding political audience he addresses.</p>
                
            <p> In C.L.R. James’s<hi rend="italic">The Black Jacobins</hi>, which tells the history
                of San Domingo and Toussaint L’Ouverture’s extraordinary transformation of the
                colony into a free state by 1803, James refuses the fiction of historical
                objectivity; students immediately respond to his passionate engagement with his
                story and his protagonist, and the book is filled with his exclamatory asides.
                Toussaint suffers none of the rending of family that Prince and Equiano experience,
                and so James’s indignation is focused on the abuses endemic to slavery and those
                historians who had covered it over: “A venal race of scholars, profiteering panders
                to national vanity, have conspired to obscure the truth about abolition” (James 51)
                he rails. By contrast Toussaint “was so genuinely kind to the whites in their
                distressful condition that they could not fail to appreciate it” (157). James cannot
                but revel in the man’s political acuity and gracious use of political speech acts
                and his tolerance as a political leader for all San Domingans; his voice and message
                are clear in quotations from letters and speeches: “Learn, citizens, to appreciate
                the glory of your new political status. In acquiring the rights that the
                Constitution accords to all Frenchmen, do not forget the duties it imposes on you.
                Be but virtuous and you will be French men and good citizens . . . Work together for
                the prosperity of San Domingo . . . [to] assure public well-being” (James 205). I
                point out to students how this passage, and Toussaint’s worry over “the fate of some
                unhappy whites who have been victims in this business’” (157), is in stark contrast
                to James’s own assessment of white treatment of Blacks: “The difficulty was that
                though one could trap them like animals . . . and beat both [man and animal] with
                the same stick . . . they remained, despite their black skins and curly hair, quite
                invincibly human beings” (11). </p>
                
            <p> To situate James’s passionate history I ask students to read Sylvia Wynter’s article
                on C.L.R. James, “Beyond the Categories of the Master Conception,” which clarifies
                her own theoretical adaptation of James’s Afro-Caribbean based theory of capitalism
                as a colonial-based economy rather than trade-based, one requiring enslaved labor
                rather than wage labor. The bourgeoise development of capitalism that overthrew a
                monarchy-based economy depended on the development of a colonial scheme based on
                unpaid labor from colonists, indentured servants, and enslaved persons. The
                monarchial symbolics of blood (blood lineage, vassalage, war), as Wynter explains,
                was replaced by a symbolics of skin color, the effects of which still reverberate
                today. Wynter posits the human condition of “becoming [B]lack” to explain the way
                that discourse co-produces social experience along with colonial capitalism for
                anyone who, we could say, has not undergone “becoming white.”<note
                        place="foot" resp="author"> Mignolo, 116. “Becoming white” is my
                        addition so that students understand the concept of race as a discursive
                        formation.</note> Discourse produces the knowledge that one is becoming
                Black in a repetition of experience that daily announces this condition, whether the
                year is 1800 or 2021. </p>
                
            <p> For students then, first-hand accounts put the entire phenomenon of the slave trade
                into perspective, and for some students of color, especially those who are African,
                African American, or Caribbean American, first-hand accounts can be empowering while
                second-hand accounts like James’s can reinforce that self-empowerment. These
                first-hand narratives give students a sense of what self-determining voices like
                Prince’s, Equiano’s, and Toussaint’s sounded like. The inner strength and the
                courage to simply live a life, or to trade up one’s own life-value, or to liberate a
                people, come through in these narratives. Romantic literature gains a special
                meaning for these students, one that speaks to them in today’s contexts; it can also
                give them a history of strength, endurance and courage. Texts from the more recent
                past such as James’s, and from today’s headlines or popular genres add resonance to
                making personal connections with such a history. Identifying with texts from a
                different time and culture has resulted in multiple research papers at the end of
                the semester on Equiano, women’s slave testimonials, and on a comparative treatment
                of women’s escape narratives in the period. Recently a student has also used
                information from short lectures I gave on the slavery and human trafficking
                practices in theperiod on the Barbary Coast and in the Ottoman Empire to develop a
                paper on Equiano that sets him in a wider context of slaver practices historically
                and within the period. </p>
                
            <p> In using an Atlanticist lens to teach this material, I try to return our focus to
                the networks of colonialism wherever this makes sense because more was at stake in
                the triangle slave trade than the economy of bodies. The forward trajectory of the
                larger stakes surely begins with the population decimation of northwestern Africa
                and the overpopulation of the West Indies, but they include the monoculture
                practices of Caribbean plantations (and continuing today with Caribbean banana
                plantations, for instance), which—concurrently with the rise in western national
                gross products—also changed the natural resource structure of Caribbean terrain.
                Through increased commerce in peoples, animals, plants, and goods, the slave trade
                also grossly heightened the effects and pace of anthropocenic change, giving
                students a sense of how disastrous history can affect worlds as well as
                    peoples.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See Carney and Rosomoff’s <hi
                        rend="italic">In the Shadow of Slavery. </hi>To teach students about the the
                    expansiveness of trade networks involving African kingdoms, see Thornton’s
                    authoritative <hi rend="italic">Africa and Africans in the Making of the
                        Atlantic World, 1400-1800</hi>.</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>But the textual analysis I’ve been putting forth still doesn’t suggest the economy of
                movement that Atlantic life involves, and metaphor is a helpful intervention here,
                specifically the chronotope of the ship.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    This is the chronotope Paul Gilroy, following Bakhtin, explicitly calls
                    attention to in <hi rend="italic">The Black Atlantic</hi>. 17.</note> That the
                ship should also be understood literally through viewing the virtual slave ship on
                the SlaveVoyages.org website gives the metaphor powerful resonance in its suggestion
                of mobility and flexible use. To image fluidity, movement (a term encompassing more
                than human mobility and displacement), and circulation, of the Atlantic world, the
                metaphor of the Atlantic-ranging ship is perhaps unsurpassed. Whereas both fluidity
                and circulation take into account the stagnation of being becalmed, Equiano’s
                autobiography underscores how thriving amongst aquatic conditions requires
                understanding oneself, or at least one’s life, in terms of the vessel that sails
                such waters. Living in and on the Atlantic waterways requires at the very least an
                abiding interest in shipping news and port landings; in order to flourish, however,
                of more value would be a working knowledge of the vessel, and indeed the
                classificatory terminology used for distinguishing vessels and their component
                parts. These, as Equiano’s life story reflects, was key not just to ship life but to
                life itself: ship life <hi rend="italic">was</hi>, in a sense, Atlantic life. And,
                learning to navigate—as Equiano does—requires a more flexible thinking, one based on
                a triangulating impulse that can reconcile oppositions through adjacencies and
                affiliations.</p>
                
            <p> Triangulation—not just the juxtaposition of three terms but the fluid and dynamic
                movement between them—is key, I would argue, to teaching Romanticism in terms of
                Atlantic movement, whether we are working with the binaries of the Anglo-American
                transatlantic or with the multiple triangulations of the Caribbean islands and
                Atlantic littoral which are always in play or potentially so. Putting the
                Atlanticship metaphor and triangulation together, we might consider what the
                triangle slave trade has culturally produced as our heritage, the disturbed flow of
                water and lives that Christina Sharpe argues in <hi rend="italic">In the Wake: On
                    Blackness and Being</hi> is demonstrably ongoing. The “wake” figures a
                disruptive dimension in the lives of African Americans that began with a cut across
                what had been, the ship cutting across the ocean’s own waves as it cuts into lives,
                cuts off lives, and changes human relations in monstrous ways. In this sense, the
                United States is in relation not only to Britain and the West African coast, but in
                relation to the ocean and its human footprint on land, an ongoing relation of
                turmoil, . the Understanding the western impact on the West Indies during this
                period gives students a way to place Romanticism within their twenty-first century
                perspective, not only as a chapter in the difficult history of enslavement but also
                as part of an aspirational identity, of a heroism born of struggle that is evidenced
                in the narratives of formerly enslaved persons where singular voices, accounts of
                uprisings and attempted uprisings, and the hopes and aspirations that fueled
                Abolition and Emancipation can be found.</p>
                
            <p> To think Atlantically allows me to pose one regulative idea—that of the world as a
                centered experience that affirms the uniqueness of the white enfranchised self that
                is supported by peripheral others and contrast it to the disenfranchised (the world,
                in other words, of thecolonial economic system)—against another regulative idea of
                the Atlantic of a fluid world of multiple and mobile players. It allows me to keep
                my students focused on the dynamic, fluid relation between center and periphery,
                larger and local contexts, and what is counted (money, bodies, trade items) and what
                does not count (lives). These are also the problems of sovereignty, and what in
                years past Romantic studies mainly focused on; they have only been transformed, but
                not displaced, in the slave trade economy and are the problems that Equiano marshals
                so well for his tale of self-recovery, innovation, and reinvention. </p>
                
            <p> The triangulation of texts (contextualized through websites on the histories of
                Abolition and the slave trade, as well as a web-video of life on a virtual slave
                ship, a reconstruction of L’Aurore <note place="foot" resp="author"> See also
                    Rediker’s <hi rend="italic">The Slave Ship.</hi></note>) allows student to
                connect to the voices that so clearly and emphatically tell their story or the
                stories of others. Most recently the three texts were those of Prince<note
                   place="foot" resp="author"> I find that research on slave testimonials
                    further helps students metabolize the truly painful passages of these texts:
                    both Helen Thomas’ <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and Slave Narratives:
                        Transatlantic Testimonies</hi> and Nicole Aljoe’s <hi rend="italic">Creole
                        Testimonies</hi> has proved invaluable here.</note>, Equiano, and James,
                which put together and triangulated pit the African, West Indian, and San Domingan
                experience in a deeply involved perspective that includes the newly independent U.S.
                Thus Equiano’s, Prince’s and Toussaint’s achievements (self-improvement,
                self-liberation, and the liberation of a people) participate in the very conditions
                that fueled the French Revolution (financed by France’s slave-trade enriched
                bourgeoisie) and the English Abolition movement (which, as C.L.R. James argues, was
                encouraged by William Pitt as Prime Minister to deflect other political tensions
                    [<hi rend="italic">Black Jacobins</hi>, pp. 53-54]). But triangulation requires
                positioning and revisiting: following Prince’s story with Equiano’s is
                achronological, but his rhetorically sophisticated style, because it distances and
                softens raw experience, allows for a more appreciative revisiting of Prince’s
                rhetorical moves. The clear parallels between Prince’s story of British colonial
                enslavement and Toussaint’s political speechmaking as he liberates both his fellow
                slaves and his island from colonial legal, economic, and political control enable
                students to bring together the three texts through both formal and experiential
                commonalities and differences. </p>
                
            <p>To balance the first-hand narrative unit on Prince, Equiano and the Haitian
                Revolution, I designed a second unit focusing on women’s experience in fictional
                texts. Beginning with the anonymous <hi rend="italic">The</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Woman of Colour, A Tale</hi> (1808), the students then read a
                novel that also creates comparisons between women whose wealth makes them decadent
                and women who regard morality as more valuable, Austen’s <hi rend="italic">Mansfield
                    Park</hi> (1814). In each case the heroine’s transplantation into a different
                family depends on a reliance on the wealth generated by exploiting legal and
                capitalist networks that masked over the horrors of enslavement. Olivia Fairfield is
                the daughter of a Jamaican plantation owner and the majestic Marcia, a gifted but
                enslaved African woman; the conditions of Mr. Fairfield’s will are that Olivia is to
                be married into, or become the dependent of, her relations, the English Merton
                family. Fanny Price is adopted into her uncle Bertram’s family as a charity case,
                and in this sense Olivia and Fanny have opposed relations to plantation wealth, but
                in a chiasmic relation to each other which students can appreciate: the biracial
                heroine brings wealth with her, the white heroine brings only her poverty. Sir
                Thomas makes his wealth from his own Antiguan plantations though the family, like
                Olivia’s Merton relations, is resident in England. In both novels the women of these
                families display the decadent lifestyles and egocentrism created by West Indian
                caste divisions, and so stand in for what Olivia calls “the most die-away lady on
                the whole island of Jamaica” (Anon. 73). Both Olivia and Fanny take the role of
                outside observer, Olivia through her Jamaican birth and biracial identity, and Fanny
                through her parents’ downward social mobility. Both are treated by their adoptive
                families as different in appearance (Olivia is beautiful and biracial, Fanny is
                small and plain) and in kind (Olivia’s Black mother; Fanny’s disreputable father).
                And both make observations that explicitly (Olivia) or implicitly (Fanny) compare
                the women of their adoptive families to the “decadent” behavior of West Indian
                women. </p>
                
            <p> However, in both novels the authorial insistence on a moral tale to be made of plot
                and characters enables the Caribbean plantation system itself to be glossed over.
                    In<hi rend="italic">The Woman of Colour</hi> this gloss is effected through
                Olivia’s fond remembrances of life on her father’s plantation, her frequent remarks
                concerning her firm connection to her enslaved brethren and her fond descriptions of
                her maid Dido, whose race and pidgin English make clear her enslaved status. In <hi
                    rend="italic">Mansfield Park</hi>, the masking is provided by Fanny’s
                translation of her uncle’s business concerns into a paternal treatment of his
                enslaved workers stemming from his moral rectitude. When triangulated with Leonora
                Sansay’s short novel <hi rend="italic">Secret History; or, The Horrors of St.
                    Domingo </hi>(also 1808), this covering over is unmasked. The white American
                narrator Mary, visiting with her sister Clara in 1803, makes frequent criticisms of
                the behavior and regulation of different castes of women, from “coloured women” in
                general contrast to “white women,” to distinctions between “Mulatto” women
                (light-skinned biracial women), Creoles (white women born in St. Domingue, soon to
                be Haiti), French women (immigrants and visitors from France), and outsiders like
                Mary. Not only are women of Domingue castes regulated by sartorial distinctions, but
                “here every female virtue is blasted in the bud by the contagious influence of
                example” (Sansay 96).</p>
                
            <p>As Sansay presents it, the very Caribbean air taints moral choice since sexual
                attraction alone determines women’s (limited) agency, so that “the mulatto women are
                the hated but successful rivals of the Creole ladies,” for they not only appear to
                be sexier but are also often wealthy: “before the revolution their splendor, their
                elegance, their influence over the men, and the fortunes lavished on them by their
                infatuated lovers, so powerfully excited the jealousy of the white ladies, that they
                complained to the council of the ruin their [“mulatto” women’s] extravagance
                occasioned to many [white] families, and a decree was issued imposing restrictions
                on their dress” (Sansay 95).<note place="foot" resp="author">
                        Mary doesn’t seem to know that “Mulatto” wealth more usually came from sons
                        inheriting land and money from their white fathers. She also doesn’t
                        acknowledge Noirs (persons of African birth, freed by Toussaint’s
                        revolution), or most of the other caste divisions that regulated Domingue
                        life.</note> Contrasted with the decadence of sexually explicit
                behavior is the novel’s real focus on political revolution; Toussaint’s
                post-revolutionary reign is looked forward to as utopian in comparison to the
                invading French forces, there to support the white plantation owners. The armed
                forces’ destructive violence is mirrored in acts of male sexual aggression,
                exemplified in the rape of Mary’s sister Clara by her abusive husband, St. Louis.
                Sex and politics come together in <hi rend="italic">Secret History</hi> in a manner
                that turns the lens on <hi rend="italic">The</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Woman of Colour</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mansfield Park</hi>:
                suddenly students can realize how the sexual politics of those novels divide out
                into sexual aggression, the politics of race, and the loss of any moral compass when
                wealth depends on the unacknowledged suffering of enslaved laborers. </p>
                
            <p> To provide a real-life component to this fictional unit that ties it back to the
                real life narratives of Prince, Equiano and Toussaint, I include here the first
                chapter of Sharpe’s<hi rend="italic">In the Wake</hi>.Sharpe’s
                meditations on, and theorization of, the historical effects of colonial schemes of
                skin color symbolism that Wynter analyzes yoke thedevelopment of colonial economies
                based on unpaid and enslaved labor. Sharpe’s reflections on her own and her family’s
                experience of the colonial symbolics of skin color (registered in Sansay’s
                delineation of the higher levels of St. Domingue’s caste system) illustrate so
                clearly how the colonial economy continues to mark the daily life of African
                Americans now. In the wake of the triangle slave trade, “the past that is not past
                reappears, always, to rupture the present” (Sharpe 9). Sharpe’s narrative, with its
                rhetorical insistence on the past’s ongoing harm, does more to make the connections
                between fiction and real-life narratives than news reports alone can do. As Sharpe
                notes, “Transatlantic slavery was and is the disaster” (5). Adding Sharpe’s critical
                reflections intermixed with personal narrative has the advantage of pulling the
                narrative and fictional units together because it enables further conversation about
                the economic and emotional risks of living in, and in the wake of, the triangle
                slave trade. This relates to Wynter’s analysis, which allows a conversation about
                colonial economies as a discourse concerning one’s relative worth. The question of
                personal versus fictionalized experience becomes a way to avoid simply comparing
                different encounters of slave and colonial life, racial prejudice, and degrees of
                gender violence; instead this comparison allows readers to triangulate and thus
                revisit/revise these three elements of the slave trade that the two units raise,
                allowing additional questions, such as one of inclusion/exclusion: who is an
                insider, we could ask, and who is excluded in the system of colonial economy?
                Prince, Equiano and Olivia present different kinds of outsider status, for instance.
                Moreover, female characters’ treatment at the hands of (usually white) men provides
                a quite different way to think about movement as well as of the stormy violence of
                the colonial economy, and requires thinking harder about the movement through the
                color caste system in both British and French colonial and post-colonial life. </p>
                
            <p> Regardless of the texts selected to teach students how to see the experience of
                enslaved persons as belonging to lives that mattered, what has made the most
                difference in teaching this topic has been to find ways to make historical texts
                relevant.In order to move beyond that framework, I have begun working with current
                events and Afrofuturism. A useful supplemental text for exploring Afrofuturism is an
                essay by the award-winning novelist N.K. Jemisin, “How Long ’til Black Future
                Month?,” which provides a quick introduction to the main ideas of Afrofuturism.<note
                   place="foot" resp="author"> This is also the title of a collection of
                    short stories by Jemisin, who is best known for her three-times Hugo-award
                    winning <hi rend="italic">Broken Earth </hi>trilogy.</note> Beginning with
                Octavia Butler (who coined the term Afrofuturism), science fiction has been the main
                genre for Afrofuturist literature and film; these are texts that recast enslavers
                and colonists through the sci-fi tradition of encounter narratives.<note
                    place="foot" resp="author">
                    H. G. Wells's <hi rend="italic">The Time Machine</hi>(1895), <hi
                        rend="italic">The War of the Worlds</hi>(1898) and <hi
                        rend="italic">The First Men in the Moon</hi> (1901) established the
                        tradition. Andre Norton’s 1960s series and Arthur C. Clarke’s “Time Odyssey”
                        series are well-known first encounter narratives.</note> An easily
                referenced text for teaching is the 2018 film <hi rend="italic">Black Panther,
                </hi>in which the imbrication of past, present and future is clearly dramatized. In
                the film, the villain (Klaue) is depicted as an archetypal white adventurer
                despoiling African resources, but rather than European he is clearly meant to
                suggest a heritage from the two Boer states of colonial Africa, with their brutal
                treatment of those inhabiting what is now South Africa. Black Panther’s (T’Challa)
                defeat of this despoiler revises the historical first encounter with white
                enslavers; instead we have a failed encounter that strengthens the progressive
                futurism of the Wakanda nation. This is not the best example, however, since Klaue
                should have been colonized by the Wakandan citizens, so asking students why Klaue’s
                death at the hands of T’Challa is a departure from AfroFuturism helps them see how
                easy it is to accept more pasteurized versions of Black narratives. </p>
                
            <p>“First encounter” narratives, made standard through works such as H.G. Wells’s <hi
                    rend="italic">The War of the Worlds</hi>, merge with “second encounter”
                narratives so that the slave trade and colonial past is the pattern through which
                alien encounter is perceived, with the alien becoming the colonized victim of such
                thinking, and yet like the historical enslaved person, a victim who bears gifts (to
                historical enslaved people’s cultural and ideological gifts, these imagined aliens
                add technological and politically liberating gifts). Contrasting this model with the
                plot of <hi rend="italic">Black Panther</hi> allowed my students to view Equiano’s
                representation of slavery, kind masters, and British political elites as pasteurized
                rather than simply self-serving (as students often read his narrative). Most
                importantly, connecting the texts they are studying with the regulative idea of
                Afrofuturism—that sovereign nations need the induction of alien life in order to
                become even more democratic, free, and at peace—allows students to consider the
                problem of both individual sovereignty and national sovereignty as the product of
                fluidity and movement. It is not a given, it can be taken away, and it must always
                be put into conversation with the interrelatedness of ocean and land. </p>
                
            <p> In revisiting Equiano’s narrative after the<hi rend="italic">Black Panther</hi>
                exercise, I focused class discussion on the plan for a free Black state in Sierra
                Leone that Equiano participates in near the very end of his narrative; my students
                were able to rethink the potential of such a scheme while also understanding it as a
                charity scheme rather than a utopian one (it is planned by “some philanthropic
                individuals,” [<hi rend="italic">Equiano, </hi>242]). Pitting this scheme, devised
                by white politicians, against the utopian nation of Wakanda also helps us see why
                Equiano would have been so wary of the project: it lacks Wakanda’s
                self-determination arising from individual participation <hi rend="italic">and</hi>
                the necessary funding and resources (individual sovereignty <hi rend="italic"
                    >and</hi> national sovereignty). Through the contextualizing lens of
                AfroFuturism, my students came to the recognition that any settlement, however
                utopian, displaces those who already inhabit the land, disturbing the eco-balance of
                lives lived for both the established inhabitants and for the newcomers. In other
                words, the past can’t be undone by charity and welfare schemes; the hard work has to
                be done here in this place, as both the Abolitionist materials and the lesson of
                Wakanda’s self-determination make clear. A useful discussion point is already
                provided here in thinking about our own future regarding territorialization
                practices versus Atlantic fluidity, the circulation and triangulations of persons
                and things versus the requirement for self-determination and lives well lived. </p>
                
            <p> Just as the slave trade fueled white liberationist politics in both Britain’s
                American colonies and Revolutionary France, so too has it grounded and set the stage
                for the more expansive empire through an increasingly laissez-faire liberally
                sanctioned world economy. Students begin to see the relation between things as they
                are and the horrifying, daily violence of the exchange in enslaved persons as
                mercantile objects, lives that simply did not matter. The necessity of teaching
                about the slave trade and the experience of enslavement alongside the heroized
                narratives of Abolitionist political labor, can be empowering in that it allows for
                the possibility of thinking about the future otherwise than in a traumatic and
                posthuman way. Certainly, we must ask what will prevail in the Atlantic world when
                environmental damage extols too much from the human habitations of the Caribbean? Or
                when the coastal cities and other human developments in the circum-Atlantic are
                submerged or simply destroyed? But a sense of play, of fluid thinking and boundaries
                allowsspace for students to imagine a different world-making from the one we have
                known and that currently goes on without our much noticing. It allows for thinking
                about different kinds of heroism, different ways of achieving self-determination
                against the apparently unstoppable weight of globalism. It allows for considering
                the ship in a stormy sea: fluidity and flexibility are the necessary survival
                skills, but they must be combined with a persistence to endure, a Mary Prince-like
                self-heroism, and a Toussaint-like tolerance. It seems to me that Atlanticism is
                poised to locate such an imagination, if we allow its triangulatory effects room to
                do this kind of work. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
