<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<!-- got rid of file description, encoding descriptions, and editorial declarations (do we need/want to move this info to the "about" section of the site) -->                   
               
    
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title type="main">David Bowie and the Legacies of Romanticism</title>
                    <title type="a">“I Can’t Give
                        Everything Away”: David Bowie and Post-Romantic Artistic Identity</title>
                    <author><name>Matthew Sangster</name></author>
                    <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>General Editor,</resp>
                        <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>General Editor,</resp>
                        <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>Praxis Series Editor</resp>
                        <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                    </respStmt>
                </titleStmt>
                <editionStmt>
                    <edition><date>2022-07-25</date></edition>
                </editionStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado,
                        Boulder</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                    <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                            or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                            purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                            use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
                        <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                            are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                            with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                            permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                            requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                            notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
                            forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
                                <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                                <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                                <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                                <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                                <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                                <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                            </address></p>
                        <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                            conditions: <list>
                                <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                    without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                                <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                    other than their current ones.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                            them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                            have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                            Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                            continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                            generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                            a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                            use.</p>
                    </availability>
                    <idno type="edition">praxis.2022.bowie.sangster</idno>
                    <idno type="resource">bowie</idno>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a" type="main">“I Can’t Give
                                Everything Away”: David Bowie and Post-Romantic Artistic Identity</title>
                            <author role="secondary">
                                <persName>
                                    <forename>Matthew</forename>
                                    <surname>Sangster</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                            <ptr
                                target="https://romantic-circles.org/praxis/bowie/praxis.2022.bowie.sangster.html"
                            />
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">“I Can’t Give
                                Everything Away”: David Bowie and Post-Romantic Artistic Identity</title>
                            <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of
                                    Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2022-07-25">July 25, 2022</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
            <encodingDesc>
                <editorialDecl>
                    <quotation>
                        <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for
                            &#226;&#8364;&#339;," for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
                    </quotation>
                    <hyphenation eol="none">
                        <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
                        <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                            keyboard</p>
                        <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
                    </hyphenation>
                    <normalization method="markup">
                        <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                        <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
                            such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                    </normalization>
                    <normalization>
                        <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                        <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
                        <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
                            been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                    </normalization>
                </editorialDecl>
                <tagsDecl>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                        12pt;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
                </tagsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
            <profileDesc>
                <textClass>
                    <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Criticism"/>
                    <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                    <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                    <keywords scheme="https://www.romantic-circles.org">
                        <term subtype="tags">cyberpunk</term>
                        <term subtype="tags">Vodoo</term>
                    </keywords>
                </textClass>
            </profileDesc>
            
            
            <!-- deleted the Nines information and the profile description -->
            
            <revisionDesc>
                <change>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                    <date>July 13, 2022</date>
                    <list>
                        <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                    </list>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
        <div type="abstract">
            <p rend="noCount">The developments of the Romantic period set the stage for modern
                framings of art and the artist, establishing powerful institutionalized discourses
                that both created the privileged spaces in which art is presumed to operate and
                reified the special modes of authority that Romantic poetry and poets had claimed.
                However, these discourses have never been set in stone. Instead, subsequent
                practitioners have negotiated and renegotiated them in making their selves and
                works. While the rock stars of the sixties did so principally through amplification,
                David Bowie established a more skeptical relationship with Romantic notions of art
                and artistry. His mastery of mediated interaction allowed him to throw himself with
                gusto at the task of expanding the field of the represented and representable, but
                his works also consistently articulate meaningful doubts about the possibility of
                transcendent communication through art. Rather than claiming to reveal truths in the
                manner of high Romantic conceptions, his works place the power to make meanings in
                the hands and minds of his audiences, employing the potency of Romantic vision while
                knowingly undercutting its potential for totalizing imposition.</p>
        </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head>“I Can’t Give
                    Everything Away”: David Bowie and Post-Romantic Artistic Identity</head>
            
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Matthew Sangster</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>University of Glasgow</affiliation>
                </byline>
            
            <p>This essay discusses how David Bowie’s self-conscious
                self-fashioning as an artist drew upon Romantic models created in canonical lyric
                poetry and through the self-presentations and receptions of Romantic poets. His
                practices, I will argue, improved on and critiqued these models’ representational
                potential and complicated their ideals of literary communication, but without
                surrendering their affective impact or their belief in the power and value of art.
                In some respects, Bowie was straightforwardly an heir to many oppositional
                Romantic-period writers, buying in to their collective programme of pushing back the
                boundaries of representation by celebrating atypical forms of experience and
                sociality. However, Bowie’s productions also work to subvert the Romantic paradigm
                that was dominant both in twentieth-century accounts of early-nineteenth-century art
                and within the music scene from which he emerged. Rather than straightforwardly
                proclaiming a triumphant subjectivity, his works challenge the veneration of stars
                by positing forms of artistry that privilege the swapping of masks, the
                fragmentation of canonical identities, and the collaborative interpretative power of
                audiences. In this, we might align him with the more sceptical views expressed by
                younger Romantic writers like Lord Byron, John Keats, and Letitia Landon, who
                sometimes pushed back against the conservative forms of universalizing
                self-aggrandizement they detected in the later work of William Wordsworth and Samuel
                Taylor Coleridge by favouring more contingent and questioning modes of
                self-fashioning. However, with the intellectual and media resources of a further
                century-and-a-half behind him, Bowie was able to go much further than those writing
                in the 1810s, 1820s, and 1830s, creating multiform fractures in his
                self-presentations that made his personas and works radically reinterpretable,
                thereby passing ownership of the powerful affects he evoked to audiences he
                conceived of as being active, dynamic, and involved.</p>
            <p>In discussing Bowie alongside canonical Romantic poetry, I will
                draw out discontinuities as well as considering similitudes. The twentieth-century
                rock song is a different beast than the nineteenth-century lyric poem, both formally
                and in sociocultural terms. The critical frameworks for discussing one form do not
                always transfer seamlessly over to the other. However, examining consonances and
                clashes has a great deal to offer to Romantic Studies and the analysis of popular
                culture. There has been a longstanding tentativeness about discussing Romantic
                legacies beyond making relatively straightforward claims regarding poetic and
                philosophical influences on rarefied forms of art. However, there are good reasons
                to make wider-ranging claims for the continuing popular currency of the modes of
                artistry developed in the early nineteenth century. Many scholars of the Romantic
                period would argue—and I would agree—that it was a time during which the roles of
                literature and artists were fundamentally renegotiated. As we are still living with
                the consequences of that renegotiation, it seems germane to be rather more explicit
                in our discussions of its ongoing pertinence, in order both to better understand the
                culture within which we live and to demonstrate the continuing liveliness of the
                artworks of an age characterized by conflicts between those who attempted radical
                expansions and powerful forces of reaction.</p>
            <p>To set the terms for discussing Bowie’s interactions with the
                legacies of Romanticism, it will first be necessary to engage with the thorny issue
                of exactly what constitutes a Romantic artist. This is at once a relatively simple
                and a very complex matter. An ideal of Romantic artistry centred on the individual
                creative genius, and ostensibly constructed around the Big Six Romantic poets
                (William Blake, Coleridge, Wordsworth, Byron, Percy Shelley, and Keats), is the most
                recognizable and enduring cliché arising from early-nineteenth-century British
                literature, and one that has a considerable influence on how we understand and
                contextualize music and musicians. Discussing rock’s discourses of authenticity,
                David Tetzlaff opines that “Romanticism remains the common language of middle class
                rebelliousness” (115). As well as marking Romanticism’s ongoing currency, Tetzlaff’s
                brief summation does a good job of bringing out some of the contradictions inherent
                in Romantic ideologies. While these can serve to constitute a shared space, that
                space is one implicated in privilege and one from which many of the specificities of
                its purported originators have been bleached away. The compound notion that
                positions the ideated Romantic as an individual indulging Byronic passions while
                producing Wordsworthian lyricism would certainly have horrified both poets.
                Nevertheless, this uneasy yet enticing blend of transgressive iconoclast and
                inspired prophet is one of the dominant cultural legacies of Romantic-period writing
                for society in general and for creative artists in particular—David Bowie included.
                When Bowie was casting around for subjects for the early songs that appeared on <emph>David Bowie</emph> in 1969, Romantic positions came easily to hand.
                The “missionary mystic of peace/love” in “Wild Eyed Boy from Freecloud;” the
                “Thinker” who “sits alone growing older / And so bitter” in “Cygnet Committee;” the
                bohemian “madness” of “An Occasional Dream;” and the “Children of the summer’s end”
                in “Memory of a Free Festival”—all have a distinctively Romantic cast. While
                “Unwashed and Somewhat Slightly Dazed” seems aware of the ironies implicit in
                declarations like “I’m the cream / Of the great utopia dream,” placing the artist
                “Upon the forehead of the age to come” (Keats, “Addressed to the Same” l. 10) is a
                quintessentially Romantic move.</p>
            <p>The notion of Romantic artistry expressed in positionings like
                these continues to inform representations, inspire imitations, condition receptions,
                and invite refutations that oppose its presumptions even as they reinscribe those
                same presumptions through evoking them. While many individual creative artists
                dispute the tenets of Romanticism, the cultural authority of the artist is still
                predicated in large part on their being an individual who is “endued with more
                lively sensibility, more enthusiasm and tenderness, who has a greater knowledge of
                human nature, and a more comprehensive soul, than are supposed to be common among
                mankind” (Wordsworth, “Preface” (1802) xxviiii). While eighteenth-century artists
                commonly purported to be social beings much like the members of their audiences,
                Romantic artists took pains to stress that they saw and felt differently. This
                special capacity for insight was a key justification when nineteenth-century
                institutions began to canonize a heightened notion of artistry, consequently
                allowing literature, in Jon Klancher’s words, to “become a specialized world in its
                own right” (1). While Romantic ideals of artistry were formed partly in opposition
                to older, pragmatic, elite paradigms, their principles of resistance were relatively
                easily normalized within subsequent secular pantheons and systems of cultural
                control. In Michael Löwy and Robert Sayre’s view, Romanticism “represents a revolt
                against the civilization created by capitalism” (19–20), but, as Tetzlaff suggests,
                evocations of this revolt have proved to be very appealing as saleable
                commodities.</p>
            <p>The Romantic paradigm of artistry is, of course, deeply problematic
                for all sorts of reasons, particularly when considered as the defining feature of an
                epoch within which it was an inchoate and oppositional discourse. Jerome McGann and
                Clifford Siskin have shown that the development of Romantic ideals and the adoption
                of the term “Romanticism” were complex and belated phenomena, particularly in a
                British context. The valuable contributions of other scholars, including David
                Higgins, Julian North, and Tom Mole, have demonstrated that the second and third
                quarters of the nineteenth century comprised the most significant period for the
                propagation of the ideals of literary Romanticism. During this period, an unstable
                composite of received social and textual elements compiled from a diverse and
                fractious body of influences was brought to some degree of coherence in the popular
                consciousness through periodical culture, biography, memorialization,
                anthologization, and the rise of institutionalized forms of literature. The most
                familiar versions of Romanticism can be seen as even more recent innovations. Seamus
                Perry has shown that while a “certain archetype of the poet, living in the dreamy
                introverted remoteness of his own consciousness, had been current throughout the
                nineteenth century . . . [a] growing conception of idealism as fundamental to a
                definition of the Romantic” was a phenomenon of the second quarter of the twentieth
                century (7). While the artists of the Romantic period and their productions created
                the conditions for a reconsideration of what an artist was (or should be), this
                reconsideration took a considerable time to bed in, and remains subject to
                reconfigurations.</p>
            <p>The status of Romanticism as an event that continued (and
                continues) to happen across different cultures and circumstances makes it difficult
                to delineate all its attributes with any degree of definitiveness. Nevertheless,
                while a critical analysis can never establish all the things that Romanticism might
                be in its multifarious national, formal, and temporal contexts, it remains possible
                to focus on aspects that sit close to the heart of its fuzzy set of potential
                meanings. One paradigmatic aspect worth considering would be Romanticism’s complex
                alignments with nature, but this does not appear to be a particularly fruitful
                avenue to pursue in discussing Bowie. While Bowies is deeply concerned with human
                nature, he makes sparse reference to the natural world in his oeuvre except as a
                subsidiary to anthropocentric conceptions. In “Eight Line Poem” (1971), for example,
                the “prairie” that the “tactful cactus” surveys is the floor of a room, and “the sun
                that pins the branches to the sky” is defined by its role as “the key to the city.”
                However, another key aspect of Romanticism—its concern with the articulation of
                selves and identities—sits right at the core of Bowie’s art, and it is in this area
                that we can trace some significant continuities and reactions.</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this discussion, I propose to examine Romantic
                identity as operating through two contrary impulses. One of these is expansive,
                seeking to include in literary representations individuals and circumstances
                hitherto excluded. The other is a more introverted and potentially problematic
                impulse that seeks to establish the special qualities of a particular self, often
                either implicitly or explicitly that of the artist. In addressing these
                sequentially, I will seek to show that Bowie’s works often align with and celebrate
                the Romantic impulse towards acceptance and understanding, while also often
                articulating a clear-eyed view of the social and psychological challenges of radical
                forms of empathy. However, Bowie’s work from the seventies onwards consistently
                questions the value of a strongly articulated artistic self, at least when this self
                is articulated in the singular. While Bowie was able to activate a potent form of
                artistic heroism, it was different in its qualities and its emphases from heroic
                visions constructed by the canonical Romantics, although while being so it
                nevertheless employed a number of archetypal Romantic techniques, including the
                fetishization of fragmentation and the glorification of abjection.</p>
            <p>First, though: representation. The centrality of Romantic
                assumptions to modern accounts of artistic value can sometimes make it tricky to
                recover a sense of their genuine radicalism at the time of their initial emergence.
                However, something of the shock of the new can still be discerned through examining
                the scathing critiques authored by advocates of the older systems Romantic thinking
                challenged. A good example is Francis Jeffrey’s review of Robert Southey’s <emph>Thalaba the Destroyer</emph> (1801) in the first number of the <emph>Edinburgh Review</emph>, in which he wrote that the new sect of
                poets he was assessing “seem[ed] to value themselves very highly, for having broken
                loose from the bondage of ancient authority, and re-asserted the independence of
                genius” (63–4). However, for Jeffrey, the Lakers’ supposed declaration of
                independence from a socialized tradition was an embarrassing imposture resulting
                from a fundamental misconception about what poetry was supposed to represent:
            <quote>The love, or grief, or indignation of an enlightened and refined
                character is not only expressed in a different language but is in itself a different
                emotion from the love, or grief, or anger of a clown, a tradesman or a market-wench.
                The things themselves are radically and obviously distinct; and the representation
                of them is calculated to convey a very different train of sympathies and sensations
                to the mind. The question, therefore, comes simply to be—which of them is the most
                proper object for poetical imitation? (66)</quote>
            For Jeffrey, needless to say, the rural, dejected, exotic, and
                psychological objects selected by Wordsworth, Coleridge, and Southey were decidedly
                improper. In the world that the <emph>Edinburgh</emph> sought to
                legitimate and defend, poetry was principally a refined form of communication within
                a dominant class. In that role, it served as both an embodiment of that class’s
                values and a validator of its right to rule. The notion of poetry that Jeffrey
                sought to reinforce was essentially imitative, rather than creative in an expansive
                or imaginative sense. Consequently, Jeffrey saw Wordsworth’s “perverted taste for
                simplicity” (68) as a monstrous imposition on polite readers that broke down
                necessary boundaries between classes and nonsensically evoked the priorities of
                people from whom poets differed in fundamental and irreconcilable manners.</p>
            <p>In making these assertions, Jeffrey was echoing a common position,
                and one on which Whiggish and more conservative commentators anxiously agreed.
                Introducing the fourth and final dialogue of his satire
                <emph>The Pursuits of Literature</emph> (published in
                parts between 1794 and 1797 and first published in full in 1798), Thomas James
                Mathias mixed an ambivalent recognition of progress with contempt and concern,
                opining that:
            <quote>We no longer look exclusively for learned authors in the usual
                place, in the retreats of academic erudition, and in the seats of religion. Our
                peasantry now read the <emph>Rights of Man</emph> on mountains, and moors,
                and by the way side; and shepherds make the analogy between their occupation and
                that of their governors. (238)</quote>
            While the full emergence of a genuinely expansive reading public is
                better dated to the 1820s than the 1790s, Mathias’s account makes it clear that the
                fear of new readers and writers was becoming a potent force. Those who strutted on
                the stage of culture were intensely aware of the growing ranks of other actors and
                of increasingly copious, inscrutable, and potentially demanding audiences.
                Commentators like Mathias figured this plenitude as fundamentally destructive: “The
                objects of publick regret and offence are
                <emph>now</emph> so numerous and so complicated, that
                all the milder offices of the Muse have lost their influence and attraction”
                (250).</p>
            <p>Mathias’s pronouncements are strikingly similar in tone to
                Wordsworth’s contention in the 1800 “Preface” to <emph>Lyrical
                    Ballads</emph> that “The invaluable works of our elder writers, I had almost said
                the works of Shakespear and Milton, are driven into neglect by frantic novels,
                sickly and stupid German Tragedies, and deluges of idle and extravagant stories in
                verse” (xix). Such similitudes demonstrate that Wordsworth was in certain ways quite
                a conventional and conservative thinker when it came to addressing cultural change,
                pressured by what Lucy Newlyn has accurately characterized as an intense anxiety of
                reception. However, his impulse in the face of a perceived expansion of the literary
                franchise was not to retrench established privilege, like Jeffrey and Mathias, but
                rather to experiment with new positionings. This was by no means a wholehearted
                embrace of new media forms and audiences—it was in many respects a form of
                resistance—but it was a response that was fundamentally creative. While his
                essentialist evocation of “great and permanent objects” (xix) ostensibly models a
                return to fundamental values, Wordsworth’s rhetorically locating these fundamental
                values in “common life” (x) enacted a paradigm shift in terms of what art could take
                as its subjects. In the eyes of more traditional commentators, Wordsworth’s solution
                to cultural desensitization was worse than the problem. However, for the acolytes
                and popularizers who spread his reputation through the same burgeoning print culture
                that he feared, Wordsworth succeeded in reflecting subjectivities not hitherto made
                available in art. In seeing this as a triumph, his advocates began the process of
                rewriting the rules by which artistry was henceforward to be judged.</p>
            <p>Discussing Jeffrey’s <emph>Thalaba</emph> review, Robert
                Miles contends that Jeffrey suspiciously detected “a striving towards the
                representation of the full otherness of others, which naturally begged the question
                of the social and political entitlements of others” (82). It seems safe to say that
                while Jeffery’s Whigs and the conservative establishment disapproved of such
                strivings, a radical expansion of the boundaries of representation in literature is
                one of the unambiguously great achievements catalysed by Romantic-period practices.
                Romantic and post-Romantic art has trumpeted the artist’s ability imaginatively to
                sympathize and encompass, changing formerly improper objects into recognized
                subjects. We might choose centrally canonical cases to exemplify this, such as
                Wordsworth’s connection with the spirit of nature at Tintern Abbey, or Blake’s
                evocations of London’s poor, or Byron’s glamorization of literal and emotional
                outlaws. However, such expansions are far from being solely the province of the Big
                Six. We might as easily consider sympathetic subjectivities in instances such as
                Charlotte Smith’s taking creative possession of Petrarch and Werther in her <emph>Elegiac Sonnets</emph>; or the bird and animal consciousnesses that
                John Clare creates; or Ann Radcliffe’s explorations of how it feels to fear or
                control; or Jane Austen’s subtle craft of human gradation. By being perceived as
                expanding the range of representable subjectivities, these writers’ works—regardless
                of their authors’ political stances—played important roles in emancipating artistic
                practice from implicitly endorsing prevailing systems of social superiority.
                Post-Romantic art claims both the world and the mind as its purview, justifying
                itself through asserting its ability to see differently and draw new connections.
                While in practice art can never wholly escape social and cultural conventions, the
                developments of the Romantic period saw it repositioned as a critical and
                experimental process whose practitioners were granted licence to push back the
                boundaries of expression and empathy. The artist was no longer a custodian of
                established forms, but rather a forger of new modes for appreciating things formerly
                neglected, misunderstood, or despised.</p>
            <p>Positioning Bowie as part of this tradition of liberation is
                relatively straightforward. Much of his work is heavily invested in parody,
                appropriation, and reinvention, but in his hands, these become means for opening up
                formerly closed systems and mindsets. A fairly obvious example would be “Lady
                Stardust” (1972):<quote><lg type="stanza">
            <l>People stared at the makeup on his face</l>
            <l>Laughed at his long black hair, his animal grace</l>
            <l>The boy in the bright blue jeans</l>
            <l>Jumped up on the stage</l>
            <l>And Lady Stardust sang his songs</l>
            <l>Of darkness and disgrace</l></lg></quote>
            The laughter in the second line of this first verse could be read
                as mockery, but the tone allows for delight too, and it is clear from the chorus
                refrain—“he was alright”—that while Lady Stardust’s performance challenges some
                members of the imagined audience, it nevertheless works as art, in part because it
                challenges. While “I smiled sadly for a love I could not obey” in the second verse
                looks back in a somewhat retrogressive manner to the cliché of “the love that dare
                not speak its name,” the reaction remains one of strong admiration, and the femme
                fatales and boys described in the previous lines constitute a crowd that is mixed,
                engaged, and itself composed of performers.</p>
            <p>As “Lady Stardust” shows, Bowie’s art pushes the value of the
                idiosyncratic, the formerly excluded, and the potentially improper. Sometimes this
                investment manifests lyrically in surreal declarations that communicate despite
                themselves. While there is no pre-established poetic context for parsing what Bowie
                means when he declares “I’m an alligator” at the beginning of “Moonage Daydream”
                (1972)—or to explain exactly what “squawking like a pink monkey bird” might
                entail—the song is a come-on made more intriguing by its fascinating crypticisms.
                Other Bowie lyrics explicitly defend neglected subjectivities. When in “Changes”
                (1971) Bowie describes “these children that you spit on / As they try to change
                their worlds,” the plural “worlds” is significant, acknowledging myriad valuable
                subjectivities, rather than Jeffrey’s singular “proper object.” The supposed
                children’s creative capacities serve to grant them liberty and self-awareness:
                “They’re immune to your consultations / They’re quite aware of what they’re going
                through.” Similarly, when Bowie asks who will love Aladdin Sane (the title character
                of his 1973 album), this is a call for a potentially impossible form of empathy,
                rather than a sneering objection. Like most pop music, Bowie’s oeuvre is shot
                through with desire, but desire in Bowie is multiple, thwarted, and shifting. His
                lyrics generally refuse to lay out one rule for the refined or to demarcate an
                in-crowd without considering who this might exclude. Instead, his songs present a
                series of possible masks that can be worn authentically despite their capacity for
                being shucked off.</p>
            <p>While Bowie might be seen as drawing on discourses rooted in
                Romanticism in moments such as these, his methods of communicating his artistry
                arguably represent a considerable improvement on those available to
                early-nineteenth-century poets and novelists. The mechanics of print production
                before the second quarter of the nineteenth century meant that even the most
                successful literary writers of the Romantic period addressed restricted and affluent
                readerships during their lifetimes, although their posthumous Victorian audiences
                were far more extensive. However, even the late-nineteenth-century reading audience
                was small by the standards of those that could be reached by singers in the
                mid-twentieth century. By the 1960s, the potential existed, in John Lennon’s words,
                for musicians to be “more popular than Jesus” (Cleave), in large part due to the
                range of media forms through which they could engage with their audiences. No longer
                were communications largely limited to written words, still visual images, and
                performances reliant on direct personal proximity; now, recorded and transmitted
                sound and vision allowed for a panoply of new forms of interaction. As a
                performative rock star in an age of mass media, the representational potential
                immediately available to Bowie was far greater than that accorded to his writerly
                Romantic forebears, in terms of both the forms he could employ and the audiences he
                could reach. He may not have had long black hair, but it was clear that he had
                makeup on his face when he sang “Lady Stardust” and its brethren to audiences of
                thousands in theatres; it was similarly obvious when he projected himself to
                millions through carefully designed records and TV appearances that deliberately
                distorted the line between stagecraft and self. By committing to visual and personal
                performance as well as lyric selves, Bowie was able to blur towards a key ideal of
                musical Romanticism: the Wagnerian total artwork—although, as I will go on to
                discuss, his manners of expression undercut the claims to universal importance that
                are often associated with this term.</p>
            <p>Romantic-period authors commonly attempted to be parsimonious with
                their biographical significations, seeking carefully to control their images.
                Wordsworth, in particular, expressed considerable frustration when he was
                refashioned by essayists like William Hazlitt and Thomas De Quincey. By contrast,
                Bowie, with the full resources of a postmodern perspective available to him, was
                able to take a more magnanimous approach. Recognizing the impossibility and
                undesirability of policing all the ways in which he might be interpreted, he instead
                multiplied himself in manners that were “open to limitless interpretations of
                meaning” (Morley 462). This proved to be an extremely effective strategy in
                commercial, aesthetic, and affective terms. As Shelley wrote enviously and somewhat
                hyperbolically of Byron in 1822, Bowie’s multifarious representations “touched a
                chord to which a million hearts responded”
                (<emph>Letters</emph> II:436).</p>
            <p>A crucial aspect of the media environment into which Bowie emerged
                was the space it provided for his audiences to co-author the meanings of his works
                in manners that were far more comprehensive than those available in the early
                nineteenth century. As David Baker puts it, “Bowie as rock star/artist functions in
                a pop/rock economy of alliance and commonality” (111). Byron and Wordsworth were
                certainly imitated, and Byron in particular—along with his publishers and
                collaborators—was a pioneer in developing what Tom Mole has characterized as a
                hermeneutic of intimacy. However, what Bowie could achieve was on a different scale.
                Rebuking a newspaper article that describes Byron as having drawn “hordes of
                screaming young women,” Mole contends accurately that these hordes “were spliced
                into Byron’s story from an entirely different cultural memory. They screamed not for
                Byron but for the Beatles” (2007 xi). While the media environment was opening up
                during the 1810s and 1820s, writers in this period were by no means as readily
                available for appropriation as twentieth-century artists who positioned themselves
                knowingly within a constellation of magazines, television appearances, costume
                designers, other musicians, movements, newspapers, controversies, personal
                interactions, radio broadcasts, sleeves, vinyl, and technology.</p>
            <p>Fans responded to this cornucopia of stimuli both through forming
                shared interpretive communities and through valuing particular irreducible
                specifics. Bowie’s productions proved to possess an enormous capacity for conjuring
                feelings of affinity. In Nick Stevenson’s words, fans reacted to Bowie and his works
                by employing them for “the creation of meaning through diverse patterns of
                identification” (149). Creative audiences were able to use Bowie’s multivalent
                capacities to transcend dominant media narratives. Patrick Glen, examining Bowie’s
                outing himself as bisexual in the <emph>Melody Maker</emph> in 1972,
                argues that while reportage often attempted to position the singer and his
                characters within constrained traditions of queer expression, Bowie’s use of
                “references drawn from complex scenes that could accommodate a number of narratives,
                symbols, individual and sexual identities” meant that “[t]hose who had not
                encountered these scenes . . . could appropriate elements of Bowie’s identity and
                references for themselves” (423). John Gill writes similarly that Bowie provided a
                powerful and outrageous, if not unproblematic, model for gay identity “at a time
                when queer appearances in the media tended to be in the form of arrests and police
                statistics” (110). Bowie was by no means always an ideal role model; as Will Brooker
                has pointed out, certain performances, such as “China Girl” (1983, although written
                earlier for Iggy Pop), can rightly be challenged for their uncomfortable cultural
                appropriations (98–100). Nevertheless, the kinds of fan responses recorded by
                Stevenson, Glen, Gill, and thousands upon thousands of articles, conversations,
                comments, forum posts, Tumblr memes, and blogs make it clear that Bowie’s modes of
                expression have often been received as being enormously liberating. While Bowie was
                not wholly responsible for the emancipatory potential of his self-presentations, he
                was nevertheless a master manipulator of the forms available to him, creating spaces
                for alternative subjectivities. These subjectivities were modelled at least in part
                on Romantic exemplars (in a few cases explicitly, as with Screaming Lord Byron, as
                Emily Bernhard-Jackson has discussed (2018)). However, these were often cleverly
                subverted by new contrasts and contexts. The affordances of modern media forms
                enabled Bowie to expand considerably on the Romantics’ accomplishments in terms of
                visibility, ease of transmission, and potential for immediate remediation.</p>
            <p>Bowie’s approaches to core Romantic concerns might also be seen as
                improvements in other respects. While we would now reject the exclusionary
                conservatism in Jeffrey’s <emph>Thalaba</emph> review, we might
                nevertheless recognize his accuracy in contending that the discourses of Romanticism
                are often intrinsically egocentric. There is a crucial contradiction at the heart of
                Romantic artistry between expanding the range of possible representations and
                focusing in on the special minds that performatively accomplish these expansions.
                This contradiction is implicit in Keats’s ideal of “<emph>Negative
                    Capability</emph>, that is when a man is capable of being in uncertainties,
                Mysteries, doubts, without any irritable reaching after fact &amp; reason” (<emph>Letters</emph> I:193). While the notion of negative capability is
                ostensibly focused on avoiding certain kinds of overdetermination, the evocation of
                uncertainties in Romantic poetry nearly always connotes a viewing consciousness,
                privileging the discriminating powers of the artist. This privileging of the
                artistic consciousness is a quintessentially Romantic phenomenon. In no previous era
                would it have been tenable to write an epic poem whose central subject was the
                “growth of a poet’s mind” (Wordsworth, <emph>Prelude</emph>) or to claim
                in all seriousness that “poets are the unacknowledged legislators of the World”
                (Shelley, “Defence” 535). Shelley and Wordsworth may have differed on a great number
                of issues, but they were united in ferociously exalting the power of the poetic
                self. In his sonnet “To Wordsworth” (1816), Shelley valorizes a “Poet of Nature” (l.
                1) who has the sublime ability to rise above “the blind and battling multitude” (l.
                10) through weaving “Songs consecrate to truth and liberty” (l. 12). Of course,
                Shelley goes on to add, “Deserting these, thou leavest me to grieve, / Thus having
                been, that thou shouldst cease to be” (ll. 13–4). Perhaps these final lines might
                helpfully be read an early-nineteenth-century equivalent of the betrayed Bob Dylan
                fan yelling “Judas!” at the Manchester Free Trade Hall—an attack that criticises a
                perceived swerve from genuine art into falsity. However, while Shelley and
                Wordsworth differed regarding the appropriate politics <emph>for</emph>
                art, they essentially concurred regarding the politics <emph>of</emph>
                art. Romantic artists might express doubts about their sociocultural effectiveness,
                but in both Shelley and Wordsworth’s visions and versions, they possess the ability
                and the responsibility to “see into the life of things” (“Tintern Abbey” l. 50) and
                be seen as reporting back authentically and comprehensively.</p>
            <p> Crucially for the purposes of this essay, this is an ideal of
                artistry that Bowie’s work at once partly endorses and utterly undercuts, showing it
                to be simultaneously absolutely ersatz and absolutely true. For Bowie, as he worked
                through a series of characters and selves compromised by recognizably Romantic
                maladies, such as self-love, madness, and addiction, the artist was simultaneously a
                visionary and a fraud. A paradigm of authentic inauthenticity lies at the heart of
                his artistic practice, which rebukes key aspects of the Romantic paradigm while
                preserving its affective charge.</p>
            <p>In seeking to become a rock star, Bowie was working in a tradition
                that often drew uncritically on the legacies of Romantic artistic exceptionalism. We
                might think here of Mick Jagger quoting <emph>Adonaïs</emph> at the Brian
                Jones memorial concert in 1969. By intoning some of Shelley’s least ambivalent
                stanzas, Jagger claimed Jones as an exemplary paragon for a vast corporeal and media
                audience. Bowie was a keen if slightly alienated observer of such spectacles. Unlike
                some sixties stars, whose careers blazed to life with astonishing quickness—but like
                many of the poets of the Romantic period who later became established as
                canonical—Bowie had to struggle to refine his own radical artistry into forms that
                would communicate, a process that entailed the development of an intense kind of
                self-reflexivity that we might liken to negative capability. However, in Bowie’s
                case, assertions about insights and performed processes of doubt are commonly
                alloyed with a reflexive irony. As Shelton Waldrep put it when discussing the
                aesthetics of self-invention, “Bowie’s famed artificiality sprang from a desire to
                reject the immediate history of rock music”
                (<emph>Aesthetics</emph> 106). We might extend this
                insight to other forms of discourse that insist on the authority of authenticity.
                Bowie was very uncomfortable with the idea of legislating the world, and through
                staging his discomfort in a plethora of different manners, he encouraged his
                audience to think about the limits of his powers of communication and the
                possibility that the performances he put on might as easily mislead as lead.</p>
            <p>A good early example of Bowie’s suspicious staging of his artistic
                self can be found in a key lyric from “Changes”:<quote><lg type="stanza">
            <l>So I turned myself to face me</l>
            <l>But I’ve never caught a glimpse</l>
            <l>Of how the others must see the faker</l>
            <l>I’m much too fast to take that test</l></lg></quote>
            “Changes” presents a vision of identity both more fluid and more
                playful than that found in stereotypical Romantic discourse. Rather than being the
                subject of infinite contemplations, the self slips easily out of view, proving
                impossible to pin down. The song recognizes that the identity others see must always
                be falsified to a certain extent and must always remain in some respects ineffable
                to its possessor. In this paradigm, the outpourings of self that Romantic poems
                imagine are not valuable because they genuinely communicate lucid truths; rather,
                their value lies in their evoking the possibility of such powerfully affective
                communications. For Bowie, the vision of transcendent, authentic correspondence that
                Romantic art holds out should not be accepted as a totalizing paradigm, and neither
                should it inevitably be seen as admirable. In his work, space is created for the
                audience and the artist to appropriate, misunderstand, and move onward. An
                unintended or misconceived meaning need not be any less powerful than an intended
                one, and painstakingly seeking to draw distinctions is a slow game to play when you
                can just communicate again with a different mask. When Bowie tells his audience in
                “D.J.” (1979) “I am what I play,” he evokes the ease with which art can efface
                identity, but also its capacity for being duplicated, reconfigured, and shared—for
                meaning different things to different people at different times and in different
                places. While the Romantic artist is capable of being in uncertainties, Bowie is
                prepared to replace the self who performs the balancing of these uncertainties with
                a kaleidoscope of different possibilities, without any irritable reaching after
                definitiveness. Through doing so, he captures a vast range of contingent forms of
                originality that model character as being lambent and mutable, rather than centred
                and cerebral.</p>
            <p>The extent to which Bowie’s self-presentations differ from strong
                Romantic evocations of the self might be demonstrated by contrasting a poem like
                Shelley’s “Ode to the West Wind” (written in 1819) with a lyric like Bowie’s
                “Quicksand” (1971). Both these works deal with an element of nature often depicted
                as being difficult to grasp, but they approach these elements in ideologically
                disparate manners. Shelley’s “Ode” is a powerful act of shamanism with a singular
                focus. The first three stanza pile up calls and invocations, a constant stream of
                addresses that conjure the wind in its various aspects and locales before seeking
                tightly to align it with the poet’s own identity. Shelley ostensibly recognizes his
                separation from the wind in his showy falling away onto the “thorns of life” (l.
                54), but the echoes of Christlike suffering point towards a rise and a resurrection
                for one self-confessedly “tameless, and swift, and proud” (l. 56). In the final
                stanza, Shelley completes a comprehensive process of identification and alignment,
                first imagining the wind sounding through him, harrowing him into a pure voice, and
                then imploring it to become the best part of his self-as-poet:<quote><lg type="stanza">
            <l>Make me thy lyre, even as the forest is:</l>
            <l>What if my leaves are falling like its own!</l>
            <l>The tumult of thy mighty harmonies</l>
            <l>Will take from both a deep, autumnal tone,</l>
            <l>Sweet though in sadness. Be thou, Spirit fierce,</l>
            <l>My spirit! Be thou me, impetuous one!</l>
            <l>Drive my dead thoughts over the universe</l>
            <l>Like wither’d leaves to quicken a new birth!</l>
            <l>And, by the incantation of this verse,</l>
            <l>Scatter, as from an unextinguish’d hearth</l>
            <l>Ashes and sparks, my words among mankind!</l>
            <l>Be through my lips to unawaken’d earth</l>
            <l>The trumpet of a prophecy! O Wind,</l>
            <l>If Winter comes, can Spring be far behind? (ll. 57–70)</l></lg></quote>
            Shelley’s megalomaniacal focus reaches its apotheosis in this
                moment, where the poet and the poem become one, encoding in being so the seeds of a
                revolution modelled as being necessarily eventually successful.</p>
            <p>This visionary mode, despite its potency and attractiveness, is one
                regarding which Bowie’s works display considerable suspicion. While he sometimes
                employs the abject manner that Shelley assays in the penultimate stanza of the
                “Ode,” he is not generally willing to crash through to the kinds of transcendence
                modelled in the final stanza, at least not without encoding a substantial degree of
                ambivalence. The subjects Bowie addresses commonly prove to be unresponsive or
                treacherous. When he breathes words into the void on a key track from <emph>Station to Station</emph> (1976)—“Lord, I kneel and offer you / My
                word on a wing / And I’m trying hard to fit among / Your scheme of things”—the song
                ends with doubts as to whether the singer’s struggles can ever be successfully
                reconciled with eternal verities: “Does my prayer fit in with your scheme of
                things?” Time in “Time” (1973) is a toxic and unreliable muse, who “speaks of
                senseless things,” demands the lives of friends, and attenuates the bonds of
                relationships. In the song bearing his name (1971), Andy Warhol is just as capable
                of doing “jolly boring” things as he is of looking “a scream”, and ultimately, he
                cannot be differentiated from a “Silver Screen”: he represents a mode of artistic
                reflection, but not of a kind that provides definitive answers.</p>
            <p> Lyrics that maintain a single subject of address in the manner of
                Shelley’s most famous lines, or Keats’s odes, or (perhaps more in theory than in
                practice) Coleridge’s conversation poems are relatively uncommon among Bowie’s
                oeuvre. Instead, he often flickers from image to image even in brief songs, creating
                effects through collage or accumulation rather than the careful delineation of a
                central presence. In “Quicksand,” he begins by evoking hermetic modes of order—“I’m
                closer to the Golden Dawn / Immersed in Crowley’s uniform / Of imagery”—but these
                opening lines already contain crucial degrees of deflection and alienation very
                different from Romantic reachings-out. Closer is not the same as part of, a uniform
                is not its wearer, and imagery is not that which is represented. Where Shelley longs
                for purity, truth, and authenticity (even while partly recognizing the desperation
                of such an ideal), Bowie suspends himself in a network of suggestions and
                possibilities that rely on allusions to others’ arts and artifices. While Shelley
                begs the wind to be his avatar, Bowie asserts himself as an aspect of wider
                cultures, a being unable to cohere into a position of singular subjectivity or
                devotion:<quote><lg type="stanza">
            <l>I’m the twisted name on Garbo’s eyes</l>
            <l>Living proof of Churchill’s lies, I’m destiny</l>
            <l>I’m torn between the light and dark</l>
            <l>Where others see their targets, divine symmetry</l></lg></quote>
            Nor does the song present this lack of definitive positioning as a
                bad thing. There are moments of paranoia and melodrama in the lyrics of “Quicksand,”
                but these are underpinned by the beauty of the elegant string parts, which evoke a
                kind of harmony that grounds the words’ reflections. Shelley’s verse is desperate to
                validate its writer’s self, to make his utterances truths, to spread across the
                globe what he asserts he knows to be right. By contrast, Bowie’s song cautions
                against certainties. Its reference to the “next bardo” evokes Buddhist notions of
                multiple lives comprising cyclical orders, rather than lines directed forwards. The
                words of the chorus—“Don’t believe in yourself, don’t deceive with belief /
                Knowledge comes with death’s release”—rebuke the kinds of confidence that would seek
                to trumpet forth prophecy. While Shelley’s “Ode” concludes with a question that begs
                a particular answer, the sung part of Bowie’s song ends with voices producing pure,
                open-throated sounds rather than words, fading into pure musicality.</p>
            <p>Through this comparison, I am not seeking to assert that either
                “Quicksand” or “Ode to the West Wind” is a better artwork than the other. Rather, I
                wish to draw out and characterize a difference in their ideological approaches that
                reflects what Bowie rejects and reconfigures from the Romantic project. Romantic
                poems depict their poets as concerned with and capable of locating meaningful
                things. Sometimes these can be captured in aphorisms like “Beauty is truth, truth
                beauty” or “The Child is Father of the Man,” sometimes their assertions are more
                diffuse or allusive, but in either case, the Romantic poems that have been
                particularly valued often frame themselves as their poet’s responses to significant
                questions about existence. Biographical circumstances meant that Shelley’s Rousseau
                was never able to tell the narrator of “The Triumph of Life” what life is, but the
                framing of the question nevertheless implies that this is something that poetry
                might potentially establish. Bowie’s work challenges such attempts at definitive
                meaning-making, in part due to his greater awareness of the importance of his
                audiences. According to <emph>Hunky Dory</emph>’s producer, Ken Scott,
                Bowie intended “The Bewlay Brothers” (1971) to be “specifically for the American
                market . . . the lyrics makes absolutely no sense, but the Americans always like to
                read into things, so let them read into it what they will” (Buckley 97). To the more
                Romantically inclined, this might sound like a terrible abdication of artistic
                responsibility, but it reflects Bowie’s sense that meaning can never be created
                solely by the artist (particularly an artist who works in concert with skilled
                musicians, technicians, and designers). Rather, significance is the product of
                complex processes of collaboration. In his practices, Bowie actively sought out
                spaces for the co-creation of meaning through the use of cut-ups in the late sixties
                and early seventies and Brian Eno and Peter Schmidt’s Oblique Strategies for
                elements of the Berlin Trilogy (<emph>Low</emph> (1977), <emph>“Heroes”</emph> (1977), and <emph>Lodger</emph> (1979)). This
                preoccupation with the interpretations of others also manifests in his lyrics. The
                subjects of his songs often shift in manners that model crossings-over of
                responsibility and identity. After the bridge in “Young Americans” (1975), the
                song’s subject moves from being a series of pitied characters (he or she “wants the
                young American”) to the audience (“You want the young American”) and finally the
                singer (“I want the young American”). The narrator of “Panic in Detroit” (1973) is a
                fan and an imitator of revolutionaries, rather than a revolutionary himself in any
                uncomplicated sense. The film-devouring potential ravers in “Drive-In Saturday”
                (1973) require a crash course in a practice in which they feel irredeemably
                secondary. On <emph>Diamond Dogs</emph>’s “Sweet Thing” (1974), the singer
                depicts himself as “a portrait in flesh,” but also wonders desperately whether his
                auditor will “see that I’m scared and I’m lonely.” Such framings demand that their
                audiences recognize that identities must necessarily be staged and seen. As Waldrep
                puts it, “Bowie gives us a way to understand the vicissitudes of performance,
                aestheticizing the link between rock music and everyday life by calling attention to
                the artificiality of both”
                (<emph>Future Nostalgia</emph> 3).</p>
            <p>A personal and ideological investment in the creative potential of
                unstable identities lies at the heart of Bowie’s artistry. He was fully capable of
                “play[ing] the wild mutation as a rock &amp; roll star” (“Star” (1972)), but in
                showing this to be play, albeit of a serious kind, he argued implicitly for a more
                fluid notion of genius that recognized the roles played by change, chance, and
                auditors. The characters who he both played and observed are commonly flawed,
                fragmented, doubting, or blinkered. Over the course of <emph>The Rise
                    and Fall of Ziggy Stardust</emph>, it becomes clear that the title character is at
                least in part an awful person, self-absorbed and self-regarding. When asked by Alan
                Yentob whether “Ziggy was a monster,” Bowie replied, “Oh he certainly was” (<emph>Cracked Actor</emph>). The nature of Ziggy’s monstrosity is often
                coded Romantically. The flaw that Jeffrey detects in the Lakers, “Making love with
                [one’s] ego,” is also Ziggy’s flaw, and “leper messiah” (“Ziggy Stardust” (1972))
                sounds like a status that Shelley would have been glad to claim in his more
                self-abasing moments. However, for Bowie, Ziggy is far from being an all-consuming
                role. His rise and fall is a story told around its central character. Even the song
                that bears his name is narrated by his bandmates, frustrated by the alienating
                effects of their lead singer’s megalomania. Crucially, though, this does not mean
                that Ziggy’s project is necessarily a failure. What matters is not so much the
                artist himself, but the inspiration that other people draw from him and build upon.
                What’s reported of the starman’s “hazy cosmic jive” (1972) is vague and garbled;
                what’s important is how his transmission makes his listeners feel, creating a
                community united for a moment in the ecstasy of shared excitement. The unity at the
                heart of the song is not so much in the lyrics, but rather in the many-voiced “na
                na” chant that follows the later choruses and runs into the closing fade. While <emph>Ziggy Stardust</emph> ironizes artistic egocentricity, it is also a
                record that advocates repeatedly for art’s power to create and evoke powerful
                connections. In both his lyrics and his practice, Bowie shows that art and its
                insights do not have to be perfect or essentially true to communicate powerfully.
                Discussing Bowie’s voice, Waldrep writes that he employs “a distinctive type of
                singing that almost oversignifies to remind listeners repeatedly that what they are
                hearing is a self-conscious performance of character and emotion (singing to make
                you think about singing) that yet connects to so many people because it is closer to
                how they experience emotion than music that attempts to be ‘naturalistic’” (<emph>Aesthetics</emph> 116). In Bowie’s work the medium and the message
                are both shown to be fallible, but their human fallibility is intrinsic to their
                effectiveness as meaningful and appropriable art.</p>
            <p>An investment in exploring the interlinked power and fragility of
                selves and communications is remarkably consistent across Bowie’s many reinventions,
                from the overdetermined dead circuit in “Space Oddity” (1969), to the insistence on
                glorious potential existing “just for one day” in “‘Heroes’” (1977), to the final
                song on his final record, “I Can’t Give Everything Away” (2016):<quote><lg type="stanza">
            <l>Seeing more and feeling less</l>
            <l>Saying no but meaning yes</l>
            <l>This is all I ever meant</l>
            <l>That’s the message that I sent</l></lg></quote>
            In the stanza’s first line, there is perhaps a little echo of the
                epitaph of W.B. Yeats, one of the self-proclaimed “last romantics” who “chose for
                theme / Traditional sanctity and loveliness” (“Coole Park and Ballylee, 1931” ll.
                41–2). Yeats’s self-chosen grave inscription, as laid out in “Under Ben Bulben,”
                runs “<emph>Cast a cold eye</emph>
                / <emph>On life, on death / Horseman, pass by!</emph>”
                (ll. 92–4). However, while Yeats’s lines are decisive, Bowie’s second line flips to
                give the other side of the equation: not quite a contradiction, but a reversal of
                the dynamics between the internal and external worlds that the first line lays out.
                While seeing more and feeling less implies a desire for a kind of cold, objective
                voyeurism, saying no but meaning yes gestures towards a positive connection
                expressed through the performance of alienation. In these lines, denial and
                affirmation tangle together in a paradox that nevertheless communicates. You can’t
                give everything away—there’s never time or words enough—but the faith remains
                nevertheless that something, perhaps something unexpected, carries and can suffice
                for someone else. If Bowie’s work throws into doubt the Romantic authority of the
                artist as transcendent visionary, it does not do so in order to break the potency of
                art, but rather to think about how accepting artists’ limitations need not
                compromise the power of their works to work for others. Bowie’s concern with his
                audience and his respect for his listeners’ capacity for making meanings maintains a
                modified faith in the value of artistic communication, but recognizes that for art
                to be genuinely representative, it needs to reach out beyond the concerns of its
                maker by embracing the potential for radical openness in the lyric utterance.</p>
            <p>While this embrace is sometimes oblique in Bowie’s music, at other
                times, it is startlingly and touchingly direct. The last song on <emph>Ziggy Stardust</emph>, “Rock ‘n’ Roll Suicide” (1972), makes a strange shift from
                much of the preceding album, moving to a second person that projects Romantic ennui
                onto its addressee. While the song begins by telling the listener that they’ve
                fallen into a state of irrevocable solipsism—“Oh, no, no, no, you’re a rock ‘n’ roll
                suicide”—the last words gloriously counterpoise this with a cry of connection that
                reasserts the brilliance not of the singer, but of the auditor who responds:<quote><lg type="stanza">
            <l> You’re not alone.</l>
            <l>Gimme your hands ’cause you’re wonderful</l></lg></quote>
            This invitation to take hold of what the song provides and use it
                as a mooring point seems to me to typify Bowie’s works’ laudable openness to
                imaginative and emotional appropriation. The capital-P poet can be a powerful ideal,
                but it also one that risks actuating Romantic art’s unpleasant potential for insular
                elitism, where the insights art models are for an elect who might perhaps deign to
                share them as long as their genius is acknowledged. Bowie’s work flirts with this
                position on occasion, but he recognized its dangers. Even in troubled moments, such
                as when he asserted that he “always had a repulsive sort of need to be something
                more than human” (Crowe), his recognizing this need as repulsive registers a concern
                about modes that close off, rather than open up. His success at tempering the
                Romantic desire for transcendence created the space for him to recognize others, and
                to be made a part of others’ lives in ways that have allowed him to persist as an
                avatar of empathy, transformation, and perverse integrity. In an article marking the
                fifth anniversary of his death, Lynsey Hanley writes that “life, for Bowie, was a
                series of encounters with people and things that made change possible, not a series
                of transactions designed to get one over on other people.” In the same article, the
                singer Edwyn Collins states that “He was warm; you could walk around with him in
                your head all day and it comforted you.” If these feelings typify what Bowie can
                conjure, then it seems clear to me that his artistic self-fashioning has been
                profoundly, Romantically successful.</p>
                <div type="citation">
                    <head>Works Cited</head>
            <bibl>Baker, David. “Bowie’s Covers: The Artist as Modernist.” <emph>Enchanting
                    David Bowie: Space/Time/Body/Memory</emph>, edited by Toija Cinque, Christopher
                Moore and Sean Redmond, Bloomsbury, 2015, pp. 103–18.</bibl>
            <bibl>Bernhard Jackson, Emily A. “‘Sometimes I feel like the whole human
                race’: Lord Byron and David Bowie Consider the Question of Identity.” <emph>Byron Journal</emph>, vol. 46, no. 2, 2018, pp. 113–25.</bibl>
            <bibl>Bowie, David. “Aladdin Sane (1913-1938-197?).” <emph>Aladdin Sane</emph>,
                RCA, 1973.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “An Occasional Dream.” <emph>David Bowie</emph>,
                Philips, 1969.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Andy Warhol.” <emph>Hunky Dory</emph>, RCA,
                1971.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “The Bewlay Brothers.” <emph>Hunky Dory</emph>, RCA,
                1971.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Changes.” <emph>Hunky Dory</emph>, RCA, 1971.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “China Girl.” <emph>Let’s Dance</emph>, EMI America,
                1983.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Cygnet Committee.” <emph>David Bowie</emph>,
                Philips, 1969.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “D.J.” <emph>Lodger</emph>, RCA, 1979.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Drive-In Saturday.” <emph>Aladdin Sane</emph>, RCA,
                1973.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Eight Line Poem.” <emph>Hunky Dory</emph>, RCA,
                1971.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “‘Heroes’.” <emph>Heroes</emph>, RCA, 1977.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “I Can’t Give Everything Away.” <emph>Blackstar</emph>, ISO, Columbia
                and Sony, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Lady Stardust.” <emph>The Rise and Fall of Ziggy
                    Stardust and the Spiders from Mars</emph>, RCA, 1972.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Memory of a Free Festival.” <emph>David
                    Bowie</emph>, Philips, 1969.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Moonage Daydream.” <emph>The Rise and Fall of Ziggy Stardust and
                    the Spiders from Mars</emph>, RCA, 1972.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Panic in Detroit.” <emph>Aladdin Sane</emph>, RCA,
                1973.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Quicksand.” <emph>Hunky Dory</emph>, RCA, 1971.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Rock ‘n’ Roll Suicide.” <emph>The Rise and Fall
                    of Ziggy Stardust and the Spiders from Mars</emph>, RCA, 1972.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Star.” <emph>The Rise and Fall of Ziggy Stardust
                    and the Spiders from Mars</emph>, RCA, 1972.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Starman.” <emph>The Rise and Fall of Ziggy
                    Stardust and the Spiders from Mars</emph>, RCA, 1972.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Space Oddity.” <emph>David Bowie</emph>, Philips,
                1969.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Sweet Thing.” <emph>Diamond Dogs</emph>, RCA,
                1974.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Time.” <emph>Aladdin Sane</emph>, RCA, 1973.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Unwashed and Somewhat Slightly Dazed.” <emph>David Bowie</emph>, Philips, 1969.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Wild Eyed Boy from Freecloud.” <emph>David
                    Bowie</emph>, Philips, 1969.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Word on a Wing.” <emph>Station to Station</emph>,
                RCA, 1976.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Young Americans.”
                <emph>Young Americans.</emph> RCA, 1975.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Ziggy Stardust.” <emph>The Rise and Fall of Ziggy
                    Stardust and the Spiders from Mars</emph>, RCA, 1972.</bibl>
            <bibl>Brooker, Will.
                <emph>Forever Stardust: David Bowie Across the Universe.</emph> I.B.
                Tauris, 2017.</bibl>
            <bibl>Buckley, David. <emph>Strange Fascination: David Bowie:
                    The Definitive Story</emph>. Virgin Books, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cleave, Maureen. “How does a Beatle live? John Lennon lives like
                this.” <emph>Evening Standard</emph>, 4 March 1966, p. 10.</bibl>
            <bibl>Crowe, Cameron. “David Bowie: Ground Control to Davy Jones.” <emph>Rolling Stone</emph>, 12 February 1976, <ref
                    target="http://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/david-bowie-ground-control-to-davy-jones-77059/"
                    >www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/david-bowie-ground-control-to-davy-jones-77059/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gill, John. <emph>Queer Noises: Male and Female
                    Homosexuality in Twentieth-Century Music</emph>. U of Minnesota P, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl>Glen, Patrick. “‘Oh You Pretty Thing!’: How David Bowie ‘Unlocked
                Everybody’s Inner Queen’ in spite of the music press.” <emph>Contemporary British History</emph>, vol. 31, no. 3, 2017, pp. 407–29.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hanley, Lynsey. “‘His life is a rebuke to cynicism’: what five
                years without David Bowie has taught us.” <emph>The Guardian</emph>, 8
                January 2021, <ref
                    target="http://www.theguardian.com/music/2021/jan/08/what-five-years-without-david-bowie-has-taught-us"
                    >www.theguardian.com/music/2021/jan/08/what-five-years-without-david-bowie-has-taught-us</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Higgins, David.
                <emph>Romantic Genius and the Literary Magazine: Biography, Celebrity, Politics.</emph> Routledge,
                2005.</bibl>
            <bibl>[Jeffrey, Francis]. Review of Southey’s <emph>Thalaba</emph>. <emph>Edinburgh Review</emph>, 1, October 1802, pp.
                63–83.</bibl>
            <bibl>Keats, John. “Addressed to the Same [B.R. Haydon].” <emph>The Poems of John Keats</emph>, edited by Jack Stillinger,
                Heinemann, 1978, p. 36.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. <emph>The Letters of John Keats, 1814–1821</emph>.
                Edited by Hyder Edward Rollins, 2 vols, Cambridge UP, 1958.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Ode on a Grecian Urn.” <emph>The Poems of John
                    Keats</emph>, edited by Jack Stillinger, Heinemann, 1978, pp. 372–3.</bibl>
            <bibl>Klancher, Jon. <emph>Transfiguring the Arts and
                    Sciences: Knowledge and Cultural Institutions in the Romantic Age</emph>.
                Cambridge UP, 2013.</bibl>
            <bibl>Löwy, Michael and Robert Sayre. <emph>Romanticism
                    Against the Tide of Modernity</emph>. Translated by Catherine Porter, Duke UP,
                2001.</bibl>
            <bibl>Mathias, Thomas James. <emph>The Pursuits of
                    Literature: A Satirical Poem in Four Dialogues</emph>. 7<hi rend="superscript"
                    >th</hi> edition, T. Becket, 1798.</bibl>
            <bibl>McGann, Jerome J. <emph>The Romantic Ideology: A
                    Critical Investigation</emph>. U of Chicago P, 1983.</bibl>
            <bibl>Miles, Robert. <emph>Romantic Misfits</emph>. Palgrave,
                2008.</bibl>
            <bibl>Mole, Tom. <emph>Byron’s Romantic Celebrity: Industrial
                    Culture and the Hermeneutic of Intimacy</emph>. Palgrave, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. <emph>What the Victorians Made of
                Romanticism</emph>. Princeton UP, 2017.</bibl>
            <bibl>Morley, Paul. <emph>The Age of Bowie: How David Bowie
                    Made a World of Difference</emph>. Simon and Schuster, 2017.</bibl>
            <bibl>Newlyn, Lucy. <emph>Reading, Writing, and Romanticism:
                    The Anxiety of Reception</emph>. Oxford UP, 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl>North, Julian. <emph>The Domestication of Genius:
                    Biography and the Romantic Poet</emph>. Oxford UP, 2009.</bibl>
            <bibl>Perry, Seamus. “Romanticism: The Brief History of a Concept.” <emph>A Companion to Romanticism</emph>, edited by Duncan Wu, Blackwell,
                1998, pp. 3–11.</bibl>
            <bibl>Shelley, Percy Bysshe. “A Defence of Poetry.” <emph>Shelley’s Poetry and Prose</emph>, edited by Donald H. Reiman and Neil Fraistat,
                W.W. Norton, 2002, pp. 509–35.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. <emph>The Letters of Percy Bysshe Shelley.</emph> Edited by Frederick
                L. Jones, 2 vols, Clarendon Press, 1964.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Ode to the West Wind.” <emph>Shelley’s Poetry and
                    Prose</emph>, edited by Donald H. Reiman and Neil Fraistat, W.W. Norton, 2002, pp.
                298–301.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “To Wordsworth.” <emph>Shelley’s Poetry and
                    Prose</emph>, edited by Donald H. Reiman and Neil Fraistat, W.W. Norton, 2002, p.
                92.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “The Triumph of Life.” <emph>Shelley’s Poetry and
                    Prose</emph>, edited by Donald H. Reiman and Neil Fraistat, W.W. Norton, 2002, pp.
                481–500.</bibl>
            <bibl>Siskin, Clifford. <emph>The Historicity of Romantic
                    Discourse</emph>. Oxford UP, 1988.</bibl>
            <bibl>Stevenson, Nick. <emph>David Bowie: Fame, Sound and
                    Vision</emph>. Polity, 2006.</bibl>
            <bibl>Tetzlaff, David. “Music for Meaning: Reading the Discourse of
                Authenticity in Rock.” <emph>Journal of Communication Inquiry</emph>, vol.
                18, no. 1, 1994, pp. 95–117.</bibl>
            <bibl>Waldrep, Shelton. <emph>The Aesthetics of Self
                    Invention: Oscar Wilde to David Bowie</emph>. U of Minnesota P, 2004.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. <emph>Future Nostalgia: Performing David
                    Bowie</emph>. Bloomsbury Academic, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl>Wordsworth, William. “Lines Written a Few Miles above Tintern
                Abbey.” <emph>William Wordsworth: 21<hi rend="superscript"
                    >st</hi>-Century Oxford Authors</emph>, edited by Stephen Gill,
                Oxford UP, 2010, pp. 49–53.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “My heart leaps up when I behold.” <emph>William
                    Wordsworth: 21</emph><hi rend="italic superscript">st</hi><emph>-Century Oxford Authors</emph>, edited by Stephen Gill, Oxford UP, 2010, p.
                264.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Preface.” <emph>Lyrical Ballads, with Other
                    Poems</emph>, 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> edition, 2 vols, Longman and Rees,
                1800, pp. v–xlvi.</bibl>
            <bibl>———.
                <emph>The Prelude, or Growth of a Poet’s Mind; An Autobiographical Poem.</emph> Edward
                Moxon, 1850.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Preface.” <emph>Lyrical Ballads, with Pastoral
                    and Other Poems</emph>, 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> edition, 2 vols, Longman
                and Rees, 1802, pp. i–lxiv.</bibl>
            <bibl>Yeats, W.B. “Coole Park and Ballylee, 1931.” <emph>The
                    Variorum Edition of the Poems of W.B. Yeats</emph>, edited by Peter Allt and
                Russell K. Alspach, Macmillan, 1957, pp. 440–2.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. “Under Ben Bulben.” <emph>The Variorum Edition of
                    the Poems of W.B. Yeats</emph>, edited by Peter Allt and Russell K. Alspach,
                Macmillan, 1957, pp. 636–40.</bibl>
            <bibl>Yentob, Alan, director. <emph>Cracked Actor</emph>.
                British Broadcasting Corporation, 1975.</bibl>
            </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
