<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <!-- got rid of file description, encoding descriptions, and editorial declarations (do we need/want to move this info to the "about" section of the site) -->

    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">David Bowie and the Legacies of Romanticism</title>
                <title type="a">“Will you stay”: “Kooks,” Hunky Dory, and Romantic Childhood</title>
                <author><name>Beatrice Turner</name></author>
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor,</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor,</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Series Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2022-07-25</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado,
                    Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                        or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                        purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                        use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                        are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                        with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                        permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                        requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                        notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
                        forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                        conditions: <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                        them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                        have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                        Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                        continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                        generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                        a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                        use.</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2022.bowie.turner</idno>
                <idno type="resource">bowie</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <title level="a" type="main">“Will you stay”: “Kooks,” Hunky Dory, and
                            Romantic Childhood</title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Beatrice</forename>
                                <surname>Turner</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <ptr
                            target="https://romantic-circles.org/praxis/bowie/praxis.2022.bowie.turner.html"
                        />
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">“Will you stay”: “Kooks,” Hunky Dory, and Romantic
                            Childhood</title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of
                                Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <date when="2022-07-25">July 25, 2022</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for
                        &#226;&#8364;&#339;," for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                        keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
                        such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
                        been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                    12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Criticism"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <keywords scheme="https://www.romantic-circles.org">
                    <term subtype="tags">cyberpunk</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">Vodoo</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <!-- deleted the Nines information and the profile description -->

        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                <date>July 14, 2022</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p rend="noCount">Poised at the start of the 1970s, David Bowie’s <emph>Hunky
                        Dory</emph> now feels prophetic in its visions of a cynical “world to come”
                    and the embittered generation who lived the long post-Woodstock comedown. This
                    essay argues that the album mobilizes a discourse of idealized childhood that is
                    one of Romanticism’s most enduring legacies, in order to enact a generational
                    struggle that is both personal—the anxiety of the parent who fears creative
                    displacement by their child—and public: the nostalgic and idealistic parent
                    generation of the 1960s versus the bitter realism of their descendants. Tracing
                    how “Kooks” replicates the image of the ‘Romantic child’ as articulated
                    primarily in Wordsworth and Coleridge’s poetry, the essay situates the
                    narrator’s reactionary impulse to keep the child a child forever against the
                    album’s surrounding cast of angry, knowing teenagers. It argues that the
                    Romantic child discourse—and the ways in which it still shapes, implicitly or
                    otherwise, ideas about the relationships between parents and children, authors
                    and texts, and reproduction and creative genius—enables the album to dramatize
                    as a coherent text the ways in which those who inherited 1960s counterculture
                    might, like Romanticism’s children in the 1820s and 1830s, resist calls to
                    mythic, timeless unknowingness and instead turn to face painfully unfolding
                    knowledge.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head>“Will you stay”: “Kooks,” Hunky Dory, and Romantic Childhood</head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Beatrice Turner</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>University of Roehampton</affiliation>
                </byline>



                <p><emph>Hunky Dory</emph> (1971) is a record on which things are everything but.
                    Exemplifying David Bowie’s talent for inhabiting and dramatizing multiple
                    identities, it is spoken both by and to the kids who have been left, as
                    “Changes” has it, “up to our necks in it” by an etiolated parent generation. At
                    its centre, however, is “Kooks,” a track whose inclusion at the heart of the
                    record bothered me when I first heard the album as an undergraduate and has
                    continued to bother me since. The bothering is, in fact, a not insignificant
                    factor in my abiding love for <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> above any other record by
                    Bowie. Set against the lyrical cynicism and extravagant orchestrations of “Oh!
                    You Pretty Things,” or “Life on Mars?”, or the visionary anti-prophecy of
                    “Quicksand” which follows it to close Side A, “Kooks”’s simple, twee arrangement
                    and sentimental parental address has always seemed wilfully naïve to me, at odds
                    with the rest of the album’s knowing embrace of coming apocalypse and its
                    associated regenerative possibilities. In an album otherwise oriented towards “a
                    world to come,” it is an appeal against change, against growing up, pointing
                    both lyrically and musically back into a mythologized childhood.</p>
                <p>The friction generated by that juxtaposition of imaginative stasis and knowing
                    momentum, or innocence and experience (to make plain the thread this essay will
                    string between a proto-glam pop album and Romantic poetry), is central to
                    understanding the album’s powerful sense of tectonic cultural shift, and to
                    understanding it as a profoundly Romantic text. <emph>Hunky Dory</emph>, as some
                    of its early reviewers recognized, is about “both fathers and sons” (Ross). But
                    childhood and parenthood as concepts do double duty in this text in a way that
                    will be familiar to readers of Romantic poetry: the album understands both the
                    powerful, ambivalent feelings that parents and children produce in each other,
                    and the no less ambivalent forms of response and interrogation at play when a
                    parent generation is supplanted by its descendants. In both of these senses, the
                    personal and the cultural, <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> speaks about the implicit
                    violence of reproduction. It presciently identifies how comfortably naïve 1960s
                    ‘Flower Power’ counterculture would look when eyed up by the more jaundiced
                    teenagers of the 1970s, while it also seeks self-consciously to mystify Bowie’s
                    own feelings about impending fatherhood. Historical particularities of 1970s
                    Britain aside, this is an agon with a clear and specific Romantic origin.
                    “Kooks” reproduces with remarkable precision an image of the idealized child of
                    nature—located most commonly in a handful of William Wordsworth and Samuel
                    Taylor Coleridge’s poems—which scholars have named the ‘Romantic child’. But it
                    also reproduces the fraught relationship this text-child has with their
                    parent-author, while the album’s surrounding cast of angry, knowing adolescents
                    dramatize the ways in which this reactionary idea of childhood has to be
                    negotiated by those who inherit it. </p>
                <p> My argument, then, is that we should read—and hear—“Kooks” as a text that
                    articulates this Romantic archetype of childhood, and <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> as
                    a text that works through a way of responding to that archetype, and to the
                    wider Romantic project. The Romantic child is the idealized child of
                    Wordsworth’s “We Are Seven” or his Boy of Winander, or Coleridge’s “Frost at
                    Midnight”. This is the child figure who arrives direct from heaven “trailing
                    clouds of glory” in Wordsworth’s “Intimations Ode” (l. 64), the “seer blest!,”
                    who Barbara Garlitz could claim in 1966 had completely redefined attitudes to
                    childhood for a century, and whose legacy in fact remains the dominant cultural
                    understanding of childhood in the Western imagination (Garlitz 639).These poems
                    imagined a radical new image of the child as someone preserved in eternal
                    innocence and creative potentiality by their seclusion from formal education,
                    society, the city, or any other form of experience that might taint their
                    intuitive ability to read the natural world. They also, however, consciously and
                    unconsciously dramatize the ways in which the adult author or parent creates
                    this ideal child by over-inscribing a real child with a set of meanings that
                    meet the author’s psychological and creative need for an eternal, archetypal
                    child. By reifying the child into an aesthetic production, its creative
                    potentiality is always forestalled; the child remains the adult’s own creation.
                    As I have argued elsewhere, it is this process of reification, and the authorial
                    anxiety of replacement that underlies it, that the Romantic poem is about when
                    it speaks about childhood.<note place="foot" resp="author">See especially
                        section two of Chapter One, “The Family, the Child, and the Memorial,” in
                            <emph>Romantic Childhood, Romantic Heirs: Reproduction and Retrospection
                            1820−1850.</emph> Palgrave, 2017.</note></p>
                
                <p>This reading of the child as the creative production of the adult speaker who
                    cannot allow them to grow up shows us what is at stake for those who reject
                    Romantic innocence, and it is this tension that <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> repeats,
                    knowingly or otherwise. It is not my intention to claim that Bowie is
                    consciously responding to and critiquing Romantic constructions of childhood;
                    however, I am arguing that they form an available and culturally powerful
                    discourse with which <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> engages. This discourse, and the
                    ways in which it still shapes, implicitly or otherwise, ideas about the
                    relationships between parents and children, authors and texts, and reproduction
                    and creative genius, enables the album to dramatize as a coherent text the ways
                    in which those who inherited 1960s counterculture might, like Romanticism’s
                    children in the 1820s and 30s, resist calls to mythic, timeless unknowingness
                    and instead turn to face painfully unfolding knowledge.</p>
                <p> Before I consider the ways in which “Kooks” in particular draws on a Romantic
                    discourse of childhood, it is useful to think about what makes it a Romantic
                    text at all, because the milieu the song works to establish, one in which Bowie
                    and son might “take the car downtown,” is firmly the contemporary everyday. This
                    sets it at odds with the rest of the album, in which the songs generally
                    freewheel between imagined temporalities, mixing present, future, and mythic
                    timelessness in a way more consistent with the usual swooping through-lines and
                    leapings-off of the Romantic lyric. “Oh! You Pretty Things,” for instance, opens
                    on a scene of cozy, anachronistic domesticity (“throw another log on the fire
                    for me / I’ve made some breakfast and coffee”) only to jump dizzyingly forwards
                    and outwards into cosmic prophecy via the image of the “crack in the sky and a
                    hand reaching down to me.” Linguistically, too, there’s an opposition between
                    the contemporary slanginess of “Kooks”’s vernacular (“I’m not much cop at
                    punching other people’s dads”) and the stylized, surrealist imagery of, for
                    example, “Eight Line Poem”: “But the key to the city / Is in the sun which pins
                    the branches to the sky.” Contemporary setting and language aside, however, it
                    is in the song’s celebration of quotidian detail and structural simplicity that
                    its Romantic influence lies.</p>
                <p> Like many of Wordsworth’s ballad poems, or Coleridge’s conversation poems, the
                    song creates a domestic universe with an affect in excess of its constituent
                    parts. This is achieved by picking out small individual images or events and
                    elevating their intensity whilst limiting the imaginative horizon of the
                    protagonists. In “Kooks,” that horizon is marked by the chorus refrain: “soon
                    you’ll grow / So take a chance / On a couple of kooks . . .” The baby boy Bowie
                    addresses will “soon . . . grow,” but into who, or what, is deferred for now.
                    Just as the world of the “little cottage girl” of “We Are Seven” is
                    circumscribed by the limits of the churchyard in which her siblings lie, Bowie
                    the new father cannot imagine a spatial or temporal world beyond the newly
                    established familial borders. Instead, he lists the items he and his wife have
                    prepared for their child’s impending arrival: “a lot of things to keep you warm
                    and dry / A funny old crib on which the paint won’t dry”; “a pair of shoes, a
                    trumpet you can blow, and a book of rules / Of what to say to people when they
                    pick on you.” As in “We Are Seven,” in which it is left to the reader to infer a
                    family’s grief from the little girl’s recitation of her mundane daily rituals of
                    eating, singing, and sewing at her siblings’ graves, this list does its own
                    explicatory work without the narrator’s explicit realization: the
                    inexpertly-painted crib and baby clothes sit on one side of the caesura created
                    by the shift in melody and metre, and on the other, the presumably decorative
                    rather than protective “paaaair of shoes” (the single stress awkwardly drawn out
                    for two beats to make up the bar), the trumpet (mimetically illustrated), and
                    the book of comebacks. It is left to the listener to get an immediate joke about
                    these bohemian parents’ preparedness (or otherwise) for their new baby, and to
                    recognize a more profound claim about the impossibility of anyone ever really
                    being able to imagine what it’s like after a child arrives.</p>
                <p> Lyrically, then, “Kooks” might be considered a Romantic poem in the
                    Wordsworthian mould. It certainly fits Wordsworth’s own criteria of “incidents
                    and situations from common life” expressed in “plainer and more emphatic
                    language,” especially in comparison to the heightened, occasionally grandiose
                    language and stylized imagery of the rest of the album (Wordsworth 596; 597). It
                    is also a good exemplar of his rule that in a poem “the feeling therein
                    developed gives importance to the action and situation, and not the action and
                    situation to the feeling” (599): the song builds upon the very slightest of
                    actual incidents. Musically, too, it has a structural simplicity which echoes
                    the plain diction of the lyrics. The song’s 4:4 time signature, the simplest of
                    tempos (and usually the first learned), has an analogue in the ballad metre
                    which drives many of Wordsworth’s narrative poems such as “Goody Blake and Harry
                    Gill,” “The Idiot Boy,” or “We Are Seven.” The ballad metre, which alternates
                    lines of iambic tetrameter and trimeter in four-line stanzas, would have been
                    familiar to an eighteenth-century reader from popular broadsides: it is what
                    might be called a ‘folk’ metre. It emphasizes rhythm over flow, drawing primary
                    attention to the repetitive bouncy stanzas, and creates an effect that is, as
                    numerous Romantic critics have observed, naïve or childlike, suggesting a
                    nursery rhyme rather than a poem with more serious literary intent.<note
                        place="foot" resp="author">See, for example, Heather Glen’s <emph> Vision
                            and Disenchantment: Blake’s Songs</emph> and Wordsworth’s<emph> Lyrical
                            Ballads</emph> and Alan Richardson’s<emph> Literature, Education and
                            Romanticism: Reading as Social Practice, 1780−1832</emph>.</note>
                    “Kooks”’s syncopated four-beat bars work in a similar way, establishing a
                    relationship between childlike rhythm and subject, and suggesting, perhaps, that
                    here is something that, unlike the rest of the album, ought not to be taken
                    particularly seriously.<note place="foot" resp="author">A version recorded for
                        John Peel at the BBC in June 1971 has a single acoustic guitar
                        accompanimentth and is played in a minor key. Bowie sings with far less
                        emphasis on the beat, and sometimes off it altogether. The result is an
                        elegiac, quite different song, but one in which the central resistance to
                        growing up remains.</note></p>
                
                <p> And yet its central position in the track order suggests that “Kooks” does
                    matter, very much, and in what follows I will attempt to show why by reading it
                    as an instance of a Romantic child poem and by unpicking the Romantic child’s
                    relationship to creative and paternal authority. The song celebrates
                    unselfconscious childish innocence and joyful resistance of adult knowledge in
                    favour of an authentic native wisdom. That stance rests upon a central tenet of
                    the Romantic child ethos, which is the suspicion of, and downright resistance
                    to, formal education and socialization, as numerous Romantic critics have noted,
                    to very different interpretive ends. <note place="foot" resp="author">The
                        ‘fantasy versus reason’ debate is familiar enough that I do not need to
                        rehearse it extensively. In the hands of children’s literature scholars such
                        as Geoffrey Summerfield, Mary Jackson and, earlier in the twentieth century,
                        F. J. Harvey Darton, Percy Muir and Mary Thwaite, the Romantic child’s lack
                        of education represented the triumph of “fantasy over reason” (Summerfield
                        175) or “a revulsion among those of enlightened artistic and literary
                        predilections against an airless, inhumanly narrow view of the child’s mind”
                        (Jackson 191). To later critics such as Mitzi Myers, Judith Plotz, Andrew
                        O’Malley and Alan Richardson, who are influenced by the social and political
                        perspectives of feminist criticism and new historicism, the Romantic
                        discourse of childhood conceals a reactionary conservatism which uses the
                        state of childhood to retreat to “a conservative fantasy of an idyllic past”
                        rather than engage with the ambivalence and complexity of a socially and
                        industrially developing society (O’Malley 128). In this reading, the
                        Romantic child’s lack of education strips deprives them of agency and
                        ensures their economic and social subjugation.</note> The fifth book of
                        <emph>The Prelude</emph> famously conjures up the “monster birth” of “these
                    too industrious times”: this is a child who has been crammed with “learning and
                    books” at the expense of his visionary connection with nature (V:293–4; 319).
                    This product of a structured education system has become “no Child / But a dwarf
                    Man” (V:295–6) while: <quote><lg type="stanza">
                            <l>old Grandame Earth is grieved to find</l>

                            <l> the playthings, which her love designed for him,</l>

                            <l> unthought of. (V:347–9)</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote> The ultimate horror of the rational child, Wordsworth suggests here, is
                    its inability to value Nature’s gifts. The visionary access to the world which,
                    as the Intimations Ode says, all children claim as their birthright, is lost to
                    a brain “choked with grammars” (V:325).</p>
                <p> “Frost at Midnight” offers a hopeful vision of an alternative future. Drawing on
                    the same language of entrapment and freedom, it deplores Coleridge’s own
                    schooldays, “pent mid cloisters dim,” and revels instead in the “far other lore”
                    that his son Hartley shall know: the “lovely shapes and sounds intelligible” of
                    the landscapes he wanders through unhindered (52; 59–60). In both texts,
                    structured learning is an impediment to accessing creative potential and to true
                    insight. “Kooks” repeats this central idea, with Bowie telling his baby son, “if
                    you ever have to go to school / remember how they messed up this old fool.” Like
                    the education in nature Coleridge desires for Hartley, he imagines his son’s
                    freedom from the formal schooling that “messed” him up: “if the homework brings
                    you down / we’ll throw it on the fire and take the car downtown.”</p>
                <p> Another important aspect of the Romantic child is their social seclusion: the
                    Boy of Winander’s companions are the owls whose “mimic hootings” he repeats (l.
                    398); those of the little girl of “We Are Seven” are her dead brother and
                    sister. Dialogue with nature requires solitude; social exchange blocks the
                    child’s visionary interpretation. “Kooks” replicates this too; Bowie’s gift of
                    “a book of rules / of what to say to people when they pick on you” makes clear
                    that being a ‘kook’, with its attendant creative gifts, means social exclusion.
                    If this all sounds equally reminiscent of the much more recent counter-cultural
                    imperative to “turn on, tune in, and drop out,” it is worth thinking about the
                    importance of Blake to Ginsberg and Dylan, Wordsworth’s influence on Ray Davies,
                    and flower power’s pantheist overtones. The popular culture of the 1960s, as
                    Luke Walker notes, was heavily indebted to the Romantic poets (1). I want to
                    insist however that on <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> we can hear something other than
                    Romanticism as it was refracted through the 1960s. The discourse of Romantic
                    childhood which it engages can be read as a celebration of the child’s intuition
                    and inherent creativity—the “self-born carol”—but we can also read it as one
                    that seeks to hold off experience and induction into the social order for
                    reasons that have much more to do with the desires of the narrating adult than
                    the child who is addressed and written into being under the supervising eye of
                    the parent-author.</p>
                <p> In Wordsworth’s “We Are Seven,” the little girl’s ideality derives from her
                    inability to understand (and therefore her proximity to) death, and I think in
                    that poem we are asked to regard the increasingly frustrated speaker not just
                    with contempt but with profound suspicion. Alan Richardson observes that
                    “Wordsworthian children of nature . . . must die so early” because, “rooted in a
                    transcendental nature rather than culturally produced,” they are left
                    “unsocialised and frozen in a state of eternal innocence” (Richardson 1989,
                    861). In fact, they are aligned with death <emph>because</emph> they are
                    culturally produced. Richardson means that Wordsworth’s children always appear
                    isolated from society and cultural structures, but this overlooks the fact that
                    they are also produced as aesthetic objects that meet certain creative or
                    psychological needs of the author. Even as the little cottage girl gracefully
                    evades her interlocutor’s attempts to subjugate her worldview to his rational
                    scheme, the poet-narrator’s interrogation compels her to produces herself for
                    him as exactly what he really needs her to be: the death-marked Romantic child.
                    His self-conscious presence in the poem reminds us that we can only ever
                    approach a child in a Wordsworth poem through the poet’s mediating art. It is
                    their production as this aesthetic ideal, as art rather than something natural,
                    that the unavoidable death of the child in nature overwrites. Lucy’s fate, to be
                    “Rolled round in earth’s diurnal course / With rocks and stones and trees,” is
                    that of all immortal Wordsworthian children: bodily interment and disintegration
                    is not just the price of transcendent immateriality but the sign of an exchange
                    between death and art (ll. 7–8).</p>
                <p> The innocent creativity of the Romantic child is always forestalled by early
                    death because a condition of being a Romantic child is that their creative
                    potential cannot ever be realized. Wordsworth’s “To H. C., Six Years Old,” makes
                    this quite explicit: <quote><lg type="stanza">
                            <l> Nature will either end thee quite;</l>

                            <l> Or, lengthening out thy season of delight.</l>


                            <l>Preserve for thee, by individual right,</l>

                            <l> A young Lamb’s heart among the full-grown flocks (ll. 21–4).</l>
                        </lg></quote> Coleridge’s description of poetic genius, the ability “to
                    carry on the feelings of childhood into the powers of manhood” (IV.i.9),
                    suggests why. His definition sets up the child as an emotional and imaginative
                    repository to be drawn on for inspiration and consolation by the poet. The child
                    in the Romantic poem, therefore, can only be either the poet’s child self
                    encountered in memory or a figure that remains fixed in a perpetual childhood,
                    their creative threat neutralized. Viewed in these terms, the Romantic child
                    figure represents a psycho-creative anxiety of replacement: this figure can
                    produce no rival poems. When, as is the case for Coleridge and for the speaker
                    of “Kooks,” that authorship is complicated and overwritten by fatherhood, the
                    anxiety of replacement is magnified, engendering a more disturbing displacement
                    of biological child by textual creation. The generative ‘shalls’ of “Frost at
                    Midnight” make Hartley a doubly-produced child: his future path determined by
                    his father’s verse. “Kooks” may style its productive force as a question—“will
                    you stay?”—but like Coleridge’s commandments, the lyrics inscribe the son as a
                    future fellow kook. Bowie’s promotional notes hammer the point: “The baby was
                    born and it looked like me and it looked like Angie and the song came out
                    like—if you’re gonna stay with us you’re gonna grow up Bananas” (Bowie,
                        <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> promotional material). Non-kookiness means not
                    staying. It means not belonging to the father.</p>
                <p> “Frost at Midnight” and “Kooks” both show a father responding to a son’s birth
                    with another creative act, an implicitly competitive gesture. But these are also
                    texts that in both cases reproduce the child as a silent creation who possesses
                    no authorial power of his own. In “Frost at Midnight,” Hartley is not merely a
                    silent presence in the text, but is imagined by his father as always without the
                    means to articulate himself: though he’ll learn to read the “lovely shapes and
                    sounds intelligible of God in nature,” the only language Hartley is going to
                    learn is that which “God utters”—a language it would be blasphemy to speak (l.
                    61). As such, the poem imagines a perpetual infancy in which Hartley’s “silent
                    breathing” is the only possible—or desirable—communication (l. 7). “Kooks” is
                    framed as a one-sided dialogue, the chorus a repeated question that leaves no
                    opening for a reply: <quote><lg type="stanza">
                            <l> Will you stay in our lovers’ story?</l>

                            <l> If you stay, you won’t be sorry</l>

                            <l> Soon you’ll grow so take a chance</l>
                            <l> With a couple of kooks hung up romancing . . .</l>
                        </lg>
                    </quote> Romancing who? The line trails off and refuses to say, but it’s the
                    kid, surely, who’s being romanced, seduced into an endless childhood through
                    that repeated entreaty to “stay” in the adults’ “story.” The speaker’s offer to
                    his son of his own extended “season of delight” conceals the fact he is
                    subordinate to the narrator’s personal narrative, one in which the author
                    remains the lover and the kook—the Romantic poet—and the child remains a child.</p>
                <p> The Oedipal threat, and the implicit violence of reifying one’s child into art
                    which “Frost at Midnight” dramatizes, reveals the problematic nature of the
                    adult desire for the child to remain a child. The question of whether this
                    desire might stem from something more personal than the politics of education
                    and the question of social progress is something to which criticism has paid
                    surprisingly little attention. The consequence has been that in texts such as
                    “Frost at Midnight” and “We Are Seven,” which dramatize this adult address to
                    and production of the ideal Romantic child, the extent to which these poems are
                    self-aware about that process has not really been acknowledged in the critical
                    urge to either condemn or to celebrate Romantic childhood. As James Holt
                    McGavran and Jennifer Daniel argue, scholarship which emphasizes the perceived
                    social and political disengagement of the Romantic child does not adequately
                    “recognize how deeply the sense of crisis—of repeated threats to children and
                    childhood across time, class, race and gender—is embedded in the Romantic
                    concept itself” (xv). Yet it is precisely that flickering self-awareness, the
                    way that Coleridge and Wordsworth poise a poem on the edge of admitting the fear
                    and jealousy the child raises whilst also acknowledging its ideality, that
                    “Kooks” engages, and that <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> as a whole responds to.</p>
                <p> Whether it is consciously understood as a Romantic tension or not, in
                        <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> Bowie puts this address to the child at the heart of
                    an album that that speaks insistently back to “Kooks”’s idealizations. In so
                    doing it reveals why, despite Bowie’s publicity statements, the relationship
                    between David Bowie the person and the speaker of “Kooks” is far from
                    straightforward. The performance works to bring out the ways in which the lyrics
                    ventriloquize this adult speaker who may well represent counter-cultural
                    freedom, but also doesn’t want the kid to grow up and become, as “Changes” has
                    it, “immune to your consultations.” There’s a neat congruence between the
                    subject and the arrangement—that simple 4:4 time, the childish-sounding piano
                    arrangement—which is missing from the other tracks. The coherence of form and
                    content almost seems designed to resist thought. Unlike “Life on Mars?” and “Oh!
                    You Pretty Things,” or “Fill Your Heart,” the listener is not required to unpick
                    the lyrics from the orchestrations. The speaker has a complex relationship to
                    Bowie: while the song was written as a response to the birth of Bowie’s
                    real-life son, he is also doing one of his voices on “Kooks.” Of course, he is
                    arguably always doing a voice, but this I think is a performatively insincere
                    voice. When he rolls his R’s on “brings you down,” we’re supposed to hear not
                    just a Bowie cipher speaking but a parody of parochial Englishness. It is a more
                    exaggerated version of Ray Davies’s vocal performance on <emph>The Kinks are The
                        Village Green Preservation Society</emph> (1968), an album with its own
                    ambivalent relationship to Romantic poetry, and to Wordsworth in particular. The
                    speaker of “We Are Seven” belongs to a text that wants to make fun of his
                    pedantry, and in a similar way Bowie’s vocal performance on “Kooks” works to
                    make the narrator sound old-fashioned and fussy, for all his carefree Romantic
                    intentions.</p>
                <p> It is the presence of this adult figure, and his Romantic conservatism
                    (although, like the Coleridge of “Frost at Midnight,” he’d never view himself as
                    a reactionary), that provides the album with a focal figure at which the rest of
                    the album’s anger and grim sense of prophecy can be directed. The opening track
                    makes this generational conflict central to the album. In “Changes,” the
                    children of the old generation are “trying to change their worlds,” exchanging
                    monolithic certainties for fragmentation and multiplicity, and the speaker turns
                    from his self-interrogations to admonish that listening parent figure: “Don’t
                    tell them to grow up and out of it.” It’s clear that a different kind of growing
                    up is stake when he asks, “Where’s your shame, you’ve left us up to our necks in
                    it”: growing up on those terms means exchanging adolescent rebellion for
                    acceptance of the status quo, rather than acquiring the social knowledge that
                    sparks the desire to create your own bespoke world. Teenaged anger at the social
                    and cultural inheritance left by the previous generation is repeated in various
                    ways across the album, but it comes into focus, and responds most directly to
                    “Kooks”’s performance of Romantic nostalgia in “Oh! You Pretty Things.”</p>
                <p> The track begins with a Blakean visionary awakening into a nightmare: “look out
                    my window, what do I see / a crack in the sky and a hand reaching down to me.”
                    This vision, seemingly addressed to one of the pretty young things, seems to
                    prophesize a new social order, a “world to come.” In the present, “the earth is
                    a bitch, we’ve finished our news / Homo Sapiens have outgrown their use,” but
                    the future offers regenerative potential that is both exhilarating and
                    terrifying to the speaker: the “nightmares” are “here to stay.” In a move that
                    exemplifies the speakers’ ambiguous position as neither one of the “coming race”
                    nor their parents, he switches address between the first and second verse, so
                    that the song is addressed back to the parents: “look at your children, see
                    their faces in golden rays / don’t kid yourself they belong to you, they’re the
                    start of a coming race.” On the album version, Bowie sings this line in an
                    ambiguous way, with a slight pause after “yourself,” so that it could mean
                    “don’t be fooled that your children or the golden rays that illuminate them have
                    anything to do with you,” or it could mean, “don’t kid yourself, these rather
                    sinister Nietzschean super children are precisely your fault.” Either way, if
                    the coming age of “Homo Superior” promises hope or destruction, the cheerful,
                    bathetic chorus line “don’t you know you’re driving your mamas and papas insane”
                    makes plain how little the parent generation understands what is happening, or
                    what futures are at stake. The father of “Kooks” who wants his son to “stay in
                    our lovers’ story” here becomes the unknowing one, unable to see that the
                    children who rejected his call for eternal innocence are engaged in remaking the
                    world for their own purposes, rather than merely driving him insane.</p>
                <p> When <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> was released, Bowie’s notes on each of the tracks
                    were used as promotional material. This is the note for “Pretty Things”: “The
                    reaction of me to my wife being pregnant was archetypal daddy—Oh he’s gonna be
                    another Elvis. This song is all that plus a dash of sci-fi” (Bowie, <emph>Hunky
                        Dory</emph> promotional material). If the song records at one level a
                    father’s sense that his child will, and should, eclipse him, then “Kooks” offers
                    an interesting corollary. It is a narrative in which the speaker’s son is not
                    part of “the coming race” and he and his generation have not “outgrown their
                    use,” but rather imagines a perpetual summer of love in which, crucially, the
                    new Elvis cannot displace him creatively. The resonance between those two tracks
                    reflects the Romantic anxiety of replacement I described in “Frost at Midnight’”
                    and in Wordsworth’s dead Romantic children, an anxiety which finds release in
                    the act of fixing the child in text. In an interview with <emph> Melody Maker
                    </emph> shortly after the album’s release, Bowie described his work as analogous
                    to psychotherapy: “my act is my couch” (Watts).</p>
                <p> But offering the text and its performance up as analysand’s narrative marshals
                    the listener into a private reading while also concealing both the cultural work
                    the song does and its historical sense. To suggest the song is a straightforward
                    conduit into his inner psychology is a characteristically misleading piece of
                    Bowie commentary. Like Wordsworth and Coleridge’s constructions of Romantic
                    childhood, “Kooks” encodes its own fissures, wearing the signs of a strained
                    artifice. The speaker is not or does want to be aware that his personal and
                    cultural moment is drawing to a close; his repeated entreaty to “stay” is
                    symptomatic of his refusal to confront both his son’s eventual adulthood and his
                    own creative displacement by the harsher art of the new pretty things. As an
                    album, <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> belongs to that new generation. It dramatizes the
                    gaze of the child back at the texts and cultural monuments of their parents, and
                    the ways in which they find those monuments wanting. “Kooks”’s position at the
                    album’s center directs our attention to its tonal incongruity, while Bowie’s
                    shapeshifting acts (from nostalgic dad to furious teenager to dispassionate
                    narrator) suggest that he’s ultimately on the side of experience, not innocence.</p>
                <p> As I said at this essay’s outset, childhood and parenthood are doubled concepts
                    in the Romantic poem, and they are on <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> , too. If “Kooks”
                    subconsciously articulates an Oedipal struggle between the poet-father and his
                    text-son that is intensely personal, it also dramatizes a publicly-oriented
                    reactionary adult incursion into teenaged self-awakening that brings into focus
                    the rest of the album’s call to “wake up, sleepyhead.” As Shelton Waldrep notes,
                    from <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> onwards, “Bowie quickly established himself and his
                    songs as anti-sixties, pro-seventies anthems for the doomed youth of the future”
                    (106). <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> seems eerily prescient about the ways in which
                    the revolutionary optimism of the 1960s would in the 70s be replaced by economic
                    stagnation and social unrest on both sides of the Atlantic. The utopian visions
                    of the 1960s, personified by “Kooks” Romantically-inclined narrator, must have
                    felt distant and naïve to those who came of age in the decade after Woodstock.</p>
                <p>
                    <emph>Hunky Dory</emph> describes a cultural shift from a Romantic idealism, one
                    in which Major Tom can look in awe at the beauty of “Planet Earth,” unifying the
                    human race through his gaze from “one hundred thousand miles,” to a social order
                    characterized by fragmentation and pop culture’s demand for performance, in
                    which, as “Life on Mars?” has it, we are each the stars of “the freakiest” and
                    “the best-selling show,” trapped in endless representation (“it’s about to be
                    writ again”). In this vision, rather than gaze back approvingly at ourselves
                    from afar, we are instead strangers to each other and ourselves, looking
                    outwards for aliens. This bears comparison I think with another
                    post-revolutionary comedown. After the Battle of Waterloo, the Romantic
                    counter-culture movement also gave way to a more cynical and conservative
                    pervading spirit. Victor Nemoianu called the post-1815 period one which
                    registered “the social and spiritual shock of the preceding age,” manifested in
                    both a “feeling of chaos” and a therapeutic interest in the family, in
                    empiricism and factual precision and in history (14–6; 30). A new generation of
                    authors, some of whom, like Hartley and Sara Coleridge, had to contend with
                    their father’s textualizations of their child selves, like the disenchanted
                    teenaged voices of <emph>Hunky Dory</emph>, saw that their parents’ generation’s
                    experiment had failed to turn radical enthusiasm into the promised better world.
                    The conservative decades of the 1820s and 1830s, like the 1970s and 1980s, would
                    require new forms of protest and new forms of art. The nihilism of punk, disco,
                    and new wave appear on the face of it to articulate creative identities that
                    stood apart from the utopian aesthetics of their precursors more successfully
                    than Romanticism’s direct inheritors were able to find sufficiently new forms of
                    expression. Yet Romanticism proved a resilient set of ideas in both centuries,
                    able to survive both Europe’s bitter struggle towards representative democracy
                    in the 1830s and the depredations of free market economics, and it remains the
                    structuring discourse for how we think and feel about childhood. The baby of
                    “Kooks” and the sleeping Hartley of “Frost at Midnight” retain an emotional
                    force that manages to transcend scepticism about their parents’ motives,
                    encoding our ambivalent collective cultural investment in the idea of the
                    eternal child.</p>
                <div type="citation">
                    <head>Works Cited</head>

                    <bibl>Bowie, David. <emph>Hunky Dory</emph>. RCA Records, 1971.</bibl>
                    <bibl> ———.<emph>Hunky Dory</emph> promotional material. <emph>Bowie
                            Bible</emph>, <ref
                            target="https://www.bowiebible.com/albums/hunky-dory/6/#The_release"
                            >bowiebible.com/albums/hunky-dory/6/#The_release </ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———.<emph>Bowie at the Beeb: The Best of the BBC Radio Sessions
                            68−72</emph>. EMI Virgin, 2000.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor. <emph>Collected Works.</emph> Edited by Kathleen
                        Coburn and others, 16 vols., Princeton UP, 1969−2002.</bibl>

                    <bibl> Darnton, F.J. Harvey. <emph>Children’s Books in England</emph>. 2<hi
                            rend="superscript">nd</hi> ed., Cambridge UP, 1960.</bibl>

                    <bibl> Garlitz, Barbara. “The Immortality Ode: Its Cultural Progeny.”
                            <emph>SEL</emph>, vol. 6, 1966, pp. 639−49.</bibl>

                    <bibl>Glen, Heather. <emph>Vision and Disenchantment: Blake’s Songs and
                            Wordsworth’s Lyrical Ballads</emph>. Cambridge UP, 1983.</bibl>

                    <bibl> Jackson, Mary. <emph>Engines of Instruction, Mischief and Magic:
                            Children’s Literature in England from its Beginnings to 1839</emph>. U
                        of Nebraska P, 1989.</bibl>

                    <bibl>Kinks, The. <emph>The Kinks are The Village Green Preservation
                            Society</emph>. Pye, 1968.</bibl>

                    <bibl>McGavran, James Holt and Jennifer Daniel, editors. “Introduction.”
                            <emph>Time of Beauty, Time of Fear: The Romantic Legacy in the
                            Literature of Childhood</emph>, U of Iowa P, 2012, pp. xi−xxv.</bibl>

                    <bibl>Muir, Percy. <emph>English Children’s Books, 1600–1900</emph>. Praeger,
                        1954.</bibl>

                    <bibl>Myers, Mitzi. “Reading Children and Homeopathic Romanticism: Paradigm
                        Lost, Revisionary Gleam, or ‘Plus Ça Change, Plus C’est la Même Chose’?”
                            <emph>Literature and the Child: Romantic Continuations, Postmodern
                            Contestations</emph>, edited by James Holt McGavran, U of Iowa P, 1999,
                        pp. 44–84.</bibl>

                    <bibl>Nemoianu, Victor. <emph>The Taming of Romanticism: European Literature and
                            the Age of Beidermeier</emph>. Harvard UP, 1984.</bibl>

                    <bibl>O’Malley, Andrew. <emph>The Making of the Modern Child: Children’s
                            Literature and Childhood in the Late Eighteenth Century</emph>.
                        Routledge, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Plotz, Judith. “The Annus Mirabilis and the Lost Boy: Hartley’s Case.”
                            <emph>Studies in Romanticism</emph>, vol. 33, 1994, pp. 181−200.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Richardson, Alan.<emph>Literature, Education and Romanticism: Reading as
                            Social Practice, 1780–1832</emph>. Cambridge UP, 1994.</bibl>

                    <bibl>Richardson, Alan. “The Politics of Childhood: Wordsworth, Blake and
                        Catechistic Method.” <emph>ELH</emph>, vol. 56, no. 4, 1989, pp
                        853–68.</bibl>

                    <bibl>Ross, Ron. “David Bowie: Phallus in Pigtails, or the Music of the Spheres
                        Considered as Cosmic Boogie.” <emph>Words &amp; Music</emph>, July 1972.
                            <emph>Rock’s Back Pages</emph>, <ref
                            target="https://rocksbackpages.com/Library/Article/david-bowie-phallus-in-pigtails-or-the-music-of-the-spheres-considered-as-cosmic-boogie"
                            >
                            rocksbackpages.com/Library/Article/david-bowie-phallus-in-pigtails-or-the-music-of-the-spheres-considered-as-cosmic-boogie</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Summerfield, Geoffrey. <emph>Fantasy and Reason: Children’s Literature in
                            the Eighteenth Century</emph>. Methuen, 1983.</bibl>

                    <bibl> Thwaite, Mary. <emph>From Primer to Pleasure: An Introduction to the
                            History of Children’s Books in England</emph>. Library Association,
                        1963.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Turner, Beatrice. <emph>Romantic Childhood, Romantic Heirs: Reproduction
                            and Retrospection 1820−1850</emph> . Palgrave, 2017</bibl>


                    <bibl> Waldrep, Sheldon. <emph>The Aesthetics of Self-Invention: Oscar Wilde to
                            David Bowie</emph> . Minnesota UP, 2004.</bibl>

                    <bibl>Walker, Luke. “Tangled up in Blake: The Triangular Relationship Among
                        Dylan, Blake, and the Beats.” <emph>Rock and Romanticism: Blake, Wordsworth,
                            and Rock from Dylan to U2</emph> , edited by James Rovira, Lexington
                        Books, 2018, pp. 1−18.</bibl>

                    <bibl> Watts, Michael. “Oh, You Pretty Thing.” <emph>Melody Maker</emph> , 22
                        January 1972, p.19.</bibl>

                    <bibl> Wordsworth, William. <emph>The Major Works</emph> . Edited by Stephen
                        Gill, Oxford UP, 2002.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
