<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<!-- got rid of file description, encoding descriptions, and editorial declarations (do we need/want to move this info to the "about" section of the site) -->                   
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title type="main">David Bowie and the Legacies of Romanticism</title>
                    <title type="a">What We Talk About When We Talk About Bowie: David Bowie and Enlightenment Philosophies of Identity
                    </title>
                    <author><name>Emily A. Bernhard Jackson</name></author>
                    <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>General Editor,</resp>
                        <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>General Editor,</resp>
                        <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>Praxis Series Editor</resp>
                        <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                    </respStmt>
                </titleStmt>
                <editionStmt>
                    <edition><date>2022-07-25</date></edition>
                </editionStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado,
                        Boulder</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                    <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                            or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                            purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                            use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
                        <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                            are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                            with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                            permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                            requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                            notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
                            forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
                                <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                                <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                                <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                                <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                                <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                                <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                            </address></p>
                        <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                            conditions: <list>
                                <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                    without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                                <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                    other than their current ones.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                            them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                            have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                            Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                            continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                            generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                            a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                            use.</p>
                    </availability>
                    <idno type="edition">praxis.2022.bowie.jackson</idno>
                    <idno type="resource">bowie</idno>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a" type="main">What We Talk About When We Talk About Bowie: David Bowie and Enlightenment Philosophies of Identity
                            </title>
                            <author role="secondary">
                                <persName>
                                    <forename>Emily A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bernhard-Jackson</surname>
                                </persName>
                            </author>
                            <ptr
                                target="https://romantic-circles.org/praxis/bowie/praxis.2022.bowie.jackson.html"
                            />
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">What We Talk About When We Talk About Bowie: David Bowie and Enlightenment Philosophies of Identity
                            </title>
                            <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of
                                    Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2022-07-25">July 25, 2022</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
            <encodingDesc>
                <editorialDecl>
                    <quotation>
                        <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for
                            &#226;&#8364;&#339;," for &#226;&#8364;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for '.</p>
                    </quotation>
                    <hyphenation eol="none">
                        <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
                        <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                            keyboard</p>
                        <p>Em-dashes have been rendered as #8212</p>
                    </hyphenation>
                    <normalization method="markup">
                        <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                        <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
                            such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                    </normalization>
                    <normalization>
                        <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                        <p>&#194;&#163; has been used for &#194;&#163;, the pound sign</p>
                        <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
                            been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                    </normalization>
                </editorialDecl>
                <tagsDecl>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                        12pt;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                    <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
                </tagsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
            <profileDesc>
                <textClass>
                    <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Criticism"/>
                    <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                    <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                    <keywords scheme="https://www.romantic-circles.org">
                        <term subtype="tags">cyberpunk</term>
                        <term subtype="tags">Vodoo</term>
                    </keywords>
                </textClass>
            </profileDesc>
            
            
                <!-- deleted the Nines information and the profile description -->
                
                <revisionDesc>
                    <change>
                        <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                        <date>July 25, 2022</date>
                        <list>
                            <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                        </list>
                    </change>
                </revisionDesc>
            </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p rend="noCount">This essay argues that David Bowie’s explorations of identity can meaningfully be
                    linked to explorations of the same topic by Enlightenment philosophers. It analyses
                    these connections in both Bowie’s work and his life and considers the ways in which
                    that life and work extend the thinking of John Locke, David Hume, and George
                    Berkeley to offer a new possible construction of identity, one that depends on the
                    viewer rather than the viewed.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            
            <div type="essay">
                <head>What We Talk About When We Talk About Bowie: David Bowie and Enlightenment Philosophies of Identity</head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Emily A. Bernhard-Jackson</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>University of Exeter</affiliation>
                </byline>
          
            <p>All culture has a history, of course. We can trace Lord Byron back to Alexander Pope;
                we can trace David Bowie back to the Beat movement.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Kevin Cann writes that in the
                            autumn of 1961 Bowie frequented “central London’s beatnik haunt
                            Trafalgar Square to talk to the denizens about Kerouac and the Beat
                            movement” (21).</note> But every history has its own history:
                we can trace Pope back to Horace and the Beats back to the Enlightenment. This
                lineage of reference prompts a question: Is posterity transitive? If I can link this
                writer to this thinker and this thinker to that thinker, am I justified in linking
                this writer to that thinker? In the case of Byron and Horace the answer is a safe
                “yes,” both because Byron produced a work called “Hints from Horace” and because his
                satire is demonstrably Horatian. The case of Bowie and the Enlightenment, however,
                is less clear. Bowie never acknowledged a debt to Enlightenment philosophy, and what
                critics know of his reading material doesn’t show any direct encounters with it.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Admittedly,
                            the evidence is small—limited to a widely published list of “David
                            Bowie’s Top 100 Books” that originated on his official website. See <ref
                                target="http://www.bowiebookclub.com/david-bowies-100-most-influential-books/"
                                >www.bowiebookclub.com/david-bowies-100-most-influential-books/</ref>.</note>
                I would argue, however, that one <emph>can</emph> link Bowie back to the
                Enlightenment, not only because of his connection to the Beats, but also because
                much of his career demonstrates a preoccupation with themes and questions that also
                troubled Enlightenment philosophers. Gavin Budge has suggested that critics might
                profit from exploring Romantic writing’s debt to British Enlightenment philosophy
                (18). This essay offers an exploration of one facet of Bowie’s debt to the same
                movement: his exploration of identity.</p>
            <p>Because “David Bowie” is an elastic term, I want to begin by explaining that the
                David Bowie I consider here is the David Bowie of the years 1972 to 1983. This is
                Bowie’s most fertile period and the one with which he remains most closely
                associated. Moreover, my discussion deals largely with Bowie’s public persona rather
                than his lyrics or music. As Adam Trainer has pointed out, “David Bowie as a
                phenomenon is primarily about performance,” and it is in his public presentation
                that he most clearly engages with Enlightenment thought.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See
                        Adam Trainer’s “‘Well, I Wouldn’t Buy the Merchandise’: David Bowie as
                        Postmodern Auteur.” Although critics have generally tended to consider
                        Bowie’s performance of self rather than his music and lyrics, there are
                        exceptions. See, for example, Wilfred Mellers, “Still Hunky Dory, After All
                        These Years”; Shelton Waldrep, <emph>Future Nostalgia:
                            Performing David Bowie</emph>; and Chris O’Leary, <emph>Rebel
                            Rebel</emph> (itself a descendant of his blog, <emph>Pushing
                            Ahead of the Dame</emph>).</note> I also want to stress that this
                essay is part of the beginning of a longer project that considers Bowie’s engagement
                with Romanticism and its Enlightenment origins. What follows here is thus a series
                of ideas that I may well end up altering or disagreeing with further down the
                line.</p>
            <p>In considering Bowie’s link to the British Enlightenment, it is useful to invoke
                ethnomethodologist Harold Garfinkel’s term, “indexicality.” Garfinkel defines
                indexicality as the meaning an object or concept has for those who invoke it, a
                meaning that does not necessarily align with its original meaning (although it
                retains something of that original meaning).<note
                        place="foot" resp="author"> As the <emph>Encyclopedia of Case Study
                                Research</emph> puts it, “Indexicality takes
                                an interest in the 'rules' people employ to make sense of verbal
                                interaction. Indexical properties of language-in-use may refer . . .
                                words that are understandable for the members of a social or
                                cultural group in a particular context. Language is understood as
                                naturally constitutive of social life and strongly depends on the
                                context and history of the place in which it is used”
                            (352).</note> Indexicality can be both transitive and
                mutable. If you hear Bauhaus’s version of “Ziggy Stardust,” for example, you now
                understand not “Ziggy Stardust” but Bauhaus’s indexicality of it. You may retain
                their indexical understanding, or you may process it into your own indexicality of
                the song, which would be your indexicality of Bauhaus’s indexicality of “Ziggy
                Stardust,” but would retain some of the meanings of Bowie’s original, too. Indexical
                transmission is thus a kind of game of signifying the children’s game of “Whisper
                Down the Lane,” although one in which each whisper does retain at least something of
                the original.</p>
            <p>Bowie’s understanding of Enlightenment thought may be seen as an indexical process
                that begins with the Beats: he often acknowledged the influence the movement had on
                    him.<note place="foot" resp="author"> “I
                            wanted to be just like Sal Paradise and Dan Moriarty [the central
                            characters of <emph>On the Road</emph>],” Bowie once said
                            (Cann 21).</note> The Beats themselves were strongly influenced
                by the works of the Frankfurt School philosopher Herbert Marcuse, who believed that
                the critical spirit of the Enlightenment found continuation in the theories of Hegel
                and Marx, and “reproached the positivists for having killed the true spirit of the
                Enlightenment by stifling its fundamentally negative dimension.” For Marcuse,
                liberating people from their alienation—from “enslavement to the instruments of
                production” and “subjection to the economic sphere”—was the only true revolution,
                and he believed it could emerge only via “outsiders to the system—the young, the
                unemployed and others at the fringes of society” (Delacampagne 207–9). In light of
                this explanation, it is not surprising that Marcuse also influenced the hippies,
                another central influence on the young David Bowie. Thus, from the Beats and the
                hippies to Marcuse to the Enlightenment, a line of indexicality offers one
                possibility for how Bowie might have encountered Enlightenment thought.</p>
            <p>However, he encountered it, though, it is certain that the most
                obvious way in which Bowie connects to British Enlightenment philosophy is through
                his exploration of the concept of identity. That Bowie both engaged with and enacted
                questions surrounding identity is a commonplace by now. What has not yet been
                discussed, however, is that Bowie’s discomfort with single identity, and his
                attempts both to multiply identity and to determine what constitutes it, are
                engagements with and experiments upon hypotheses advanced by John Locke and David
                Hume.</p>
            <p>In his <emph>Treatise of Human Nature</emph> (1739),
                Hume argues that the notion of cohesive identity is a chimera: “There is properly
                no simplicity in [the mind] at one time, nor identity . . . whatever natural
                propension we may have to imagine that simplicity and identity . . . They are the
                successive perceptions only, that constitute the mind” (301). The assumption that
                people possess one continuous identity is, for Hume, founded on an error:
            <quote>A fiction, either of something invariable and uninterrupted, or of something
                mysterious and inexplicable, or at least with a propensity to such fictions. What
                will suffice to prove this hypothesis to the satisfaction of every fair enquirer, is
                to shew from daily experience and observation, that the objects, which are variable
                or interrupted, and yet are suppos’d to continue the same, are such only as consist
                of a succession of parts, connected together by resemblance, contiguity, or
                causation. . . . A change in any considerable part of a body destroys its identity;
                but ‘tis remarkable, that where the change is produc’d <emph>gradually</emph> and <emph>insensibly</emph> we are less apt to ascribe
                to it the same effect. The reason can plainly be no other, than that the mind, in
                following the successive changes of the body, feels an easy passage from the
                surveying its condition in one moment to the viewing of it in another, and at no
                particular time perceives any interruption in its actions. (I.4.6)</quote>
           Bowie positions himself as a Humean through the best-known facet of his career: his
                    personae.<note place="foot" resp="author">For more on Bowie
                            and Hume, see Theodore G. Ammon, “The Flux of It All.”</note>
                These personae and their reception prove Hume’s assertion that gradual change,
                although resulting in a new identity, is not perceived that way by those who witness
                it. If one traces the arc of Bowie’s evolution during the 1972–1983 period, one can
                see that the consecutive personae enact a process of progressive, interconnected
                change: Ziggy Stardust’s scarlet hair and pale skin (1972–73) remain in Aladdin Sane
                (1973), who dons an eye patch to become Hallowe’en Jack (1974), who cuts and
                lightens his hair but keeps it an autumnal shade and retains his pallor to become
                the Thin White Duke (1975–76), whose Germanic “kalte Pracht” [“cold splendour”] (Du
                Verger 13) is carried forward to an actual stay in Berlin from 1976 to 1979, during
                which period Bowie grows his hair out to its natural colour, which he keeps for
                1980’s <emph>Scary Monsters (and Super Creeps)</emph> album, on the cover
                of which not only is his hair helpfully colored red by the designer but he is
                dressed as a Pierrot, an image that features in the cover art of 1969’s <emph>Space Oddity</emph> album.<note
                        place="foot" resp="author"> For further versions of Bowie, see the Pin-Ups gallery on
                            his official website: <ref target="http://www.davidbowie.com/pinups"
                                >www.davidbowie.com/pinups</ref>.</note> Yet, because of
                resemblance and contiguity, these “successive changes” produce “an easy passage from
                the surveying its condition in one moment to the viewing of it in another.” All are
                understood to be the same “David Bowie,” despite the fact that if one placed a
                picture of Aladdin Sane next to a picture of the <emph>Scary
                    Monsters</emph> persona, one would be hard pressed to define them as sharing the
                same identity.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            This leaves aside the final version of Bowie, wandering Manhattan in a
                            puffa jacket and a messenger bag, who looks nothing like any of the
                            personae. See <ref
                                target="mailto:medium.com/@sadydoyle/waiting-for-bowie-47e07fc3878a"
                                >medium.com/@sadydoyle/waiting-for-bowie-47e07fc3878a</ref>.</note></p>
            <p>[Insert photos]</p>
            <p>In fact, according to Hume, they do not share the same identity, and Bowie seems to
                follow him in this, too. When asked by Russell Harty in 1975 whether for his next
                persona he intended to continue with the “glittery Ziggy Stardust thing,” Bowie
                responded, “I think the image I adopt may well be me. I’m sort of inventing me at
                the moment.” A good deal of music-critic dissatisfaction with Bowie, and a certain
                amount of philosophical discussion, centers around his alleged inauthenticity.
                Matthew Lampert, for example, asserts that “From the beginning, Bowie built his solo
                career on the inauthentic” (152), while Bethany Usher and Stephenie Fremaux argue
                that he “creates fictional characters brought to life through live performance and
                media interviews” (58). But Bowie’s response to Harty suggests something quite
                different: that the personae are not acts but selves. Indeed, he shows an attachment
                to the multiple self throughout his career, particularly vocally in this 1974–76
                period: “If I’ve been at all responsible for people finding more characters in
                themselves than they originally thought they had, then I’m pleased,” he says in the
                1974 documentary <emph>Cracked Actor</emph> (28:19), while the title of
                Bowie’s 1974 song, “Who Can I Be Now?” seems an extension of Hume’s odd description
                of his attempts to quantify selfhood. “When I enter most intimately into what I
                    call <emph>myself</emph>,” Hume writes, “I always stumble on some
                particular perception or other, of heat or cold, light or shade, love or hatred,
                pain or pleasure. I never can catch <emph>myself</emph> at any time
                without a perception, and never can observe any thing but the perception.” Bowie’s
                title lays bare what these statements suggest: that the self can simultaneously be
                an other, and that humans can simultaneously possess within them more than one self
                (in Hume’s case, one that is analysed and one that analyses).</p>
            <p>Bowie’s personae support this conclusion. Each has a different background (space, the
                Weimar Republic, post-apocalypse), not just fully realized but also different from
                the background of the other personae, and from Bowie’s own background. Each makes a
                different—or differently inflected—type of music; each has his own style of dress;
                each even moves differently on stage, the icy stillness of the Thin White Duke
                bearing no resemblance to the loose knees of <emph>Let’s Dance</emph>’s
                pop singer.<note place="foot" resp="author"> For a discussion that argues
                        for a uniformity of movement across Bowie’s personae, see Thorsten
                        Botz-Borstein, “You Don’t Have to Be Stupid to Be Cool.” For one that
                        considers the role of Bowie’s voice in the creation of persona, see Kevin
                        Holm-Hudson, “‘Who Can I Be Now?’: David Bowie’s Vocal Personae.”</note>
                Wade Hollingshaus asserts that “Bowie’s audiences are well trained in their approach
                to Bowie’s work; as they search for and identify the silent speech of that work,
                they allow whatever they find to coalesce around the ‘Bowie’ image” (121), but this
                is not quite the case. Bowie’s audiences may file each persona under the heading
                “David Bowie,” but they also recognize them as distinct beings in their own right:
                no Bowie fan worth her salt would tell you that Ziggy Stardust and the elegant
                clotheshorse of <emph>Let’s Dance</emph> are the same guy.<note place="foot" resp="author"> I use this
                            word deliberately, in anticipation of this article’s later discussion of
                            Locke’s use of the terms “man” and “person.”</note> When
                assuming a persona, then, Bowie both is and is not, simultaneously. Rob Sheffield
                describes the David Bowie of the Thin White Duke period as “a blond coat hanger with
                a dead rock star hanging on it” (39), and this mordant witticism is a more serious
                assessment than it at first appears to be. In <emph>Cracked Actor</emph>
                Bowie muses that “I couldn’t decide whether I was writing the characters or whether
                the characters were writing me” (37:00). Bowie may always be himself, but so are his
                    personae.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Simon Critchley writes, “during the 1970s . . . Bowie, almost
                            ascetically, almost eremetically, disciplines himself into becoming a
                            nothing, a mobile and massively creative nothing that could assume new
                            faces, generate new illusions, and create new forms”
                    (102).</note></p>
            <p> In this way the personae are living enactments of Hume’s assertion that “The mind is
                a kind of theatre, where several perceptions successively make their appearance;
                pass, re-pass, glide away, and mingle in an infinite variety. . . . There is
                properly no simplicity in it at one time, nor identity in different. . . . They are
                the successive perceptions only, that constitute the mind” (I.4.6). The mistake
                critics and philosophers make is to read identity from Bowie’s exterior into his
                interior: because Ziggy Stardust is made visible to the audience from dyed hair,
                make-up, and costumes, the understanding is that he must be an assumed identity, an
                acted part. In fact, it would be more accurate to read from Bowie’s interior to his
                exterior: Ziggy is an extrusion of portion of David Bowie, garbed and colored in
                order to reify an interior way of experiencing the world.<note place="foot" resp="author"> In fact,
                            Usher and Fremaux all but acknowledge this, although they are determined
                            to make Bowie’s adherence to the truth of the personae mean something
                            else: “It is well documented that Ziggy Stardust, Aladdin Sane, and the
                            Thin White Duke each took over Bowie to the point of excess. . . . Press
                            and fans’ inability to differentiate between Bowie and his personae was
                            supported by Bowie himself who, at times, spoke in character as Ziggy or
                            emphasized them as being one and the same . . . In this way, Bowie’s use
                            of personae was meant to be a piece of performance art”
                        (58–9).</note></p>
            <p>Funnily enough, critics help Bowie to prove this—via another Humean assertion. In the
                second book of the <emph>Treatise</emph>, Hume argues
                for selves as social constructions:
            <quote>If a person considered himself in the same light, in which he appears to his admirer,
                he would first receive a separate pleasure, and afterwards a pride or
                self-satisfaction, according to the hypothesis above explained. Now nothing is more
                natural than for us to embrace the opinions of others in this particular; both from
                sympathy, which renders all their sentiments intimately present to us; and from
                reasoning, which makes us regard their judgment, as a kind of argument for what they
                affirm. These two principles of authority and sympathy influence almost all our
                opinions; but must have a peculiar influence, when we judge of our own worth and
                character. (2.1.11)</quote>
           As Ruth Boeker has pointed out, “If a self were merely a
                    bundle of perceptions which is given in introspection, then it would be
                    difficult for others to have access to myself, and to praise and blame me . . .
                    a self will be accessible both from a first person . . . perspective and from
                    the perspective of others” (5). By this logic, if a Bowie persona appears to be
                    a fully-formed identity, then he is. A perceived self is (at least to some
                    degree) an actual self. And both critics and fans frequently treat Bowie’s
                    perceived selves as if they were actual selves. Every Bowie fan has a favorite
                    persona, and the choice is based not on the excellence of the costumes nor the
                    execution of the accompanying stage show, but on the character the persona
                    exudes.
                <note place="foot" resp="author"> Certainly the
                            costumes and stage show play a part in creating the persona, but rare is
                            the fan who chooses “her” persona based on these. As for the choice of
                            persona, a very informal straw poll suggests that The Thin White Duke is
                            the
                favourite.</note> Even academic writers often speak of a given persona as a being in his own right: Hollingshaus, for example, asserts that “Ziggy is more than just an alter ego for David Bowie. Ziggy is the protagonist in a rock star suicide” (107). Sometimes even as the personae are understood as Bowie creations they are simultaneously treated as real, as when Hollingshaus writes that “D.A. Pennebaker’s documentary recording of Ziggy’s farewell concert performance shows Bowie and his band, the Spiders, getting into costume backstage before the concert” (102). Strictly speaking, Ziggy doesn’t have a farewell concert. He doesn’t have anything, because he doesn’t exist separately from David Bowie. Yet, as Hollingshaus’s wording shows, it is difficult not to think of the two identities as having separate selfhoods.
            </p>
            <p>Bowie’s fully realized personae, then, raises the very
                    Humean question of how to identify identity. I have written elsewhere about the
                    complications inherent in performances of the song “Ziggy Stardust.” Within the
                    world of that song, its lyrics about a left-handed, odd-eyed rock star are sung
                    in the voice of a member of his backing band. At the same time, in the stage
                    performance, these lyrics are being sung by a left-handed, odd-eyed rock star
                    dressed as the rock star he is singing about, but in the voice of that
                    backing-band member. The singer is, of course, neither the rock star the song
                    describes nor the backing-band member telling the story: he is David Bowie,
                    singing in one persona about another persona. It would be difficult to find a
                    better realization of Hume’s assertion that consciousness is made up of
                    “successive perceptions only.”
                <note place="foot" resp="author"> See Emily Bernhard-Jackson,
                            “‘Sometimes I feel like the whole human race’: Lord Byron and David
                            Bowie Consider the Question of
                    Identity.”</note> Indeed, Bowie’s stage performances of “Ziggy Stardust” raise the possibility that identity may consist of different perceptions occurring <emph>simultaneously</emph>. And in giving shape to Hume’s hypothesis and raising
                    that possibility, the performances also connect back to the question that Hume
                    poses: “What then gives us so great a propension to ascribe an identity to these
                    successive perceptions, and to suppose ourselves possest of an invariable and
                    uninterrupted existence thro’ the whole course of our lives?” (1.4.6).</p>
            <p>Well, one might reply, what gives us such a propension in this case is the fact that all of the personae are performed by the same person, David Bowie. What’s more, this assertion has John Locke to back it up. In his
                <emph>Essay Concerning Human
                Understanding</emph> (1689), Locke draws a distinction between “man” and “person,” two labels I have avoided applying to Bowie in this article precisely because Locke gives them quite specific definitions. For Locke, “man” refers to “the same continued life communicated to different particles of matter, as they happen successively to be united to [an] organized living body” (II.27.8), while “person” means “a thinking intelligent being, that has reason and reflection, and can consider itself as itself, the same thinking thing, in different times and places; which it does only by that consciousness which is inseparable from thinking. . . . It [person] is a forensick term appropriating actions and their merit; and so belongs only to intelligent agents capable of a law” (2.27.9–26). Using these definitions, David Bowie is both a man and a person, one who performs the personae and is not a being separate from them.
            </p>
            <p>There is a problem, however. Also using these definitions, David Bowie, both man and
                person, does not exist. Bowie never legally changed his name; his particles of
                matter and thinking intelligent being were both legally—forensically—attached to the name David Jones throughout his life.
                And while arguing for a distinction between David Bowie and David Jones may at first
                seem a piece of pedantic literalism, it becomes less so when one knows that from
                very early on in his career, Bowie (or whatever we should call him) drew a
                distinction between David Bowie and himself. As early as an 1969 interview about his
                involvement with the Beckenham Arts Lab, he speaks of “Bowie” as if he were a
                separate entity:
            <quote><l><emph>Interviewer: I wonder if you will still live
                    within the same social framework if the record goes to number one?</emph></l>
            <l>D: Yes, why not. We’ll invite the straight journalists back . .
                . after the Folk Club and Bowie will still be doing the same things and not
                answering the same questions.</l>
            <l>. . .</l>
            <l>D: I got immersed in Buddhism and had a big re-think about
                where I was at. . . . The David Bowie career was a physical manifestation of where I
                was at spiritually—it may seem that
                I’ve moved around a lot, but at least I was honest to my head . . . (Finnigan
                90–2)</l></quote>
            This dissociation of Bowie from Bowie continues as his career progresses. In the 1973
                documentary, <emph>Ziggy Stardust and the Spiders from Mars</emph>, he
                tells an interviewer that “I believe in my part all the way down the line, right the
                way down. But I do play it. Because that’s the way I do . . . that’s part of what
                Bowie is supposedly all about” (Pennebaker). In a 2014 interview in British
                newspaper <emph>The Guardian</emph>, Bowie’s wife Iman indicated that this
                division continued throughout Bowie’s life: “Bowie is just a persona. He’s a singer,
                an entertainer. David Jones is a man I met” (Cadwalladr). It would seem that David
                Bowie was just another persona for David Jones.</p>
            <p>What are we to do with this? It is possible to discuss Ziggy Stardust, et al., as
                acted personae because it is possible to conceive of them as separate from David
                Bowie the performer. It is extremely difficult, however, to make the cognitive leap
                necessary to conceive of “David Bowie” as merely a persona enacted by the walking,
                talking being that we only know as David Bowie. What is this being if it is not
                David Bowie? Have critics been talking about Bowie when all along they should have
                been talking about Jones? Or are we to give David Bowie the legitimacy of personhood
                when he’s in use (as it were), since in that capacity he gives interviews, expresses
                beliefs, offers thoughts? Are these beliefs and thoughts different to Jones’s? Is
                the man who tells a dumb joke to camera in an outtake posted on YouTube David Bowie
                (he’s on camera!) or David Jones (it’s a personal moment!)?</p>
            <p>All of which is to say that thinking of “David Bowie” as the ultimate piece of
                performance art by David Jones, performed so well that “he” appears to have become a
                fully extant being in his own right, raises fundamental questions about the nature
                of identity, and of personae. At what point does a persona become an identity, and
                to what extent is an identity a persona? Bowie’s “Bowie” persona asks this not in
                the tedious postmodern sense that invokes discourse, performativity, the absence of
                essential self, etc., etc., but in a concrete sense that extends Enlightenment
                questions about identity until they very nearly snap.</p>
            <p>In fact, one might argue that he does make them snap but in the experiences of his
                real life rather than on stage. Having separated man from person, Locke remains
                preoccupied by the question of what precisely makes a person a person:
            <quote>[I]t is plain, consciousness, as far as ever it can be extended—should it be to ages
                past—unites existences and actions very remote in time into the same person . . . so
                that whatever has the consciousness of present and past actions, is the same person
                to whom they both belong. . . . But yet possibly it will still be objected,—Suppose
                I wholly lose the memory of some parts of my life, beyond a possibility of
                retrieving them, so that perhaps I shall never be conscious of them again; yet am I
                not the same person that did those actions, had those thoughts that I once was
                conscious of, though I have now forgot them? To which I answer, that . . . if it be
                possible for the same man to have distinct incommunicable consciousness at different
                times, it is past doubt the same man would at different times make different
                persons. (2.27.9–20)</quote>
           In other words, for Locke, if a man has no memory of a part of his life, then during
                that part he was, quite literally, not himself. Bowie may be the only public figure
                to offer an opportunity to consider the real-life implications of this
                philosophy.</p>
            <p> It’s well known that for Bowie (and Jones) the 1970s were a whirlwind of heavy drug
                    use.<note place="foot" resp="author"> For simplicity’s sake, the essay
                        continues to refer to him as Bowie until its end.</note> One result of
                this excess was that it left him with what he described as “incredible losses of
                memory. . . . Whole <emph>chunks</emph> of my life. I can’t remember, for instance, any—any—of 1975.” In one interview, Bowie detailed watching
                footage of himself performing as Ziggy Stardust and thinking, “This boy used to
                dress like that for a living? My <emph>God</emph> this is funny”; in
                another he remarked of recording the Thin White Duke’s 1976 album <emph>Station to Station</emph> that “I can’t even remember the studio. I know it was
                in LA because I’ve read it was. . . . I listen to <emph>Station to
                    Station</emph> as a piece of work by an entirely different person” (Loder 334),
                and once asked to explain his puzzling 1971 song, “The Bewlay Brothers,” he said, “I
                can’t imagine what the person who wrote that had on his mind” (Pegg 39).</p>
            <p> This real-life self-dissociation is something more extreme than Hume’s “successive
                perceptions.” Even if one agrees with Hume that a consciousness is merely a
                succession of impressions and/or thoughts passing through the mind, one must grant
                that these impressions are in some way connected, since empirical examination of
                one’s own consciousness reveals that one thought gives rise to another, which gives
                rise to another, which connects to an earlier impression, and so on. But the
                condition that Bowie outlines is one of disconnection: a consciousness (or
                personhood, or identity) interrupted then taken up again later. According to Locke’s
                reasoning, this would mean that David Bowie, the man, was in fact different <emph>persons</emph> throughout his life:
            <quote>Let any one reflect upon himself, and conclude that he has in himself an immaterial
                spirit, which is that which thinks in him . . . let him also suppose it to be the
                same soul that was in Nestor or Thersites, at the siege of Troy . . . but he now
                having no consciousness of any of the actions either of Nestor or Thersites, does or
                can he conceive himself the same person with either of them? . . . [T]his
                consciousness . . . not reaching to any of the actions of either of those men, he is
                no more one self with either of them than if the soul or immaterial spirit that now
                informs him had been created, and began to exist, when it began to inform his present body (1.27.14)</quote>
            Since Bowie was ambulant and conversational (albeit sometimes barely), and working,
                during the years he cannot remember, there was some sort of identity existent, but
                by Locke’s lights this identity was not David Bowie. This would seem to turn the
                critical conversation on its head. It suggests that rather than thinking of the
                personae as performances by David Bowie, we should think of David Bowie as being
                performed, at least sometimes, by the personae: the Thin White Duke in 1975, Ziggy
                Stardust in 1973, and someone going by the name “David Bowie” and wearing a dress
                for men in 1971.</p>
            <p> In other words, Bowie’s life experience suggests not simply that a persona can be an
                identity, nor that an identity may actually be a fully-fleshed and embodied persona,
                but that, in the most literal sense of the phrase, we are who we seem to be: if it
                looks like “David Bowie” and it sounds like “David Bowie,” then it <emph>is</emph> David Bowie, no matter who might be living inside it. Bowie’s lacunae
                of memory, coupled with his consistent existence as an acknowledgement as “David
                Bowie” during these periods of blankness, suggest that real, true being lies not
                inside the consciousness or the mind, where things may change and go missing, but in
                the perception of a cohesive self by others.<note place="foot" resp="author"> He put out an album, presented a Grammy, made a movie, and performed with
                        Cher all under this name in 1975.</note></p>
            <p> While this loops back to Hume’s notion of selves as social, it also connects to the
                philosophy of George Berkeley.<note place="foot" resp="author"> For another analysis of Bowie’s connection to
                            Berkeley, see Nicolas Michaud, “The Babe with the
                    Power.”</note> For Berkeley, objects exist only as the mind perceives
                them. This does not mean that they vanish when not perceived, but rather that they
                exist <emph>for</emph> the mind as that mind
                understands them: as Berkeley puts it, “For what are . . . Objects but the things we
                perceive by Sense, and what, I pray you, do we perceive besides our own ideas and
                Sensations?” (I.4). Philosophers often consider what this means for the self that
                perceives, but they don’t tend to focus on what it might mean for the <emph>perceived</emph>. One is on safe ground asserting that a tomato
                exists for a mind only as a mind perceives it, but what about an ant? A cat? A boy
                from Bromley who makes himself into an icon? Berkeley’s <emph>esse est
                    percipi</emph> [to be is to be perceived] suggests that the last of these, at
                least, has a minimum of two identities: the one in his own mind (however
                multifarious that may be), and the one perceived by those who encounter him. It
                further suggests that the identity in his own mind may be less his identity than the
                one others behold. While that interior identity may sometimes be absent, the one
                others see remains present: <emph>percipi est esse</emph>.</p>
            <p> Now, where does that leave us? Both intrigued and somewhat slightly dazed, I
                imagine—but I judge only from my own perceptions. It also, however, leaves us with a
                David Bowie whose most significant connection to Enlightenment thought may be that
                he does what Enlightenment philosophers cannot quite force themselves to do: he
                brings his viewers face to face with the insolubility of identity. Even Hume, the
                boldest of these thinkers, ends his analysis by taking refuge in the assertion that
                “all the nice and subtile questions concerning personal identity can never possibly
                be decided, and are to be regarded rather as grammatical than as philosophical
                difficulties” (I.4.6). Bowie, I think, would disagree, precisely because he makes
                subtle questions concerning personal identity vividly material. Bowie moves abstract
                Enlightenment ideas into the world of lived art—indeed, he literally brings them to
                life. He thus suggests that despite the new media, digital effulgence, and virtual
                reality in which we are all constantly immersed (and of which he took full
                advantage), we continue to wrestle with an old question: Who am I? And who am I now?
                And now?</p>
                <div type="citation">
                    <head>Works Cited</head>
                    
            <bibl>Ammon, Theodore G. “The Flux of It All.” <emph>David Bowie and
                    Philosophy: Rebel Rebel</emph>, edited by Theodore G. Ammon, Open Court, 2016, pp.
                19–29.</bibl>
            <bibl>Berkeley, George. <emph>A Treatise Concerning the Principles of Human
                    Knowledge</emph>. Edited by Kenneth Winkler, Hackett, 1982.</bibl>
            <bibl>Bernhard-Jackson, Emily. “‘Sometimes I feel like the whole human race’: Lord Byron
                and David Bowie Consider the Question of Identity.” <emph>Byron
                    Journal</emph>, vol. 46, no. 2, 2018, pp. 113–25.</bibl>
            <bibl>Botz-Borstein, Thorsten. “You Don’t Have to Be Stupid to Be Cool.” <emph>David Bowie and Philosophy: Rebel Rebel</emph>, edited by Theodore G. Ammon, Open
                Court, 2016, pp. 9–18.</bibl>
            <bibl>Bowie, David. Interview with Russell Harty. <emph>The Russell Harty
                    Show</emph>, ITV, 28 November 1975. <emph>YouTube</emph>, uploaded by
                JGGstudios, 2 Dec 2016, <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dmypRafb9Ew"
                    >www.youtube.com/watch?v=dmypRafb9Ew</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>———. <emph>Scary Monsters (and Super Creeps).</emph> RCA Victor, 1980.</bibl>
            <bibl>Budge, Gavin. <emph>Romantic Empiricism: Poetics and the Philosophy of
                    Common Sense, 1780–1830.</emph> Bucknell UP, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cadwalladr, Carol. “Iman: I am the face of a refugee.” <emph>The
                    Observer</emph>, 28 June 2014. <emph>The Guardian</emph>, <ref
                    target="http://www.theguardian.com/fashion/2014/jun/29/iman-i-am-the-face-of-a-refugee"
                    >www.theguardian.com/fashion/2014/jun/29/iman-i-am-the-face-of-a-refugee</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cann, Kevin. <emph>David Bowie Any Day Now, The London Years
                    1947–1974</emph>. Adelita, 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl>Critchley, Simon. <emph>David Bowie</emph>. OR Books, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl>Delacampagne, Christian. <emph>A History of Philosophy in the Twentieth
                    Century</emph>. Translated by M.B. DeBevoise, Johns Hopkins UP, 1999.</bibl>
            <bibl>Du Verger, Jean. “David Bowie’s urban landscapes and nightscapes: A reading of the
                Bowiean text.” <emph>Miranda</emph>, no. 17, 2018, pp. 1–29, <ref
                    target="https://doi.org/10.4000/miranda.13401"
                    >doi.org/10.4000/miranda.13401</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>“Ethnomethodology.” <emph>Encyclopedia of Case Study
                    Research</emph>. Edited by A.J. Mills, G. </bibl>
            <bibl>Durepos, and E. Wiebe, SAGE Publications, 2010, pp.
                    351–3.</bibl>
            <bibl>Finnigan, Mary. <emph>Psychedelic Suburbia: David Bowie and the Beckenham
                    Arts Lab</emph>. Jorvik, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl>Garfinkel, Harold. <emph>Studies in Ethnomethodology,</emph> Prentice-Hall,
                1967.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hollingshaus, Wade. <emph>Philosophizing Rock Performance: Dylan,
                    Hendrix, Bowie</emph>. Scarecrow, 2013.</bibl>
            <bibl>Holm-Hudson, Kevin. “‘Who Can I Be Now?’: David Bowie’s Vocal Personae.” <emph>Contemporary Music Review</emph>, vol. 37, no. 3, 2018, pp.214–34.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hume, David. <emph>A Treatise of Human Nature</emph>. Penguin, 1985.</bibl>
            <bibl>Lampert, Matthew. “The Madness and the Musician.” <emph>David Bowie and
                    Philosophy: Rebel Rebel</emph>, edited by Theodore G. Ammon, Open Court, 2016, pp.
                151–72.</bibl>
            <bibl>Locke, John. <emph>An Essay Concerning Human Understanding</emph>. Penguin
                Classics, 1998.</bibl>
            <bibl>Loder, Kurt. “David Bowie: Straight Time.” <emph>Rolling Stone</emph>, 395,
                12 May 1983, <ref
                    target="http://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/david-bowie-straight-time-69334/"
                    >www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/david-bowie-straight-time-69334/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Mellers, Wilfred. “Still Hunky Dory, After All These Years.” <emph>The
                    Bowie Companion</emph>, edited by Elizabeth Thomson and David Gutman, Macmillan,
                1993, pp. 51–9.</bibl>
            <bibl>Michaud, Nicolas. “The Babe with the Power.” <emph>David Bowie and
                    Philosophy: Rebel Rebel</emph>, edited by Theodore G. Ammon, Open Court, 2016, pp.
                85–95.</bibl>
            <bibl>O’Leary, Chris. <emph>Rebel Rebel</emph>. Zero Books, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl>Pegg, Nicholas. <emph>The Complete David Bowie</emph>. 6<hi
                    rend="superscript">th</hi> ed., Titan, 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl>Pennebaker, D.A., director. <emph>Ziggy Stardust and the Spiders from
                    Mars</emph>. Twentieth Century Fox, 1973.</bibl>
            <bibl>Sheffield, Rob. <emph>Talking to Girls About Duran Duran</emph>. Plume,
                2010.</bibl>
            <bibl>Trainer, Adam. “‘Well, I Wouldn’t Buy the Merchandise’: David Bowie as Postmodern
                Auteur.” <emph>Cinema and Music</emph>, vol. 28, October 2003, <ref
                    target="http://sensesofcinema.com/2003/cinema-and-music/bowie_postmodern_auteur/"
                    >sensesofcinema.com/2003/cinema-and-music/bowie_postmodern_auteur/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Usher, Bethany and Stephanie Fremaux. “Turn Myself to Face Me: David Bowie in the
                1990s and Discovery of Authentic Self.” <emph>David Bowie: Critical
                    Perspectives</emph>, edited by Eoin Devereux, Aileen Dillane, and Martin J. Power,
                Routledge, 2015, pp. 56–81.</bibl>
            <bibl>Waldrep, Shelton. <emph>Future Nostalgia: Performing David Bowie.</emph>
                Bloomsbury Academic, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl>Yentob, Alan, director. <emph>Cracked Actor</emph>. BBC, 1975, <ref
                    target="https://archive.org/details/BBC_A_Film_By_Bowie_Cracked_Actor_1975"
                    >archive.org/details/BBC_A_Film_By_Bowie_Cracked_Actor_1975</ref>.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
