<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
				<author>
					<name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name>
				</author>
				<editor>Tim Fulford</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="edition">about</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:>
						<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address>
					</p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
								Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>Tim Fulford</author>
						<title>About this Edition</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title>
						<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
						<author>
							<name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name>
						</author>
						<editor>Tim Fulford</editor>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
							<pubPlace>University of Maryland</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p>Dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>&#163; has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="g" corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']">
					<category xml:id="people">
						<catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']">
					<category xml:id="places">
						<catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g7 #g27" scheme="#genre"/>
				<catRef target="#EEd.25.names" scheme="#people"/>
				<catRef target="#EEd.25.places" scheme="#places"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change n="5" when="2009-06-08" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="4" when="2009-04-30" who="#AB">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
				<list>
					<item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="3" when="2009-03-30" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="2" when="2009-03-20" who="#AB">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
				<list>
					<item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="1" when="2008-10-03" who="#KL">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name>
				<list>
					<item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="paratext">
				<head>About this edition</head>
				<p>Throughout the edition, letters are presented in chronological order, each letter being assigned its own number. Unpublished
					letters have all been newly transcribed from manuscript. Where letters have been previously published, we have returned to and
					transcribed the original manuscript when it survives. In cases where we have been unable to locate the manuscript of a published
					letter, copy-text is taken from the published version and this is recorded in the editorial headnote. </p>
				<p>All letters are transcribed in full and editorial intervention in the text has been kept to a minimum. Bloomfield’s original
					spelling, and mis-spelling, grammar and punctuation has been retained. Deletions are indicated by striking through the deleted
					word or phrase, but without any attempt to indicate the heaviness of the deletion. Throughout the text, ‘x’ is used to indicate an
					illegible character: e.g. ‘he xxid’. Underlining is indicated by italics: e.g. ‘<hi rend="ital">he</hi> said’. Editorial [...]
					within the text of an individual letter are used to indicate issues relating to the manuscript: a tear, cut, missing section or
					area obscured by a seal mark or blot, or a substantial section of a letter in the hand of a co-correspondent. Editorial
					&lt;...&gt; are used to indicate an authorial insertion of text above or below the line. </p>
				<p>Each letter has an editorial headnote which records the manuscript location and any previous instances of publication. This edition
					provides new information about when many of Bloomfield’s letters were written, and re-dates letters that have been misdated or
					misleadingly dated by previous editors; ‘?’ is used to indicate a dating about which there remains some uncertainty.</p>
				<p>Detailed information about Bloomfield’s correspondents, along with other important figures in his letters, can be found in the
					‘People’ section. Information about where Bloomfield lived and places that were significant to him is provided in the ‘Places’
					section of this edition. </p>
				<p>Editorial notes to the text are used to clarify references to persons, books, places, and events within the main body of each
					individual letter. They also identify quotations and provide translations of foreign language material.</p>
				<p>
					<hi rend="bold">People </hi>
				</p>
				<p>Tim Fulford is a Professor of English at Nottingham Trent University. He has published several monographs and articles in which
					Bloomfield features, including <title>Literature, Science and Exploration in the Romantic Era: Bodies of Knowledge</title> (2004).
					He edited <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>, vol. 3 of <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works, 1793-1810</title> (2004) and is
					co-general editor, with Lynda Pratt, of the forthcoming <title>Robert Southey: Later Poetical Works, 1811-1838</title>. Pratt and
					Fulford’s edition <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title> is also online at Romantic Circles.</p>
				<p>Lynda Pratt is a Reader in Romanticism and Director of the Centre for Regional Literature and Culture at the University of
					Nottingham. She has published widely on Southey and his circle. She was general editor of <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works,
						1793-1810</title>, 5 vols (2004) and is co-general editor, with Tim Fulford, of the forthcoming <title>Robert Southey: Later
						Poetical Works, 1811-1838</title>, 4 vols (Pickering and Chatto, 2011). Her edited collection <title>Robert Southey and the
						Contexts of English Romanticism</title> was published in 2006.</p>
				<p>Carol Bolton is a Lecturer in English at Loughborough University. Her monograph <title>Writing the Empire: Robert Southey and
						Romantic Colonialism</title> was published in 2007. She has published widely on Romantic period writing and is a volume editor
					of <title>Robert Southey: Later Poetical Works, 1811-1838</title>. </p>
				<p>Averill Buchanan is an AHRC-funded research fellow on <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title> and is based at the
					University of Nottingham. She completed an AHRC-funded PhD at Queen’s University Belfast in 2004 on the Anglo-Irish writer Mary
					Tighe. Her monograph <title>Mary Tighe, 1772-1810: The Irish Psyche</title> will be published by Ashgate in 2011.</p>
				<p>John Goodridge is a Professor at Nottingham Trent University. Among his publications are <title>Robert Bloomfield, Selected
						Poems</title> (2007), <title>Robert Bloomfield: Lyric, Class and the Romantic Canon</title> (2006, with S. White and B.
					Keegan), <title>Eighteenth-Century British Labouring-Class Poets, 1700-1800</title> (2003, with W. Christmas, B. Keegan and T.
					Burke) and <title>John Dyer, The Fleece: a Poem in Four Books (1757)</title> (2007, with J. C. Pellicer).</p>
				<p>Sam Ward is an AHRC-funded research fellow on <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title> and is based at the University
					of Nottingham. He completed a PhD at Nottingham Trent University in 2006. He has published essays on John Clare and Robert
					Bloomfield. His research interests also include James Montgomery.</p>
				<p>
					<hi rend="bold">Contact </hi>
				</p>
				<p>The editors welcome comments and corrections. Please contact:</p>
				<p>Tim Fulford: <ref target="mailto:tim.fulford@ntu.ac.uk">Tim.Fulford@ntu.ac.uk</ref></p>
				<p>
					<hi rend="bold">About the Design </hi>
				</p>
				<p>This electronic edition was TEI-encoded by Averill Buchanan under the supervision of Laura Mandell and her team at Miami University
					of Ohio, and with the assistance of David Rettenmaier and Mike Quilligan at the University of Maryland. Mandell transformed the
					TEI files into HTML by using modified versions of the transforms provided by the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml"
						>TEI</ref>. The HTML pages do not use frames but rather make extensive use of tables and stylesheets for layout and
					presentation. The site works best when viewed with Mozilla Firefox v. 3, Netscape 4.0, Internet Explorer 4.0, or higher, or a
					comparable browser; earlier browsers may not display everything properly.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
