<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
				<author>
					<name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name>
				</author>
				<editor>Tim Fulford</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="edition">birdsinsects</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:>
						<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address>
					</p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
								Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>Robert Bloomfield</author>
						<title>The Birds and Insects' Post Office</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title>
						<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
						<author>
							<name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name>
						</author>
						<editor>Tim Fulford</editor>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
							<pubPlace>University of Maryland</pubPlace>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p>Dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>&#163; has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="g" corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']">
					<category xml:id="people">
						<catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']">
					<category xml:id="places">
						<catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g12" scheme="#genre"/>
				<catRef target="#EEd.25.names" scheme="#people"/>
				<catRef target="#EEd.25.places" scheme="#places"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change n="5" when="2009-06-08" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="4" when="2009-04-30" who="#AB">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
				<list>
					<item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="3" when="2009-03-30" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="2" when="2009-03-20" who="#AB">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
				<list>
					<item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="1" when="2008-10-03" who="#KL">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name>
				<list>
					<item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">
				<head>The Bird and Insects' Post-Office <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Remains</title>, II, pp.
						125-66</note></head>
				<p rend="center">PREFACE</p>
				<p rend="center">_____</p>
				<p rend="indent1">We all know that Æsop has made his birds and beasts talk, and reason too; and that so well, as still to make the
					volume bearing his name, a favourite with thousands. Perhaps too, we all know that some French author, has objected to this method
					of teaching; alleging that children should not be imposed upon (or something to that effect), and led to believe in the <hi
						rend="ital">reality</hi> of talking birds and beasts. To me it appears plainly that they do not, nor are they inclined to
					believe in any such reality. Observe two or three children at play with a favourite kitten. When one of them, in mere wantonness,
					shall give the little animal a rap on the nose, or a squeeze by the tail, the owner of the cat will instantly exclaim — ‘Poor
					little pussy, she does not like that, <hi rend="ital">she says</hi>!’ Now, the child knows very well that the cat did not say a
					word about the matter, but she looked and acted as if she had, and that was enough. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">In the following pages, I have endeavoured to make my winged and creeping correspondents, talk in their own
					character, according to their well-known habits and pursuits. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I have added a few notes, sometimes of illustration and sometimes of inquiry; for, as natural history is almost a
					boundless field, I may stand in need of correction myself. It will be obvious that I have taken only some of the plainest and
					simplest subjects, for the purpose of trying whether any interest can be awakened in young minds by such means. And as I like to
					write for children, and think a great deal of information might be blended with amusement in this way, I hold myself acquitted of
					the charge of trifling and puerility, and am the young reader’s friend and well-wisher, </p>
				<p rend="right">R. B. </p>
				<p>P. S. — The letters signed C. are written, or translated, if you please, by my <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon"
						>eldest son</ref>; together with the verses on the close of May-day, at the end of the volume. </p>
				<p rend="center">THE</p>
				<p rend="center">BIRD AND INSECTS’</p>
				<p rend="center">POST-OFFICE.</p>
				<p rend="center">______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER I. </p>
				<p>FROM THE MAGPIE TO THE SPARROW. </p>
				<p>LITTLE JABBERER, </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I HAVE many times thought of addressing to you a few words of advice, as you seem to stand in need of such a friend.
					You know that I do not stand much upon ceremony; I am always ready for talking and for giving advice, and really wonder how other
					birds can keep themselves so quiet. Then you will pardon my frankness, since you know my character, when I inform you, that I
					think you remarkably tame and spiritless: you have no enterprise in you. In an old farm-yard, shuffling amongst the straw, there
					you may be found morning, noon, and night; and you are never seen in the woods, and groves, with me and my companions, where we
					have the blessing of free liberty, and fly where we please. You must often have heard me sing; that cannot be doubted, because I
					am heard a great way. As to me, I never come down to your farm, unless I think I can find a hen’s egg or two amongst the nettles,
					or a chicken or duck just hatched. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I earnestly advise you to change your manner of life, and take a little free air, as I do. Stop no longer in your
					dull yard, feeding upon pigs’ leavings, but come abroad with me.— But I must have done, till a better opportunity; for the
					gamekeeper with his gun has just turned the corner. Take my advice, and you may be as well off, and learn to sing as well as I do. </p>
				<p rend="right">Yours, in great haste, </p>
				<p rend="right">Mag. </p>
				<p rend="center">______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER II. </p>
				<p rend="center">THE SPARROW’S REPLY. </p>
				<p>OLD MAG. (I won’t say neighbour), </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I WAS hopping along the top ridge of the house when I received your insolent and conceited epistle, which does you
					no credit, but is very much in your usual style. ‘Little Jabberer,’ indeed! and pray, what is your letter of advice? Nothing but
					jabber from beginning to end. You <hi rend="ital">sing</hi>, you say. I have heard you often enough: but if yours is singing, then
					I must be allowed to be no judge of the matter. You say you are afraid of the game-keeper; this, perhaps, shows some sense in you;
					for he is paid for killing all kinds of vermin. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">And so you come down to our farm when you think you can steal something! Thus, if I did not hide my eggs, and my
					young ones, in a hole too small for you to enter, I can see pretty plainly, how I should come off with your thieving and your
					advice. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">Be advised in <hi rend="ital">your</hi> turn: keep away from our yard; for my master has a gun too; and your
					chattering, which I suppose you call singing, he abominably hates. You will be in danger of catching what the game-keeper
					threatens, and then where is the great difference between your station and mine? </p>
				<p rend="indent1">From my lodging under the thatch of the stable, I am, as you may happen to behave yourself, </p>
				<p rend="right">Yours, at a convenient distance, </p>
				<p rend="right">&amp;c. &amp;c. </p>
				<p rend="center">_______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER III. </p>
				<p rend="center">FROM A YOUNG GARDEN SPIDER TO HER MOTHER. </p>
				<p>DEAR MOTHER, </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I CANNOT exactly tell what happened before I came out of the shell; but, from circumstances, I can give you some
					information. When I came to life, amongst some scores of other little merry yellow creatures, I found myself, and all of us,
					enclosed in a thing, through which we with our eight eyes could see very well, but could not instantly get out. I soon perceived
					that we, in the egg state, wrapped in a white bag, as you left us, had been put into a thing called a bottle, by one of those
					great creatures, whom we always call <hi rend="ital">striders</hi>; but this was a particular one of that tribe, who wanted to
					play tricks with us — one whom they would perhaps call a philosopher.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="author">This part of the
						letter is very difficult of translation, as the plain word, in spider’s language, means merely ‘a deep one.’ [Bloomfield’s
						note]</note> Well, his own sense (if he had any) told him that we could not live without air; so he left the cork out, and
					went about his business; no doubt, of much less consequence than the lives of all us prisoners — but that they do not mind. But
					how long were we prisoners? Why, as soon as ever we were out of the shell, we began to spin, and linked our webs so thick
					together, that the philosopher’s bottle would hold us no longer. We climbed out in a crowd, and spread our webs over the room, up
					to the very ceiling. I shall never forget how the great booby stared, when he saw us all climbing up our own rope-ladders! I
					wonder if those great creatures are not sometimes caught in webs spun by their fellow-creatures, and whether they are not
					sometimes put by hundreds into a bottle, without possessing any means of escape? But I am but a child, and must live and learn
					before I talk more freely. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">Long life to you, dear mother, and plenty of flies. </p>
				<p rend="right">Yours ever, &amp;c. </p>
				<p rend="center">_______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER IV </p>
				<p rend="center">FROM A YOUNG NIGHTINGALE TO A WREN. </p>
				<p rend="right">Dated ‘Home Wood.’</p>
				<p>NEIGHBOUR, </p>
				<p rend="indent1">WHEN we last met, you seemed. very lively and agreeable, but you asked an abundance of questions, and particularly
					wanted to know whether we nightingales really do, as is said of us, cross the great water every year, and return in the spring to
					sing in your English groves. Now, as I am but young, I must be modest, and not prate about what I cannot as yet understand. I must
					say, nevertheless, that I never heard my parents talk of any particular long journey which they had performed to reach this
					country, or that they should return, and take me, and the rest of the family with them, at any particular time or season. I know
					this, that I never saw my parents fly further at one flight, than from one side of a field to another, or from one grove to the
					next. Who are they who call us ‘birds of passage?’<note n="2" place="foot" resp="author">COWPER, that excellent man and poet, and
						close observer of nature, writes as follows to his friend, on the 11th of March, 1792. <p rend="center">
							<hi rend="ital">‘To John Johnson, Esq.</hi>
						</p><p>‘You talk of primroses that you pulled on Candlemas-day, but what think you of me, who heard a nightingale on New
							Year’s day? Perhaps I am the only man in England who can boast of such good fortune. Good indeed! for if it was at all an
							omen, it could not be an unfavourable one. The winter, however, is now making himself amends, and seems the more peevish
							for having been encroached on at so undue a season. Nothing less than a large slice out of the spring will satisfy
							him.’</p><p rend="indent1">He adds the following lines on the occasion: </p><p><hi rend="ital">‘To the Nightingale, which
								the Author heard sing on New Years-day</hi>, 1792. </p><lg type="stanza">
							<l>‘Whence is it that amazed I hear </l>
							<l rend="indent1">From yonder wither’d spray. </l>
							<l>This foremost morn of all the year. </l>
							<l rend="indent1">The melody of May? </l>
						</lg><lb/><lg type="stanza">
							<l>And why, since thousands would be proud </l>
							<l rend="indent1">Of such a favour shown. </l>
							<l>Am I selected from the crowd. </l>
							<l rend="indent1">To witness it alone? </l>
						</lg><lb/><lg type="stanza">
							<l>Sing’st thou, sweet Philomel, to me. </l>
							<l rend="indent1">For that I also long </l>
							<l>Have practis’d in the groves like thee, </l>
							<l rend="indent1">Though not like thee in song? </l>
						</lg><lb/><lg type="stanza">
							<l>Or, sing’st thou rather under force </l>
							<l rend="indent1">Of some divine command, </l>
							<l>Commission’d to presage a course </l>
							<l rend="indent1">Of happier days at hand? </l>
						</lg><lb/><lg type="stanza">
							<l>Thrice welcome, then! for many a long </l>
							<l rend="indent1">And joyless year have I, </l>
							<l>As thou to-day, put forth my song </l>
							<l rend="indent1">Beneath a wintry sky. </l>
						</lg><lb/><lg type="stanza">
							<l>But thee no wintry skies can harm. </l>
							<l rend="indent1">Who only need’st to sing </l>
							<l>To make e’en January charm, </l>
							<l rend="indent1">And every season Spring. </l>
						</lg><p>[Bloomfield's note]</p></note> They certainly may know more of the extent of the GREAT WATERS than we can, neighbour
					Wren, but have they considered our powers, and the probability of what they assert? I am sure, if my parents should call on me to
					go with them, I shall be flurried out of my life. But it is my business to obey. I have so lately got my feathers, that I cannot
					be a proper judge of the matter. As to the swallows and many other birds going to a vast distance, there is no wonder in that, if
					you look at their wings; but how would you, for instance, perform such a journey; you, who seem to be in a constant agitation and
					flutter; you, who even when you sing, put yourself into a violent passion, as if you had not a minute to live? <hi rend="ital"
						>We</hi> nightingales are the birds for song! This you will acknowledge, I dare say, though I have not began yet. I will give
					you a specimen when I come back (if I am really to go), and you will hear me in ‘<hi rend="ital">Home Wood</hi>’ when it is dark,
					and you have crept into your little nest in the hovel. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">Believe me, I have a great respect for you, and am your young friend, </p>
				<p rend="right">THIRD-IN-THE-NEST.</p>
				<p rend="center">_______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER V. </p>
				<p rend="center">FROM AN EARWIG, DEPLORING THE LOSS OF ALL HER CHILDREN. </p>
				<p>DEAR AUNT, </p>
				<p rend="indent1">YOU cannot think how distressed I have been, and still am; for, under the bark of a large elm, which, I dare say,
					has stood there a great while, I had placed my whole family, where they were dry, comfortable, and, as I foolishly thought,
					secure. </p>
				<p rend="indent1"> But only mark what calamities may fall upon earwigs before they are aware of them! I had just got my family about
					me, all white, clean, and promising children, when pounce came down that bird they call a wood-pecker; when, thrusting his huge
					beak under the bark where we lay, down went our whole sheltering roof! and my children, poor things, running, as they thought,
					from danger, were devoured as fast as the destroyer could open his beak and shut it. For my own part, I crept into a crack in the
					solid tree, where I have thus far escaped: but as this bird can make large holes into solid timber, I am by no means safe. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">This calamity is the more heavy, as it carries with it a great disappointment; for very near our habitation was a
					high wall, the sunny side of which was covered with the most delicious fruits; peaches, apricots, nectarines, &amp;c. all just
					then ripening; and I thought of having such a feast with my children as I had never enjoyed in my life. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I am surrounded by wood-peckers, jackdaws, magpies, and other devouring creatures, and think myself very
					unfortunate. Yet, perhaps, if I could know the situation of some larger creatures — I mean particularly such as would tread me to
					death if I crossed their path — they may have complaints to make, as well as I. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">Take care of yourself, my good old aunt, and I shall keep in my hiding-place as long as starvation will permit. And,
					after all, perhaps the fruit was not so delicious as it looked — I am resolved to think so, just to comfort myself. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">Yours, with compliments, as usual. </p>
				<p rend="center">________</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER VI. </p>
				<p rend="center">FROM THE WILD DUCK TO THE TAME DUCK. </p>
				<p rend="right">Dated Lincoln and Ely Fens. </p>
				<p>DEAR COUSIN, </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I SUPPOSE I must call you so; though I declare I know not how we are related. But though I am thought so very wild
					and shy, I have still a kind of fellow- feeling for you; and, if you are not gone to the spit before this comes to you, I should
					be glad of your reply in a friendly way. You know very well that you are intended to be eaten, and so are we — when they can catch
					US. I understand that you never fly, and that you seldom waddle above a meadow’s length from your pond, where you keep puddling
					and groping from daylight till dark. This, I assure you, is not the life that I lead. We fly together in vast numbers in the
					night, for many miles, over this flat, wet country: so, as to water, we have an inexhaustible store; we may swim ourselves tired.
					But, I dare say, every station of our duck-lives is subject to some disadvantages and some calamities. Thus, with all our
					wildness, we are not secure; for we are taken sometimes by hundreds in a kind of trap, which is called a decoy.<note n="3"
						place="foot" resp="author">‘<hi rend="ital">Bedford Level</hi>, a tract of fens consisting of 300,000 acres, in the counties
						of Norfolk, Suffolk, Huntingdon, Northampton, Lincoln, Cambridge, and the Isle of Ely, which appears to have been dry land
						formerly, by the ruins of houses, large trees, &amp;c. that have been found in several parts. After divers expensive
						attempts to drain these fens in the reign of Henry VI. and Charles I., William, duke of Bedford, and others, in 1649,
						undertook and completed it, so far as to bring about 100,000 acres of good land into use. In these fens are several decoys,
						where astonishing quantities of wild-fowl are taken during the season. One of these, not far from Ely, generally sends 3000
						couple weekly to London, and is let for 500<hi rend="ital">l</hi>. a year.’<p rend="indent1"><hi rend="ital">See Walker’s
								Gazetteer, article ‘Bedford Level</hi>.’ [Bloomfield’s note]</p><p>John Walker’s <title>The Universal Gazetteer; Being
								a Concise Description, Alphabetically Arranged of the Nations, Towns, Cities, Harbours, Canals, Kingdoms, Empires,
								Oceans, Rivers, Mountains, States, Provinces, Seas, Lakes, Capes, &amp;c. in the Known World; the Government,
								Manners, and Religion of the Inhabitants, with the Extent, Boundaries, and Natural Productions, Manufactures and
								Curiosities of the Different Countries. Containing Several Thousand Places not to be met with in any similar
								Gazetteer</title>, first published in 1795, and frequently enlarged. </p></note></p>
				<p rend="indent1">Some of our tribe have been made tame like you (but I hope <hi rend="ital">you</hi> are not so false-hearted), and
					then their masters feed them plentifully, in a place contrived on purpose, with a narrow entrance, with which these <hi
						rend="ital">traitor ducks</hi> are well acquainted, so that they can pass in and out at a place which we strangers should
					never have thought of. They are sent out in the dusk of the evening, when they soon join with large companies of us strangers; and
					knowing, as they do, their way home, and that they shall find food, they set off, close at each other’s tails, along a ditch or
					water-course, and we fools follow them. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">The entrance, as far as I could see of it, is very narrow; for I have been <hi rend="ital">twice</hi> within a
					hair’s breadth of being caught, and do not pretend to know all about it; but I wish heartily, that every duck and drake in the
					country — ay, and every one of our allies, the geese, too, could say as much; could say that ‘they had twice been on the verge of
					destruction, by keeping bad company, but had escaped.’</p>
				<p rend="indent1">What becomes of my companions, when taken, I think I have heard pretty accurately; for there is somewhere, a very
					large assemblage of fellow-creatures to those, who catch us, and whose demand seems never to be satisfied. Well, never mind,
					cousin; I am determined to fly and swim too, as long as I can, and I advise you to do the same, and make the most of your day. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">Hoping to hear from you, I am affectionately your wild cousin. </p>
				<p rend="center">_______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER VII. </p>
				<p rend="center">THE TAME DUCK’S REPLY. </p>
				<p>COUSIN WILDING, </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I CONFESS I did not at all expect to hear from you; for I always believed you to be one of those thoughtless young
					creatures which are to be found in other stations of life, as well as in yours and mine, who, as soon as they get fledged, and
					able to get abroad, care no more for their parents, and those who brought them up, than I care for a shower of rain. However, you
					have escaped danger <hi rend="ital">twice</hi>, and you have reason to congratulate yourself. I have been sitting here upon ten
					eggs for three weeks past, and, of course, have another week to be confined; but then the thoughts of the pleasure I shall have in
					hatching and guiding my young ones to the water, is ample payment for all my pains. They will look so clean and so delighted, and
					will do as they are bid by the smallest quack that I can utter, that I must be a bad mother indeed if I am not proud of them.
					Perhaps you will wonder when I tell you that we have a creature here — fledged indeed — which is called a hen; a strange,
					cackling, flying, useless, noisy, silly creature, which is as much afraid of water as you are of your decoy. I have often known
					one of these birds to hatch nine or ten of my eggs; and then if you wanted to ridicule the lifted foot of conceit, and the dignity
					of assumed importance, you should see her lead her young, or more properly, see the young lead her to the nearest water they can
					find. In they go, and she begins to call and scold, and run round the edge to save them from drowning! Now, what fools these hens
					must be compared to us ducks! at least, I, for one, am determined to think so. I have seen this same hen with the brood about her,
					scratching in our farmyard with all her might; when, not considering who was behind her, or who under her feathers, she has kicked
					away one little yellow duck with one of her claws, and another with the other, till I wished I had her in a pond; I would have
					given her a good sousing, depend upon it. But really, cousin, don’t you think that this way of contradicting our natures and
					propensities, is very wrong? Suppose, for instance, I should set upon a dozen of that silly creature’s eggs which I mentioned
					above — for I will never consent to have them matched with us — I should then, to be sure, have a week’s holiday, as they sit but
					three weeks: but what should I bring to light? a parcel of little, useless, tip-toed, cowardly things, that would not follow me
					into the pond — I cannot bear to think of it. I have written you a long letter, and can think of no more but quack! quack! quack!
					and farewell. </p>
				<p rend="center">_______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER VIII. </p>
				<p rend="center">FROM THE GANDER TO THE TURKEY-COCK.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editor">By Charles Bloomfield, eldest son of the
						deceased [note by Weston]</note>
				</p>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l>OLD friend, you certainly have merit; </l>
					<l>You really are a bird of spirit! </l>
					<l>I’m quite surprised, I must confess; </l>
					<l>I did not think you did possess </l>
					<l>Such valour as you’ve lately shown — </l>
					<l>In fact, ’tis nearly like my own. </l>
					<l>You know I’ve always been renown’d </l>
					<l>For bravery, since first I found </l>
					<l>That I could hiss; and feel I’m bolder </l>
					<l>Each year that I am growing older. </l>
					<l>You must, I’m sure, have often seen, </l>
					<l>When in the pond, or on the green, </l>
					<l>With all my family about me, </l>
					<l>(I can’t think how they’d do without me). </l>
					<l>Some human thing come striding by, </l>
					<l>And how, without a scruple, I </l>
					<l>March after him and bite his heel; </l>
					<l>And then, you know, the pride I feel </l>
					<l>To hear, as back I march again. </l>
					<l>The feat extoll’d by all my train. </l>
					<l>But if I were to tell you all </l>
					<l>The valiant actions, great and small, </l>
					<l>That ever were achieved by me, </l>
					<l>I never should have done, I see; </l>
					<l>For cows, and pigs, and horses know </l>
					<l>The consequence of such a foe. </l>
					<l>However, I am glad to find </l>
					<l>That <hi rend="ital">you</hi> have such a noble mind, </l>
					<l>And think, my friend, that by and by </l>
					<l>You’ll rise to be as great as I. </l>
				</lg>
				<p rend="indent2">Your old friend, </p>
				<p rend="indent4">HISS. </p>
				<p rend="center">________</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER IX. </p>
				<p rend="center">THE DUNGHILL COCK TO THE CHAFFINCH. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I HAVE often, during the spring and summer, heard you of a morning piping away in the hedges, sometimes as soon as I
					was up myself, and thought your singing pretty fair, and that you conducted yourself as you ought to do. But this I cannot say
					lately; for it is quite overstepping the bounds of decency and good manners, when you and your brother pilferers, now the winter
					is come, make it your daily practice to come by scores, as you do, into our yard, and without any ceremony eat up all the barley
					you can lay your beaks to. I suppose when the spring comes again, and you find more to satisfy you outside a farm-yard than
					within, you will be off to the hedges again. I shall let you alone, unless the barley runs short, which is to support my wives and
					children; when, if you still venture to continue your pilferings, you must not be surprised should some of you feel the weight of
					my displeasure. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I must go after my family, who are all out of my sight since I have been writing this. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">Yours, in haste, and a friend if possible, </p>
				<p rend="indent11">CHANTICLEER. </p>
				<p rend="center">_______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER X. </p>
				<p rend="center">THE BLUE-BOTTLE FLY TO THE GRASS-HOPPER.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editor">By C. Bloomfield [Joseph Weston's
						note]</note>
				</p>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l rend="indent1">As I roam’d t’other day, </l>
					<l rend="indent1">Neighbour Hop, in my way </l>
					<l>I discover’d a nice rotten plum, </l>
					<l rend="indent1">Which you know is a treat; </l>
					<l rend="indent1">And, to taste of the sweet, </l>
					<l>A swarm of relations had come. </l>
				</lg>
				<lb/>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l rend="indent1">So we all settled round, </l>
					<l rend="indent1">As it lay on the ground, </l>
					<l>And were feasting ourselves with delight; </l>
					<l rend="indent1">But, for want of more thought </l>
					<l rend="indent1">To have watch’d, as we ought, </l>
					<l>We were suddenly seized — and held tight </l>
				</lg>
				<lb/>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l rend="indent1">In a <hi rend="ital">human’s</hi> clench’d hand. </l>
					<l rend="indent1">Where, unable to stand, </l>
					<l>We were twisted and tumbled about; </l>
					<l rend="indent1">But perceiving a chink, </l>
					<l rend="indent1">You will readily think </l>
					<l>I exerted myself — I got out. </l>
				</lg>
				<lb/>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l rend="indent1">How the rest got away </l>
					<l rend="indent1">I really can’t say, </l>
					<l>But I flew with such ardour and glee, </l>
					<l rend="indent1">That again, unawares, </l>
					<l rend="indent1">I got into the snares </l>
					<l>Of my foe, Mr. Spider, you see; </l>
				</lg>
				<lb/>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l rend="indent1">Who so fiercely came out </l>
					<l rend="indent1">Of his hole, that no doubt </l>
					<l>He expected that I was secure: </l>
					<l rend="indent1">But he found ’twould not do, </l>
					<l rend="indent1">For I forced my way through, </l>
					<l>Overjoy’d on escaping, you’re sure. </l>
				</lg>
				<lb/>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l rend="indent1">But I’ll now take my leave, </l>
					<l rend="indent1">For the clouds, I perceive, </l>
					<l>Are darkening over the sky; </l>
					<l rend="indent1">The sun is gone in, </l>
					<l rend="indent1">And I really begin </l>
					<l>To feel it grow cooler — Good bye! </l>
					<l>I’m, as ever, yours — Blue-bottle Fly. </l>
				</lg>
				<p rend="center">_______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER XI</p>
				<p rend="center">THE GLOW-WORM TO THE HUMBLE-BEE.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editor">By C. Bloomfield. [Joseph Weston's
						note]</note>
				</p>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l>EXCUSE, Mr. Bee, this epistle, to one </l>
					<l>Whose time, from the earliest gleam of the sun </l>
					<l>Till he sinks in the west, is so busily spent, </l>
					<l>That I fear I intrude; — but I write with intent </l>
					<l>To save your whole city from pillage and ruin. </l>
					<l>And to warn you in time of a plot that is brewing. </l>
					<l rend="indent1">Last night, when, as usual, enjoying the hour </l>
					<l>When the gloaming had spread, and a trickling shower </l>
					<l>Was beading the grass as it silently fell, </l>
					<l>And day with reluctance was bidding farewell; </l>
					<l>When down by yon hedge, nearly opposite you, </l>
					<l>And your City of Honey, as proudly I threw </l>
					<l>The rays from my lamp in a magical round; </l>
					<l>I listen’d, alarm’d upon hearing the sound </l>
					<l>Of human intruders approaching more near; </l>
					<l>But I presently found <hi rend="ital">I</hi> had nothing to fear, </l>
					<l>For the hedge was between us, and I and my gleam </l>
					<l>Lay hid from their view: when the following scheme </l>
					<l>I heard, as they shelter’d beneath the old tree, </l>
					<l>And send you each creature’s own words, Mr. Bee:— </l>
					<l>‘See, Jack, there it is; now suppose you and I, </l>
					<l>‘With a spade and some brimstone, should each of us try </l>
					<l>‘Some night, when we’re sure all the bees are at rest, </l>
					<l>‘To smother them all, and then dig out the nest?’</l>
					<l>— ‘I know we can do it,’ said Jack with delight; </l>
					<l>‘I can’t come to-morrow; but s’pose the next night </l>
					<l>‘We both set about it, if you are inclined; </l>
					<l>‘And then we’ll halve all the honey we find.’— </l>
					<l>‘Agreed,’ said the other, ‘but let us begone.’— </l>
					<l>And they left me in thought until early this morn; </l>
					<l>When I certainly meant, if your worship had staid </l>
					<l>But a minute or two, till my speech I had made. </l>
					<l>To have saved you the reading, as well as the cost </l>
					<l>Of a letter by post — but my words were all lost. — </l>
					<l>For though they were lavish’d each time you came near, </l>
					<l>Or was close over head, and I thought you <hi rend="ital">should</hi> hear; </l>
					<l>Yet the buzz of importance, as onward you flew, </l>
					<l>Bobbing into each flower the whole meadow through, </l>
					<l>So baffled your brains that I let you alone, </l>
					<l>For I found, that I might as well speak to a drone; </l>
					<l>Yet, rather than quietly leave you to fate, </l>
					<l>(Such a villanous thought never enter’d my pate), </l>
					<l>I send you this letter, composed by the light </l>
					<l>Of my silvery lamp in the dead of the night, </l>
					<l>And about the same time, and the very same place, </l>
					<l>That, a few nights ago, when the moon hid her face, </l>
					<l>I beheld, nearly hid in the grass as I lay, </l>
					<l>And my lamp in full splendour reflecting its ray </l>
					<l>In the eye of each dew-drop, the Fairies unseen </l>
					<l>To all human vision, trip here with their Queen </l>
					<l>To pay me a visit, to dance and to feast; </l>
					<l>And their revels continued, till full in the east. </l>
					<l>The sun tinged the clouds for another bright day, </l>
					<l>When each took the warning, and bounded away; </l>
					<l>’Tis the same at this moment:— farewell, Mr. Hum, </l>
					<l>I’ve extinguish’d my lamp, for the morning is come. </l>
				</lg>
				<p rend="right">SPANGLE. </p>
				<p rend="center">_______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER XII. </p>
				<p rend="center">FROM THE PIGEON TO THE PARTRIDGE. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">WHAT a long time it is since I received your kind letter about the ripening corn, and the dangers you were presently
					to be subject to, with all your children. You will think me very idle, or very unfeeling, if I delay answering you any longer; I
					will therefore tell you some of my own troubles, to convince you, that I have had causes of delay, which you can have no notion of
					until I explain them. You must know, then, that we are subject to more than the random gun-shot in the field, for we are sometimes
					taken out of our house a hundred at a time, and put into a large basket to be placed in a meadow, or spare plat of ground suiting
					the purpose, there to be murdered at leisure. This they call ‘<hi rend="ital">shooting from the trap</hi>,’<note n="7"
						place="foot" resp="author">I once witnessed this silly and barbarous sport; and saw at least a score of maimed and wounded
						birds upon the barns, and stables, and outhouses of the village. I was utterly disgusted, and it required a strong effort of
						the mind, to avoid wishing that one of the gunners, at least, had hobbled off the ground with a dangling leg, which might for
						one half year have reminded him, of the cowardly practice of ‘shooting from the trap.’ [Bloomfield’s note]</note> and is done
					in this way. We being imprisoned, as I have said, as thick as we can stand in the basket, a man is placed by us, to take us out
						<hi rend="ital">singly</hi>, and carry us to a small box, at the distance of fifty or sixty yards; this box has a lid, to
					which is attached a string, by means of which, he, the man (if he is a man), can draw up the lid, and let us fly at a signal
					given. Every sensible pigeon of course flies for his life, for, ranged on each side, stand from two to four or six men with guns,
					who fire as the bird gets upon the wing; and the cleverest fellows are those, who can kill most; — and this they call <hi
						rend="ital">sport!</hi> I have sad cause to know how this sport is conducted, for I have been in the trap myself. Only one
					man, or perhaps a boy fired at me as I rose; but I received two wounds, for one shot passed through my crop, but I was astonished
					to find how soon it got well; the other broke my leg just below the feathers. O what anguish I suffered for two months, — at the
					end of which time it withered and dropped off. So now instead of running about amongst my red-legged brethren, as a pigeon ought,
					I am obliged to hop like a sparrow. But only consider what glory this stripling must have acquired, to have actually fired a gun,
					and broke a pigeon’s leg!! Well, we both know, neighbour Partridge, what the Hawk is; he stands for no law, nor no season, but
					eats us when he is hungry. He is a perfect gentleman compared to these ‘Lords of the Creation,’ as I am told they call themselves;
					and I declare to you upon the honour of a pigeon, that I had much rather be torn to pieces by the Hawk than be shut up in a box at
					a convenient distance to be shot at by a dastard. You partridges are protected during great part of the year by severe laws, but
					whether such laws are wise, merciful, or just, I cannot determine, but I know that they are strictly kept, and enforced by those
					who make them. Take care of yourself, for the harvest is almost ripe. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I am your faithful </p>
				<p rend="indent3">ONE-LEGGED FRIEND AT THE GRANGE. </p>
				<p rend="center">_______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER XIII. </p>
				<p rend="center">THE WOOD-PIGEON TO THE OWL. </p>
				<p>MY GOOD, OLD, WISE, SECLUDED, AND QUIET FRIEND, </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I WRITE to you in the fulness of my heart, for I have been grossly insulted by the Magpie, in a letter received this
					morning; in which, I am abused for what my forefathers did long before I was born. I know of nothing more base, or more unjust,
					than thus raking up old quarrels,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="author">The poor pigeon, I think, must here allude to the old
						well-known quarrel between the two families, about building their nests. The magpie once undertook to teach the pigeon how to
						build a more substantial and commodious dwelling, and certainly it would have become the learner to have observed her
						progress, and not interrupt the teacher; but the pigeon kept on her usual cry, ‘take two, taffy, take two,’(for thus it is
						translated in Suffolk), but Mag insisted this was wrong, and that one stick at a time was quite enough; still the pigeon kept
						on her cry, ‘take two, take two,’ until the teacher in a violent passion gave up the undertaking, exclaiming, ‘I say that one
						at a time is plenty, and if you think otherwise, you may set about the work yourself, for I will have no more to do with it.’
						Since that time the wood-pigeon has built a wretched nest sure enough, so thin that you may frequently see her two eggs
						through it, and if not placed near the body of a tree, or on strong branches, it is often thrown down by the wind, or the eggs
						rolled out; yet the young of this bird, before they are half grown, will defend themselves against any intruder, at which time
						the parent bird will dash herself down amongst the standing corn, or high grass, and behave, as though her wings were broken,
						and she was utterly disabled; and this she does to draw off the enemy from her young; so that this bird is not so foolish as
						Mag would make us believe. [Bloomfield’s note]</note> and reproaching those who had nothing to do with them. The letter must
					have come through your office, but I know you have not the authority to break open and examine letters, passing between those who
					should be friends, I therefore do not accuse you; but sometimes the heart is relieved by stating its troubles, even when no
					redress can be expected. I know that you cannot bring to punishment that slanderer, that babbler of the woods, any more than I
					can; but I wish you would give me a word of comfort, if it is ever so short. </p>
				<p rend="indent2">From the plantation of firs,</p>
				<p rend="indent4">near the forest side, </p>
				<p rend="indent6">WOOD-PIGEON. </p>
				<p rend="center">_______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER XIV. </p>
				<p rend="center">THE OWL IN REPLY TO THE WOOD-PIGEON. </p>
				<p>DISTRESSED NEIGHBOUR, </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I AM sorry for your trouble, but cheer up your spirits, and though you are insulted, remember who it is that gives
					the affront, it is only the magpie; and depend upon it, that in general, the best way to deal with impudent fools is to be silent,
					and take no notice of them. I should have enough to do, if I were to resent all her impertinences. She will come sometimes round
					the ivy where I lodge in the old elm, or into the tower on the top of the hill; and there she will pimp and pry into my private
					concerns and mob me, and call me ‘old Wigsby’ and ‘doctor Winkum,’ and such kind of names, and all for nothing. I assure you it is
					well for her, that she is not a mouse, or she should not long escape my talons: but whoever heard of such a thing as eating a
					magpie? I live chiefly on mice (when I am at liberty to catch them), but I have my complaints to make, as well as you, for you
					know I hold a high situation in the post-office, and I suppose you know, likewise, that the letters are brought in so very late,
					that it often takes me half the night to sort them, and night is the very time when I ought to get my own food! At this rate of
					going on, and if the cats are industrious as usual, there will not be a mouse left for me, if I do not give up my place. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I have heard that my family are famed for wisdom; but for my part, I will not boast of any such thing: yet I am wise
					enough to know, that other people in high offices expect either a good salary or perquisites, as a reward for their labour, or
					what is easier still, somebody to do all the work for them. If I hold in my present mind until next quarter, I will certainly send
					in my resignation. Thus you see what an important thing it is to suit the office to the person, or the person to the office on
					whom it is conferred; for had the magpie, or instance, been secretary, every one of the letters would have been peeped into, for a
					certainty, for nothing can escape her curiosity. I will try to bear with my situation a little longer, and believe me to be. </p>
				<p rend="indent11">Your true friend </p>
				<p rend="indent9">SECRETARY TO THE</p>
				<p rend="indent10">BOARD OF MANAGERS.</p>
				<p rend="center">______</p>
				<p rend="center">LETTER XV. </p>
				<p rend="center">FROM A SWALLOW IN THE SOUTH OF FRANCE TO AN ENGLISH ROBIN. </p>
				<p>DEAR LITTLE BOB, </p>
				<p rend="indent1">I REMEMBER your peaceful singing on the top of your shed, near my late dwelling, and I remember, also, that I
					promised to write you some account of my journey. You may recollect, that at the close of your summer, when flies become scarce,
					we all assembled on a sunny morning, on the roof of the highest building in the village, and talked loudly of the flight we
					intended to take. At last came the day appointed, and we mounted up in a vast body and steered southward. Being hatched in
					England, I had thought your valleys and streams matchless in beauty; and for any thing I know to the contrary, they certainly are;
					but I am now a traveller, and have a traveller’s privilege to say what I like. When we reached the great water, I was astonished
					at its width, but more still to see many travelling houses going at a prodigious rate, and sending forth from iron chimneys
					columns of black smoke over the face of the water, reaching further than you ever flew in your life; they have a contrivance on
					each side which puts the waves all in commotion, but they are not wings. My mother says that in old times, when swallows came to
					England, there were no such things to be seen. We crossed this water, and a fine sunny country beyond it, until I was tired, and
					we now found flies more abundant, though the oldest amongst us assure me, that we must travel further still, over another wide
					water, into a country where men’s faces are of the same colour as my feathers, black and tawny; but travellers see strange things.
					When I come to England again, I will endeavour to find out your village. I hope, for your sake, you may have a mild winter and
					good lodgings. </p>
				<p rend="indent1">This is all the news worth sending, and I must catch flies for myself now, you know. </p>
				<p rend="indent10">So farewell, </p>
				<p rend="indent11">for I am in haste.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="author">It is much to be wished that the above letter had
						contained some information on a very curious subject, for I would rather believe the swallow himself, than many tales told of
						them. It has been said, that instead of flying to southern countries, where they can find food and a congenial climate, they
						dive into the waters of a bog, and lie in a torpid state, through the winter, round the roots of flags and weeds. R.
						Bloomfield.</note>
				</p>
				<p rend="center">_______</p>
				<p rend="center">ON HEARING THE CUCKOO AT MIDNIGHT,</p>
				<p rend="center">MAY 1ST, 1822. </p>
				<p rend="center">BY CHARLES BLOOMFIELD. </p>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l>’TWAS the blush of the spring, vegetation was young, </l>
					<l>And the birds with a maddening ecstasy sung</l>
					<l>To welcome a season so lovely and gay — </l>
					<l>But a scene the most sweet, was the close of May-day. </l>
				</lg>
				<lb/>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l>For the air was serene, and the moon was out bright, </l>
					<l>And Philomel boldly exerted her might </l>
					<l>In her swellings and trillings, to rival the sound </l>
					<l>Of the distant defiance of Nightingales round. </l>
				</lg>
				<lb/>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l>While the Cuckoo as proudly was heard to prolong, </l>
					<l>Though day-light was over, his own mellow song, </l>
					<l>And appeared to exult; and at intervals, too. </l>
					<l>The Owl in the distance join’d in with ‘Too-whoo.’</l>
				</lg>
				<lb/>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l>Unceasing, unwearied, each, proud of his power, </l>
					<l>Continued the contest from hour to hour; </l>
					<l>The Nightingale vaunting — the Owl in reply — </l>
					<l>With the Cuckoo’s response — till the moon from the sky </l>
				</lg>
				<lb/>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l>Was hastening down to the west, and the dawn </l>
					<l>Was spreading the east; and the Owl in the morn </l>
					<l>Sat silently winking his eyes at the sight; </l>
					<l>And the Nightingale also had bidden ‘good-night.’</l>
				</lg>
				<lb/>
				<lg type="stanza">
					<l>The Cuckoo, left solus, continued with glee. </l>
					<l>His notes of defeat from his favourite tree; — </l>
					<l>At length <hi rend="ital">he</hi> departed; but still as he flew. </l>
					<l>Was heard his last notes of defiance, ‘Cuckoo.’</l>
				</lg>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
