<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.228</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS. 30809, ff. 48–49</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="228" type="letter"><head>228. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1808-03-01">1 March 1808</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS. 30809, ff. 48–49</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>City Road</placeName></address><date when="1808-03-01">March 1. 1808</date></dateline><salute>Dear Isaac</salute></opener><p rend="indent1">	Your last letter is to explain, and I write for the same purpose. In my last I advanced nothing but what is true, but I did not undertake to tell the <hi rend="ital">whole</hi> truth. I enumerayted such unlucky circumstances as had occur’d to render me unable to assist you <hi rend="ital">now</hi>. Which would be the most unkind or imperious man, he who refus’d without giving any reasons, and consequently leaves the applicant to accuse his covetousness or contempt of destress; or, he who refuses by an exposition of his affairs sufficient for his justification, and sufficient to prove that he had by the party’s there mention’d, been ungenerously and ungratefully used? I certainly had no thought nor no business with what advantages you gain’d by coming to London, from your sister Sophia, that is good news but it affects not in the least the truth of what I had in my head; that an estimate of <hi rend="ital">probable</hi> gain against certain <hi rend="ital">loss</hi> (of time) should be reasonably and fairly made, and, I see nothing in this that ought to offend, I spoke it as I would to any one else. I still think the same with respect to the impossibility of your keeping a family on the wages you are able to get from the grinding farmers during the winter. As to my <hi rend="ital">eight</hi> turning out to be <hi rend="ital">six</hi>, seems to alter the matter but little, especially as, while you cut off two from <hi rend="ital">one</hi> end of the reconing, <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldElizabethsisterlaw">your wife</ref> will, in all likelyhood, keep adding at the other. I return your letter that you may see I have a scrupulous kind of feeling on that head; and on reading mine again you will perhaps perceive a disclosure of affairs and of names, that renders it advisable to beg you to do the same when you have opportunity.</p><p rend="indent1">	You mention, if I understand you right, that you thought that I might show the letter; this, had I been ever so able and ready to engage in the job, I should not have done without your special desire. A discovery may sometimes be made in two lines, I have a worse opinion of the world in proportion as I am ill used, and I could not trust them. I had no desire of mentioning any thing that <hi rend="ital">you</hi> have had, any more than another. A good many littles makes a deal. And I had not nor have not now any desire to exculpate myself from blame, I know I have spent too fast. And if it be true that prosperity is harder to bear than adversity, I have had my trials. When you say that you should, in my situation, have acted in family matters as I have done; it is allmost a fair inference to add, that you would in other things have acted as I may have done, or else the inference must be, that you would have had better conduct.</p><p rend="indent1">	With respect to your mentioning the paying for your board, the thought is honourable to yourself, but it appears to me more strange than perhaps you are aware of, I know it <hi rend="ital">impossible,</hi> and you must know so too (unless from expected profits).—And as to myself I should deem the <hi rend="ital">taking pay</hi> for my brother’s food a kind of disgrace, such as I hope will never stick to my cloth.</p><p rend="indent1">	One half of the world think that I have have from the <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">D of G</ref> nearly sufficient to support my family!! Others, without a moment reflecting <hi rend="ital">how</hi> and in what <hi rend="ital">state</hi> I was found, or how I have been taken from the seat, and all my expences falling on my profits, think that I am growing rich.! I am in no kind of fear of wanting that is not one of my follys. I have the means in my own head, should the present resources diminish. They certainly <hi rend="ital">will</hi> by <hi rend="ital">degrees</hi>, and I must then either follow up my popularity by new publications, or pull down my expences and send my children out. This too, I am not afraid of.—</p><p rend="indent1">	If I husband my income wisely for the <hi rend="ital">future</hi> I have nothing to fear, and to die rich never entered into my head.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">	Love to all yours truly</salute><signed rend="right">Robert</signed></closer><postscript><p>If this letter comes back with the other when <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> sends a parcel, I should take it the better.</p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><rs>Address:</rs><name><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac Bloomfield</ref></name> / <placeName><ref target="places.html#Honington">Honington</ref></placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>