<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.198</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library MS Montagu.d.3, ff. 111–12</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="198" type="letter"><head>198. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Thomas Hood</ref>, <date when="1806-11-19">19 November 1806</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Bodleian Library MS Montagu.d.3, ff. 111–12</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>City Road</placeName></address><date when="1806-11-19">Nov 19. 1806</date></dateline><salute>Dear Sir,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1">	For the purpose of mutual understanding, I give you a copy below of the note which I found, (through my engagement as to sending the monthly parcel to <ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston</ref> ) I was bound to send to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> a few days past; and I subjoin a few remarks on the preface which I have this minute read attentively. The letter I have copied is that to which <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L.</ref> alludes in his late communication to the printer.</p><p rend="center">(Copy)</p><p rend="right">‘London.<date when="1806-11-12"> Nov 12. 1806</date>’</p><p>‘To <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">C Lofft Esq.</ref></p><p>Sir, </p><p rend="indent1">	After having seen through the press the whole of the poem, I accompanied a neighbour in a journey into Kent, both for health and for business. I have been absent more than three weeks, and during that time avoided all communication with the publishers that I might not even in appearance, break my engagement of leaving the preface to your own fancy and direction. On my return I found that your postscript, (the only part of the preface I have seen) had, during my absence been sent to my home, and going immediately to the printers I found that the Book had been <hi rend="ital">finished</hi>, and part of it sent home to the publishers; and enquiring very naturally, whither they had printed the Postscript,? Was answer’d, No!</p><p rend="indent1">	If this is news Sir to you, I neither tell it with terror nor with exultation. I think I have felt too severely on this subject ever to feel much again. It is with real sorrow that I learn the death of <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Mr Kirk White</ref>, and having said this little, and sent the publishers as soon as absence would permit, I feel to have discharged a duty.’</p><p rend="indent1">	And am &amp;c</p><p rend="right">Rob Bloomfield’</p><p>Now Sir, with respect to the preface which my friend <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> has arranged (I suppose) to his own will, I own that he has reinstated less than I was prepared to expect of that which I had excluded, I expected to find <ref target="people.html#SwanJames">Mr Swan’s</ref> long letter respecting the effort of memory (page 27), <ref target="people.html#DrakeNathan">Dr Drake’s</ref> annalises, <ref target="people.html#LofftSarah">Mrs Loffts</ref> sonnet, and <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Loffts</ref> additional verse to my song, with many other things, which to me are grown tedious by frequent repetition, but I find that these from some motive or other, are not restor’d. I am truly glad they are not. In his notes respecting Newspapers and Debating societies he had originally written and pertinaciously retained a downright attack upon Government.—<hi rend="ital">Now</hi> he has softene’d it down to a mere opinion! Yet, I still wish it was not there, for, I am not a politician, nor never shall be. It is highly curious to find that he has retaind the high and partial praise bestow’d on me by my <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">Brother</ref> ‘that he never knew my fellow for mildness of disposition &amp;c &amp;c, and yet wish’d a postscript to be printed in <hi rend="ital">the same preface</hi>, in direct opposition to any such statement? In the preface he tells the world that ‘adversity has not deprest, and prosperity he is persuaded will not corrupt him,’ yet in a postscript <hi rend="ital">to the same preface</hi> he retracts his opinion and tells the world that it has! It is seeing the glaring contradiction of the two statements that makes me think that the rejection of the Postscript, (even if it were only on account of <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> himself) is in every way right and desirable, for whatever <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L.</ref> may lay to my charge, any statement will avail him more than that which contradicts itself. At least such is my opinion.</p><p rend="indent1">	I observe in the present measure, that <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L.</ref> has done with an ill grace, a great deal of that which I in my private letters endeavourd to effect by entreaty and argument he has done that which he felt angry about when I stated it my self in the last edition, viz. corrected the dates of my age, &amp;c. as inadvertently [m]isstated by <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">my brother</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1">	When I sent <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L.</ref> a copy of the last Edition he inform’d me immediately he had cut out the preface and burnt it, and inserted in its stead a <hi rend="ital">protest against me and the publishers.</hi></p><p rend="indent1">	Under all these circumstances I know not whither it would be of any use to send him the present Edition, or to write any more. If I should feel my self in the humour I will shew you a copy, for in the temperament in which he now appears, to cringe would be disgrace, and to irritate, a crime.</p><p rend="indent1">	There are some errors of the press, arising I doubt not from the singularity of his handwriting, and for which <ref target="people.html#WilsonWilliam">Mr Wilson</ref>, in my mind stands entirely acquitted.</p><p rend="indent1">	I have thought it correct thus to state my opinion and should feel oblidged if you would communicate this to <ref target="people.html#SharpeC">Mr Sharp</ref> and <ref target="people.html#WassMr">Mr Wass</ref> &amp;c. &amp;c.</p><p rend="indent1">	As to whatever <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L</ref> may in his rage advance against me in <hi rend="ital">public</hi>, I am confidently sure it will hurt me much less than many of his private letters have done.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">	I am yours Sir Respectfully</salute><signed rend="right">Rob Bloomfield</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>