<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.265</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Pierpont Morgan Library, New York, MA 4500</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="265" type="letter"><head>265. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerMary">Mary Lloyd Baker</ref>, <date when="1811-08-14">14–15 August 1811</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Pierpont Morgan Library, New York, MA 4500</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>London.</placeName></address><date when="1811-08-14">Aug 14. 1811</date></dateline><salute>My Dear Madam</salute></opener><p rend="indent1">	Your long and interesting epistle gave me real pleasure, first for its remarks, and still more from the consideration that you are able so to write and so to enjoy over again the scenery I have described. This is as it should be.—I hope the enclosed copies will suffice for the present, as I have no more by me, but will get a supply, and attend to the request of <ref target="people.html#SharpCatherine">Miss Sharp</ref> as well as other unaccomodated friends. And so my Gleaner has no right to sing about matrimony<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The ‘Gleaner’s Song’ appears in Book 1 of <title>Banks of Wye</title> (pp. 20–21).</note> because we had no matrimony in the Boat, or at least were not <hi rend="ital">just then</hi> upon such an expedition? Upon my poetical veracity I do not see the strength of your objection, but as matrimony is a very tender subject, as well as a longwinded one, I had better give you <ref target="people.html#PittWilliam">Mr Pitt’s</ref> answer when he did not choose to give any, ‘I have not made up my mind.’ The apostles<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Rock buttresses flanking the river Wye near Chepstow.</note> shall be duly honour’d if the public will bear a reprint. I understand the Castle-looking rocks on the crown of the little Doward<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Rock outcrops with caves, including ‘King Arthur’s Cave’, near Ross-on-Wye.</note> to be the real Arthurs Hall, which in the map is mark’d nearly so, but for fear of being wrong I hisitated in saying ‘This crown of rude rock, Arthur’s Hall.’ Your other critiques are worthy of alteration and I thank you, but as you demand and have a right to demand information on another subject I must proceed to it before I gossip the sheet full.</p><p rend="indent1">	My acquaintance is so extensive, much too extensive in many channels) that I have communications with several different worlds!!!!! Yes, there is the bookselling world, the engraving world, the poetical world, the Quaking world, the busy world, the idle world, the interested, and the <hi rend="ital">curious</hi> world, which is more plague than all the rest. I have often tried to look back to the commencement of some of my present how d-do friendships to discover how they came about, and I generally find that <hi rend="ital">I</hi> did not begin them. Amongst other strangers came a <ref target="people.html#InskipThomas">watchmaker</ref>, a native of Bedfordshire, and after a lapse of time I found him really a man of mind, and that he corresponded with one at <ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref> certainly superior to himself in information, wit and indeed in most particulars where extraordinary mind can evince itself. I soon knew them both, the latter is a respectable shopkeeper at <ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref>, through whose means I made a Harp for <ref target="people.html#OsborneGeorge">Sir G Osborne</ref>, and nothing would satisfy him in the main but that I should have a holliday, and share his board and his wine. I did so, and returning gave my <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Eldest daughter</ref> a treat to the same <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr Weston’s</ref>, to keep company with his young sister from Oxfordshire, and I think they mutually improved each other, and we were most honourably and hospitably treated. It was there I conceived the plan of perpetuating as far as the circumstances of my case would permit, the joys of the country. I hir’d of him a house at fifteen pounds per an. much better than this I live in at 40 besides taxes and I know, and still know that I could retrench in expenses and shake off full two thirds of the people who come here to look down my throat. I should have a beautifull corn country around me, and the immediate enjoyment of <ref target="places.html#Chicksands">Chicksands</ref> and its library; <ref target="people.html#WhitbreadSamuel">Mr Whitbread’s</ref> noble estates and the free ramble by a stream full of fish, and pray remember that al these would come to me cheaper by nearly £50 per ann. than living here to the evident injury of my health, the greatest of all considerations yet metion’d. some would exclaim ‘With all this connexion what a trade he might get in a shop?’ yes, if I could change Robin Bloomfield into Dick Shud of pudding lane. But before these arguments have much weight with me, I must see Dick Shud turn poet, for why should not he change his nature, and his habit as soon as I. I am determined he shall begin first. My glass is fast running for Forty Five, and <hi rend="ital">I will not be a Tradesman.</hi> But if I cannot subsist without, I mean to petition to be an under turnkey at Newgate, and then you will all know where to direct to me.—After all, my dear madam, I am not certain of going into the country. I wish to go at Michilmas but my town connexions are so tight woven, so multifarious that I am, at least at present, tied by the leg. </p><p>Aug 15 I wrote last night by candlelight, as you may perceive amidst the repeated interruptions to which I am exposed, and amongst the rest was one for his M.S. which had been left for my examination! How kind, to help me out as to employment when I have none of my own! Now honestly will this plain statement stand for a liquidation of my debt? If not make out your bill again and I will attend to it.—</p><p rend="indent1">	Have you Hook’s Instructions for the Piano Forte?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Hook’s Instructions for the Piano Forte: James Hook, <title>Guida di musica; being a complete book of instructions for beginners on the harpsichord or piano forte ... to which is added twenty-four progressive-lessons</title> (London, 1785) and later editions 1796, 1810.</note> I have been amusing myself as I walkd, in adapting words to two or three of his lessons.—I send you the original M.S. and tell you at the same time that it was the first of six, so bent was I to accomplish my task. This copy is written in the best greek I am acquainted with, and where it is blackest my little son has help’d me. It contains much downright nonsense, but in <hi rend="ital">your</hi> hand I am not submitting it to the world, but for your [illegible word] amusement, and you, I am sure, would be sorry to expose me by its too great publicity. The accompanying packet to <ref target="places.html#FerneyHill">Ferney Hill</ref> will of course be deliverd, and as my time grows short, I must leave the blank to be fill’d at your leisure with my best remembrances, Loves, and Respects. And am Madam</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">	Yours most truly</salute><signed rend="right">Robert Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p>Particular Loves to the Children.</p><p><label>P.S.</label> you need not fear my inlisting either under <ref target="places.html#WhitbreadSamuel">Mr W.</ref> the patriot or <ref target="people.html#OsborneGeorge">Sir G.O.</ref> the Courtier. The rise of a Nation to corruption and its declention, are much like the growth and decline of an Oak. I never knew a writing politician who did not of necessity forfeit that independence which I wish to keep. I will have nothing to do with rearing or pulling down their fabricks. I will enjoy the sunshine of favour, and hold my tongue. My old patron the <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">Duke of Grafton</ref> is no more, I loose £15 per ann. I never flatterd him, and shall probably never have another.—</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>