<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.5</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        17–18</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="5" type="letter"><head>5. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Elizabeth
                        Glover</ref>, <date when="1797-10-22">22–[29] October 1797</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        17–18</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right">Sunday night, <date when="1797-10-22">October 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1797</date></dateline><salute>Dear Mother</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have constantly seen your letters to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref>, and have always been anxious
                    to hear of your wellfare, whenever you have appeared full of hopes and domestic
                    peace I have read your letters with pleasure, when you have been under the
                    pressure of ill health or bad prospects, the natural though painful conclusion
                    is, I cant help you; you I believe often think over those things, you know the
                    difficulty of keeping afloat in the dirty stream of the world, and I think you
                    know too the hearts of us all, that the power, and not the will, is wanted. — It
                    is sixteen years last June since I washed my old hat in the Horse-pond and sold
                    my smock for a shilling to Sam Shelver’s boy, and set off to London to turn
                    shoemaker, and I always remark that though I am aquainted with the principle
                    alterations and deaths and changes, children grown to Men and Women since
                    &amp;c, the first thought that is, I mean whenever not thinking of other
                    things my mind returns to the country, for the first moment, it always presents
                    the old picture. I see <ref target="people.html#AustinWilliamUncle">my
                        uncle</ref> master of the farm instead of <ref target="people.html#AustinWilliamCousin">my cousin</ref>, and can see in
                    imagination my old neighbours and things just as they were; fixing the memory
                    thus, brings in a strong point of view the quick successions and changes amongst
                    us; for if I had 16 years ago fixt my attention on a flourishing oak, or a whole
                    grove of oaks, the alteration might be disernable, but not striking. <ref target="places.html#RidlesworthHall">Ridlesworth hall</ref><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> tells me is not far beyond
                        <ref target="places.html#Fakenham">Fakenham</ref> wood, I sometimes allmost
                    envy <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldKitty">Kitty</ref> her situation, being
                    always shut up in a garrot I am debard from the pleasures for which I have so
                    strong a relish, but let me not grumble neither, for I have other pleasures,
                    perhaps quite my share; for at this very time I have pleasure in telling you
                    that <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">my wife</ref> is now fast
                    recovering from a short indisposition that alarmd me a good deal at first, by
                    the simtoms her disorder showd we could not but suppose that the [illegible
                    word] pain she felt must proceed from the Gravel, but on applying to a surgeon
                    it did not appear to be that and he was obliged to use instrumental as well as
                    phisical help, whereby she is now almost well, and we shall again meet the
                    winter cheerfully. Our chief visitor is <ref target="people.html#ChurchJoseph">my Wifes Father</ref>; he generally comes from <ref target="places.html#Woolwich">Woolwich</ref> once or twice in a summer, and
                    again at Christmas. He is always doubly welcome, for as well as being a
                    chearful, smiling man he is sure to more than pay for his entertainment by some
                    means or other, he works at boatbuilding in the king’s yard at <ref target="places.html#Woolwich">Woolwich</ref>, he is 64 years old, is quite
                    harty, and when useless to work he is sure of being put on the superannuated
                    list, and receive 20£ a year as long as he lives, but this will not keep him and
                    he don’t much like the prospect good as it is, for he is fixd upon independence,
                    he comes regularly the first Sunday in every month to his sisters at <ref target="places.html#Rotherhithe">Rotherhithe</ref>, I believe I have spoke
                    of those people before, they are well able to keep him, but he would rather
                    trust to himself, — My <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah</ref>
                    goes to school, and I think shows signs of a good memory, the mistress teach
                    them to repeat by heart, hymns, and moral verses, I like the method vastly; and
                    like to hear them spoken by such young tongues, <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah</ref> have learnd the morning
                    hymn ‘Awake my soul and with the Sun’,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Awake my soul and with the sun’, written by Thomas Ken and included in his
                            <title level="m">Manual of Prayers for the Use of the Scholars of
                            Winchester College</title> (London, 1674). François H. Barthélémon wrote
                        music for Ken’s verses, under the title ‘Morning Hymn’; this was first
                        published in <title level="m">A Supplement to the Hymns and Psalms Used at
                            the Asylum or House of Refuge for Female Orphans, printed for William
                            Gawler, organist to the Asylum</title> (London, c. 1785):<lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Awake, my soul, and with the sun</l><l rend="indent3"> Thy daily stage of duty run;</l><l rend="indent3"> Shake off dull sloth, and joyful rise,</l><l rend="indent3"> To pay thy morning sacrifice.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Thy precious time misspent, redeem,</l><l rend="indent3"> Each present day thy last esteem,</l><l rend="indent3"> Improve thy talent with due care;</l><l rend="indent3"> For the great day thyself prepare.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> By influence of the Light divine</l><l rend="indent3"> Let thy own light to others shine.</l><l rend="indent3"> Reflect all Heaven’s propitious ways</l><l rend="indent3"> In ardent love, and cheerful praise.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> In conversation be sincere;</l><l rend="indent3"> Keep conscience as the noontide clear;</l><l rend="indent3"> Think how all seeing God thy ways</l><l rend="indent3"> And all thy secret thoughts surveys.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Wake, and lift up thyself, my heart,</l><l rend="indent3"> And with the angels bear thy part,</l><l rend="indent3"> Who all night long unwearied sing</l><l rend="indent3"> High praise to the eternal King.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> All praise to Thee, Who safe has kept</l><l rend="indent3"> And hast refreshed me while I slept</l><l rend="indent3"> Grant, Lord, when I from death shall wake</l><l rend="indent3"> I may of endless light partake.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Heav’n is, dear Lord, where’er Thou art,</l><l rend="indent3"> O never then from me depart;</l><l rend="indent3"> For to my soul ‘tis hell to be</l><l rend="indent3"> But for one moment void of Thee.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Lord, I my vows to Thee renew;</l><l rend="indent3"> Disperse my sins as morning dew.</l><l rend="indent3"> Guard my first springs of thought and will,</l><l rend="indent3"> And with Thyself my spirit fill.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Direct, control, suggest, this day,</l><l rend="indent3"> All I design, or do, or say,</l><l rend="indent3"> That all my powers, with all their might,</l><l rend="indent3"> In Thy sole glory may unite.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> I would not wake nor rise again</l><l rend="indent3"> And Heaven itself I would disdain,</l><l rend="indent3"> Wert Thou not there to be enjoyed,</l><l rend="indent3"> And I in hymns to be employed.</l></lg><lb/><lg><l rend="indent3"> Praise God, from Whom all blessings flow;</l><l rend="indent3"> Praise Him, all creatures here below;</l><l rend="indent3"> Praise Him above, ye heavenly host;</l><l rend="indent3"> Praise Father, Son, and Holy Ghost.</l></lg></note> and the evening hymn, ‘Glory to thee my God this night’,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Glory to thee my God this night’, also written
                        by Thomas Ken:<lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Glory to thee, my God, this night,</l><l rend="indent3"> For all the blessings of the light:</l><l rend="indent3"> Keep me, O keep me, King of kings,</l><l rend="indent3"> Beneath thine own almighty wings.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Forgive me, Lord, for thy dear Son,</l><l rend="indent3"> The ill that I this day have done;</l><l rend="indent3"> That with the world, myself, and thee,</l><l rend="indent3"> I, ere I sleep, at peace may be.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Teach me to live, that I may dread</l><l rend="indent3"> The grave as little as my bed;</l><l rend="indent3"> Teach me to die, that so I may</l><l rend="indent3"> Rise glorious at the awful day.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> O may my soul on thee repose,</l><l rend="indent3"> And with sweet sleep mine eyelids close;</l><l rend="indent3"> Sleep that shall me more vigorous make</l><l rend="indent3"> To serve my God when I awake.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> When in the night I sleepless lie,</l><l rend="indent3"> My soul with heavenly thoughts supply;</l><l rend="indent3"> Let no ill dreams disturb my rest,</l><l rend="indent3"> No powers of darkness me molest.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Praise God, from whom all blessings flow;</l><l rend="indent3"> Praise him, all creatures here below;</l><l rend="indent3"> Praise him above, ye heavenly host:</l><l rend="indent3"> Praise Father, Son, and Holy Ghost.</l></lg></note> she likewise recites Pope’s ‘Universal Prayer’,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander Pope’s ‘Universal Prayer’
                            (1738):<lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Father of All! in every Age,</l><l rend="indent4"> In every Clime ador’d,</l><l rend="indent3"> By Saint, by Savage, and by Sage,</l><l rend="indent4"> Jehovah, Jove, or Lord!</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Thou Great First Cause, least Understood!</l><l rend="indent4"> Who all my Sense confin’d</l><l rend="indent3"> To know but this,—that Thou art Good,</l><l rend="indent4"> And that my self am blind:</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Yet gave me, in this dark Estate,</l><l rend="indent4"> To see the Good from Ill;</l><l rend="indent3"> And binding Nature fast in Fate,</l><l rend="indent4"> Left free the Human Will.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> What Conscience dictates to be done,</l><l rend="indent4"> Or warns me not to doe,</l><l rend="indent3"> This, teach me more than Hell to shun,</l><l rend="indent4"> That, more than Heav’n pursue.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> What Blessings thy free Bounty gives,</l><l rend="indent4"> Let me not cast away;</l><l rend="indent3"> For God is pay’d when Man receives,</l><l rend="indent4"> T’ enjoy, is to obey.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Yet not to Earth’s contracted Span,</l><l rend="indent4"> Thy Goodness let me bound;</l><l rend="indent3"> Or think Thee Lord alone of Man,</l><l rend="indent4"> When thousand Worlds are round.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Let not this weak, unknowing hand</l><l rend="indent4"> Presume Thy Bolts to throw,</l><l rend="indent3"> And deal Damnation round the land,</l><l rend="indent4"> On each I judge thy Foe.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> If I am right, oh teach my heart</l><l rend="indent4"> Still in the right to say;</l><l rend="indent3"> If I am wrong, Thy Grace impart</l><l rend="indent4"> To find that better Way.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Save me alike from foolish Pride,</l><l rend="indent4"> Or impious Discontent,</l><l rend="indent3"> At ought thy Wisdom has deny’d,</l><l rend="indent4"> Or ought thy Goodness lent.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Teach me to feel another’s Woe;</l><l rend="indent4"> To hide the Fault I see;</l><l rend="indent3"> That Mercy I to others show,</l><l rend="indent4"> That Mercy show to me.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Mean tho’ I am, not wholly so</l><l rend="indent4"> Since quicken’d by thy Breath,</l><l rend="indent3"> O lead me wheresoe’er I go,</l><l rend="indent4"> Thro’ this day’s Life, or Death:</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> This day, be Bread and Peace my Lot;</l><l rend="indent4"> All else beneath the Sun,</l><l rend="indent3"> Thou know’st if best bestow’d, or not;</l><l rend="indent4"> And let Thy Will be done.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> To Thee, whose Temple is all Space,</l><l rend="indent4"> Whose Altar, Earth, Sea, Skies:</l><l rend="indent3"> One Chorus let all Being raise!</l><l rend="indent4"> All Nature’s Incense rise!</l></lg></note> and Goldsmith’s beautiful verse, ‘pitty the sorrows [of] a poor
                    old Man’,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> This line, which was revised
                        in manuscript by Oliver Goldsmith, appears in Thomas Moss’s poem ‘The
                        Beggar’s Petition’, published in his <title level="m">Poems on Several
                            Occasions</title> (Wolverhampton, 1769):<lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Pity the sorrows of a poor old man,</l><l rend="indent4"> Whose trembling limbs have borne him to your
                                door,</l><l rend="indent3"> Whose days are dwindled to the shortest span;</l><l rend="indent4"> Oh give relief, and Heaven will bless your store.</l></lg></note> my children give me a deal of pleasure now and I hope they
                    always will, — there are times, when the fire burns clear, and we are all well,
                    and our beer drawn good, and the candle fresh snuffd, that I feel myself quite
                    happy, when the muddy stream of the world, as I before calld it, seem quite
                    clear and palatable, indeed I always admired some verse I have somewhere seen,
                    beginning, ‘The hearth was clean, the fire clear, the kettle on for tea’,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘The hearth was clean, the fire clear,
                        the kettle on for tea’. William Hazlitt also quotes this anonymous lyric,
                        ‘The Happy Fireside’, in <title level="m">The Round Table: a Collection of
                            Essays on Literature, Men and Manners</title>, 2 vols. (Edinburgh,
                            1817):<lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> The hearth was clean, the fire was clear, </l><l rend="indent4"> The kettle on for tea,</l><l rend="indent3"> Palemon in his elbow-chair, </l><l rend="indent4"> As blest as man could be. </l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Clarinda, who his heart possess’d, </l><l rend="indent4"> And was his new-made bride, </l><l rend="indent3"> With head reclin’d upon his breast </l><l rend="indent4"> Sat toying by his side. </l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Stretch’d at his feet, in happy state, </l><l rend="indent4"> A fav’rite dog was laid, </l><l rend="indent3"> By whom a little sportive cat </l><l rend="indent4"> In wanton humour play’d. </l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Clarinda’s hand he gently prest; </l><l rend="indent4"> She stole an amorous kiss, </l><l rend="indent3"> And blushing modestly confess’d </l><l rend="indent4"> The fulness of her bliss. </l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Palemon, with a heart elate, </l><l rend="indent4"> Pray’d to Almighty Jove, </l><l rend="indent3"> That it might ever be his fate, </l><l rend="indent4"> Just so to live and love. </l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Be this eternity, he cried, </l><l rend="indent4"> And let no more be given: </l><l rend="indent3"> Continue thus my lov’d fireside, </l><l rend="indent4"> I ask no other heav’n.</l></lg>Hazlitt’s source (and most likely Bloomfield’s too) was <title level="m">Elegant Extracts: or Useful and Entertaining Pieces of Poetry,
                            Selected for the Improvement of Youth</title>, 2 vols. (London, 1791),
                        II, pp. 282–83.</note>——You seem to dispair of hearing from <ref target="people.html#HingstonElizabeth">Bet</ref>, but I think it very likely
                    that we shall, and that shortly; because when she went away she was to write
                    from New York if she could; she did not even know that she should go on shore
                    there, but perhaps sent coastways to philadelphia, in which case we were not to
                    hear from her till Autumn; my Landlady has a young brother who went for a
                    soldier, and was drafted off to go to the East Indies, they received a letter
                    from him to day (Oct 29) dated as far back as last february; <ref target="people.html#HingstonElizabeth">Bets</ref> will not be so long on its
                    passage, we are expecting news every week, — </p><p rend="indent1"> Give our respects and remembrance to <ref target="people.html#GloverJohn">my Father</ref>, tell <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref> I have not happened
                    to have a musical shopmate for some years past, I have therefore made no
                    progress that way, my love to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldElizabethsisterlaw">his wife</ref> and little
                    ones; and I remain your affectionate and dutiful Son</p><closer><signed rend="right">Rt. Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> and family are all well</p></postscript><closer><address><rs>Address:</rs><name><ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth"> Mrs
                        Glover</ref></name><placeName><ref target="places.html#Honington"> Hunnington</ref></placeName></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>