<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.222</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28265, ff. 335–36; also Add. MS 28268 ff. 256–57 with slight differences; published in Hart, p. 46; includes fair copy of missing letter addressed ‘To Misses Catherine and Frances Park. / and co. c. 1800–1801’</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="222" type="letter"><head>222. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerMary">Mary Lloyd Baker</ref>, n.d.<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28265, ff. 335–36; also Add. MS 28268 ff. 256–57 with slight differences; published in Hart, p. 46; includes fair copy of missing letter addressed ‘To Misses Catherine and Frances Park. / and co. c. 1800–1801’</note></head><p>The following is a copy of a Letter sent to two young Ladies, the Daughters of <ref target="people.html#ParkThomas">Thos Park</ref> Esq of High St Mary-le-bone, where I had left my walking stick</p><p rend="center">MISSING.</p><p>‘Whereas, on Monday afternoon an elderly gentleman remarkable for taciturnity and an unaltered countenance, accompanied his friend from the City to the West end of the town, and have not since been heard of.</p><p rend="indent1">	The said gentleman is a citizen of respectable appearance wearing a large full-bottom’d peruke, which though it has never been comb’d is as smooth as on the first day it was form’d. It is presumed the said gentleman is not detain’d from any legal process, nor for any riotous behaviour in the streets, he being never known to be guilty of such misdemeanours, except (as is allways the case when kings do wrong) except he may have been used as an <hi rend="ital">instrument</hi> in the hands of wicked and designing men. And in thus likening the said gentleman to his present most gracious Majesty and other kings, no harm whatever is meant, as in some other particulars he might be liken’d most truly, particularly this—He speaks not himself, but others speak for him.</p><p rend="indent1">	The said gentleman has never declared his opinion on politicks; but still it is known that he is neither a <hi rend="ital">Jacobin</hi>, nor a <hi rend="ital">Ministerialist</hi>; but it is thought that in the cause of Reform he would in certain cases be of great service.</p><p rend="indent1">	The said gentleman was never instructed in Grammar or Logic any more than his friend; yet it is shrewdly suspected; that, should his friend be attack’d he would be able to lay down some strong arguments on the side of justice. The said gentleman has somtimes been seen in a Cook-shop and somtimes in better company; but, (what is very important in these times) was never yet known to eat or to drink!! which considering him as a Citizen, is perhaps the most extraordinary trait in his character. His backwardness in speaking his own praise will not hinder us from supposing that he has served his country; a large scar on his left cheek seems to confirm that opinion. His complexion like his friend’s is remarkably dark, and he stoops considerably, which is supposed to proceed from intense study; for, as the said gentleman never wastes his time in idle conversation, it is universally believed that he must <hi rend="ital">know</hi> a great deal. Whither he does or not his friend would be glad to know where he is.—</p><p>In plain English—I left my favourite walking-stick at your house; take care of it for me; and command the services of</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">	Your Obedient Ser<hi rend="sup">t</hi></salute><signed rend="right">Rob Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="center">R. B.</p><p rend="indent1">	Seven years ago I wrote the above to a friend’s daughter at Marylebone, and I think I once promised you a copy, but did not then imagine that I should have so <hi rend="ital">fair</hi> and decided an apology for so doing. But the fact is, that I walked with the same stick to <ref target="places.html#Fulham">Fulham</ref>, and it remains (I hope) in your hall. It is a specimen of my carving at the time I began ‘The Farmer’s Boy;’ it was my companion at Shooter’s Hill—</p><p rend="indent3">			I took my staff and wander’d here— <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield quotes his own ‘Shooter’s Hill’, line 20, from <title>Wild Flowers</title> (p. 76).</note></p><p>and is one of my valuables. I am certain that you will enquire for it of the servants. I am not in want of it, only to have it secured. Remind <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">Mr. Baker</ref> that if he comes this way on <hi rend="ital">horseback</hi>, he cannot put <hi rend="ital">Coxe’s two quartos</hi>* under his arm. Another delightful day! Health be with you all.</p><p rend="right">Robert Bloomfield</p><p>* Coxes Hist: (of Monmouthshire I believe)<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably William Coxe, <title>An Historical Tour in Monmouthshire: Illustrated with views by Sir R. C. Hoare, Bart. A New Map of the County, and other Engravings</title> (London, 1801).</note></p><p>It was some book which he promised to lend me to read – <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">T J Ll B</ref></p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><rs>Address:</rs><name> To <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerMary">Mrs. Baker</ref></name></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>