<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.227</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 252–53</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="227" type="letter"><head>227. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1808-02-17">17 February 1808</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 252–53</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>City Road.</placeName></address><date when="1808-02-17">Feb 17. 1808</date></dateline><salute>Brother Isaac</salute></opener><p rend="indent1">	Yesterday on returning from Hammersmith where I had been through the slush of melted snow after salve for <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">my Boys</ref> knee, I found your letter, and as I was tired, I felt a severe fit of depression. I sit down this morning to give you as fair a statement of my mind and situation as I can put upon paper, and leave the conclusions to yourself. But first; I had for the last three weeks felt myself calld upon to write somthing as to the Anthems. You may remember that <ref target="people.html#PlumptreJames">Mr Plumptre</ref> had five more than he paid for in hope of selling them. He lately wrote to say ‘how does your Brother’s anthems go on? I fully expected a letter from him. I have heard a very good account of them from several quarters, but have not been fortunate enough to sell the extra copies. How shall I dispose of them? Shall I return them to you.’ This was the <hi rend="ital">sence</hi> of the letter for I cannot find it to give you a copy. I have not yet reply’d to it. Since that, I found a Master Carpenter whose name is Burden at Southgate, Middx, who I learnd was a famous singer, and was in his youth employd at Lincoln Cathedral &amp;c. I sent by the coach a copy of the Anthems with a letter of explanation, hoping that, at least, it might produce me somthing to write to you about, but I have heard nothing on the subject. <ref target="people.html#GilchristOctavius">Mr Gilchrist</ref> did not pay his £5. 10s untill the day before Christmass. Mr Wyatt has not paid the one pound, this, with two copies which I am sure will never be paid, leaves me 30 Shillings wrong as to the subscribed copies. I owe you 3 Shills for a copy which <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomasN">Longman</ref> sent for, and 5 shills when I get it for one sent to Canterbury.</p><p rend="indent1">	They have been constantly seen, and often talkd of, but like <ref target="people.html#PlumptreJames">Mr Plumptre</ref> I have not the satisfaction of selling them. So much for the musical part of the epistle.</p><p rend="indent1">	Your machine, for ought I can tell who never thought of mechanics in my life, may be a useful and valuable discovery. I wish you lived near to some Lord Stanhope or other, who would enter into the subject with you, and help you through it.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Lord Mahon, Philip Henry, the Fifth Earl Stanhope (1753–1816) was an inventor and politician renowned for his radical views and support for schemes designed to improve the lot of agricultural labourers. Bloomfield hopes that Isaac will gain such support for his invention of an improved pea/potato dibbler.</note> Your letter seems but half expressd, it is easy for me to conceive that this winter and all future winters will destress you, and render it impossible for you to support 8 children without assistance. And I want you as clearly to perceive that it is not allways in my <hi rend="ital">power</hi> to do it, setting my <hi rend="ital">will</hi> out of the question, In support of this I will tell you the following tale in my own defence. Last good Friday Mr Hawkins solicited the loan of £15 for a month at <hi rend="ital">farthest</hi>, to enable him to meet a Bill then coming against him. Before the month was out he told me he was a bankrupt, and this being a debt of honour I could not [words obscured in repair of MS], and the debt stands over without the possibility of getting it by law, and I am afraid he dont mean to pay it.—About 5 months past our next door neighbour’s wife borrow’d £5 for a week, and has never mention’d it since.—You know that what little I had put by out of any gains I some time ago (3 years) lent upon interest to my wife’s relation Fisher, I have never seen principal or interest since, and am sadly afraid never shall without troubling him. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Our boy</ref> wanting a deal of nursing, and the work of the house running behind, we have been oblidged to have <ref target="people.html#Honour">Honour</ref> back for a time, and to make room for her agreed for the <ref target="people.html#ChurchJoseph">old man</ref> to live at his Daughter Wyat’s where I pay for the board ten Shills per week, for, of his 20 £ annuity, he has 4 shill per week to spend, and the other 4 to clothe him.—About 3 weeks past I was drawn for the Tower Hamlets Militia, and oblidged to find a Man, so that I last monday morning paid £20. 3 shill to get rid of it. I drew £40 last week from the Booksellers, and have not <hi rend="ital">now</hi> a guinea in the house, not at my <hi rend="ital">command</hi> except by letting myself down by asking against; whatever I may have to recieve for my years account, I cannot know this six weeks, or two months! I owe Mr Naylor 5 pounds—I have seven pound ten due for Harps, and about 14 to make.  </p><p rend="indent1">	You mention living rent free, to that you are entirely wellcome I never expected any other. You would be equally wellcome to the use of my shop, but much more than that is implied in the proposal, for who would keep your family the while. I have shown you that to send money is to me utterly impossible without making myself an <hi rend="ital">everlasting</hi> domestic rod. I have been whipt enough allready. This I know will be sad news to you, but no consideration shall induce me to hide the truth, or to make you think that I am saving money and growing rich. The world is sadly decieved, and I shall one day cut an awkward figure as to pecuniary matters, and have a poor story to tell. I am afraid your journeys to London generally eat up your profits in loss of time. It must have been so with the Anthems; But this seems still more an uncertain speculation in which <hi rend="ital">I</hi> can have less influence from knowing nothing about it. If under these <hi rend="ital">true</hi> but disheartening circumstances you either <hi rend="ital">must</hi> or <hi rend="ital">can</hi> come to London, the workshop you perceive is the smallest consideration in the case, I am <hi rend="ital">extreemly</hi> unhappy dayly and hourly for my <hi rend="ital">own</hi> intention, and must leave yours unaided though with a set of feelings which I doubt will do me no good. My Best love to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldElizabethsisterlaw">your wife</ref> and children.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">	Yours truly in Affection</salute><signed rend="right">Rob Bloomfield</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>