<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.304</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        364–65</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="304" type="letter"><head>304. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1816-11-22">22 November 1816</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        364–65</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1816-11-22">Friday Nov 22. 1816</date></dateline><dateline rend="right"><date>St Cecilia’s Day.</date></dateline></opener><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> ‘Twas at the Royal feast for Persia won</l><l rend="indent4"> By Philips warlike son:’<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Twas at the Royal feast for Persia won / By Philips
                            warlike son:’ Lines 1–2 of John Dryden’s ‘Alexander's Feast; or, the
                            Power of Music a Song in Honour of St.Cecilia's Day: 1697’.</note></l></lg><p>My Dear Life—</p><p rend="indent1"> Cheer up! I am going to tell you all about it, and first of
                    myself. You will rejoice to hear that my Rhumatism is much abated, and that, by
                    acquiring <hi rend="ital">by force</hi> a relish for reading, my November days
                    have past much better than I or you expected. I was yesterday to have dined with
                    the tennantry at <ref target="places.html#Chicksands">Chicksands</ref>, but I am
                    tied to the fireside by an inflamation in my left ancle arising from a late
                    accidental blow on the shin by falling off my chair! You may stare, but I was
                    resting said left foot on the fender, when by an instantaneous slip I was thrown
                    completely off my balance, and struck my leg violently on the Brass top. We have
                    brought down the inflamation by vinegar and sound sopping, and all goes
                    well.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr Weston</ref> must have smiled at my
                    promise of sending you this on the day that I spoke of: that day was past, and I
                    am persuaded that the very day on which I was just double your age was no other
                    than <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles’s</ref> birth day,
                    when you was at Winsor! You can recon it better than I.</p><p rend="indent1"> We did not forget your birthday, and I expect you will drink to
                    my next half century, next Tuesday week.—</p><p rend="indent1"> I am sadly afraid that my friends have been too sanguine in their
                    hopes of the subscription. In Suffolk I hear of no more than £120 and in Kent
                    about £20. From London not a word of intelligence, Gloucestershire Do, though by
                    a letter from <ref target="people.html#SharpCatherine">Miss Sharp</ref> as far
                    back as Sep 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, I know that they are apprised of what is
                    on foot! In <ref target="people.html#SharpCatherine">Miss Sharps</ref> letter
                    she informs me as follows. ‘I must beg you <hi rend="ital">without delay</hi> to
                    give you the name and age of your <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldRobertHenry">second son</ref> and to state to
                    me distinctly and circumstancialy what your views for him are—. I mean to apply
                    to the Trustees of Lord Crew’s Charities at Bamborough* in Northumberland, on
                    whom our families have peculiar claims—and it is not unlikely, (though far from
                    certain) but I may be able to procure ten pounds per ann for him for 5 years
                    either for education, or as an apprentice fee, but then I must set forth his
                    situation with some degree of precision &amp;c’ The same letter says ‘If you
                    think your <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">eldest son</ref> from
                    his infirmity of lameness stands more in need of assistance, I beg you will say
                    so, and give me the particulars of his case. It is immaterial to me which son it
                    is I apply for so long as I serve you, Indeed if for any reason you should deem
                    one of your daughters more immediately an object of interest, you may say so
                    &amp;c’ I gave the necessisary information immediately to this excellent
                    Lady, but have not heard a word since. In another letter <ref target="people.html#SharpCatherine">Miss Sharp</ref> informs me that by the
                    death her Cousin Jamima Sharp of Durham, an <hi rend="ital">immense
                        accession</hi> of Fortune has fallen to <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">Mr Loyd Baker</ref>!!! (Lucky Dog)
                    have not I told you how it would be a thousand times? I will carefully keep <ref target="people.html#SharpCatherine">Miss Sharps</ref> letters for you, for
                    in the same epistle it is plainly stated that she has suffered a dreadful
                    disappointment as to the <hi rend="ital">understood</hi> distribution of the
                    property, and her calm and dignified manner of telling me so places her amongst
                    the highest class of Christian philosophers.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Bloomfield’s of <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref>, and the Philips’s of Barton are among the Suffolk
                    subscribers.</p><p rend="indent1"> I did mean here to tell you a long story about the tattle of <ref target="places.html#Chicksands">Chicksands</ref>, but if I attempt it now
                    the post will be gone, and leave you in suspence till Tuesday. I only assure you
                    that it <hi rend="ital">now</hi> gives me not the least disturbance. You will
                    hear it all in due time—Last night the Honest Citizen John Peppercorn drank tea
                    and spent a great many animated words with me; it was very kind, and I like
                    it.—We are all well, and send a whole bag of Love to you, and to <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr &amp; Miss Weston</ref>, and I am
                    half in the dark, but in the daylight of affection</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Your father,</salute><signed rend="right">Robt Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p>*I <hi rend="ital">have</hi> heard of a Lord Crew’s splendid donation, but do
                        not quite understand their extent. Bamborough Castle with great estates and
                        perhaps still belongs to the Sharp family<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1720, Lord Crewe, Bishop of Durham, left Bamborough
                            Castle, and extensive nearby properties, for charitable purposes,
                            including, by 1810, a National School in the village of Bamborough, and
                            an officer to fire a cannon from the dangerous rocks every fifteen
                            minutes in foggy weather, besides providing for the education of thirty
                            girls within the castle walls. John Sharp, Catherine’s uncle, had been
                            one of the trustees of the charity until 1792.</note></p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><rs>Address: </rs><name><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Miss Bloomfield</ref>,</name> / <placeName><ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr Weston’s</ref> Draper, / Twickenham, / Middx.</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>