<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.63</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Suffolk Record
                        Office, Bury St Edmunds, 317/3</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="63" type="letter"><head>63. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Capel
                        Lofft</ref>, before <date when="1801-10-31">31 October
                        1801</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Suffolk Record
                        Office, Bury St Edmunds, 317/3</note></head><lb/><p rend="center">(Extracts)</p><p>Mr Bentley speaks highly of your exertions in my favour at the same time I think
                    I am not transgressing to say that he wishes you could perfect the manuscript
                    now, as to punctuation and whatever else we may agree to do to them, which he
                    says would save much trouble and delay afterwards — And I am further permitted
                    to say, that if it could be of any service to the cause, <ref target="people.html#ParkThomas">Mr Park</ref> offers to see the proofs, and
                    to correct what might be deemed errors of the printer, &amp;c. I mention
                    these things with the utmost diffidence, and I am quite sure <ref target="people.html#ParkThomas">Mr P</ref> has no idea of transcending your
                    accuracy and attention.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is always understood that the expence of the proofs going into
                    the country falling upon you, and your time is always valuable; there are among
                    the particulars that gave rise to the suggestion; nobody wishes me even to
                    change Booksellers, much less to change Editors.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have just now been with <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Mr
                        Hill</ref>, where I met by accident with <ref target="people.html#ParkThomas">Mr Park</ref> again. We had a long
                    consultation, as <ref target="people.html#ParkThomas">Mr P</ref> — has another
                    epistle from <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Miss Seward</ref>, whose
                    remarks they prize; but both gentlemen make no scruple of saying that if her
                    criticisms are given in the future editions, something should be withdrawn to
                    make room for it, or the price will and must be raised, which is thought
                    universally to be wrong, and by all means to be avoided. I say universally
                    because I never yet found one who did not think so. Other people may have their
                    own particular opinions, but I will state my own first.</p><p rend="indent1"> The note from Cook’s Voyage is mine,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield’s note on the comparative equality of ranks in
                        Tahitian society, quoted from George Forster, <title>A Voyage Round the
                            World, in His Britannic Majesty’s Sloop, Resolution, Commanded by Capt.
                            James Cook, During the Years 1772, 3, 4, and 5</title>, 2 vols. (London,
                        1777), I, 365–67, appears in the 1800 edition of <title>The Farmer’s
                            Boy</title>, as a note to lines 341–42 of ‘Summer’ ‘... life’s
                        intercourse; the social plan / That rank to rank cements, as man to man’:
                        ‘ALLOWING for the imperfect state of sublunary happiness, which is
                        comparative at best, there are not, perhaps, many nations existing whose
                        situation is so desirable; where the means of subsistence are so easy, and
                        the wants of the people so few … The evident distinction of ranks, which
                        subsists at <hi rend="ital">Otaheite</hi>, does not so materially affect the
                        felicity of the nation as we might have supposed. The simplicity of their
                        whole life contributes to soften the appearance of distinctions, and to
                        reduce them to a level. Where the climate and the custom of the country do
                        not absolutely require a perfect garment; where it is easy at every step to
                        gather as many plants as form not only a decent, but likewise a customary
                        covering; and where all the necessaries of life are within the reach of
                        every individual, at the expence of a trifling labour; … ambition and envy
                        must in a great measure be unknown. It is true, the highest classes of
                        people possess some dainty articles, such as pork, fish, fowl, and cloth,
                        almost exclusively; but the desire of indulging the appetite in a few
                        trifling luxuries can at most render individuals, and not whole nations,
                        unhappy. Absolute want occasions the miseries of the lower class in some
                        civiliz’d states, and is the result of the unbounded voluptuousness of their
                        superiors. At <hi rend="ital">Otaheite</hi> there is not, in general, that
                        disparity between the highest and the meanest man, that subsists in England
                        between a reputable tradesman and a labourer. The affection of the
                        Otaheitans for their chiefs, which they never fail’d to express upon all
                        occasions, gave us great reason to suppose that they consider themselves as
                        one family, and respect their eldest born in the persons of their chiefs.
                        The lowest man in the nation speaks as freely with his king as with his
                        equal, and has the pleasure of seeing him as often as he likes. The king, at
                        times, amuses himself with the occupations of his subjects; and not yet
                        deprav’d by false notions of empty state, he often paddles his own canoe,
                        without considering such an employment derogatory to his dignity. How long
                        such an happy equality may last is uncertain: and how much the introduction
                        of foreign luxuries may hasten its dissolution cannot be too frequently
                        repeated to Europeans. If the knowledge of a few individuals can only be
                        acquired at such a price as the happiness of nations, it were better for the
                        discoverers and the discovered that the <hi rend="ital">South Sea</hi> had
                        still remain’d unknown to <hi rend="ital">Europe</hi> and its restless
                        inhabitants. / REFLECTIONS ON OTAHEITE, Cook’s second Voyage.’</note> but
                    many superficial readers not attending to your initial, L; call it yours, I
                    think it harmless in itself, but I wrote it before I knew for certain that the
                    public would see it, and before I had considered the consequence of introducing
                    even the appearance of politics into a Rural production, (let my own private
                    notions be what they may) and therefore I am willing, nay wish that to be
                    omitted in future. And, as to <ref target="people.html#SwanJames">Mr.
                        Swans</ref> letter, you cannot but recollect, Sir, that from the first the
                    person and profession of <ref target="people.html#SwanJames">Mr. Swan</ref> was
                    mistaken by you and I question if your friendly and wellmeant statement can now
                    appear to you of importance enough to be retained,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The long quotation from James Swan’s letter (Letter 34),
                        first included in the 3rd edition of the 1800 <title>Farmer’s Boy</title>
                        (London, 1800), was dropped from some later editions, although Lofft
                        continued to refer to it in a footnote.</note> I think not. <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Mr. Hill</ref> says, that the note
                    respecting the debating societies will now be useless,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield refers to the following note which appeared in the
                        Preface to <title>The Farmer’s Boy</title>: ‘It is another of the
                        Constitutional Refinements of these times to have fettered and as to every
                        valuable purpose, silenced, these Debating Societies. They were at least, to
                        say the lowest of them, far better amusements than drunkenness, gambling, or
                        fighting. They were no useless Schools to some of our very celebrated
                        Speakers at the Bar and in Parliament: and, what is of infinitely more
                        importance, they contributed to the diffusion of Political Knowledge and
                        Public Sentiment. L.’</note> as the law it alludes to has just ceased, and
                    he suggested to me the propriety of reserving for the first volume the lines on
                    ‘Revisiting the Country’,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield’s
                        lines on ‘Revisiting the Country’ (included in a manuscript fair copy by
                        George Bloomfield in Letter 31) were not omitted from subsequent editions.
                        First printed in the 2nd edition of the poem, from the 3rd they appeared
                        before the first part, ‘Spring’:<lb/><p rend="indent3">ON REVISITING THE PLACE OF MY NATIVITY.</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> THOUGH Winter’s frowns had damp’d the beaming
                                eye,</l><l rend="indent3"> Through Twelve successive Summers heav’d the
                                sigh,</l><l rend="indent3"> The unaccomplish’d wish was still the same;</l><l rend="indent3"> Till May in new and sudden glories came!</l><l rend="indent3"> My heart was rous’d; and Fancy on the wing,</l><l rend="indent3"> Thus heard the language of enchanting Spring:—</l><l rend="indent4"> ‘Come to thy native groves and fruitful fields!</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Thou know’st the fragrance that the wild-flow’r
                                yields;</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Inhale the Breeze that bends the purple bud,</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘And plays along the margin of the Wood.</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘I’ve cloth’d them all; the very Woods where thou</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘In infancy learn’d’st praise from every bough.</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Would’st thou behold again the vernal day?</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘My reign is short;—this instant come away:</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Ere Philomel shall silent meet the morn;</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘She hails the green, but not the rip’ning corn.</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Come, ere the pastures lose their yellow
                                flow’rs:</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Come now; with heart as jocund as the hours.’</l><l rend="indent4"> Who could resist the call?—that, Giles had done,</l><l rend="indent3"> Nor heard the Birds, nor seen the rising Sun;</l><l rend="indent3"> Had not Benevolence, with cheering ray,</l><l rend="indent3"> And Greatness stoop’d, indulgent to display</l><l rend="indent3"> Praise which does surely not to Giles belong,</l><l rend="indent3"> But to the objects that inspir’d his song.</l><l rend="indent3"> Immediate pleasure from those praises flow’d:</l><l rend="indent3"> Remoter bliss within his bosom glow’d!</l><l rend="indent3"> Now tasted all:—for I have heard and seen</l><l rend="indent3"> The long-remember’d voice, the church, the
                                green;—</l><l rend="indent3"> And oft by Friendship’s gentle hand been led</l><l rend="indent3"> Where many an hospitable board was spread.</l><l rend="indent3"> These would I name,... but each, and all can feel</l><l rend="indent3"> What the full heart would willingly reveal:</l><l rend="indent3"> Nor needs be told; that at each season’s birth,</l><l rend="indent3"> Still the enamell’d, or the scorching Earth</l><l rend="indent3"> Gave, as each morn or weary night would come,</l><l rend="indent3"> Ideal sweetness to my distant home:—</l><l rend="indent3"> Ideal now no more;—for, to my view</l><l rend="indent3"> Spring’s promise rose, how admirably true!!</l><l rend="indent3"> The early chorus of the cheerful Grove,</l><l rend="indent3"> Gave point to Gratitude; and fire to Love.</l><l rend="indent3"> O Memory! shield me from the World’s poor strife;</l><l rend="indent3"> And give those scenes thine everlasting life!</l></lg><p rend="indent3"> LONDON, MAY 30,
                            1800.                
                            ROB. BLOOMFIELD.</p></note> and to shorten the preface by the omission;
                    these, Sir, are the heads of what I am obligated to hear, and almost obligated
                    to repeat.</p><p rend="indent1"> I solemnly declare that I never heard from any tongue, partisan
                    or not partisan, a word of reproach or discredit to the character of <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. Lofft</ref>, or his wellknown
                    benevolence and attachment to the interest of literature, and will <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. Lofft</ref> be offended with a man whom
                    his own example has taught to be frank and open, if he as solemnly declare, that
                    there exists as well among those of <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr.
                        Lofft’s</ref> political persuasion and those of a contrary character, a very
                    general, if not universal opinion, that political thoughts and references
                    (however just in themselves) ought not to be seen in this instance where rural
                    poetry only should be found.</p><p rend="indent1"> They quarrel, not with your (or our) political opinions as such,
                    but at their being found there. It is not in my power, and I hope it is not in
                    my nature to dictate, but I do certainly know Sir that the entire omission of
                    every thing of that tendency would give the majority, if not every reader a
                    fresh interest in the history of the poem, and the commendatory notes from
                        Litchfield,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Lichfield was the home
                        town of Anna Seward.</note> and from equal authorities would unquestionably
                    benefit the poem; and that to benefit the poem is your sincere and ardent wish,
                    there is not a man or woman in England who doubts it.</p><p rend="indent1"> When at <ref target="people.html#GedgePeter">Mr. Gedge’s</ref> I
                    wished much to apprize you of the public opinion as to our Boy Giles,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Boy Giles: <title>The Farmer’s
                        Boy</title>.</note> but I dare not then, I shall you may be sure Sir, after
                    such a letter as this, be anxious for your opinion, and I will not damp my
                    spirits with the idea of your being offended. Your conscience I know will acquit
                    you for having done the utmost in your power, and, if the opinion of readers run
                    counter to any part of it, I really do not see why you, of all persons
                    concerned, should not have that matter stated, and be left to act as your good
                    judgement may direct.</p></div></body></text></TEI>