<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.388</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Remains, II, pp.
                        195–98</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="388" type="letter"><head>388. <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Joseph Weston</ref> to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George Bloomfield</ref>, with a
                    postscript from <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1824-06-05">5 June 1824</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote"><title>Remains</title>, II, pp.
                        195–98</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1824-06-05">June 5, 1824</date></dateline><salute>Sir, </salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It was the wish of your late brother, Mr. Robert Bloomfield, my
                    much lamented friend, that I should prepare the materials for a sketch or memoir
                    of his life; should such be thought useful, and publish such parts of his
                    correspondence and other papers as I might deem fit for the purpose. These, with
                    a preface and a few tributary verses to his memory, will compose two
                    moderate-sized volumes, and will serve to complete what may properly be called
                    his works. They have received the approbation of <ref target="people.html#ParkThomas">Mr. Park</ref>, and I shall now send them to
                    the booksellers for theirs. In the preface I have thought it my duty to notice
                    the cowardly attack made on your brother’s character and writings, in the
                    Monthly Magazine for September 1823, and have little doubt of making the
                    libeller either look very silly or retract his slander.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Weston refers to the following article in the <title>Monthly
                            Magazine</title>, September 1823: <quote>At Shefford, 57, <hi rend="ital">Mr Robert Bloomfield</hi>, author of the Farmer’s Boy,
                            once very popular, and of other poems. He was the son of a poor taylor
                            in Suffolk, originally employed as a farmer’s boy, and afterwards
                            followed the employment of a shoe-maker. Having, about 1800, finished
                            his four Poems on the rural employments of the seasons, be brought them
                            to London to endeavour to get them published. His first application was
                            to Mr. Charles Dilly, who recommended him to the editor of the Monthly
                            Magazine. He brought his Poems to our office; and, though his unpolished
                            appearance, his coarse hand-writing, and wretched orthography, afforded
                            no prospect that his production could be printed, yet he found attention
                            by his repeated calls, and by the humility of his expectations, which
                            were limited to half a-dozen copies of the Magazine. At length on his
                            name being announced when a literary gentleman, particularly conversant
                            in rural economy, happened to be present, the poem was formally
                            re-examined, and its general aspect excited the risibility of that
                            gentleman in so pointed a manner, that Bloomfield was called into the
                            room, and exhorted not to waste his time, and neglect his employment, in
                            making vain attempts, and particularly in treading on the ground which
                            Thomson had sanctified. His earnestness and confidence, however, led the
                            editor to advise him to consult his countryman, Mr. Capel Lofft, of
                            Troston, to whom he gave him a letter of introduction. On his departure,
                            the gentleman present warmly complimented the editor on the sound advice
                            which he had given ‘the poor fellow;’ and, it was mutually conceived,
                            that an industrious man was thereby likely to be saved from a ruinous
                            infatuation. Bloomfield, however, visited Mr. Lofft, and that
                            kind-hearted and erudite man, entering sanguinely into his views, edited
                            the work through the press, wrote a preface, and the poem appeared as a
                            literary meteor. Its success was prodigious. The author was to divide
                            the profits with the bookseller, and they soon shared above £1000
                            a-piece. The reputation of the poem at length seemed so thoroughly
                            established, that the bookseller offered to give Bloomfield an annuity
                            of £200 per annum for his half; but this he refused, in the confidence
                            that it would produce him double. At length, however, new objects caught
                            the public attention; the sale died away; and, in three or four years, a
                            small edition per annum only was required. All this was in the usual
                            course; but Bloomfield, whose expectations had been unduly raised,
                            keenly felt the reverse; he was obliged to seek other employment, and
                            his health and spirits suffered in consequence. Other attempts produced
                            but moderate recompense; and, becoming peevish, he entered into a paper
                            war with his patron Mr. Lofft, and lost the sympathy of many of his
                            first friends. He was nevertheless a man of real genius; and, though the
                            bloated popularity of his Farmer’s Boy led to no permanent advantage,
                            yet it had, and still has, admirers, some of whom never ceased to be
                            kind to the author. His ambition, however, was disappointed; and, for
                            some years, be was in a state of mental depression, which, it is stated,
                            rendered his death consolatory to his connections. Under these
                            circumstances, and they are such as constantly attend genius without
                            pecuniary independence, the editor of this Magazine is not ashamed of
                            the advice which he gave Bloomfield at his outset. The world would have
                            lost nothing by the non-appearance of the Farmer’s Boy, as it then
                            existed in Bloomfield’s original manuscript, and the poet would have
                            enjoyed the comforts of an industrious life, enhanced by his love of the
                            Muses. Bloomfield, however, never forgave the adviser, and the phrase
                            with which the conversation ended. ‘I earnestly advise you <hi rend="ital">to stick to your last</hi>,’ which was used without any
                            suspicion that such was his real employment, he often quoted with
                            indignation in the hey-day of his subsequent popularity.</quote> Weston
                        replied to it in the Preface to the <title>Remains</title> but also in the
                        November number of <title>The Monthly Magazine</title>, 1823, pp. 182–83:
                            <quote>We have been favoured with the following remarks on the works of
                            the late Robert Bloomfield, and with pleasure give place to them. Our
                            correspondent errs through over zeal, in supposing that our former
                            notice was written in the spirit of detraction. That spirit has never
                            disgraced the Monthly Magazine, and never will. ‘His “Farmer’s Boy,”
                            though his first, on the whole, may, I think, be deemed his best
                            production; in which he displayed, not only great poetical talent, but
                            also great practical knowledge of agriculture. The account of the early
                            life of the author, prefixed to this work by his ingenious friend Mr.
                            Lofft, is highly interesting, and shows the native excellence of his
                            moral character in a striking point of view. His next production was the
                            “Rural Tales,” which are many of them truly excellent; and of his “Wild
                            Flowers,” the same may be justly said. His poem of “Good ‘Tidings, or
                            News from the Farm,” intended as a tribute of respect and gratitude to
                            Dr. Jenner, for the discovery of the Cow Pox,—which contains also a just
                            and eloquent acknowledgment to Lady Wortley Montague, who first
                            introduced Inoculation for the Small Pox into this country, from
                            Turkey,—has I think been less noticed than it deserves—it possesses many
                            glowing beauties—many poetic excellencies, feeling, generous, and
                            pathetic sentiments. In 1807, Mr. Bloomfield accompanied a select party
                            of friends down the romantic river Wye, in Wales; and of this pleasing
                            excursion, he afterwards published, under the title of “Banks of Wye,” a
                            poetical journal, divided into four books; the account of this voyage is
                            interspersed with the history of surrounding antiquities, and the
                            traditions of the country. In this volume, if not as a whole equal to
                            his preceding productions, there are occasional touches of real poetry,
                            and some truly interesting episodes; the little piece on the departure
                            of Mr. Morris, the beloved but unfortunate possessor of the beautiful
                            gardens of Piercefield in Monmouthshire, is truly affecting. In 1822,
                            Mr. Bloomfield once more appeared before the public; and
                            notwithstanding, as he tells us in his preface, “May-day with the Muses,
                            was written under great anxiety of mind, and in a wretched state of
                            health,” it will be found to possess considerable merit. The idea which
                            supplied our author with materials for this poem, is something novel and
                            unique; if too much so to be probable, when we have perused the
                            interesting tales to which it introduces us, I think we may very well
                            excuse it. The first piece of “The Drunken Father,” is quite in the
                            author’s own style; though there are two or three stanzas very
                            imperfect, which might probably be omitted advantageously. The allusion,
                            in “The Forester,” to the melancholy events at Claremont, is truly
                            happy,—the following lines from this piece are very
                            admirable:</quote><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l>“Empires may fall, and nations groan, </l><l>Pride be thrown down, and states decay!</l><l>Dark Bigotry may rear her throne,</l><l>But science is the light of day.”</l></lg><lb/><quote>—“The Shepherd’s Dream,” and “The Soldier’s Home,” are also
                            pieces of great merit; and the last tale of “Alfred and Janet,” written,
                            as the author says, for the express purpose of convincing a female
                            friend, “that it is possible for a blind man to be in love,” adds
                            another laurel to the many before entwined round the brow of the writer.
                            The poetical fame of Bloomfield is fixed upon an imperishable basis; and
                            in despite of the censures of puny critics and self-sufficient
                            commentators, his works will be read in after ages, with pleasure and
                            delight. Even those who do not admire his poetry, must assent to the
                            moral tendency of all his productions:—if he erred in his pictures of
                            human nature in the lower walks of life, it was indeed by looking on its
                            brighter side, and painting man not as he is, but as he ought to
                            be.’</quote></note> I wish, however, to march on solid ground; and the
                    only tender place I as yet apprehend, is contained in that sentence of Robert’s
                    letter to you, where he says—‘I took the manuscript of the Farmer’s Boy to your
                        <hi rend="ital">Magazine Man</hi>’, without saying who this man was. If your
                    memory serves, I will thank you to inform me what Magazine it was to which your
                    brother alludes, and who was at that time the editor of it; and whether you have
                    any reason for thinking that the person who wrote the libel above alluded to can
                    possibly be the same;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">George’s
                        identification of ‘the Magazine Man’ appears in Letter 389.</note> or if you
                    are <hi rend="ital">quite sure</hi> it must be some other person; for if the
                    latter be the case, I have other evidence to prove that nearly the whole is a
                    collection of willful misrepresentations, the exposure of which may tend to
                    place the reputation of your brother, and that of his traducer, in their proper
                    light.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is my present intention to blend the account of your brother’s
                    early life, published in the stereotype edition, with certain historical
                    memoranda which he has left in considerable abundance, together with his
                    correspondence, and such authentic anecdotes as I can collect among his friends
                    and acquaintance, into a Biographical Sketch, and perhaps leave the composition
                    and style to some abler pen. I hope, however, in my ministerial office to do
                    impartial justice to a man whose talents I admired, whose virtues I venerate,
                    and whose untimely death I shall always deplore. I forsee, however, that it must
                    be a cloudy concern—perhaps you will allow me to enliven the detail now and then
                    with an extract from your poetry, which I think is often excellent, and abounds
                    in your letters. I beg to add, that any anecdotes or other communications from
                    you will always be received with thankfulness. I shall remain here until the
                    12th, but a letter at any time addressed for me to Mr. Bristow, Park-street,
                    Windsor, will be sure to reach me safely.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> I remain sir,</salute><salute rend="indent1"> Your humble servant,</salute><signed rend="right"><ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Joseph Weston</ref></signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> It is very extraordinary that we can get no intelligence
                        either from <ref target="people.html#LockwoodEdward">Mr. Lockwood</ref> or
                            <ref target="people.html#WaymanJohn">Mr. Wayman</ref> as to the cottage
                        business. It would save great trouble and expense if they would conclude it
                        while I am here, having induced the creditors to accept a moderate
                        composition, under the promise that the proceeds of this estate should be
                        added—for the performance of which I consider my honour and credit both
                        pledged. At any rate I should like to know how the matter stands, and if it
                        is not giving you too much trouble, should feel much obliged if you would
                        urge <ref target="people.html#LockwoodEdward">Mr. Lockwood</ref> to send
                        such information.</p><p rend="indent1"> My Dear <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">Uncle</ref></p><p rend="indent1"> This little space will serve to tell you we are all well, and
                        that is as much as I have to say now except we hope <hi rend="ital">you</hi>
                        are.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your affectionate niece,</p><p rend="right"><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah Bloomfield</ref></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>