<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.35</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Pierpont Morgan Library, New
                        York, MA 4500</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="35" type="letter"><head>35. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#VaughanWilliam">William
                        Vaughan</ref>, <date when="1800-07-22">22 July 1800</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Pierpont Morgan Library, New
                        York, MA 4500</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>London</placeName></address><date when="1800-07-22">July 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> — 1800 —</date></dateline><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have written a long letter to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref>, great part of which I shall
                    copy to you, and beg pardon for my intrusion when I see you,</p><lb/><p rend="indent1"> ‘Mr <ref target="people.html#VaughanWilliam">Vaughan</ref> has
                    given me the new edition of <ref target="people.html#BurnsRobert">Burns</ref>,
                    his life and letters, &amp;c 4 vols.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">The Works of Robert Burns; with an Account of his Life
                            and a Criticism on his Writings</title>, 4 vols. (Liverpool,
                        1800).</note> I know not how much I am oblidged to Mr <ref target="people.html#VaughanWilliam">Vaughan</ref> for the favour. I cannot
                    read three pages of his life without walking across the room to relieve my
                    stomach. I wish he was alive that I might see him for the small trouble of
                    walking to Scotland for that purpose.’</p><lb/><p rend="indent1"> ‘A kind of enchantment took possession of my mind and sences too
                    on Friday evening, from eight till twelve O’clock. The hot breezes of a summer’s
                    day were gone to rest; and a Water expanded itself before me that seem’d to have
                    no motion but the swelling of a slow rising tide; the western clouds lay still;
                    and Echo was ready to answer every word and every breath. I floated on its
                    surface allmost before I was aware, and saw the busy world dusty, and fateagued
                    travelling in two distinct tracks over my head. The oblique shadows pointed at
                    me from the shore; gladness was the ruler of all present, and was obey’d. At
                    last landing, I left the pleasant waters to go on, to catch new shadows and wash
                    other shores, and had scarcely felt my feet before a Fairy Vision extended
                    itself that defied the eye of indifference. The Magic power that had caused and
                    seem’d to govern the whole scene had hung ten thousand lighted sparks twinkling
                    like stars around the boughs of trees, so that the under side of the foliage
                    became illuminated and gave to the eye an ashcolour’d green; every leaf as still
                    as the trunk on which it grew, for not a breath of air passd over them. On the
                    illuminated sand below appear’d a mixd society of creatures, apparently mortal
                    who either actually were happy or had left for a time the appearance of
                    unhappiness behind them. A great proportion of those wore a female garb, but, as
                    they were not fateagued with labour or exposed to the sun I could not discover
                    why it was that their necks and shoulders were bare. I was meditating on these
                    things when a fresh and sudden kind of enchantment set the whole assembly in
                    motion, for who moves not at the sound of musick? As the bodies of trees growing
                    near to the eye sometimes intercept and cut parts of a distant landscape, so did
                    they here, as it were, cut the vibrations of the musick traveling from the
                    centre of the scene to its confines. Somtimes it was sweetly melancholy, and a
                    voice made the shades ring with,</p><p rend="indent4"> Faithless Edward is not here</p><p>Then at intervals in a remote part of the enchanted grove, a delightfull thrill
                    came through the bosom from the roll of the fife and the “spirit stirring Drum”.
                    The fantastick bounces of the Tamborine invited the heart to mirth and every
                    note going to the boundary of the grove, seem’d to return in search of others
                    but that instant struck from the instrument or voice. Smiles of hilarity were on
                    every countenance, and particularly on those of the Fairies who with a waving
                    plume and bosoms heaving to the sounds they gave, stood and pour’d forth spirit
                    of song. Six voices caught from each other the words</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> Lads and lasses lets be gay</l><l rend="indent4"> For this is Nature’s holyday<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield quotes from ‘May Day’ by Peter Pindar (John
                            Wolcot), whose works he comments on in Letter 32): <lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> The daisies peep from ev’ry field, </l><l rend="indent3"> And vi’lets sweet their odour yield; </l><l rend="indent3"> The purple blossom paints the thorn, </l><l rend="indent3"> And streams reflect the blush of morn. </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Then lads and lasses all, be gay, </l><l rend="indent3"> For this is Nature’s holiday. </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Let lusty Labour drop his flail, </l><l rend="indent3"> Nor woodman’s hook a tree assail; </l><l rend="indent3"> The ox shall cease his neck to bow, </l><l rend="indent3"> And Clodden yield to rest, the plough. </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3">Then lads, &amp;c. </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Behold the lark in ether float, </l><l rend="indent3"> While rapture swells the liquid note! </l><l rend="indent3"> What warbles he, with merry cheer? </l><l rend="indent3"> Let Love and Pleasure rule the year? </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3">Then lads, &amp;c. </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Lo, Sol looks down, with radiant eye, </l><l rend="indent3"> And throws a smile around his sky; </l><l rend="indent3"> Embracing hill and vale and stream, </l><l rend="indent3"> And warming Nature with his beam. </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Then lads, &amp;c.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> The insect tribes in myriads pour, </l><l rend="indent3"> And kiss with Zephyr ev’ry flow’r; </l><l rend="indent3"> Shall <hi rend="ital">these</hi> our icy hearts
                                    reprove, </l><l rend="indent3"> And tell us we are foes to Love? </l></lg><lb/><lg><l rend="indent3"> Then lads, &amp;c.</l></lg></note></l></lg><lb/><p>I also observed that round the whole scene were distributed a great variety of
                    tables set with the choicest and most tempting refreshments; such they apeard to
                    be; but whither on being touch’d as in some other enchanted woods and castles
                    they would have vanished from before me I cannot tell as I did not put it to the
                    trial. I could not help admiring much as assemblage of younger Fairies who,
                    cloathed in white, and full of mirth, danced to the Tamborine, and ran in
                    parties from the illuminated to darker shades, from tree to tree, and seemd as
                    ignorant of what we mortals call care and pain, as if they had never heard of
                    them.</p><p rend="indent1"> Musick and Beauty are powerfull allurements. If the mere scene
                    had been shewn without them, I should have prefer’d the view of the evening sky
                    on the water, to the Fairies lamps, their grassless groves, and their publick
                    tables. And Fairy Visions in my estimation must still yield to a green grass
                    bank; the soul-chearing balm of the morning air; leaves brightened by <hi rend="ital">Natures</hi> Luminary; and violets peeping through the long
                    grass as if to see how high he has mounted. Nor are those cheap, those common
                    scenes without the charm of Musick. When I heard the uncage’d Blackbird and the
                    Nightingale last May, and tried to bear in mind the amazing variations of the
                    latter bird, tried to draw near the twig, that supported him, and saw the little
                    feathers on his throat fall smooth at every pause, I felt Musick’s most
                    bewitching power. If ungovernable sighs rise at such a moment who would try to
                    check them? If gratefull reflection joins the ear and the eye’s feast and should
                    produce a tear, an empassion’d stamp of the foot; or, an exulting skip upon a
                    molehill, that tear, and that triumph is the triumph of Nature. — ’</p><p> Pray Sir forgive me these long digressions, and I surely need not add that I
                    have seen <ref target="places.html#Vauxhall">Vauxhall</ref>.</p><p><ref target="people.html#RogersSamuel">Mr Rogers</ref> finding I had not seen
                    that celebrated place of amusement proposed the treat, and was accompanied by Mr
                    Tuffen and <ref target="people.html#SharpGranville">Mr Sharp</ref>, to whom I
                    was greatly oblidged for the unexpected and agreeable treat. I know that <ref target="people.html#VaughanWilliam">Mr Vaughan</ref> will particularly ask
                    me what I think of <ref target="places.html#Vauxhall">Vauxhall</ref>, and I know
                    of no better way of telling him than by sending him a copy of the contrast I
                    have here given.</p><p> I have the 4 vols of <ref target="people.html#BurnsRobert">Burns</ref><note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">The works of Robert
                            Burns; with an Account of his Life and a Criticism on his
                            Writings</title>, 4 vols. (Liverpool: printed by J. M’Creery for T.
                        Cadell and W. Davies, London; and W. Creech, Edinburgh, 1800).</note>
                    according to your order for which, Sir, and for all other favours I remain
                    your</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">Most Obedient Servant</salute><signed rend="right">Robert Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p><name><ref target="people.html#VaughanWilliam">Mr Vaughan</ref></name>, <placeName>Mincing Lane, London</placeName></p></postscript><closer><address><rs>Address:</rs><name><ref target="people.html#VaughanWilliam">Mr Vaughan</ref></name><placeName> / Dunster Court / Mincing Lane / Fenchurch Stt.</placeName></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>