<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.88</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 98–101;
                        published Hart, p. 27</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="88" type="letter"><head>88. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1802-05-30">30 May 1802</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 98–101;
                        published Hart, p. 27</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>London.</placeName></address><date when="1802-05-30">Sunday Evening May 30 1802</date></dateline><salute>Dear George</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> How often I have threatened to write to you in such a strain as
                    to admit of free observation, and to give you the characters of about fifty
                    persons whose names I have, and may hereafter have occasion to mention in my
                    letters; it would only be giving you necessary information. At other times I
                    have lookd out themes for a monthly exchange of sentiments between us conducted
                    with the freedom of friendship and a total exclusion of satire. All these self
                    promises have faild in consequence of that perpetual round of alack, exercise,
                    Bookselling, thinking, visiting, and composing, with which I have long been
                    surrounded.</p><p rend="indent1"> I thank you for your comical poem, and should have acknowledged
                    it before—I have just read to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref>
                    the ‘Star’s’ account of the Bull baiting in the House of Commons,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">On 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> May the
                            <title>Star</title> newspaper carried a report of the debate in the
                        House of Commons on bull-baiting. During that debate William Windham alluded
                        to Bloomfield as an instance of the dangers consequent upon the labouring
                        classes abandoning such traditional sports as bull and bear-baiting in
                        favour of literature.</note> and I here send you a paper containing such
                    extracts from different prints as may perhaps be entertaining to you; pray send
                    it to me again. It was long ago expected that some publick notice would be taken
                    of <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. Lofft’s</ref> reflections in the
                    prefatory part of the Farmer s Boy. The lot has fallen to <ref target="people.html#WindhamWilliam">Mr.W</ref> I think the poor people of
                    England have very little cause to thank him for his compliment on the score of
                    their capabilities and pursuits.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Monday
                        24 May 1802 saw the second reading of the Bill to prevent Bull-Baiting and
                        Bull-Running (see <title>Parliamentary Register</title>, 80 (1802), 485–95):
                        Windham (490) opposed the motion on the grounds that the indulgence of these
                        amusements was part of ‘the old English character’ which made the common
                        people ‘best fitted to resist the schemes of innovation’ that Methodists and
                        Jacobins were undertaking: it was ‘among the labouring and illiterate part
                        of the people that Jacobinical doctrines had made the smallest progress’.
                        Windham (491–92) ‘took occasion to quote a passage from the Memoirs of a
                        rural poet of considerable celebrity (Bloomfield, author of the Farmer’s
                        Boy, &amp;c. by a Gentleman of respectable literary talents, Capel
                        Lofft,) in which it is mentioned, that the Poet was in the habit of spending
                        his time in reading in his garret, or attending a debating society, which
                        the editor recommends as a much more worthy mode of employing himself, than
                        if he had been occupied with gambling, drinking, or fighting. Mr. W. paid
                        some very handsome compliments to the originality of many of the thoughts of
                        this Poet, to his natural simplicity and unaffected elegance of language. He
                        wished what he now said to be considered as an unexaggerated declaration of
                        his opinion of the merits of the poem; and he hoped it would be considered
                        as nothing improper when he added, that he wished this opinion, thus
                        publicly delivered, to be viewed as an advertisement of the merit of the
                        poem. But with this high opinion of the merits of the poet, he had doubts
                        how far it was proper to encourage ideas of literary profit or renown in
                        those who had been bred to a useful trade. In particular instances it might
                        not be prejudicial; but to inculcate such notions as those contained in the
                        passage of the memoirs to which he had referred, could tend only to a
                        mischievous purpose’.</note> We might as well be totally without minds, for
                    he seems to doubt the propriety of exerting them, or of making any <hi rend="ital">inward</hi> store of pleasure for ourselves. So much of this
                    speech is the most unadulterated aristocracy that I have ever seen. I cannot
                    help thinking what an opposition of sentiment would be expressd between <ref target="people.html#WindhamWilliam">Mr. W___</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyRobert">Mr. Southey</ref> both perhaps
                    extraordinary men; the latter all fire and zeal in the cause of information and
                    perfectability! All things are to be accomplished by teaching; passions that
                    have their foundation in Nature are to be rendered tractable and tame; <hi rend="ital">all</hi> are to be wonderfully wrought upon by instruction!
                    whereas thousands of us are absolutely incapable of being taught. some never
                    learn even to scrub a Room or to poke a fire: and with whom no new or improved
                    practice even in trifles can turn the bent of early and narrow impressions.
                    These would make wonderfull progress in their great work, the <hi rend="ital">Empire of Mind</hi>, as they call it. In general information I think there
                    is this great advantage. As God has given us all souls of some sort or other,
                    without any regard to wealth or station, general information in a humble degree,
                    a dispersion of total ignorance, is the way to let such souls as have the power,
                    emerge to observation, and perhaps to actual service to their country, but it
                    does not <hi rend="ital">create</hi> such souls. If all the natural talents of a
                    country are drawn into action, and if great talents be an ornament to the age in
                    which they appear, then the system of general instruction seems calculated to
                    produce in some measure that end; for if a heap of rough stones were ordered to
                    be polished, and workmen were employed for that purpose they would find some
                    porous, some brittle, some that would take a polish, and some on which labour
                    would be thrown away, and in short find, as Rowe says, that </p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> Unless souls, which differ like Human Faces,</l><l rend="indent4"> Were alike in all, &amp;c.— <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Rowe, <title>Tamerlane</title>, act 3, scene 2:
                            ‘differ like human faces’. The wording as Bloomfield gives it appears in
                            Edward Bysshe, <title>The Art of English Poetry</title>, vol. 2, 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edn. (London, 1724), p. 110.</note></l></lg><p>the polish would not be alike in all. The great Heap of Stones mentioned by <ref target="people.html#WindhamWilliam">Mr Windham</ref>, i.e., the <hi rend="ital">common people</hi> of his native country, are a rough set no
                    doubt, but I dislike the doctrine of keeping them in their dirt, for though it
                    holds good as to the preservation of potatoes, it would be no grateful
                    reflection to good minds to know that a man’s natural abilities had been
                    smother’d for want of being able to read and write. how can we consistently
                    praise the inestimable blessing of letters and not wish to extend it? Or why
                    should the great and the wealthy confine the probable production of intellectual
                    excellence to their own class, and exclude, by withholding the polish, all that
                    might amongst the poor by nature be intended to be Newtons and Lockes? I mean
                    only by what I have said about perfectibility to let you know that I deem it
                    wise, and deem it our duty to instruct, and to give every mind exercise, that it
                    may enjoy pleasure from it if capable; but that this doctrine of teaching, when
                    pushed to the strange expectation of the capability of the means (powerful as it
                    is,) to effect a change in the principals of nature, is wrong; for though I look
                    not on the Human Heart through the dark spectacles of Calvinism, I doubt we
                    shall always find innate covetousness and innate ambition, the parents of
                    crimes.— But I might write thus to the end of my life, and then leave somthing
                    unsaid.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#WindhamWilliam">Mr. W.’s</ref> argument as to Hunting
                    and Shooting has some truth in it; but they will not bear perhaps a close
                    comparison with Bull-baiting. and after all our pity for animals I must think
                    that when <ref target="people.html#SherdianRichard">Mr. Sheridan</ref> said that
                    ‘we do not learn lessons of good from animals when <hi rend="ital">forced</hi>
                    and <hi rend="ital">taught</hi> to be enemies to each other,’ that it does not
                    strictly apply to Bull Baiting, for, (though I never saw a Baiting) I can
                    believe that the Dog at least likes it, and seeks it; and as to the Fox Hound,
                    my Uncle kepd a puppy of the <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">D
                        of Grafton’s</ref>, who used to absent himself in the woods alone for a
                    whole day in pursuit of game, he was ordered to be confined that he might not
                    run the flesh off his bones.—And after all I doubt not but <ref target="people.html#SherdianRichard">Sir Richard</ref> and perhaps <ref target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Mr.Wilberforce</ref> too, have <hi rend="ital">travelled post</hi>, and caused more pain to two or four
                    generous animals subjected to <hi rend="ital">man’s</hi> tyrany, than ever a
                    Bull in England felt from <hi rend="ital">dogs</hi>. </p><p rend="indent1"> I feel much obliged to <ref target="people.html#WindhamWilliam">Mr Windham</ref> for so high an expression of approbation as to my self,
                    though perhaps here I may be allowd to say, that his doctrine and his
                    illustration are rather at variance. And realy I think it best to let those read
                    and think who find a pleasure in it.</p><p rend="indent1"> I had a shopmate once (<del rend="strikethrough">Will
                        Broders</del>) who, in this great city, was connected with Bull baiting and
                    its followers—that was his pleasure; but neither he nor <ref target="people.html#WindhamWilliam">Mr W.</ref> would ever make it mine! If
                    we Bloomfields apply <ref target="people.html#WindhamWilliam">Mr W.’s</ref>
                    advice to ourselves, we may say, where is the wisdom of saying that the little
                    sons of a little Taylor should amuse themselves with <hi rend="ital">athletic
                        exercises</hi>? If we happen to think a moral page a better object to admire
                    than the frizzled forehead of a bull, and like the ascending of a lark in
                    preference to the mounting of a bull-dog, what has <ref target="people.html#WindhamWilliam">Mr. W—</ref> to do with it?</p><p rend="indent1"> My dear little <hi rend="ital">Muse</hi>, come along!! and we’ll
                    mount up to Heaven; and when out of sight and hearing of the <hi rend="ital">athletic</hi> school, look down upon the spot, and call to mind the
                    littleness of the strong sinew and the Bully’s voice. The Grave will swallow
                    them and their deeds! and thou wilt not give them the most glorious crown of
                    mortal triumph; a name amongst the advocates of moral good, and the feelings
                    that teach us Charity!!—</p><p rend="indent1"> And now, after this flourish, I come down to <hi rend="ital">Terry Firma</hi> again, to speak a word of <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat’s</ref> new poem, ‘The Culprit’.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Nathaniel Bloomfield’s poem ‘The Culprit’
                        was published in his <title>An Essay on War, in Blank Verse; Honington
                            Green, a Ballad... and Other Poems</title> (London, 1803), pp. 43–59.
                        See the text <ref target="../HTML/culprit.html">here</ref>.</note> Though I
                    am not calld upon for my opinion I cannot resist the impulse that tells me to
                    declare my wonder at the surprising strength of mind evinced in this new and
                    hasty sketch of an interesting subject. The stanzas are some of them not quite
                    music, and this he will no doubt admit, I have been wiping my eyes over it, but
                    perhaps Brothers should not be Criticks on Brothers’ works, nor be trusted in
                    their plaudits.—</p><p rend="indent1"> I have just left ‘Little Davy’ at the Great House in
                        Piccadilly.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Presumably Bloomfield had
                        taken a copy of <title>The History of Little Davy’s New Hat</title> to
                        Carlton House, home of the Prince of Wales.</note> Yesterday brought me a
                        <hi rend="ital">very kind</hi> Letter from <ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston</ref>, mentioning that a <ref target="people.html#LangshawJohn">Mr
                        Langshaw</ref> of Lancaster had set my Winter Song,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Winter Song’ from <title>Rural Tales</title>, pp. 117–19.
                        Langshaw’s setting was published as <title>Dear boy, throw that icicle down:
                            Ballad with an Accompaniment for the Piano Forte or Harp</title>
                        (London, 1801).</note> and that a copy is sent to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref>.— Thus you see that Mr Guest
                    is not alone. By <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac’s</ref>
                    wishing so much to find a musical <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Lofft</ref> one would think that he is sensible of defects, or dubious of
                    trusting wholly to himself, and yet he argues that my shewing them to
                    professional men in constant habit of playing in concert, is not the right way
                    of proceeding. I wish to God I could find him one, but as I have now found it
                    too late to insert an advertisement in the poems, and have sung Rover
                    accompanied with a Violin and Violoncello, the latter by a practicioner in the
                    Bass, and they all agreed unanimously as to the merit of the tune, but as
                    unanimously agreed that imperfections and errors exist in the Bass of this Song,
                    and of Lucy, this must be proved and remedied before they can be printed, unless
                        <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref> would wish to
                    have them to stand untouch’d, which was more than I could or wishd to say to
                        <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. L</ref> as to The Farmer’s
                        Boy.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac’s musical settings of
                        Bloomfield’s ‘The Shepherd and his Dog Rover’ and ‘Lucy’ are not extant in
                        the British Library. It seems that of Isaac’s settings the one which saw
                        print was Isaac Bloomfield, <title>Rosy Hannah; a Favourite New Song The
                            Words Written by Robert Bloomfield, Author of ‘The Farmer’s Boy’, The
                            Music, Composed by his Brother Isaac Bloomfield</title> (London,
                        [?1801]). ‘Rosy Hannah’ was also set by another composer, James Hook:
                            <title>Rosy Hannah, A Much Admired Song, with an Accompaniment, for the
                            Harp or Pianoforte, Composed for Mr. Braham, by Mr. Hook (The Words from
                            Bloomfield’s Poems)</title> (London, [?1810]).</note> It is very certain
                    that I could have orderd them to be engraved <hi rend="ital">as they stand</hi>,
                    but would not <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref>
                    rather have this said <hi rend="ital">now</hi>, than after publication?? As I am
                    no Musician myself, these things said are disagreeable, because if I insist upon
                    it they <hi rend="ital">are not</hi> defective, it would do the cause hurt;
                    everybody persuades me to print them, and says that anyone in the habit of
                    composing will correct the Bass for us—I am still acting thus contrary to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac’s</ref> opinion; for I
                    have hopes of seeing <ref target="people.html#ShieldWilliam">Mr. Shield</ref> to
                    know from undoubted authority whither they are imperfect or not before anything
                    can reasonably be resolved on.</p><p rend="indent1"> I send the Critical Review for your inspection, and can say
                    allmost for a certainty that the article respecting myself is written by <ref target="people.html#SoutheyRobert">Mr Southy</ref>.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey’s article on Bloomfield’s poetry appeared in
                        the <title>Critical Review</title>, 35 (May 1802), 67–75. See the text <ref target="../HTML/CriticalReview.html">here</ref>.</note> Send it back to
                    me.— But if you can find that the paper containing the statements of <ref target="people.html#WindhamWilliam">Mr. W.’s</ref> speech would be wellcome
                    at <ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston</ref>, so be it; and then send it
                    back next Month. </p><p rend="indent1"> I did not see the <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">Duke</ref> to day, but expect a letter very shortly. </p><p rend="indent1"> Excuse me to <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my
                        Mother</ref>, and remember us to your wife and children.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Yours,</salute><signed rend="right">Robert Bloomfield.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>