<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.242</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        269–70</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="242" type="letter"><head>242. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1809-09-14">14 September 1809</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        269–70</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><date when="1809-09-14">Thursday Noon, Sept 14. 1809</date></dateline><salute>My Dear Girl</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your bundle of letters and the egg came safe of Tuesday night and
                    was most particularly wellcome, I enjoyd the evening exceedingly and thank’d
                    you. Remember that the road leading down from the Heath field towards <ref target="places.html#Sapiston">Sapiston</ref> was my favorite boyish walk and
                    makes a conspicuous figure in the Farmer’s Boy. You had a grove with long green
                    walks or ridings on your left, and there <hi rend="ital">was</hi> a grove on
                    your right, I suppose now down.—It was there I heard the morning song of the
                    birds and have often seen the Rabbit, the Pheasant, and all the tennants of the
                    woods in there glory, and I was in mine. You mentioned in your first that you
                    walkd with <ref target="people.html#GloverJohn">Mr Glover</ref> the Heath and
                    returnd down to <ref target="places.html#Sapiston">Sapiston</ref>, having the
                    park— passing on your right. I think you must then have past over the upper part
                    of Mr Farrers Back—, as it reaches from nearly the back of his house to that
                    lane which has on the right hand as you return’d, what is calld park-grove.—I
                    really doubt whether your Swans have not deciev’d you. I never saw Swans in that
                    Brook in my life, and cannot imagine to whom they could belong. I think they
                    were Geese and you will say that I suppose you a Goose for not knowing the
                    difference, but I would rather hear that you make all the <hi rend="ital">Suffolk Geese Swans</hi> than that you find them all dab-chicks. We learn
                    from <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft’s</ref> note that <ref target="people.html#LofftSarah">Mrs L</ref>, and Nancy are returnd, and I
                    therefore hope that you will go there perhaps before you write again. I think
                    you would like to see old Thetford, and hope you will make a point of going up
                    the ‘Danish mounds of partial green’.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield quotes line 41 of his poem ‘Barnham Water’ from <title>Wild
                            Flowers</title> (p. 98). See <ref target="../images/image34.html">here</ref> for their depiction in Brayley.</note> I wish
                    particularly that you would let us have a letter every Friday in future, and I
                    shall look out for it accordingly. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">Your Uncle George</ref> in a note with the parcel said that ‘the woman of
                    the house where she resides is a <hi rend="ital">Rum one</hi>, loves the Bottle,
                    and is afflicted with the <hi rend="ital">meagrims</hi>.’ So you must be on your
                    guard and not mind every trifle that occurs. I suppose young George will be home
                    to London by the time you get this. Dont you really believe that Fakenham Wood
                    is larger than ours at Hornsey? I wish Jonas may please himself with a tune to
                    my Song, and that you may be able to sing it at <ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston</ref>. When does <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref> Fair begin? try to inform us
                    in your next. Our Chickens grow surprizingly and I have made a revolution as to
                    their appartments which has render’d them dry and handier to feed, I have taken
                    away the whole of the large Coop and both the small ones, and built them one
                    over the other on each side of the wash-house door, and cover’d with laths the
                    duck-yard from end to end for the Hens, so they have more room as well as being
                    shelterd. The whole appears now something in this way. [Drawing of hen house on
                    the page with text of the letter incorporated around it]</p><p rend="indent1"> Do if possible learn what is expected for the Dish and pay for
                    it. The picture I should like home if they seem willing to part with it. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlotteAunt">Your Aunt Charlotte</ref> and
                    Nurse, and <ref cRef="people.html#BloomfieldElizabeth1789 ">Cousin Betsy</ref>
                    had tea with us on Tuesday, they are all well. Old Robbin Nair was calld ‘old
                    Robbin’ at least thirty years ago. He was once a Soldier and served in the West
                    Indies. If John Nash is living he is a very civil old man, and was one of the
                    harvest-men when I was a boy, you would like to talk with him, and <hi rend="ital">he</hi> would like it. Dont you now see the great pleasure and
                    advantage of being able to draw, (I don’t mean you to look at my specimen) for
                    if you could as expiditiously as <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerMary">Mrs
                        Baker</ref> pop all the Barns and Stables in your pocket what a prize it
                    would be to last during the winter evenings! I wish you to give us a hint as to
                    what <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacNephew">young Isaac</ref> is about,
                    and where he is.—</p><p rend="indent1"> And now for more home news. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryDaughter">Mary</ref> of course cannot
                    write untill I send a parcell which I will do next time in reply to yours which
                    I expect on tomorrow week. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldRobertHenry">Robert</ref> talks without ceasing. I have got a load of good manure into
                    the Garden, perhaps Mr G will wonder at the price which is Twelve Shillings.
                    Mary Binley when she heard that we had a parcell, and that you had not written
                    to her replied ‘you mind and tell your Father to blow her up’. I am sorry to say
                    that he is not at all cured, he roil’d me last night, that I was very hard set
                    to keep quiet with him, Another dream! and a kind of percevering hopes that I
                    know not what to do with. I know your present determination, and whenever you
                    return I will stick by you like a Leech, but I think it probable that before
                    that time I shall have a talk with him which will be very unsavory to us both.
                    For myself I have had some horrid nights, and am this morning very indifferent
                    indeed. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">Your Mother</ref> is
                    midling, and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryDaughter">Mary</ref> is
                    chearful and willing. Tomorrow is <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles’s</ref> birthday and they all think of you by turns. If you would
                    like a bit of domestic information, a picture of matrimony, I have to inform you
                    that our Neighbour behind the wainscot has discovered that his wife has been
                    noodling him, and running him in debt, and the consequence is, that she is out
                    of his house, and he has advertized that he will pay no debts that she may
                    contract. I have room left to wish you every blessing that belongs to affection
                    and truth, and Am</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Once more your Affectionate Father</salute><signed rend="right">Rob Bloomfield </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>