<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.389</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Remains, II,
                        pp. 198–203</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="389" type="letter"><head>389. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George Bloomfield</ref> to
                        <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Joseph Weston</ref>, <date when="1824-06-09">9 June 1824</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote"><title>Remains</title>, II,
                        pp. 198–203</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury St. Edmunds</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1824-06-09">June 9, 1824</date></dateline><salute>Sir,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I beg leave to say I received your letter, dated <ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref>, June 5th. The magazine man
                    mentioned by my brother Robert, was <ref target="people.html#BentWilliam">Mr. W.
                        Bent</ref>, successor to S. A. Cumberlege, at the Kings Arms,
                    Paternoster-row, London; but who was the editor of the magazine, I am ignorant.
                        <ref target="people.html#BentWilliam">Mr. Bent</ref> was the publisher. His
                    was the Universal Magazine; I read it more than twenty years. <ref target="people.html#BentWilliam">Mr. Bent</ref> kept the MS. a week or two,
                    and sent it back to my brother by a grave book-faced looking man, who said it
                    did not suit <ref target="people.html#BentWilliam">Mr. Bent</ref>, &amp;c.
                    My brother offered it to <ref target="people.html#LaneWilliam">Mr. Lane</ref>,
                    the great wholesale novel manufacturer. He returned it almost immediately with a
                    note of two lines, to say, it was not in his line. My brother afterwards left it
                    with <ref target="people.html#DillyCharles">Mr. Dilly</ref> in the Poultry. <ref target="people.html#DillyCharles">Mr. Dilly</ref>, when my brother
                    afterwards called for the MS. said it wanted revisal, &amp;c. My brother
                    then sent it to me here, at <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref>,
                    and it was on my own petition, without my brother’s knowledge, that <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. Lofft</ref> took it under his patronage.
                    But I have lived near seventy years in the world, and have seen enough of
                    mankind to know, that the wretch who has once vouched a falsehood, will invent
                    fifty more to make it good. Still, however, <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. Lofft</ref>* is yet living, and will certainly prove he had no letter
                    of recommendation. But then the calumniator may still say he gave my brother
                    such letter. Should he do this, though I would stake my salvation on its being
                    false, how could it be disproved? The coward staid till the death of poor Robert
                    ere he dared make his attack. O, sir, if you could conceive how it hurt my mind
                    when I read the statement in the monthly Magazine for September 1823! ...</p><p rend="indent1"> The tale is told as if my brother’s misfortunes arose from his
                    talents—as if his success had done no good—<ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesBury">C. Bloomfield Esq.</ref> did not
                    know there was such a man as me in existence till Robert’s success brought me to
                    his knowledge on Robert’s account—for whose sake he, <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesBury">Mr. B.</ref>, took me and mine
                    into his protection. His great benevolence and charity have conferred favours on
                    me it would fill a sheet to detail, and at this moment his bounty nearly feeds
                    me; but for Robert’s success I should have been unknown to this gentleman and,
                    consequently, must have wanted bread, and have been in a workhouse. And poor
                        <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">brother Isaac</ref>, who
                    was in his youth a gay lad, and on a footing with the young farmers of the
                    village must, when weighed down with a family of nine children, have trembled at
                    a vestry to those he once deemed his equals. But Robert took him up, and was his
                    true friend—took him and his family to London, and placed them in a shop. The
                    scheme failed—he sent them down again and gave them the rent in the cottage for
                    twenty years, clothed the boys, &amp;c. The rent alone must have been sixty
                    pounds. My brother <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref>, I doubt
                    not, had often his assistance. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref>
                    had thirteen or fourteen children. All the comforts myself and brothers enjoyed,
                    evidently sprung from the success of Robert. This sneaking assassin without a
                    name, who wrote the article for the Monthly Magazine for September, 1823, keeps
                    all this positive good—these real blessings out of sight— and tells us how happy
                    Robert might have been had he continued to be a journeyman shoemaker. Even here
                    he acts with cruel duplicity. He does not tell his readers that Robert was for
                    the last twenty years seldom capable of bodily labour. He leaves the reader to
                    think he was a man capable of hard exertion, whereas, the reverse was the case;
                    the suppression of truth is, in this case, as much a calumny as the fabrication
                    of falsehood.</p><p rend="indent1"> While his resources lasted, Robert was always ready to <hi rend="ital">prove by his conduct</hi> that he acted to others as he would
                    have wished them to have acted towards him had <hi rend="ital">they</hi> been in
                    his place and he in theirs. Here it may be objected, how came he to get into
                    debt? He certainly, while his income was good, had not that cold, prudential
                    caution which men of the world possess. I am willing to admit with that
                    calumniator, his ambition was disappointed. It would have been his ambition to
                    keep <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac’s</ref> family from
                    the parish; to keep his brother <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> from trouble, &amp;c. &amp;c. This he could not do. But
                    to read the article in the Monthly Magazine, the reader might be led to think
                    that he was ambitious of aping the man of ‘<hi rend="ital">pecuniary
                        independence, &amp;c.</hi>’</p><p rend="indent1"> The only luxury I ever knew him indulge in, was a Cockney garden;
                    and here he was more to be pitied than blamed. He staid some time after he came
                    into money in his old lodgings in <ref target="places.html#MulberryCourt">Mulberry-court</ref>, till he was literally hunted out of it. Persons of
                    consideration, who came in great numbers to see him, complained of the place
                    being disagreeable. <ref target="people.html#GedgePeter">Mr Peter Gedge</ref>,
                    the printer, called on him—gave him half-a-guinea, and advised him to get into a
                    better situation. Robert then hired a respectable lodging in Short-street,
                    Moorfields. His landlord put the key under the door in the night, and left
                    Robert to pay £9 rent to the proprietor of the house, or lose his goods. He then
                    hired a very small house near the <ref target="places.html#Shepherd">Shepherd
                        and Shepherdess</ref>, in the City Road. Here he had, what was certainly, a
                    large Cockney garden! When his income became reduced, he retired to <ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref>, where his rent, &amp;c.
                    was comparatively small. He never kept a servant, or a horse, as many a one
                    would have done. His whole conduct in prosperity proved his fraternal love, his
                    filial affection, and his readiness to assist to the utmost of his power those
                    who applied to him. Those who knew him best will wonder how a man so inoffensive
                    and unobtrusive can be charged with ambition. But the writer of the article
                    above alluded to, says by <hi rend="ital">inference</hi>, that the <hi rend="ital">poor</hi> man of talents should not dare to enter the fields of
                    literature, but leave them to the men of ‘<hi rend="ital">pecuniary
                        independence</hi>.’</p><p rend="indent1"> I hope, sir, you will not tire in the glorious work you have
                    begun. You cannot please every body—you cannot produce a perfect book:</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> Whoever thinks a faultless piece to see,</l><l rend="indent4"> Thinks what ne’er was, nor is, nor e’er shall be.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander Pope, ‘An Essay on Criticism’,
                            part ii, lines 53–54.</note></l></lg><p>But to endeavour to rescue the character of him who is not here to defend
                    himself, is, I repeat it, a glorious task, and all the wise and good will
                    applaud the design, whatever impediments the interested and the wicked, may
                    throw in your way.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">Your humble servant</salute><signed rend="right">G. Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p>* The account of this gentleman’s death had not <hi rend="ital">then</hi>
                            arrived.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">This note is Joseph
                            Weston’s. Lofft died abroad on 26 May 1824.</note></p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><rs>Address: </rs><name>To <ref cRef="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr. Weston</ref>,</name> / <placeName><ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref></placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>