<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.301</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        362–63</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="301" type="letter"><head>301. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1816-03-18">18 March 1816</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        362–63</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>Shefford.</placeName></address><date when="1816-03-18">March 18. 1816</date></dateline><salute>My Dear life</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Yours gave me and all of us great pleasure. I am rejoiced to find
                    that you are coming home, even for a little while. We will make the most of it I
                    warrant you, you shall go to bed every night with a sore throat from talking,
                    and get up in the morning and dread your days work: but how, my Soul will you
                    get home? how stands your cash? you cannot have enough surely to get home either
                    way? And it so happens that I have no supply for you, I have only a £60 Bill,
                    not due till the middle of the summer! unfortunate. to get ready money <hi rend="indent1">now</hi> seems as impossible as to dig Diamonds. But I advise
                    you—do not start,—to state your case, or rather mine, to <ref target="people.html#LockwoodEdward">Mrs Lockwood</ref>, or <ref target="people.html#BirdIsaac">Mr Bird</ref>. If either will furnish you
                    with two or three pounds I will pay them with the first money that comes into my
                    hands. If you have enough to get to London with, borrow half a guinea there to
                    come down to <ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref> with, for you may
                    ride to <ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref> for 8s outside, as we
                    have extra coaches, and a grand opposition. You will see by this that I have no
                    hope of meeting you at Cambridge. There is a Coach lately established which runs
                    from Cambridge to Oxford, and passes through Bedford &amp;c, but even with
                    this you must, I apprehend, sleep a night at Cambridge and be merely set down at
                    Bedford where somebody must meet you. You know how gladly I would meet you if I
                    could, but besides the complaint in my pocket, I have others which I must in
                    justice inform you of.</p><p rend="indent1"> For some weeks past I had been troubled with an incessant
                    sickness at the stomach which would neither take or keep food, and soon after
                    came on an inflammation in the right leg, which completely lamed me for many
                    days. I applied to Gaye yesterday week, and he has cured the leg by consistent
                    soaking of rags dipt in a cold Lotion, it is now perfect again, only braced with
                    a 4 yard bandage, or roller. I have likewise taken some internal medicine which
                    makes me eat heartily, and I expect to be quite well very soon; yet you will see
                    that to ride or to walk too much just now would be imprudent, to say the least
                    of it. Let this likewise stand for my excuse for not visiting <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref>; but how shall I sufficiently
                    thank <ref target="people.html#LockwoodEdward">Mr &amp; Mrs Lockwood</ref>
                    for their kind and lasting friendship to you and myself? I hope <ref target="people.html#LockwoodEdward">Mr Lockwood</ref> is better than when
                    you wrote last. I have got into a thick correspondence occasiond by the Suffolk
                    Gents endeavouring to do me good,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">For
                        these efforts, see Letter 303.</note> but it is impossible to give you
                    knowledge of the matter by letter. Come and talk with me, <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Weston</ref> is gone, [illegible deleted
                    words]—Take notice, I expect a letter on <hi rend="ital">Sunday morning</hi> to
                    say when you start for London, and all about it, be precise, but not
                    precipitate, in all you do; and write to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Uncle Nat</ref> that they may meet you at the Bull, They live close by, and
                    go three nights as well as one, if you cannot appoint a <hi rend="indent1">certain</hi> day. I shall write to London tomorrow and will give them a
                    hint that you are coming &amp;c. Ride inside if you can borrow or steal the
                    money, for March is not to be trusted a moment.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Health and happiness to you now and for ever.</salute><signed rend="right">Your Old Dad.</signed></closer><postscript><p>How is <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldKitty">Aunt Kate</ref>?</p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><rs>Address: </rs><name><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Miss Bloomfield</ref>,</name> / <name><ref target="people.html#LockwoodEdward">Ed Lockwood</ref>’s Esq,</name> / <placeName>nr Angel Hill, / <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref>, / Sfk</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>