<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.77</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, f. 85; extract
                        published in Hart, p. 23</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="77" type="letter"><head>77. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1802-01-31">31 January 1802</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, f. 85; extract
                        published in Hart, p. 23</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>London</placeName></address><date when="1802-01-31">Jan. 31 1802</date></dateline><salute>Dear George,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have made two Memorandoms as follows, and hope you will oblidge
                    me by being punctual</p><p rend="indent1"> 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Send one whole or half a real Suffolk
                    cheese one of the poorest you can get, ‘a 9 meal cheese’ the worse it is the
                    better—(I hope I can write Irish to you and be understood.)—</p><p rend="indent1"> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Send me if possible my last Northamton
                    Journal, containing the story of Barret<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">This journal is not extant; to judge by Bloomfield’s many enquiries of
                        different relatives, he never recovered it.</note> and much other nonsence.
                    I mention it to <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my Mother</ref> and to
                        <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldKitty">Kitty</ref>.—</p><p>Thank my Aunt Bird for the Hare, and say that her son call’d here half an hour
                    ago. <ref target="people.html#BuchanLord">Lord Buchan</ref> is an eccentric
                    character; you will find so by his letter; he has nearly lost the sight of one
                    eye. There is a kind of benevolent wildness in his manner; and an amazing
                    vivacity in his conversation. You will find a copy of my letter to him and his
                    reply. <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> will forward them to
                    you again, you may keep the copy of <ref target="people.html#BuchanLord">Lord
                        B.’s</ref> letter if you like, but send me the copy of mine to him. I must
                    not lose it.— Did I say that I had a letter from Mr Smith your neighbour, and
                    one from the Rev Mr. Mills? The latter gentleman thanks <hi rend="ital">me</hi>
                    for a copy of the poems which he says I sent him. You can give me a light here,
                    as to how far you used my name, that in case of my replying I may run into no
                    inconsistancy.—I once sent you a Boy, who has turn’d out exreemly well. I send
                    you another somthing younger, and wish you to deal thus with him.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The first Boy is, of course, <title>The Farmer’s
                            Boy</title>. The second, which Bloomfield was now sending, was
                            <title>The History of Little Davy’s New Hat</title>.</note> keep him
                    amongst you till the 9th of March; I am allmost afraid to let him pass through
                        <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L’s</ref> hands, but send it to him*
                    with the request that he would forward it to <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my Mother</ref>, who, as well as <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldKitty">Kitty</ref> may read it in a month, and
                    then let me have it again, don’t make mention of it except in your letters to
                    me, for I know not yet if I have to dread ridicule or hope for praise.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. Lofft’s</ref> last says, ‘Mr
                        Dingle<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Dingle was a Bury St Edmunds
                        bookseller.</note> has sold a hundred of the Tales, and sent for another
                    hundred in doubt whether he shall get them before the impression is all sold
                    off’—I am not sure that they sell so fast as that, but they sell quite fast
                    enough. I yesterday read your letter to Mrs. Philips, I was there, as you will
                    see by <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my Mother’s</ref> letter. The
                    good Old Auditor of the Excise call’d on me, but I was out. I waited on him and
                    made a good day’s work, altogether. The <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">Duke</ref> will be in town in a
                    week or ten days. You may [words deleted in cutting of letter]</p><p>[written in another hand]: ‘this letter was cut and Lines printed from it in the
                        <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref> post, written by <ref target="people.html#BuchanLord">Lord Buchan</ref> Blacklock’.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The part of the letter cut off was printed in
                        the <title>Bury and Norwich Post</title>, 10 February 1802. It consists of a
                        poem by Buchan in tribute to Bloomfield: <lb/><p rend="indent2">THE EARL OF
                            BUCHAN TO R. BLOOMFIELD</p><p rend="indent3">AUTHOR OF THE FARMER’S BOY,</p><p rend="indent2">On reciting his Rural Tales at his house in the
                            Adelphi.</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent2"> BLOOMFIELD I come from Modan’s holy spring*</l><l rend="indent2"> To hear thee speak, to hear thee sweetly sing!</l><l rend="indent2"> Sing on thou Farmer’s Boy, and soothe my soul,</l><l rend="indent2"> I’ll waft thy rural lays from pole to pole.</l><l rend="indent2"> Sing poet, sing the joys of rural life,</l><l rend="indent2"> Britain shall now renounce her wonted strife.</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘E’en all the joys that victory brings,</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Her bellowing guns and flaming pride;</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Cold momentary comfort flings</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Around where weeping friends reside.’**</l><l rend="indent2"> Sing poet, sing thy ‘ancient wedded pair’;</l><l rend="indent2"> Let tears through smiles, and every joy be there.</l><l rend="indent2"> BLOOMFIELD, before thy days, when mine were green</l><l rend="indent2"> On Avon’s bank poor CHATTERTON was seen;</l><l rend="indent2"> I saw him too, and his hard fate deplor’d,</l><l rend="indent2"> And dropt a tear, though then a glitt’ring Lord!</l><l rend="indent2"> BLACKLOCK I lov’d, and his lov’d praise remains</l><l rend="indent2"> To soothe my fancy in his dying strains***.</l><l rend="indent2"> BEATTIE was mine, and wou’d to heav’n his days</l><l rend="indent2"> Were cloath’d in light, and like his charming
                                lays****!</l><l rend="indent2"> Praise from my lips, ’twas BURNS’delight to
                                boast—</l><l rend="indent2"> MINE was the glory—HE deserved it most.</l><l rend="indent2"> These are the joys of my declining years,</l><l rend="indent2"> I hear the stormy stream without its fears*****!</l></lg><p rend="indent3">*Fountain of St. Modan, at Dryburg.</p><p rend="indent3">**From Bloomfield’s 'French mariner’ inserted in last
                            week’s paper.</p><p rend="indent3">***Alluding to some lines which he wrote to Lord Buchan on
                            his death-bed.</p><p rend="indent3">****Beattie is blind, and lives at Edinburgh.</p><p rend="indent3">*****‘Strepitumque Acherontis avari.’</p> The <title>Bury
                            and Norwich Post</title> had earlier, on 3 February, printed ‘The French
                        Mariner’ from <title>Rural Tales</title>, pp. 78–82.</note></p><p>*You will buy <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my Mother</ref> a bottle
                    of Rum or Brandy and send her the change of the Note which you will send in her
                    Letter —I don’t mean you to send Davy to <ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston</ref> now. A week hence will be time enough. </p></div></body></text></TEI>