<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.305</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 366–68,
                        quoted briefly by Phillips</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="305" type="letter"><head>305. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1816-12-27">27 December 1816</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 366–68,
                        quoted briefly by Phillips</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1816-12-27">Dec 27. 1816</date></dateline><salute>My Dear Girl</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> When your parcel came to hand we had just devourd a couple of
                    fine Fowles sent us from <ref target="places.html#StanfordBury">Stanford
                        Bury</ref>, and I rejoiced to hear of your health and peace, and the same of
                    your friends.</p><p rend="indent1"> As you want news I will now transcribe from a slate where I have
                    kept memorandums, such occurrences as this poor L—y dead place affords.</p><p rend="indent1"> Mr Long the shopkeeper has faild long ago, his stock and goods
                    sold, himself, I believe, in London, his family dispersed. You know that <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr Weston’s</ref> Estate was knockd down
                    to Mr Impey who prov’d incapable of holding it; consequently it has been
                    transfer’d to his Wife’s Brother, a Mr Demer of Hitchin, a boasting hollow lump
                    of worldly cunning. This is my landlord. At the time our repairs were going on
                    Mr Impey left his former house in the street by Taylor’s and came next door to
                    us, which place was vacant by the removal of Wells, this indeed on the part of
                    Wells was rather worse than a removal, for his <hi rend="ital">real</hi> wife
                    came here from Brighton and stird him up, till he sold all his goods to Impey
                    and I believe decamp’d for a while but they are still here in town. Having Impey
                    close by us we were for some weeks rejoiced by the sounds of Old Coppers and
                    Sauspans and became sure of a <hi rend="ital">comfortable</hi> situation, when
                    all at once Mr Impey became insolvent, and about three weeks ago his sale
                    comprehended his stock and goods! He now makes a workshop of Brigg’s thatch’d
                    shed where the tailors used to work.—</p><p rend="indent1"> I learn that Mr Ibbs of this town has taken Mr Palmers Farm at
                    Rowney—Nightengall has given up his Farm to a Mr Inskip.—Polehanger is in the
                    occupation of a Mr Kirk, or Kirkby—Tom Hoffer and young Steven have had a short
                    lodgement at Bedford Jail for a row with Mr Layman at the Bonfire—I am sorry to
                    say that the Frocks you sent for <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlotteShot">Charlotte</ref> are too short
                    for the great <hi rend="ital">morther</hi>: as she has grown an inch and half
                    since last April, and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref> is an inch and half taller than she. They will yet come into
                    use and I thank you for your thoughtfulness and affection in sending them. I am
                    sorry to inform you that we have had a great deal of Fever around us lately, but
                    not very fatal, though of the Typhus kind I believe. Mr Gay’s children were
                    nearly all bad with it, and a young woman formerly their servant, but now
                    married and living at Brigg’s caught it being their nurse. They are all out of
                    danger.—Our old washwoman Saunders and three children have gone through this
                    visitation successfully, and being so near us we have used some caution.— Last
                    week the other washer Mother Seeny, or Maddie, or Hoffman, or what not, had the
                    misfortune to burn to a cinder <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">your
                        mothers</ref> best Gown, together with the chair on which it was left <hi rend="ital">just for a minute</hi> of course; a few minutes more would have
                    burnt all the goods she has and perhaps the primises! We had lately a harmless
                    Flood, so that if you put together <hi rend="ital">Flood, Fire, Fever</hi> and
                        <hi rend="ital">Bankruptcy</hi> you will have at least some of the plagues
                    of life.—I hear of no <hi rend="ital">Widdings</hi> and therefore must proceed
                    to other subjects.—</p><p rend="indent1"> The Subscription—aye, the subscription, goes on very much like a
                    Donkey in a dirty lane with his legs tired—From <ref target="people.html#SharpCatherine">Miss Sharp</ref> I only hear of
                    disappointments as to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldRobertHenry">Robert</ref>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Catherine Sharp had
                        offered to write to the Trustees of Lord Crewe's charity at Bamborough
                        Castle on behalf of Bloomfield's son (see Letter 303).</note> and that <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">Lloyd Baker</ref> is busy with his
                    new estate at Hardwick house near Gloucester, and that his neighbour <ref target="people.html#CooperRobert">Mr Cooper</ref> has spent a <hi rend="ital">great</hi> sum of money in an unsuccessful attempt in the folly
                    of electioneering, and means to try again!!! <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> says he has no success from
                    his friend <ref target="people.html#PolwheleRichard">Mr Palwheel</ref> in
                    Cornwall, nor no reply from the Lord Mayor—There is a Miss Cropley of Euston Stt
                    Euston Square who has opend a correspondence with me and who most <hi rend="ital">womanfully</hi> takes the part of Little Davy<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">As he formerly did by using the name ‘Giles’,
                        Bloomfield here calls himself by the name of one of his fictional
                        characters.</note> and offers a direct application to ‘The Literary Fund’ on
                    my behalf, this is not concluded on—My old friend <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Mr Hill</ref> of Queenhythe has written from
                    Paris to have his name down for ten pounds to the subscription and <ref target="people.html#WilliamsonEdmund">Mr Williamson</ref> of <ref target="places.html#Campton">Campton</ref> has sent up to Messrs Rogers,
                    five pounds from some gentlemen whom he would not name—I learn from Wass the
                    younger that there is now due to me a small and final Dividend of 9d in the
                    pound! These jolly old Ninepences will amount to about £14.—</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#OsborneGeorge">Sir George</ref> has just sent Mr Coats
                    to ask when it will be <hi rend="ital">convenient</hi> for me to accept a Dozn.
                    of Port.—The post hour creeps on—I agree almost entirely with <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr Weston</ref> as to the Examiner; if
                    they do not take care it will die like our old Mirror, expiring in a [word cut
                    off] pah, pah.’—I will particularly attend to Mr Wes[word cut off] request, and
                    in due time by writing take down the hump on his back as easily as I would take
                    off my night-cap.—I see no Reviews, no papers, but <hi rend="ital">Hunt</hi> and
                    the mild, moderate <hi rend="ital">Cobbett</hi><note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Hunt brothers’ <title>Examiner</title> and William
                        Cobbett’s <title>Political Register</title> led radical opposition to the
                        government during the crisis year of 1816.</note> —I feel lost—</p><p rend="indent1"> We are all well—and that is a great thing to say, for which I
                    always feel thankfull, as to all the rest it will rub out when it is dry.—I have
                    no Rhumatism////This moment Mrs Flint calld to say that she will send a parcel
                    to Twickenham on Monday or Tuesday—</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Best love to Mr &amp; Miss <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Weston</ref> now and for ever</salute><salute rend="indent1"> You want none of my love of course, and so I only
                        say</salute><signed rend="right">Dad</signed></closer><postscript><p><label>PS</label> We had thoughts of sending Poor Toms Book of plays, perhaps
                        it may not come in Mrs Flints parcel, but we will take care of it.</p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><rs>Address: </rs><name><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Miss Bloomfield</ref>,</name> / <name><ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr Weston’s</ref></name>, / <placeName>Draper, / Twickenham, / Middx.</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>