<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.290</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        340–43</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="290" type="letter"><head>290. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1814-06-14">14 June 1814</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        340–43</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right">Continuation of the trip to Dover. <date when="1814-06-14">June 14. 1814</date></dateline><salute>My dear Hannah</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> My last had brought you to Mrs Podevin’s, where we slept as sound
                    as we could amidst a noisy mix’d company of all Nations and the next morning
                    (Friday) <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Weston</ref> was up first as you
                    might expect, and went down to the pier to take a first view of Old Ocean. Foggs
                    still obscured the Cliffs and rolld from the Sea in clouds, encircling the tops
                    of the heights and Castle. After a good breakfast we assended the Castle hill,
                    and found that we could gain admission without any pass but a three Shilling
                    piece. This is a noble eminence, and compleatly fortified. A number of 32
                    pounders are placed on the lower extremities of the rocks over the sea, The
                    weight of one of these Guns is 55 hundred pounds and a Quarter, and some odd
                    pounds, about the weight of 50 such men as myself. The famous long brass Gun
                    ridiculously calld ‘Queen Ann’s pocket-piece,’ was given to Elizabeth by the
                    States of Scotland, it is 24 feet, 2 inches in length, and carries only a twelve
                    pound ball. It has not been fired for many years, being much decayd by age and
                    the weather. The highest ground within the walls of the castle is ocupied by a
                    very old building originally erected or strengthend at least by the Romans. We
                    took pains to knock out of the wall a portion of Roman Brick, which is no other
                    way curious than being at least 17 Centuries old. The principal building is a
                    large square Tower, or Keep, which is used as an immence pergola of powder and
                    ball. By far the most remarkable sight in the fortress is the late works
                    performed by that little enterprizing adventurous animal calld Man. A brick
                    Archway calld a ‘Casemate,’ decends in a sloping direction into the body of the
                    chalk hill, about wide enough to enable 4 men to walk a breast, after
                    penitrating a long way almost in the dark you find opens up on either hand being
                    immence Arched Rooms each capable of lodging and accomodating from 2 to 3
                    hundred men. The light admitted comes from perpendicular air holes, or wells’
                    decending from the top of the cliffs, and still more from a Gallery opening
                    immediately over the beach, where you look down upon the white waves, and up to
                    the face of the chalk which hangs overhead. Most of the Soldier here were of
                    that cowardly class of legal murderers calld sharpshooters, whose trade I cannot
                    like in spite of their use and importance.</p><p rend="indent1"> In the Afternoon we again climb’d to the same situation, when a
                    Frigate came into the Harbour and fired several guns to announce the arrival of
                    Lord Castlereah.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Lord Castlereagh:
                        Foreign Secretary, returning from Paris after attending talks with other
                        leaders of the victorious Grand Coalition which had forced Napoleon’s
                        abdication and exile in May.</note> These guns were answerd by the 24
                    pounders place’d on what they term the ‘Drop fort,’ which covers the round top
                    of a chalk hill where once stood ‘the Devel’s drop,’ as <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Unkle Nat</ref> can tell you. We had here
                    a fine opportunity of remarking what I had often before noticed, the progress of
                    sound. When the Frigate fired we saw the flash, and a column of smoke sent
                    rapidly forward over the waves, and after about seven pulsations came the
                    report, which thunderd along <del rend="strikethrough">amidst the</del> the
                    cliffs till echo seemd tired of mocking. The 24 pounder from the Battery gave a
                    still more powerful repercussion,—</p><p rend="indent1"> Here I percieve I have something to fetch up in my narative. Near
                    Gad’s Hill, so famous for the exploits of Sir John Fallstaff we met a party of
                    Cossacks, about ten or eleven, they made a most strange appearance. Their Horses
                    were good, but they appear’d small, the whole group of men had the appearance of
                    deep Melancholly, or at least of solid unalterable patience stampd upon their
                    countenances, till the passengers on our Coach, and others, chiefly French
                    prisoners, gave them a hearty cheer, at which time they answerd with a bow and a
                    smile,—They wore long or bushy beards, with cloaks of bearskin reaching half way
                    over the horse, And my companion remarkd that ‘their eyes lookd like two bullets
                    dropd into a bunch of Moss’ This you well know is in his usual stile, for never
                    surely was a man better calculated to fight his own way through a brickdust
                    world, or to make more pertinent remarks.</p><p rend="indent1"> Saturday morning At Dover. The sea breeze made me hungry, and
                    toil made me sleep. This morning we pland out for an expidition to Shakespears
                    Cliff, and accordingly steerd in that direction, but unfortunately went by the
                    Sea beach, and after having spent some thousands of unnessisary steps enquired
                    of a Soldier whither we could get up the cliffs in any way before we reach’d our
                    intended spot. The Soldier answer’d yes, we might get up the cliff about a
                    Quarter of a mile further on. This information was correct as far as it went,
                    but the path upwards was extreemly steep, but did not appear dangerous at first
                    setting out. Having climbd about 3 parts up, we found the difficulty encrease,
                    and finding a firm foothold and handhold by means of strong tuffts of coarse
                    grass, I was force’d to rest, when <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr
                        Weston</ref> was about 20 yards above me declaring that we could get no
                    further. He laughd at my terror, placed as I was beneath him, and dreading much
                    more the task of decending again than hazarding my neck by climbing higher, for
                    to decend seem’d impossible without extreem hazard of sliping, and perhaps
                    rolling down to the beach. After taking breath, and blaming our selves for the
                    unthinking attempt, <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Weston</ref> again
                    asscended but for the life of me I dare not look at him in his attempt. He
                    gain’d a flat ledge of chalk where he lay down in perfect safety, and encouraged
                    me to persevere. My Umbrella was sorely in my way as it prevented my laying firm
                    hold of the grass, but as it would not do to stand there all day gazing at the
                    Sea below, and my companion above, I set off again, and got near enough to give
                    him my Umbrella, leaving my hands at liberty. In this situation he grasp’d my
                    wrist with both hands as he lay, and I felt as if all was finishd, and very
                    naturally exclaim’d ‘Now I shall do, now I’m safe,’ but at that moment out
                    tumbled the nubly chalk from under my toes and left me hanging by one hand. I
                    tried again, and reachd the brink. We find still other difficulties before we
                    reachd the top, but landed safe at last, laughing at past danger. I do not mean
                    to exagerate this story by telling you that we were ‘about seven leagues above
                    the Moon,’ as Miss Weston was informd on another occasion, but meerly to record
                    the circumstance. It was of course the lowest part of the cliff and difficult as
                    it is to judge of elevation of this kind I suppose we climbd about twice,
                    perhaps 3 times the height of our steeple at <ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref>. The path from hence was pleasant and easy to the summit of
                    Shakespear, and along the coast to Foulkston. The white cliffs on the coast of
                    France were very conspicuous, though the weather was by no means propitious.
                    Shakespear says that ‘the Surge which oer the idle pebbles chafes cannot be
                    heard so high’<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The murmuring surge /
                        That on th’unnumb’red idle pebble chafes / Cannot be heard so high. I'll
                        look no more, / Lest my brain turn, and the deficient sight / Topple down
                        headlong’. Edgar to Gloucester in <title>King Lear</title>, act 4, scene
                        6.</note> but this is one of Old Willy’s long stretches, for the murmer of
                    the waves is distinctly heard, though the depth is dreadfuly and sublimly
                    terrible. We amused ourselves in throwing down the largest flints we could find,
                    and seeing them bound and rebound against the rugged face of the prisipise. This
                    being the King’s birth-day, a royal salute was fired from the Castle and
                    Batteries and ships in the Bay, and answerd by a line of troops on the Beach
                    consisting of a Regiment of Cavalry, (the Scotch Greys,) and several regiments
                    of Regulars, Sharpshooters and Militia firing a Fieu de joy, which running fire
                    had a fine effect, echoing along the steep shores. The whole was concluded by a
                    general Huzza from the whole line. Spent the evening at a sale of prints and
                    engravings from London in an elegant Room which is both Theatre and Assembly
                    Room. </p><p rend="indent1"> Sunday morning, Rain, cold, and, wind. Rambled three miles down
                    the beach beneath the Castle Cliff towards the south Foreland, till stopd by a
                    mass of Rock which appeard to have recently fallen from above and coverd the
                    narrow road between the steep and the sea; filld our pockets with Seaweeds and
                    shells. Afternoon saw a Brig come in from Bologn firing guns in the distance.
                    This drew a croud to the beach and we walkd a long way under Shakespear’s Cliff,
                    but on the arrival of a boat instead of Old Blucher,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Marshall Gebhard von Blucher, leader of the Prussian forces
                        against Napoleon.</note> she landed Count Meternich the Austrian Ambasador,
                    whom the croud took on their shoulders and caried against his will to the Ship
                    Inn. We now learnt for a certainty that the fleet under the command of the Duke
                    of Clarence would leave Bologn Harbor the next day.—At 6 next morning landed
                    amidst a roar of Cannon the Old veteran Blucher, and Barclay de Tolly,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Michael Andreas Barclay de Tolly, Field
                        Marshall and Commander in Chief of the Russian forces in the invasion of
                        France.</note> Count Platoff<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Count
                        Matvei Ivanovich Platoff, hetman of Cossacks, and Russian commander in the
                        Napoleonic wars.</note> &amp;c, but I had been too much fateagued to
                    start so soon, and therefore did not see them at this time. All was expectation
                    and suspence for half the day, the croud increased on the piers, the Batterie,
                    the shore, and the Rigging of the vessels. At noon the fleet was plainly seen
                    steering out of the Harbour of Bologn, consisting of the Impregnable, of 98 guns
                    bearing the Russian Eagle, the prusian colours, &amp;c, surmounted by the
                    English flag at the Mainmasthead, 2, or 3 74s, Several Frigates, Sloops, and the
                    two Royal Yatchs—The whole bore up and anchord about a mile and half from shore.
                    All was silence for a considerable time, till we percievd that they had ‘man’d
                    the <hi rend="ital">Yards</hi>,’ which is placing the men in a standing position
                    along the yards and Rigging till every vessel presented the appearance of a Comb
                    teeth-upwards, (there’s a sublime simily for you) [includes a sketch of
                    this]</p><p rend="indent1"> At this time a boat decorated with Colours was seen to put off
                    from the Impregnable, when the crews of nearly thirty ships gave a tumultuos and
                    wild shout which they continued and repeated. It is impossible to convey to you
                    an idea of the singularity of such a sound over the face of the Sea! Old Neptune
                    seem’d to have open’d his caverns and given us a salute from the depths of his
                    dominion, To me it had more of horror than exultation, and I shall never forget
                    it. Immediately after the Impregnable fired her guns on both sides, and was
                    followd by the 74s and every ship in sight, untill the face of the Ocean was one
                    hurrying mingling mass of smoke. As the boats approachd the shore almost every
                    gun from the Castle and Battery took up the same tumultuous roar, that we stood
                    amidst a scene which cannot! be described. This infernal uproar continued untill
                    the Emperor and King and their crews landed on the beach between lines of the
                    Scotch Greys and all the troops in the garison who were not employ’d at the
                    Batteries. They walkd through the croud, the former to Mr Fectors, a Banker, and
                    the King to the York Hotel. They walkd through the town several times with the D
                    of Clarence, Sir Charles Stewart,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir
                        Charles Stewart, half-brother of Castlereagh, ambassador to the Hapsburg
                        Emperor at Vienna.</note> Blucher, Platoff, and 20 other great names. A vast
                    number of Russian and foriegn officers paraded the town. Some of the finest men
                    I ever saw. The town was in a ferment during the night. Double ranks of Soldiers
                    from end to end of the streets, and a universal hubbub of voices, and the
                    strongest mixture of dresses, beards, and carriages ever seen. We did not go to
                    our Inn untill eleven, compleatly tired, when we heard what we deem’d a repeated
                    Fieu de joy fired by the troops, but found next morning that the rushing sound
                    had proceeded from the firing a number of Congreves Rockets on the pier. We
                    regreted much the loss of this sight. Slepd sound. </p><p rend="indent1"> Tuesday Morning—I having recieved a letter from <ref target="people.html#BrydgesSamuelEgerton">Sir Egerton Bridges</ref>, we
                    resolve’d to make the best use of it, and imediately went as directed to Mr
                    Fector, with a reasonable hope of being introduced to <ref target="people.html#AlexanderTsar">Alexander</ref>, who speaks good English,
                    or at least to be permitted to see him to more advantage.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Minet Fector, a wealthy Dover banker, later
                        the town’s MP, was organising the reception of the dignitaries, including
                        the Tsar Alexander.</note> Here we found ourselves dissappointed. They had
                    departed for London at 5 in the morning! Not to loose all the benifit of the
                    letter, we procured from Mr Fector a pass to the Heights and Citadel. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">My Brother</ref> knows that the Cliffs at
                    the Back of Margate Street are extreemly high and abrupt, so that no
                    communication could be had without much labour. To accomplish this they have
                    litteraly bored a hole into the base of the chalk, a large brick arch slanting
                    upward for perhaps 2 or 3 hundred yards, and then asscending perpendicularly by
                    means of 3 distinct flights of stairs circling round a large shaft or well which
                    admits light from the face of the Cliff above. This ascent I judge to be about
                    the height of the Monument, but much larger.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The Monument is a 202 foot tall Doric fluted column, located at the junction of Monument Street and Fish Street Hill, London, near the north end of London Bridge. It was designed by Sir Christopher Wren and erected to commemorate the Great Fire of London. Its  height represents the distance between the monument and the starting point of the fire.</note> Above this is a range of Barracks
                    not in sight from the street and still above this building the Drop fort, with
                    13 24 pounders. The crown of this fort or Hill is cut round into a deep ditch
                    which is passd by a drawbridge. The Citadel comprehends the still higher large
                    round eminence between this And Old Shakespear. Here they have excavated
                    bomb-proof Barracks, and can lodge an army almost impregnably, scouring all the
                    ditches with Cannon, and defying every thing but starvation.—Returned soundly
                    tired and stiff.—Took places for Canterbury, where we arived at 7 on Tuesday
                    night.—</p><p rend="indent1"> During our stay at Dover we had secur’d beds, which was no slight
                    consideration, for on Monday night we had in the house the Duke of Saxe Wiemar
                    and his wife, two Generals, a Colonel, and 2 Aid de Camps, most of whom had to
                    sat up all night and smoke, and in the morning we found the dukes attendants
                    devouring a cold fowl on the Landing place for want of better accommodation.—I
                    calld on my friends here, but Mrs Pierce has retired from business and is
                    succeeded by her son. We visited the tomb of Churchill the Poet,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Churchill (1731–64), the verse satirist
                        and author of <title>The Rosciad</title> (London, 1761).</note>—saw Mr
                    Kingsford, and in short filld our time up compleatly.</p><p rend="indent1"> At Canterbury I calld on my old friend Mr Cullen, who breakfasted
                    with us next morning, and accompanied us to the Old Cathedrial. Triumphal Arches
                    of flowers were raised over the principal street, composed of whole limbs of
                    Laburnum and Lilack suspended on scaffold poles from house to house, but every
                    boddy were dissappointed and vex’d, as the Emperor had slid through the town in
                    private at seven in the morning.</p><p rend="indent1"> Wednesday at 9 set off for London accompanied by foreigners,
                    particularly in one Coach, which containd 6 Russian Officers, who smoked their
                    strange pipes all the way, sending a cloud out at each window. Like old Taylor
                    they had ‘a little Hell of their own.’ On our Coach Box rode a mery old prusian
                    General Trasco, who smoked immoderatly.—Rochester was likewise decorated with
                    flags and flowers and the whole road was a scene of high holiday.—Landed safe at
                    the Bricklayers Arms, where an officer of the Customs examined <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr Weston’s</ref> box for smuggled Lace!!!
                    I have since had a delightful ride home, and cannot repent of having taken this
                    charming holiday, for constitutionaly it has done me ten pounds worth of good,
                    and such a scene cannot occur again without another French revolution and
                    another combination of Emperors and Armies.</p><p rend="indent1"> ‘Thus Time knits or spins the worsted from Life’s Ball,’<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield quotes verse 49, lines 193–194
                        of ‘The Horkey’ from <title>Wild Flowers</title> (p. 49).</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Yours Dear Girl, most Affectionately </salute><signed rend="right">Robt Bloomfield.</signed></closer><postscript><p>NB. Very large Mackerel at Dover 20 for a Shilling</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>