<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.61</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 64–65;
                        published in Hart, p. 15</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="61" type="letter"><head>61. <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Capel Lofft</ref> to Robert
                    Bloomfield, <date when="1801-10-28">28 October 1801</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 64–65;
                        published in Hart, p. 15</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>Troston</placeName></address><date when="1801-10-28"> 28 Oct 1801.</date></dateline><salute>Sir,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have received your letter which it is impossible for me not to
                    think a very harsh one.</p><p rend="indent1"> You have undoubtedly the full right of an author over your works
                    and the full privilege of a man to judge &amp; act on your judgment: but I
                    must also feel as a man and I am accustomed as I feel to express myself. </p><p rend="indent1"> If you reflect you will not find that my idea that <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hood</ref> had his share in this
                    objection which you have at length stated to my notes could be said to be
                    groundless. You had said yourself that every person who had seen either the MS.
                    or the proofs had objected to the notes. Was I to suppose, could I suppose,
                    consistently with fact and your own letters, that <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hood</ref> had not seen either.</p><p rend="indent1"> I never call on anyone, nor did I on you, for a disclosure of
                    names that I have not a right to ask. And you must think I could not be ignorant
                    who had seen the proofs nearly to a man: since nearly all who were likely to
                    have seen them were, I imagine, those whom I introduced to you and whose names I
                    cannot want to ask.</p><p rend="indent1"> I did say that it was very proper you should write the preface. I
                    had written one: and that was enough. More than sufficient fault was thought
                    necessary to be found with a considerable part of that preface. I was there
                    supposed to have said more than was proper and to have anticipated on the
                    judgment of the public. Perhaps I know what is called the public better than you
                    as yet know it. I know that public is just to authors after their deaths but is
                    commonly too careless to be just to them in their life unless its attention be
                    called to a new author.</p><p rend="indent1"> My appendix too was blamed; it was said to be too long. My
                    remarks on my removal as a Justice were treated I must say neither with delicacy
                    nor I think with good judgment.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In the
                        appendix to the third edition of <title>The Farmer’s Boy</title> (London,
                        1800), Lofft complains of his dismissal as a Justice of the Peace after his
                        outspoken support, in person and in the press, of Sarah Lloyd, a servant
                        unjustly condemned to death for her part in a murder.</note> I was justly
                    sick of all this. And it required nothing less than the intrepid zeal of a very
                    sincere friendship to write anything for a future edition after such unpleasant
                    reception of what I had written. Reception not from the public not in general
                    from reviewers who have appeared well contented but from the author and from
                    some of the author’s acquaintance: not more friends to him possibly nor better
                    judging friends than myself.</p><p rend="indent1"> It has at length thus happened that my share as editor has
                    reduced itself to the revision of the press (a task which you will better
                    estimate if you ever undertake it); the suggestion of occasional corrections
                    which have been few there having been few wanted and these very short
                    unfortunate notes. Unfortunate in your reception of them and in the light in
                    which you have been led to consider them. Whether otherwise unfortunate,
                    publication will be the best proof. They assuredly will not appear to lead any
                    judgment which does not wish to be led by them: they are not prefixed but
                    subjoined to the poems. The poem to which each is attached will have been read
                    before the note is seen, if at all seen. </p><p rend="indent1"> Of course, as to the 8vos &amp; quartos you and <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hood</ref> do as you please. You will
                    omit the notes entirely if you like better. I only will do nothing with them but
                    what I have. I will put them into no other form. The fable of the man and his
                    three sons travelling over the bridge is a good lesson and my experience
                    confirms it. </p><p rend="indent1"> The first thing is to do what we think right. If those whom it
                    concerns cannot think with us, life is not to be worn out with fruitless
                    experiments and endeavours at new modes to please. Those who can be pleased are
                    commonly pleased at first by those who endeavour it with sincerity. </p><p rend="indent1"> I am very glad the Shepherd and his Dog will be in the
                        Mirror.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield’s ‘The Shepherd
                        and his Dog’ appeared in <title>The Monthly Mirror</title>, 12 (October
                        1801), 272, immediately preceding an extract from William Holloway’s ‘The Peasant’s
                        Fate’.</note> Though I do not like <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr
                        Hood</ref>, I like that publication. I have had the pleasure of seeing a
                    sonnet and a charming one by <ref target="people.html#LofftSarah">Miss
                        Finch</ref>, transplanted from it into the Morning Chronicle.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Lofft married Sarah Watson Finch in 1801. There
                        appeared in <title>The Monthly Mirror</title>, 12 (1802) 198 and <title>The
                            Morning Chronicle</title> on 24 October 1801 ‘Sonnet, By a Young Lady,
                        Written in the Evening, in a Retired Village’.<lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> What calm this tranquillising scene pervades,</l><l rend="indent4"> While Night’s fair Regent from her utmost height</l><l rend="indent4"> Pours forth libations of the tend’rest Light—</l><l rend="indent3"> Beneath whose beam each grosser Shadow fades!</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> No longer now the Village Peal I hear,</l><l rend="indent4"> Which thro the branches of you spreading Trees,</l><l rend="indent4"> Borne on the light wing of the Ev’ning Breeze,</l><l rend="indent3"> With Melody most pleasing touch’d the ear!</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> SILENCE hath lull’d the darken’d hemisphere;</l><l rend="indent3"> Nor Sound perceptible the ear can seize,</l><l rend="indent4"> Save that the lonely Owl, whom these Shades
                                please,</l><l rend="indent3"> Now pours his plaint—now wheels his low career;</l><l rend="indent3"> And by his drear and solitary flight</l><l rend="indent3"> Adds import to the PATHOS OF THE NIGHT!</l></lg>Bloomfield’s own ‘Highland Drover’ had appeared in the
                            <title>Chronicle</title> a few days earlier on 5 October; sonnets by
                        Lofft were printed there on 6 and 16 October.</note> Not by me: for I am not
                    connected with the editor, but by the good taste of the editor, and of some who
                    are. </p><p rend="indent1"> Market Night and the Shepherd and his Dog Rover would furnish two
                    excellent subjects for wood engraving. </p><p rend="indent1"> I did not say writing notes on your poems deprived me of a
                    pleasure. But I said, or meant to be understood that I wrote them and often
                    revised the proofs at times of such anxiety and agitation that there are not
                    many things but that I would willingly have done in those moments. You introduce
                    the epithet ‘scoundrel’ in a manner that astonishes me. You will find a parcel
                    for you at <ref target="people.html#WalkerAdam">Mr Walkers</ref>, containing Mr
                    Blacks poem on the Conjunction of Jupiter &amp; Venus with some other
                    poetical pieces which I desire you to accept.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Suffolk curate John Black’s <title>The Conjunction of
                            Jupiter and Venus, in Leo... a Happy Prelude to a Propitious Peace; a
                            Poem. Mercury’s Apology for the Curate’s Blunder, an Impromptu... and
                            other Poetical Pieces</title> (Ipswich, 1801).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> You say that no doubt I mean your good. I wish my judgment as
                    well as my meaning were somewhat in credit with you. Probably you will be
                    displeased that I should remind you to make the proper entry as author in
                    Stationers’ Hall, previously to this publication, and of your transfer of the
                    moiety of your copyright to <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hood</ref>.
                    I repeat again that without this neither you nor he are protected in the
                    copyright if anyone chooses to interfere.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> I remain yours, &amp;c.</salute><signed rend="right"><ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">C. Lofft</ref></signed><address><addrLine><placeName><ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston:</ref></placeName><date when="1801-10-28"> Oct. 28, 1801.</date></addrLine></address><address><addrLine><rs>Address: </rs><name>Mr Bloomfield</name> / near the <placeName><ref target="places.html#Shepherd">Shepherd and Shepherdess</ref> / Old City Road / London</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>