<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1892</idno><idno type="nines">rce3163</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), II, pp. 7–9.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1892" type="letter"><head>1892. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles
                        Danvers</ref>, [started before and continued on] <date when="1811-03-31">31
                        March [1811]</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/
                        Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol/ at T. Richards Esqr/
                        Plaistreet House/ near/ Taunton<lb/>Endorsement: 1811/ 31 March<lb/>MS:
                        British Library, Add MS 47890<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), II, pp. 7–9.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Charles</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The moment your letter reached me with the ages of the children I
                    wrote to <ref target="people.html#SmithThomasWoodruffe">Friend
                        Smith</ref>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        children of John Danvers (d. 1812) the younger brother of Charles Danvers, a
                        surgeon and apothecary in Woolwich, who had been made bankrupt in 1808. See
                        also Southey to Thomas Woodroffe Smith [c. 23 February 1811], Letter
                        1874.</note> As yet I have received no answer. He will certainly exert
                    himself, &amp; probably is doing so at this time, – but he is confined to his
                    house, &amp; will hardly ever be well enough to leave it. This may occasion some
                    delay, – that we shall hear from him to some purpose I have great hopes. I gave
                    him T. Reids<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Thomas
                        Whitehead Reid (1786–1845), younger half-brother of Samuel Reid. Originally
                        a sugar-refiner, he was by this time a merchant in London.</note>
                    direction.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnetts</ref> death has shocked me very
                    much. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> told me of it but I
                    knew nothing of the particulars till now.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Burnett had died in the infirmary of Marylebone workhouse in February
                        1811.</note> Three months ago two long letters from him to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> found their way
                    &amp; were opened because the handwriting was known. They talked of illness
                    &amp; distress, &amp; asked <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> to join with him in some schemes of authorship which <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Cs</ref> name would enable him to
                    effect with the booksellers. And they abused me in such a manner as to show that
                    he was clearly deranged upon that subject for he affirmed that I was doing all I
                    could to ruin his reputation from envy &amp; the certain knowledge I had that if
                    he could have fair play he should excel me, – I wrote to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> telling him the
                    substance of these letters, said that the only thing which could be done for
                        <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> was to obtain for him
                    such a situation in the army or navy as he had left, – &amp; that if this could
                    be done I would willingly contribute 20£ towards equipping it for it, but that
                    he must not know from whom it came.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s letter to Coleridge has not survived.</note><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> I am sure has never
                    opened the letter, – &amp; if it had been possible to save <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> (which probably it was not)
                    it would have been just the same. – Some such fate was to have been expected,
                    but it has shocked me grievously. In an evil hour did he become acquainted with
                    me, &amp; yet had he listened to my advice often &amp; urgently repeated, he
                    might at this hour have been alive &amp; happy, a useful &amp; a worthy member
                    of society.</p><p rend="indent1"> His hatred to me was undoubtedly pure madness, – I never received
                    a line from him since he left this place, &amp; certainly was glad that he had
                    chosen to break with me, because his <del>cond</del> manners toward women were
                        <del>sxxx</del> quite insufferable. Still I would have done any thing which
                    was possible to relieve or serve him, &amp; if <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> had opened my letter
                    &amp; seen him, we should then have known his real state of disease, &amp; he
                    should gave wanted no comfort &amp; no assistance that money could have procured
                    for him. – I have nothing for which to blame myself, but this does not prevent
                    me from being grieved as well as shocked.</p><p rend="indent1"> There will be a difficulty (insuperable I fear) about Xts
                        Hospital<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The public school,
                        Christ’s Hospital (founded 1552), which had many free places.</note> because
                    your poor brother is not a freeman of London. If <ref target="people.html#SmithThomasWoodruffe">friend Smith</ref> fails I will
                    apply to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>.</p><p><date when="1811-03-31">March 31.</date></p><p rend="indent1"> This letter has lain some days unfinished &amp; I have not yet
                    heard from <ref target="people.html#SmithThomasWoodruffe">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Smith</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> We have had nothing but sickness after sickness in the house for
                    the last three months, &amp; so it still continues. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> is just recovering from a
                    smart bilious attack, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> now is being dosed with bark for a sore throat &amp; fever: –
                    so I have been kept in a state of half idleness by disquietude. This throws me
                    back – for which there is no occasion, &amp; my arrangements are terribly
                    dislocated in consequence. I thought to have been in London the first week in
                    May, &amp; now I must work unremittingly to get there by the last. My absence
                    must be six weeks at least, – I meant it to be eight, – this brings me to
                    Midsummer. – I begin to fear that this will end in putting off my journey till
                    the autumn which I am exceedingly unwilling to do because it is time that I
                    should visit <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">his wife</ref>. – Till
                        <del>xxx</del> this be final I cannot write to Hort<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Jillard Hort (1764–1849), Unitarian minister, at
                        the Frenchay Chapel in Bristol 1803–1815 and later in Cork. He was the
                        addressee of Coleridge’s ‘To the Rev. W. J. H,’, <title>Poems on Various
                            Subjects</title> (London and Bristol, 1796), pp. [12]–14.</note> (as I
                    would else do) &amp; say how glad I should be to see him here at Midsummer. But
                    if I am at home I shall be very glad to receive him, &amp; of this you shall be
                    apprized as soon as possible. – It is among the possibilities that we may travel
                    together – for if <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> be at
                    Bath I shall make that place on my way back.</p><p rend="indent1"> You seem to value the <del>xx</del> criticism in the Register
                    more than it deserves – it is flashy &amp; that is all. I do not know who wrote
                    it, – some Scotchman or he would never have dreamt of comparing <del>xx</del> me
                    with Campbell!<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey, Thomas
                        Campbell (1777–1844; <title>DNB</title>) and <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> had been described as ‘the
                        three most successful candidates for poetical fame’ in <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.2 (1810), 419.</note> I hardly
                    conceive it would be as reasonable to institute a comparison between <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> &amp; Brandon hill.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. between the Lake district mountain
                        Skiddaw (the fourth highest mountain in England) and the much smaller
                        Brandon Hill, which lies between Clifton and Hotwells, Bristol.</note> – I
                    like the temper of the British Review<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The British Review and London Critical Journal</title>, which ran
                        from 1811–1825. It was owned by John Weyland (1774–1854; <title>DNB</title>)
                        and edited by William Roberts (1767–1849; <title>DNB</title>). The
                            <title>Review</title> was distinctly Tory and evangelical.</note> &amp;
                    am glad to see something like a right old English feeling gaining ground in the
                    country. What a fine thing is this of Grahams!<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Major-General Thomas Graham (1748–1843;
                            <title>DNB</title>), had just played a crucial part in the victory of an
                        Anglo-Spanish force at Barrosa on 5 March 1811.</note> &amp; what a <del>xx
                        xxxxx</del> lucky speech did <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord
                        Grenville</ref> make about Portugal last week!<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Grenville had made a speech in the House of Lords on 18
                        March 1811 on the futility of British intervention in Spain and Portugal.
                        Southey noted laconically, ‘Two days after these opinions were delivered,
                        the telegraph announced the news of Massena’s retreat’, <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register, 1811</title> (1813), I, p. 264, referring to the French
                        general, André Massena’s (1758–1817) retreat from Portugal into Spain, which
                        began on 13 March 1811.</note> Huzza for the Portugueze, – it does my heart
                    good to hear of their fighting side by side with us.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>