<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2650</idno><idno type="nines">rce3921</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, Don. d.
                        3.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2650" type="letter"><head>2650. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1815-08-29">29
                        August 1815</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ Queen Anne
                        Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ 1 SE 1/ 1815<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, Don. d.
                        3<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Harry</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Baillie &amp; Sir Henry Halford<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The eminent London
                        physicians Matthew Baillie (1761–1823; <title>DNB</title>) and Sir Henry Halford (1766–1844; <title>DNB</title>).</note> are
                    as much masters of their own time, as I am of mine at this season. It is one series of interruptions. – Eight &amp; forty hours
                    will be enough for me in town, in the way of business I shall have only to raise the supplies, &amp; see <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">Aunt</ref> with the ursine
                        nobility<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Hills’ sons, <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref>, <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Herbert</ref>, <ref target="people.html#HillErrol">Erroll</ref> and <ref target="people.html#HillAlfred">Alfred</ref>.</note> of <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>. You may call
                    at my tailors for me (Hyde.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hyde (first name unknown; d. 1820), was Southey’s London
                        tailor.</note> 1. Warwick Street Golden Square) &amp; order a black coat with <del>a pair of</del> some speckled grey
                    pantaloons of such make &amp; materials as your Lordship (in these things of approved judgement) may think most suitable: they may
                    be made in readiness &amp; sent to your house. I must shoe myself at the patent warehouse, – for I have found the nail-shoes
                    answer admirably well. And as I shall travel to London in that hat which <del>I dare</del><ref target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa"> Louisa</ref> I dare say has not forgotten, you will perhaps think it expedient that I
                    should purchase a new one in town, &amp; accompany me, thro some bye streets, to a shop where I may be fitted in the newest
                    fashion.</p><p rend="indent1"> Thus far &amp; not a word of the day when I set off. The delay cannot inconvenience you so much as it vexes me, for
                    fear it should inconvenience you at all. I hope to leave home this day week, <del>which will bring</del> &amp; in that case to
                    reach London on Friday. It is not unlikely that <ref target="people.html#KosterHenry">Henry Koster</ref> will accompany me to
                    town, &amp; join us at Ramsgate. He has been laid up here so long, that now when he is got fairly upon his legs again, he seems
                    like one of the family, &amp; if he gets leave to go we shall find him a useful person to place upon the staff.</p><p rend="indent1"> Good night! I must lose no time in letter writing. You shall hear again from me when I write to Carlisle to secure
                    my place in the mail. – Should we not do wisely if we <hi rend="ital">hoy’d</hi> it to Margate, baggage &amp; all together?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The hoy (a small ship or barge) was a popular way of travelling from London to the port of
                        Margate, Kent.</note> If you should approve of the hint you will doubtless give the preference to the Evangelical hoy.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1807 a weekly packet ship from London to Margate was advertised, which was aimed at
                        religious travellers. ‘No profane conversation’ was allowed. It was the subject of much parody in the press.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref> –</salute><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1815-08-29">Tuesday. 29 Aug. 1815.</date></p><p>I am in great hopes of getting a set of the Acta Sanctorum in Flanders. Nothing would delight me so much, &amp; scarcely
                        anything would be of such essential utility.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was to meet with mixed success on
                            his book-buying expedition in Belgium and France. For a while, he hoped he had bought the complete set of the rare, 53
                            volume <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (Brussels, 1643–1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue of his library. In fact he
                            received from the bookseller a 6 volume edition of 1783–1794, no. 152 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> Indeed
                        I expect to deal largely in books.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>