<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1782</idno><idno type="nines">rce3053</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 287–289 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1782" type="letter"><head>1782. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1810-05-30">30 May
                        1810</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To / The Reverend Herbert Hill / Streatham
                        /Surry.<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmarks: E / 2 JU 2 / 1810 / [illegible] JU 2/ 1810 END<lb/>MS: Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 287–289 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1810-05-30">May 30. 1810.</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> The Chronica del R D Rodrigo<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Chronica del Rey Don Rodrigo con la Destruycion de Espana, y como los Moros la Ganaron</title> (1587); Southey
                        eventually obtained a copy, no. 3341 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> is a different book from that forgery of
                    Miguel de Luna’s<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Miguel de Luna (fl. C16th/C17th), <title>Historia Verdadera del Rey Don
                            Rodrigo</title> (1589), based on a non-existent Arabic manuscript dealing with the invasion of Spain in 711. Southey owned
                        an edition of 1676, no. 3218 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> of which a duplicate copy was sent with the
                        divinity.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> It is also an older book. Morales<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ambrosio de Morales (1513–1591), <title>Coronica General de Espana, con las Antiguedades de las
                            Ciudades de Espana</title> (1791–1793), no. 3557 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> mentions it &amp; the
                    Chro. de S Isidro<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isidore of Seville (c. 560–636), archbishop who was later canonised. His
                            <title>Chronica Majora</title> covers events from the creation to 615, with particular emphasis on Spain.</note> in such a
                    manner as to make me very curious to see both of them, – from the fables at which he hints, they seem to be in the very wildest
                    strain of fiction. – I am afraid my directions about sending the boxes by canal were not observed, as it is very improbable that
                    they should have reachd you <del>by</del> &lt;at&gt; the same time with those which went by waggon; – but I am forty miles from
                    the canal, &amp; this is not the first time I have felt myself imposed upon by carriers, without perceiving any means of redress.
                    There is <del>not</del> nothing in which clear laws &amp; summary justice are more needed than in the breach of business, where
                    frauds are so easily committed, &amp; in almost all cases with perfect impunity.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have been three weeks from home since your last letter was written. The two Ediths<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May
                        Southey</ref>.</note> were with me &amp; we returned on Friday last. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary</ref>
                    is evidently in very precarious health, &amp; I have little expectation that she will ever be better, – short breath, – pains in
                    the chest &amp; side, &amp;c – manifestations alarming in any person<del>on</del>. &amp; especially so in one of her make. We left
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> there, over head &amp; ears in love, &amp; few jests upon the blockade he was
                    carrying on, (the Ladys name happening to be Castle)<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom’s future wife, <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref>.</note> were all that past between us on the subject, – since my return
                    however I have received a letter from him telling me she has promised to marry him, &amp; saying he shall talk over his plans when
                    we meet. She is about 30, – &amp; if fortune were out of the question, he might have seached England thro &amp; not have chosen
                    better, – <del>xxx</del> how money-matters may turn out I very doubtful: but unless there were something I do not think he would
                    have proceeded thus far. </p><p rend="indent1"> My Register-work<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>
                        (1810).</note> was finished before I left home. At Durham I got at Purchas<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel
                        Purchas (bap. 1577, d. 1626; <title>DNB</title>), editor, compiler and Anglican clergyman. Southey had consulted
                            <title>Purchas, his Pilgrimage</title> (1613) or <title>Hakluytus Posthumus, or Purchas his Pilgrimes</title> (1625) in Durham Cathedral
                        Library.</note> &amp; gutted that Roteiro (Rutter it is there called) of D Joam de Castro,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> João de Castro (1500–1548) Portuguese naval officer. His <title>Roteiros</title> (1538–1541) were the logbooks
                        of his voyages. They were not published in full until 1833.</note> which from its internal evidence was, I have little doubt,
                    written by himself. It is a pity that we have only an abstract of it. An interval of idleness, which is to me more wearisome than
                    any labour, has given me a new appetite for employment, &amp; I am busily occupied upon my second volume, – to which with such
                    alternations of work for the Review as are always wholesome as well as convenient (for over-application to any one subject
                    disturbs my sleep. &amp; I have long since learnt by neutralizing &lt;as it were&gt; one set &lt;of thoughts&gt; with another to
                    sleep as sweetly as a child) – I shall devote the next three months uninterruptedly. My first volume<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> seems to be well liked by
                    my friends; – they all speak of it as amusing; – which I was at one time apprehensive it would not be. –</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> the bookseller, with whom the Quarterly has led me into a correspondence,
                    promises to procure for me a MSS. Hist of Lima<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> written by one of its
                    viceroys. I shall be glad to see it, &amp; am a good deal obliged by this mark of attention on his part, – but those books upon
                    Paraguay would be far more useful at this time, – for I have no other guides than Charlevoix,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> As Southey had not yet acquired Pierre Francois Xavier de Charlevoix (1682–1761), <title>Historia
                            Paraguajensis, ex Gallioc Latina, cum Animadversionibus et Supplemento</title> (1779), no. 691 in the sale catalogue of
                        his library, he may have had to rely on Charlevoix’s <title>Histoire du Paraguay</title> (1756), no. 645 in the sale catalogue
                        of his library.</note> &amp; the mutilated translation of Techo in Churchill<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Jesuit Nicholas del Techo (1611–1685). An English translation of his Latin ‘History of the Provinces of Paraguay, Tucuman, Rio
                        de la Plata, Parana, Gualra, Ulrvaica and Chile’ was included in the fourth volume of John Churchill (c. 1663–c.1714;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Collection of Voyages and Travels in Various Parts of the World</title> (1704).</note> –
                    Luckily a very brief summary of historical events is all that I am called upon, or indeed, consistently with the main purpose
                    &amp; plan of the work ought to give, – still it <del>xx</del> is impossible to do this to my own satisfaction unless I feel
                    myself thoroughly well acquainted with the whole series of events. Surely <ref target="people.html#BellJohn">John Bell</ref> might get at these books, for they are neither old enough, nor valuable enough to be
                    scarce.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> will have me reviewed as early as possible in the Quarterly, in the next
                    number if he can.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810)
                        was reviewed (by Reginald Heber) in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 454–474. Southey – despite his
                        public protests to the contrary – was not entirely happy with it, particular Heber’s singling out of his use of unusual words;
                        see Southey to William Gifford, 4 January 1811, Letter 1849.</note> There &amp; in the Critical<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> See, the generally commendatory account in the <title>Critical Review</title>, 21 (September 1810), 27–43. At
                        this time, the <title>Critical</title> was edited by Robert Fellowes (1770–1847; <title>DNB</title>).</note> I expect friendly
                    treatment.</p><p rend="indent1"> Scott sent me his poem<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott’s <title>The Lady of the Lake</title> (1810).
                        It sold over 20,000 copies in the year of its publication.</note> to Durham. I like it better than either Marmion or the
                        Lay,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Lay of the Last Minstrel</title> (1805) and <title>Marmion</title> (1808).</note> tho its</p><p rend="indent1">measure is less agreable, – but the story has finer parts, &amp; <del>xxx</del> is better conceived. The portraits
                    both of Camp &amp; his master are remarkably good.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Saxon (fl. 1795–1828) had
                        painted a picture of Scott with his favourite bull terrier, Camp, in 1805. This formed the basis of the engraving for the
                        frontispiece of the <title>Lady of the Lake</title> (1810).</note> He talks of a journey to the Hebrides, but if that does not
                    take place of a visit southward, in which case <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> will be taken on his way, &amp; we
                    are to concert some plans for employing <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref> press.</p><p rend="indent1"> The old Douay establishment is removed to England – to a place called Ushaw, about four miles from Durham.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ushaw, a Roman Catholic seminary. Originally founded as the English College, Douai in
                        1568, it moved to Ushaw Moor, near Durham, in 1808.</note> They began it upon a Bank of Faith system, after Huntingdons
                        manner,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The preacher and religious writer William Huntington (1745–1813;
                            <title>DNB</title>), whose <title>God the Guardian of the Poor and the Bank of Faith</title> (1785–1802) describes how
                        Providence assisted his early preaching career by supplying him with food, clothing and all else he needed. Southey later
                        condemned Huntington’s account as unparalleled ‘in the whole bibliotheca of knavery and fanaticism’ (<title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 24 (January 1821), 482).</note> – having only <del>xx</del> 2000£ to begin with, – tho 12000 have already
                    been expended, &amp; pretty near as much more will go before it is compleated. There are 100 students there already, chiefly boys,
                    &amp; preparations &lt;are&gt; making for doubling the number. I rode over with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; one of his Catholic friends to look after the library. The philosophical tutor Lingard<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The priest and historian John Lingard (1771–1851; <title>DNB</title>).</note> showed me a vol. of
                    the Acta Sanct. Benedictorum,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (1643–1940), a 68 volume biography of all the saints, arranged by their feast-days.</note> –
                    Saints, as they chuse to call them, said he, bending his head <del>xx</del> upon one side, &amp; glancing up a pair of cunning
                    eyes at me, to show his liberality. In the evening however the Ecclesiastical Antiquities of the Anglo Saxons,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lingard’s <title>The Antiquities of the Anglo-Saxon Church</title> (1810); no. 1728 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> by this very Mr Lingard were put into my hands – &amp; there he relates miracles, &amp;
                    abuses <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> for what he calls <hi rend="ital">his</hi> Romance of S Dunstan!<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Antiquities of the Anglo-Saxon Church</title>, 2nd edn (London, 1810), pp. 394–395: ‘in his account of St Dunstan …
                        [Turner] has improved their incoherent fables into a well-connected romance’. Lingard’s critique was of Turner’s
                            <title>History of the Anglo-Saxons</title>, 4 vols (London, 1799–1805), III, pp. 132–191.</note> – These fellows are all
                    alike. I asked what the number of the English Catholicks was supposed to be &amp; was told 300,000. This is most likely
                    exaggerated, – I should not have guessed them at half. <del>X</del></p><p rend="indent1"><del>Xxxxx</del> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> – I long to see <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">D Duardos</ref>, &amp; think of doing so either at the fall of the leaves, or
                        <del>before</del> &lt;about&gt; their return, – as may best suit my occupations. We are all going on well,</p><closer><salute rend="indent5"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent6"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>