<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1900</idno><idno type="nines">rce3171</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian
                        Library, Oxford, MS Eng. Lett. d. 215.  Previously  published: R. H. Cholmondeley, The Heber Letters,
                            1783–1832 (London, 1950), pp. 239–240 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1900" type="letter"><head>1900. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Richard Heber</ref>, <date when="1811-04-09">9 April
                        1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [deletions and readdress in another hand] To/ Richard
                        Heber Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ <del>Elliots Brewery</del> &lt;Hodnet Hall&gt;/ <del>Westminster</del>
                        &lt;Shrewsbury&gt;<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: B/ AP 25 AP/ 1811<lb/>Watermark: [partial] 1809<lb/>MS: Bodleian
                        Library, Oxford, MS Eng. Lett. d. 215<lb/>Previously published: R. H. Cholmondeley, <title>The Heber Letters,
                            1783–1832</title> (London, 1950), pp. 239–240 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1811-04-09">April 9. 1811</date></dateline><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your books which have been in my possession since the spring of 1808 are on their way to London, by waggon,
                    carefully packed &amp; directed to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman’s</ref> care. I am very much obliged to you for
                    the pleasure which they have given me. Contrary to my expectation I thought Tristan below its fame, &amp; Lancelot little
                        better.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had borrowed a series of ‘Round Table Romances’; see Southey to Henry
                        Herbert Southey, 16 October 1808, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Three</title>, Letter 1517. These
                        included the romance cycles known as the <title>Prose Tristan</title> (c. 1230–after 1240), attributed to Luce de Gat and
                        Helie de Boron, and the <title>Lancelot-Grail</title> (early 13th century).</note> Isaye le Triste<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Early fifteenth-century French medieval romance.</note> exhausted my patience, for after proceeding some way
                    it seemed to me so thoroughly worthless that I laid it aside. But Giron &amp; Meliadus are both of a very superior character,
                    these I have no doubt are the work of the same author.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Two medieval French prose romances,
                        they formed part of the romance cycle <title>Palamades</title> (13th century). Their putative, probably pseudonymous, author
                        was Helie de Boron.</note> In the former Spenser seems to have found his Braggadochio,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        A braggart; a character in Edmund Spenser (c. 1552–1599; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Faerie Queene</title>
                        (1590–1596).</note> – for certainly there is a character there much more nearly resembling him than the one in Ariosto<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rodomonte, a vainglorious character in Ludovico Ariosto (1474–1533), <title>Orlando
                            Furioso</title> (1532).</note> which has been said to be the prototype. Perhaps it may be more clearly made out in
                    Alamannes poem.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poetic romance <title>Girono Il Cortese</title> (1548), whose author
                        was the Italian statesman and poet Luigi Alemanni (1495–1556). Southey owned an edition of 1761; no. 23 in the sale catalogue
                        of his library.</note> I have it at hand &amp; when a little more at leisure will go thro it.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Morte Arthur<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Thomas Malory (1415/18–1471; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Le Morte d’Arthur</title> (1485).</note> concerning which I have so long appeared to play the part of the dog in
                    the manger towards Scott, is now fairly in his hands, &amp; what few memoranda I have made will be consigned to him.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Scott’s interest in Arthurian romance was long-standing. He had edited <title>Sir
                            Tristrem</title> (1804) and cited the <title>Morte Arthur</title> in the notes to <title>Marmion</title> (1808). Arthurian
                        stories and romance motifs were central to his own <title>The Lady of the Lake</title> (1810) and ‘Lyulp’s Tale’, part of
                            <title>The Bridal of Triermain</title> (1813). Southey was wrong: he, not Scott, went on to publish an edition of the
                            <title>Morte Arthur</title> in 1817.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Can you supply me with the two Mathers’ books about New England?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Cotton
                        Mather (1663–1728), <title>Magnalia Christi Americana, or the Ecclesiastical History of New England from 1620 to 1698</title>
                        (1702); no. 1904 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library; and <title>A Brief History of the War with the Indians in
                            New-England</title> (1676), by Increase Mather (1639–1723), the father of Cotton Mather.</note> I have planned a poem
                    founded upon Philips war with the New Englanders, which was the decisive struggle between the white &amp; red races in N America,
                    – &amp; which also secured the preponderance of the English over the French settlements there.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> King Philip’s War, or Metacom’s Rebellion, 1675–1676. An armed conflict between English colonists and the
                        Native American inhabitants of New England. Southey’s poem was ‘Oliver Newman’, left incomplete at his death.</note> At first
                    sight nothing can appear more anti-heroic, nor more anti-picturesque than stiff puritan manners, &amp; you will not think I have
                    diminished the difficulty by chusing a primitive Quaker for the hero. Yet my second sight is as hopeful, as any poet could desire.
                    – I have sent to America for all the American books which can in any point <del>illust</del> illustrate the subject, – these
                    earlier authors are more likely to be found on our side the water, – &amp; you will serve me by looking out any which bear upon
                    the early history of the English colonies.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall be in town in about two months &amp; should have been there by this time had it not been for M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Clarke<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776–1852; <title>DNB</title>), a
                        former mistress of Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763–1827; <title>DNB</title>). After the end of their affair in May
                        1806, she had threatened to publish intimate details of their relationship. More recently, both had been at the centre of a
                        scandal over the alleged misuse of military patronage. After a lengthy investigation, the charges against the Duke, who was
                        Commander-in-Chief of the army, were found to be unproven. It had, however, become apparent that Mrs Clarke had received money
                        from individuals keen for her to use her influence with the Duke, and that the Duke himself had known of her actions. For
                        Southey’s account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 109–301.</note> &amp; the last Austrian
                    War. <note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The War of the Fifth Coalition of Austria and Britain against France. Austria’s
                        participation ended with the Treaty of Schonbrunn, 14 October 1809. For Southey’s account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register,
                            for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 575–659.</note> Between them they have swoln my annual labours to an extent very
                    inconvenient for myself. You probably know that the historical part of the Edinb. An. Register is mine, for I am not in the habit
                    of keeping things of this kind secret, tho all such things have the greater authority when the author is unknown, by a perversity
                    which it would not be difficult to explain. I have taken great pains with these Annals in collecting information whenever it was
                    possible from the best sources, &amp; I have been very succesful in obtaining it, especially with regard to Spain.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> new Review,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The British Review and London Critical Journal</title> ran from 1811–1825.</note> so far as it succeeds, will interfere
                    with the sale of the Quarterly, but I doubt whether there will be sufficient sea-room for two, sailing upon the same tack, &amp;
                    in that case the British will sink. I have mist an opportunity of tomahawk-ing <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> there is to be an essay on the state of criticism in the Register, <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> thinking the person who had volunteered to <del>xx</del> write it was grown out of love with the task &amp;
                    desirous to relinquish &lt;it&gt; applied to me. – Before he could get my answer the finished essay was brought him. He speaks of
                    it very highly but says that it is far far too gentle, – a fault which he would not have <del>falted</del> found with any
                    production of mine upon that subject.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘On the Present State of Periodical Criticism’
                        appeared in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.2 (1811), 556–581. It concluded: ‘The tone of criticism
                        … at the commencement of the nineteenth century may be characterized as harsh, severe, and affectedly contemptuous … it has
                        unfortunately become more deeply involved in the toils of the political statesman’ (p. 581).</note> I would have exposed the
                    abominations of the Scotch Review in morals &amp; politics, &amp; their utter ignorance of the first principles of taste as
                    clearly as <ref target="people.html#CoplestonEdward">Copplestone</ref> has done their lack of Greek,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> [Edward Copleston], <title>A Reply to the Calumnies of the Edinburgh Review against Oxford</title> (Oxford,
                        1810), reacting to an attack on ‘classical learning as currently taught in England’, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 15
                        (October 1809), 40–53. Copleston noted in response that no one would ‘apply to the Edinburgh Review for information about the
                        Classics’ (<title>Reply</title>, p. 118). For the reviewers’ reaction see <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 16 (April 1810),
                        158–187. Copleston followed up with <title>A Second Reply to the Edinburgh Review</title> (1810) and <title>A Third Reply to
                            the Edinburgh Review</title> (1811). Southey was possibly under the misapprehension that Copleston was the author of
                        ‘Replies to the Calumnies Against Oxford’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5 (August 1810), 177–206. He was not. The review
                        had been written by the Oxford theologian John Davison (1777–1834; <title>DNB</title>).</note> – &amp; upon the score of
                    honesty I would, as they deserve, have whipt them like common rogues.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> Your friend <ref target="people.html#MitfordJohn">Mitford</ref> appears to me a man of very great promise. I
                        judge so more especially from his sonnets.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Published in John Mitford, <title>Agnes,
                                The Indian Captive: A Poem, In Four Cantos. With Other Poems</title> (London, 1811), pp. [189]–200; see Southey to
                            John Mitford, 20 March 1811, Letter 1886.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>