<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2521</idno><idno type="nines">rce3792</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS
                            30927.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 8–10 [misdated 20 December 1815]Dating note: This letter was begun on 17 December, the day after Southey received the letter from
                        Croker he refers to here.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2521" type="letter"><head>2521. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1814-12-17">[17–] 22 December
                        [1814]</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey. R. N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helens/ Auckland<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS
                            30927<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 8–10 [misdated 20 December 1815]<lb/>Dating note: This letter was begun on 17 December, the day after Southey received the letter from
                        Croker he refers to here.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I want your help about the beginning of Oliver Newman.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Oliver Newman’,
                        left incomplete at Southey’s death.</note> It must open with a funeral at sea. Do you put shot in the coffin (when there is
                    one) or fasten the weights in any other manner? And in what manner, when the ceremony was to be perfomed with some respect, would
                    you hoist it over? &amp; from what part of the ship? Give me all the technicals.</p><p rend="indent1"> My plan is pretty well made out,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Watkin Williams
                        Wynn, 15 December 1814, Letter 2516.</note> &amp; I believe my mind is made up upon the choice of metre, which is always a
                    perplexing choice. It will be that of Thalaba.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> Blank verse might lead me into repetitions, – &amp; rhyme will not do for
                    a poem much of which must be essentially dramatic.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> expects that the quarto Roderick will be gone before a small edition can be
                    ready; – it is therefore in the press again.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of <title>Roderick, the
                            Last of the Goths</title> was published in two duodecimo volumes in 1815. The first edition of 1814 had been in quarto
                        format.</note> This was to be looked for, – but it will not have &amp; cannot have a great sale. The passion for novelty is
                    soon satisfied, &amp; the Poem is of far too high a character to become popular, till time has made it so. It is like an acorn
                    upon Latrigg now. The thistles &amp; the fern will <del>grow</del> &lt;shoot up&gt; faster, &amp; <del>perhaps</del> put it out of
                    sight for a season; but the oak will strike root &amp; grow.</p><p rend="indent1"> Will you be glad or sorry to hear that I must write an Ode?<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Ode, Written
                        in December 1814’. It was thought unsuitable by the authorities, and was not published until Southey’s <title>Minor
                            Poems</title>, 3 vols (London, 1815), II, pp. 227–238. It was retitled ‘Ode, Written During the War with America, 1814’ in
                        the 1837–1838 edition of Southey’s poetical works.</note> I verily believed that the performance had been dropt last year,
                    &amp; thought it was an act of over-caution when I wrote last week to ask <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> whether or
                    not it was so.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to [John Wilson Croker], 6 December 1814, Letter 2512.</note>
                    He tells me last night that tho the custom ought to be abolished, it is not yet, &amp; therefore I must write one: &amp; he holds
                    out a vague sort of prospect of its abolition, upon which very little dependance can be placed. You may be sure I care very little
                    about this. An immediate &amp; public abolition of so idle a custom would <del>xxx</del> reflect credit upon the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> but as for me, it may very possibly be more to my credit that it should
                    continue; for subjects can never be wanting to a man who looks at public events as I do, in their causes &amp; consequences. So
                    instead of <hi rend="ital">pesting</hi> the ode (that French word is better than either our synonims in c or in d,) I set about
                    it; formed the plan immediately, &amp; have today written 37 lines; – which considering I had a headache in the morning, &amp;
                    took a humming dose of magnesia at two o clock to get rid of it, is pretty well. If you were a medical man you would think it a
                        <del>xxx</del> curious fact that this dose should have performed its work in the course of two <del>xxx</del> hours: – it has
                    carried away the head aches, – &amp; I should have written <del>xx</del> another stanza of the ode, instead of taking up this
                    letter for your lordship, if I had not <del>xxx</del> wished to get it as much out of my mind as possible before I go to bed.</p><p rend="indent1"> We had yesterday the most remarkable storm that <ref target="people.html#WilsonMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Wilson</ref> or any person in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> can remember. The wind was nearly due south;
                    &amp; it took up the water of the lake, literally like dust: we could see it beginning to rise far up under Brandelhow, white as
                    smoke or as a morning mist, gathering &amp; growing all the way to the bottom of the lake, &amp; there dispersed as far as the
                    tempest could carry it. The report from the town was that “slates were flying about there like crows.” – &amp; in fact the long
                    sort of pent house above the Queens Head is nearly unroofed. It still blows a heavy gale.</p><p rend="indent1"><del>Xxxxx xxxxx xxx xxxx xxxxx xxxx xxxx xxxx xxxx xxxx xxxx xxxx</del> The West Indies<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Tom Southey’s planned <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827).</note> you cannot compleat without going
                    to London, &amp; working at the public libraries there, &amp; this it will be worth while to do when you have done all that can be
                    done from the materials within your reach. We must overhaul them when I come to you.</p><p>22 Dec.<hi rend="sup">r</hi></p><p rend="indent1"> My od<hi rend="ital">e</hi>ous job was finished yesterday, thirteen stanzas in the rhymeless measure of the
                    Congratulatory Odes, which Milton, after the Greeks, calls Apolelymenon, – a good hard word for <hi rend="ital">loose</hi>.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Milton (1608–1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Samson Agonistes</title> (1671), ‘Of
                        that sort of Dramatick Poem which is called Tragedy’: ‘The measure of verse used in the Chorus is of all sorts, called by the
                        Greeks Monostrophick, or rather Apolelymenon, without regard had to Strophe, Antistrophe, or Epode’.</note> I want a name for
                    the Ode sadly – but to call it merely from the metre Carmen Apolelymenon would be such “a word on” – A Title Page as might well
                    make the reader bless himself. so I suppose it <del>xxx</del> must simply be called an Ode. I dismiss the American war by a [MS
                    missing] that it may soon be at an end,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The United Kingdom and United States were at war
                        1812–1814, but negotiations to end the conflict were underway and the Treaty of Ghent was signed 24 December 1814.</note> with
                    a reference to the memory of Washington,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Washington (1732–1799), first President
                        of the United States of America, 1789–1797.</note> – then turn to what are the labours which befit the county in peace launch
                    out upon the two great subjects of General Education &amp; Colonization. I will get it franked to you if I can.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> has a frightful abscess below the ear. It began with a discharge from the
                    inside &amp; has lasted very long. I hope it is going on well at present, &amp; think so. But it a most distressing thing to dress
                    it twice a day. She has never thoroughly recovered from that dreadful bilious attack in October; – &amp; I am afraid she is at
                    this time threatened by another: – so that I am far from being easy in mind. </p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> Love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref></salute><salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>