<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2212</idno><idno type="nines">rce3483</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2212" type="letter"><head>2212. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1813-01-27">27 January 1813</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster.<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ 30 JA 30/ 1813<lb/>Endorsements:
                            Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 27. 1813.<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> That I am very much offended, &amp; very much vexed at <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">this dirty
                        fellows</ref> proceedings, need not be said. The upshot I dare say will prove as Deacon<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a reference to Southey’s Westminster contemporary Deacon Morrell (1775–1854), a clergyman and landowner who lived
                        at Sackville Street in Westminster.</note> expects, &amp; then this will be the last trouble you will have with a business, in
                    which I am very sorry that it has been my ill luck to involve you. I shall have some loss, which is a bad thing, &amp; some
                    trouble, which is worse to a man of my kidney, before I can get rid of him; – rid however I will be; &amp; shall at a convenient
                    season inform him that <del>I</del> unless <del>I a xxxxxxxx</del> an arrangement be made for paying me thro <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> or <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, I shall withdraw from
                    the Register<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey ceased working for the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> after
                        1813.</note> as soon as the current volume is concluded. This at all events. But meantime I shall put out my feelers, &amp;
                    endeavour to discover some means of <del>making xx</del> securing an equal income by other means. From what I hear &lt;said&gt; of
                        Rokeby,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott’s <title>Rokeby: A Poem</title> (1813), set during the civil war of the
                        seventeenth century.</note> it is to be augured (between ourselves) that <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>
                    will get no more three-thousanders, but it is by no means unlikely that I could obtain 500 £ for a poem of equal length, – &amp;
                    it would be less labour to me to produce one than to bring forth one of these <del>xxxx</del> yearly Annals. – Be this as it may I
                    must disentangle myself from all dialogue with a scoundrel.</p><p rend="indent1"> How is that you do not seem to have received a note of mine accompanying the 4 book of Roderick,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> which was franked up to <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> some week or ten days ago? The 5 &amp; 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> are both nearly transcribed for you. I have
                    finished the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &amp; if it be not <hi rend="ital">El imposible vencido</hi>,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Triumph over the impossible’. Manuel Larramendi (1690–1766), <title>El Imposible Vencido</title> (1729), a
                        grammar of the notoriously complex Basque language, no. 1606 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> it is as
                        <del>near tho</del> &lt;like&gt; it as possible. I want two books for the chance <del>of</del> or rather certainty of finding
                    ornament-seeds in them. They are Jornandes,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jornandes (c. mid 6th century), Roman
                        bureaucrat and author of <title>De Getarum (Gothorum) Origine et Rebus Gestis</title> and <title>De Regnorum ac Temporum
                            Successione</title>. Both were widely used by later historians.</note> &amp; Gregory of Tours.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> St Gregory of Tours (c. 538–594), historian and bishop. An edition of his <title>Historiae Francorum</title>
                        (1561) was no. 1240 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Will you ask <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> or the <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Czar</ref>, who are in the way of finding such books, to purchase
                    them for me. My subject, singularly rich in other respects, is singularly poor in costume, – &amp; I must hunt for trappings
                    wherever they are to be found.</p><p rend="indent1"> I never doubted that <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> play would meet with a
                    triumphant reception.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Remorse</title>, staged at Drury Lane, London, 23 January-12 February 1813. This run made it a moderate success.</note><del>But</del> Be it known now, &amp; remembered hereafter, that this self-same play, having had no other alterations made to it
                    now, than <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> was willing to have made then, was rejected in 1797 by Sheridan
                    &amp; Kemble:<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The actor John Philip Kemble (1757–1823; <title>DNB</title>) and the
                        playwright, theatre proprietor and politician Richard Brinsley Sheridan (1751–1816; <title>DNB</title>) had rejected it in
                        1797, when it was titled ‘Osorio’.</note><del>whereas</del> had these sapient caterers for the public brought it forward &lt;at&gt; that &lt;time&gt;, it is by no means
                    improbable that the author might have produced a play as good every season: with my knowledge of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge’s</ref> habits, I verily believe that he would.</p><p rend="indent1"> Have you had any conversation with <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>? Of two desirable things, a ship, or the step, – rank would be the best; but either
                    very desirable.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your public financial news is bad enough.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Grosvenor Bedford worked at the
                        Treasury, where there was some worry at the impending deficit in the public finances for 1813–1814.</note> Concerning my own
                    finances do not be uneasy. Since I wrote my last note to you, I have received a Bill of <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Sir Shufflers</ref> at two months which is put into circulation. <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>
                    talked of publishing by the beginning of February, he is a bad calculator I believe, – but whenever he does publish, my
                        article<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s review of Patrick Colquhoun (1745–1820; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Propositions for ameliorating the Condition of the Poor: and For Improving the Moral Habits, and Increasing the
                            Comforts of the Labouring People</title> (1812), appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812),
                        319–356. It was altered by Gifford and Croker prior to publication.</note> will send me 25 £; <del>&amp; is</del> it deserves
                    the double payment in an especial manner (tho less so than the Inquisition<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                        review of <title>The History of the Inquisitions; including the Secret Transactions of those Horrific Tribunals</title>
                        (1810); <title>Letter upon the Mischievous Influence of the Spanish Inquisition as it actually exists in the Provinces under
                            the Spanish Government. Translated from El Español, a periodical Spanish Journal published in London</title> (1811);
                            <title>Narrativa da Perseguição de Hippolyto Joseph Da Costa Pereira Furtado de Mendonça, Natural da Colonia do
                            Sacramento, no Rio-da-Prata, prezo e Processado em Lisboa pelo pretenso Crime de Fra-Maçon, ou Pedreiro Livre</title>
                        (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (December 1811), 313–357.</note> did) &amp; I am inclined to think that this sweet
                    remuneration will be made. Meantime if I want money, as peradventure may be the case if <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> is as much behind hand in publication<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. behind with publication of
                        the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> as usual, I can draw upon <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your char shall be enquired about without delay. I am not sure that they are in season: &amp; if they are perhaps
                    so many as four dozen of good size may not be to be had on demand – for you know this is not the time when lakers drop in to
                    dinner, &amp; in frosty weather the lake is the safest stew. My next shall unfurl upon this point.</p><p rend="indent1"> Milman<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Either the poet Henry Hart Milman (1791–1868; <title>DNB</title>),
                        or, more likely one of his older brothers, Sir William George Milman, 2nd Baronet (1781–1857), who Southey recorded as staying
                        at Keswick for about a year at this time (see, Robert Southey to Chauncy Hare Townsend, 12 April 1818, <title>The Collected
                            Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>). The two paintings were of scenes in Portugal: Almourol Castle, a ruined
                        Templar castle on an island in the Tagus; and a view of the Agueda river, the boundary between Spain and Portugal.</note> goes
                    to London in April. He has painted me two pictures the Castle of Almourol, – &amp; a copy of that view on the Agueda.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1813-01-27">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 27. 1813.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>