<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2088</idno><idno type="nines">rce3359</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text is taken from Eustace R. Conder,
                            Josiah Conder: A Memoir (London, 1857).  Previously  published: Eustace R. Conder, Josiah Conder: A
                            Memoir (London, 1857), pp. 161–164.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2088" type="letter"><head>2088. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ConderJosiah">Josiah Conder</ref>, <date when="1812-05-05">5 May
                        1812</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Eustace R. Conder,
                            <title>Josiah Conder: A Memoir</title> (London, 1857)<lb/>Previously published: Eustace R. Conder, <title>Josiah Conder: A
                            Memoir</title> (London, 1857), pp. 161–164.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1812-05-05">May 5, 1812.</date></dateline><salute>My Dear Sir,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I received last night the communications with which you and your highly esteemed friends have favoured me.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Conder had given Southey a series of poems by himself and his friends James Montgomery, Ann
                        (1782–1829; <title>DNB</title>) and Jane Taylor (1783–1824; <title>DNB</title>) and Joan Elizabeth Thomas (‘Eliza Thomas’) (c.
                        1786–1877) to send to the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>. James Montgomery’s ‘Verses, Written on a Blank Leaf in the
                        “Hymns for Infant Minds”’, and his translation of two Italian sonnets (from Pellegrini Salandri (1723–1771) and Francesco
                        Petrarca (1304–1374)) appeared in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.1 (1812), xcii–xciii and civ–cv; see
                        Southey to James Montgomery, 26 March 1812, Letter 2066. At least one poem by Jane Taylor, ‘To the Moon’, was also published
                        in this volume, ciii. ‘A Character, a Fragment’, ci–cii, was probably by Ann Taylor. Conder’s poem ‘The Reverie’ was rejected, much to Southey’s disgust; see Southey to Neville White, 27 September 1812,
                        Letter 2151. Conder later revealed in <title>The Star of the East; with Other Poems</title> (London, 1824). p. viii, that ‘The
                        Voice of the Oak’, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.1 (1812), xcviii–ci, was by ‘Eliza Thomas’, whom he
                        married in 1815.</note> They are sent off this evening to Edinburgh, with my recommendation, little as they stand in need of
                    it; and if the editor<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The decisions about poetry in the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register</title> were probably influenced by Walter Scott.</note> be not already overstocked, or if they should
                    not arrive too late, I have no doubt but that he will be as happy to insert them as I shall be to see them there. The discretion,
                    which you gave me, I so far used as to affix your name to the stanzas with the Latin motto, knowing how naturally every reader
                    into whose hands they may fall will inquire who is the author.</p><p rend="indent1"> Upon the subject of the new system of education, two persons who desire the general good, and have neither party
                    nor private interests to serve, can hardly fail of coming to the same conclusion, when they understand each other, and understand
                    the system. My view of the subject is, that it is a thing of far too great importance to be trusted to so evanescent a source of
                    support as contributions, of which nine-tenths are procured like votes at a county election, by dint of earnest solicitation and
                    the activity of party spirit. It is the interest, the business, and the duty of the State to provide for the education of all
                    those whose parents have not the means of providing it for them. Parochial schools ought to be established in every parish
                    throughout the kingdom. If this were done, it is absurd to expect that the State should not provide that these children be
                    educated according to the religion of the State; that is to say, that they should be instructed in the Church catechism. And it
                    would naturally follow, that the parish priest should become the superintendent of the parish school. My own wish would be, that
                    the parish clerk should always be the master; care being taken to train up a race for this purpose, for thus the character would
                    be raised into respectability.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was a keen advocate of the Madras system of <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">Andrew Bell</ref>. He had recently expanded a lengthy defence of Bell, and attack on <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Joseph Lancaster</ref>, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (August 1811), 264–304,
                        into a full-length study, <title>The Origin, Nature and Object, of the New System of Education</title> (1812). The latter
                        advocated that the ‘school and church establishments ought … to be intimately connected’ (p. 197) and that the pupils at these
                        new national schools ‘should be allowed to accompany the master to church’ (p. 118). Even Bell felt that Southey had gone too
                        far and in a letter of 10 March 1812 cautioned against compulsion in this matter (‘we should draw the children to church by
                        cords of love, and not drag them by chains of iron’), see Southey, Caroline Southey and Charles Cuthbert Southey, <title>The
                            Life of the Rev. Andrew Bell</title>, 3 vols (London, 1844), II, pp. 656. <title>Hints to the Public and the Legislature,
                            on the Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title> (1809), reviewed in <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 480–514 originally contained Southey’s suggestion about Parish Clerks, but the passage
                        was cut out. In the early nineteenth-century Clerks could be full or part-time and duties varied enormously from parish to
                        parish. They might include reading lessons in church, organising the choir, serving at the altar and leading the responses,
                        opening the church, ringing the bell and even digging graves if there was no sexton.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Thus much for the application of the system in England. In Scotland, of course, such alterations are to be made as
                    would suit the catechism to the Kirk (though I believe little, if any, would be required); and in Ireland, when you give it to the
                    Catholics, you must let them teach their monstrous idolatry. But you are not to expect that a scheme will succeed in that country,
                    which endeavours to embrace Papist and Protestant, by carefully excluding all points of difference. The Papists are far too wise
                    to suffer this; and I know that when it has been tried, and a few parents have been found willing to send their children to these
                    schools, the priest has waylaid them with a horsewhip, and horsewhipped them back. I have not seen your friend’s book,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> but Mr. Wakefield<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        philanthropist, land agent and writer on political economy, Edward Wakefield (1774–1854; <title>DNB</title>), author of
                            <title>Ireland, Statistical and Political</title> (1812). He had visited Southey in Keswick in 1811; see Robert Southey to
                        Thomas Southey, 11 October 1811, Letter 1964. The ‘horsewhip’ anecdote probably comes from their conversations.</note> and the
                    Bishop of Meath<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Lewis O’Beirne (1747–1823; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Meath
                        1798–1823. The son of a County Longford farmer, he had been educated for the Catholic priesthood, but converted to
                        Protestantism and became a Church of Ireland clergyman. He had been a well-known Whig, but by 1811 he was increasingly
                        conservative and a defender of the Church of Ireland.</note> have told me several curious facts which tend to show that the
                    horsewhip is of almost as much use to the Irish priest as the crucifix!</p><p rend="indent1"> With regard to the origin of the new system, it is no more a matter of consequence than that it is always of
                    consequence that impostors should be exposed, and honour awarded where it is due. <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Lancaster</ref> is not only, by the admission of his own partisans, a worthless and an impudent fellow, but he has materially
                    injured the system which he has stolen. The mode of teaching spelling and writing at once, destroys entirely the two fundamental
                    laws of the Madras system—that whatever is learnt must be learnt thoroughly, and that every boy must find his level. And by his
                    system of punishment he sows the seeds of the vilest passions.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lancaster had argued for a
                        system of punishments based upon public humiliation of the offender, see <title>The British System of Education</title>
                        (London, 1810), pp. 34–37. These included making badly-behaved pupils wear labels that described their offence, eg. ‘Idle’,
                        ‘Suck finger Baby’. Lancaster assured his readers that these punishments had been tried for 13 years with great
                        success.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> He derives his popularity from the worthlessness of his most conspicuous opponents—John Bowles,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Bowles (1751–1819; <title>DNB</title>), barrister, author, fanatical anti-Jacobin and the
                        subject of long-running fraud allegations. His <title>A Letter Addressed to Samuel Whitbread, Esq. M.P., in consequnce of the
                            Unqualified Approbation Expressed by Him … of Mr. Lancaster’s System of Education</title> and its sequel, <title>Education
                            of the Lower Orders, A Second Letter to Samuel Whitbread … containing Observations on His Bill for the Establishment of
                            Parochial Schools in South Britain</title> both appeared in 1808.</note> Archdeacon Daubeny,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Daubney (1745–1827), Archdeacon of Salisbury 1804–1827 and author of <title>A Charge Delivered to the
                            Clergy of the Archdeaconry of Sarum, on the 26th, 27th, 28th and 29th of June 1810</title> (1810).</note> the Rev. Dr.
                        Hook,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Hook (1772?-1828; <title>DNB</title>), clergyman. He was believed to owe
                        his rapid promotion through the church hierarchy to marriage to Anne (d. 1844), daughter of Sir Walter Farquahar (1738–1819;
                            <title>DNB</title>), physician and confidant of the Prince of Wales. Hook had served as chaplain to the Prince, held a
                        series of valuable livings, including Prebend of Winchester Cathedral 1807–1825, and in 1825 became Dean of Worcester. He
                        espoused political and religious orthodoxy, publishing sermons against Jacobinism and Methodism. Not all his family pursued
                        respectability with such avidity. Hook’s brother was the hoaxer Theodore Edward Hook (1788–1841; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
                    etc.—fellows with whom it is mortifying to think alike upon any subject, because you are sure they would not be right, if it were
                    not for some unworthy motive. The Dissenters are consistent in taking up his cause, but I do not think they are wise in doing it.
                    There is a monstrous coalition of fanatics, infidels, and Roman Catholics against the Church of England. I do not subscribe to the
                    Church; if I could do it, I should be in orders—an office to which my inclination would always strongly have led me. My mind has
                    undergone many changes, and is in many points nearer to the Church than when I forbore to enter it as a minister. Still, I am far
                    from being in communion with it, or from ever expecting to be so. But I am perfectly sensible of the infinite good which we derive
                    from such a Church, and of the dreadful consequences which would inevitably attend its overthrow. Your metaphor of the waste lands
                    is a happy one; what I contend against is that scheme of improvement which would throw down the inclosures. You will agree with me
                    that the great object is to secure the benefit of national education; this can only be done by a permanent parochial
                    establishment. When next I write to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, I will desire him to give you my treatise
                    upon <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">Bell</ref> and the <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Dragon</ref>, which goes to
                    this end.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. <title>The Origin, Nature and Object, of the New System of
                            Education</title> (1812).</note> It is in a spirit of controversy, which is not ill directed when its aim is to expose the
                    falsehoods of such writers as the Edinburgh Reviewers.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Although the <title>Origin</title>
                        did make several swipes at the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, Southey did remove some of his more offensive comments prior
                        to publication. These included a mock-dedication to Francis Jeffrey.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I hope your good father<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The map engraver and bookseller Thomas Conder
                        (1746/7–1831; <title>DNB</title>).</note> continues well. Believe me, yours very truly,</p><closer><signed rend="indent3"> ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>