<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1923</idno><idno type="nines">rce3194</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.78.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1923" type="letter"><head>1923. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1811-05-15">15
                        May 1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/
                        Durham<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.78<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1811-05-15">May 15. 1811.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Harry</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> How do you direct to <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref>, – squiring him, or doctoring him? &amp;
                    if he is to be besquired, (as surely any man who wields the ill-looking weapons represented in the Cyclopædia<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A plate in Abraham Rees (1743–1825; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Cyclopaedia</title> (1802–1820).
                        Gooch was an obstetrician, so this may well be a reference to illustrations of instruments like the forceps.</note><del>xxxxxx the</del> in the plate of surgical instruments may <del>well</del> be stiled armiger<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Someone entitled to a coat of arms and therefore to be addressed as ‘Esquire’.</note> with a vengeance) – What
                    is his christian name? – Is it not <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Robert</ref>? – I will write to him, – &amp; if I could
                    be of any service to him, you may be assured there are very few men whom I should so willingly endeavour to serve. It is not
                    impossible that something may be in my power. I will try to introduce him to the Quarterly,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gooch did become a very occasional contributor to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> – &amp; <del>xxxxx xxxx
                        thing</del> other possibilities occur to me which I will explain to him when you send me his proper <del>dire</del> address.
                    As he is unsettled at this time. I wish we could prevail on him to pay a visit to the North. We shall return by the end of July,
                    &amp; if he would then come &amp; pass a few weeks here, it might be of service both to his spirits &amp; health; – he could
                    review as well as in London, &amp; might mature some literary plan of <del>xxxxxx</del> extent &amp; importance. I have something
                    in my mind which if it appears to him in the same light as it does to me – may give him both pleasure in the execution, &amp;
                    reputation &amp; profit in the end.</p><p rend="indent1"> I suspect that you have not received a letter in which I communicated the intelligence of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> T Southeys</ref> death, &amp; the division of his property
                    between his man Tom<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey’s servant Tom (dates and surname unknown).</note> &amp;
                        M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> William Oliver,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly William Oliver (1775–1830) of Hope
                        Corner, Taunton.</note> – <del>not having any thing</del> &lt;not a sixpence <del>being</del> having been left&gt; to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">his sister</ref>. As neither you nor <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> make the
                    slightest allusion to this I think it likely my letter may have miscarried.</p><p rend="indent1"> You must not let my proffered sponsorship stand in the way of any body else. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary’s</ref> Uncle<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> will
                    doubtless like a godson as well as a God-daughter, &amp; my offer<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Henry
                        Herbert Southey, 20 April 1811, Letter 1907.</note> was only conditional, in case you were not otherwise provided.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am still closely confined by this everlasting Register.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The historical
                        section of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> covering events in 1809 was substantially longer than that for 1808,
                        so much so, that <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">John Ballantyne</ref> insisted that Southey preface it with an
                        explanation; see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title> (1811), [v]–vi.</note> It will exceed 700 pages, &amp; for
                    the whole additional <del>labour</del> extent I have my labour for my pains. Unluckily this is not the worst part of the account.
                    I have a twelfth share of the work, which ought to produce 80 £ for the year: but the increased bulk will eat up almost the whole
                    of the profit, if not quite, for the booksellers (foolishly as I think) are afraid to raise the price in proportion to the
                    quantity, – so that I expect to <del>be</del> &lt;lose&gt; certainly three score &amp; perhaps fourscore pounds, by three months
                    additional labour, the loss of the said three months being equivalent to 150£. At billiards it might be very amusing to play the
                    losing game so well,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The ‘losing game’ was a form of carom billiards (an early type of
                        billiards), in which players scored points by pocketing the cue ball via a cannon off the opponent’s ball.</note> – in this
                    case it is not quite so <del>well</del> pleasant. </p><p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#BunburyHenryWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bunbury</ref> was buried yesterday in our
                    church.</p><p rend="indent1"> Our love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary</ref>. If she puts off her confinement till the
                    latter end of July we shall perhaps see you here during your state of singleness. I beg you will please to remember me to my good
                    friends M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Croft &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Reid &amp; Mr Viner.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                            M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Croft &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Reid: unidentified. Mr Viner was possibly Samuel Viner (c.
                        1740–1815), a minor canon of Durham Cathedral.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> I had a visit the other day from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Collinson of Gateshead, – the biographer of
                            Thuanus.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Collinson (c. 1782–1857), Rector of Gateshead 1810–1840 and author
                            of <title>The Life of Thuanus: With Some Account of His Writings, and a translation of the Preface to His History</title>
                            (1807). Jacques Auguste de Thou (1553–1617), known as ‘Thouanus’, was a statesman, scholar and author of a highly
                            controversial history of his own times.</note> He seems a man whom I should like well upon farther acquaintance.</p><p rend="indent1"> J of Arc, &amp; Madoc &amp; Kehama<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> A fourth edition of <title>Joan of
                                Arc</title> appeared in 1812, a third edition of <title>Madoc</title> in the same year, and the <title>Curse of
                                Kehama</title> went into a second edition in 1811.</note> are all in the press for new editions.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>