<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2263</idno><idno type="nines">rce3534</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4812D.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), II, pp. 323–325 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2263" type="letter"><head>2263. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1813-05-23">23
                        May 1813</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.P./
                        Duke Street/ Westminster <lb/>Postmark: FREE/ 26 MY 26/ 1813<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4812D<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), II, pp. 323–325 [in part].</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Wynn</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> will put you in full possession of the law of the Trade, &amp; can tell you
                    all the facts in Townsends case,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Townsend (1739–1816; <title>DNB</title>),
                        geologist, author of <title>A Journey Through Spain in the Years 1786 and 1787; with Particular Attention to the Agriculture,
                            Manufactures, Commerce, Population, Taxes, and Revenue of that Country</title> (1791). He had entered into an agreement
                        whereby his publishers took the risk of publication and shared any profits equally with him. (The same terms Southey struck
                        with Longman.) Townsend was shocked to discover that his publishers interpreted this as giving them half the copyright of the
                        book in perpetuity. He considered legal action, but was persuaded against it on the grounds that he had no case; see Southey
                        to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 15 April 1812, Letter 2078.</note> when the bookseller would have tried it, &amp; in the case
                    of <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Kirk Whites</ref> Remains<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White</title> (1807).</note> which I very much hope they will now be ashamed to bring to
                        trial.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, [c. 13 April 1813] (Letter
                        2246), 24 April 1813 (Letter 2251), and [c. 18 May 1813] (Letter 2258).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My opinion is that literary property ought to be inheritable like every other property, &amp; that a law which
                    should allow you the use of the trees upon your estate for eight &amp; twenty years, &amp; after that term make them over to the
                    Carpenters Company, would not be more unjust than that which takes from me &amp; my heirs the property of my literary labours
                    &amp; gives it to the Company of Booksellers. – I am afraid you do not agree <del>xx</del> with me in this, – &amp; certain that
                    even if you do nothing more can be done towards a restitution of the Authors rights than simply to make their complaint when you
                    speak upon the subject.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is doing something to get the 28 years absolute.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A parliamentary
                        committee to enquire into existing copyright law was established in March 1813. Its findings led to legislation in 1814. This
                        extended copyright to an unconditional 28 years or the life of the author if longer (rather than 14 years, plus as much of
                        another 14 years that the author might live). This was applied to new publications and those already published by living
                        authors. Posthumous works were also given a copyright period of 28 years.</note> If the authors right of sale were limited to
                    14 years, would it not be practicable to prevent the mode of destroying his interest which you foresee, by enacting that after the
                    expiration of the term from which the copyright was sold, he should be entitled to a certain portion of the profits of the edition
                    upon sale, – a moiety, which would just put him upon the footing that booksellers are readiest to offer.</p><p rend="indent1"> An Author advanced in years can have no copyright to sell except of the works of his old age – the lease of all his
                    others will be pretty far run out. I believe that very little more would be given <del>for</del> by the bookseller for the double,
                    than for the single term. <del>– &amp; that to the author the latter part of the term</del> In reality the latter part of the term
                    is <del>xxxx</del> either worth nothing, – or more than the first. The gourd has produced its fruit &amp; is withered &amp; gone
                    for ever, – <del>The xxx</del> long before the olive begins to be productive. To the great body of authors it is the same thing
                    whether their right of property <del>xx xxxxx</del> expires at the end of fourteen years or <del>xxxx</del> last till the day of
                    judgement; – for even of the books which obtain reputation, not one in ten passes thro a second edition. But to those who
                        <del>acquire</del> really acquire a permanent rank in the literature of their country the injury <del>becomes heavier year
                        after the</del> is heavy indeed.</p><p rend="indent1"> I should rather the right of sale were limited, – it would give the author some share of those prizes in the
                    lottery which now fall, almost wholly, to the bookseller. – The second term would have enriched Cowper.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poet William Cowper (1731–1800; <title>DNB</title>).</note> And if you can give us a lease for life I may
                    possibly be benefitted by it. </p><p rend="indent1"> My labours in the Register end with this volume.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813) was the last issue to which Southey contributed.</note><ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">John Ballantynes</ref> shuffling conduct has been the occasion of my withdrawing from it:
                        <del>B</del> I hope however that he will not succeed in cheating me, as <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">his
                        brother</ref> has the character of an honourable man – a <del>character</del> &lt;reputation&gt; directly the reverse of his
                    own. But for this occasion I should probably have continued the employment, tho the confinement which it imposed was inconvenient.
                    Perhaps I may not at first dispose of my time <del>to be as</del> with equal profit. My first thought is, if <del>x</del> it can
                    be arranged with the publishers of the Register, to write the history of the War in the Peninsula,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832), published by Murray.</note><del>xxxx xxxx xxx</del> using the chapters in the Register – as I did the review of Nelson:<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Life of Nelson</title> (1813) was an expansion of Southey’s article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February
                        1810), 218–262.</note> – that is, retaining what would be injured by alteration. Had I been Historiographer<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1812 Southey had failed in his campaign to be Historiographer Royal. The appointment had gone
                        to James Stanier Clarke (1765?-1834; <title>DNB</title>).</note> the booksellers would have jumped at such a proposal, &amp; I
                    should have found it the most lucrative engagement of my life. Whether they will now let me rescue it from Stanier Clarke is
                    perhaps doubtful. I have such materials by me, &amp; so many channels of information open, that I shall be sorry for the sake of
                    the history itself &amp; of my own reputation (setting <del>xxx</del> aside all consideration of the budget) – if this scheme
                    should not be carried into effect.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall probably, after all, make my journey to London in four or five weeks hence, – an unlucky time, when half
                    the people whom I should like to see will have left it. But if I miss you then, I may catch you on my return, as Ludlow will most
                    likely be one of my halting places, – &amp; Hodnett if <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> should be there. A
                    journey will be serviceable to me. Of late I have had some anxiety about the childrens health, – &amp; some indispositions of my
                    own.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><salute rend="indent3"> Yrs affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1813-05-23">May 23. 1813.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>