<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2325</idno><idno type="nines">rce3596</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS
                        47891.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2325" type="letter"><head>2325. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, [c. <date when="1813-11-09">9 November
                        1813</date>]<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] London November Nine/ 1813/ Miss
                        Barker/ Keswick/ Cumberland/ J. Donnington<lb/>Postmark: FREE/ 9 NOV/ 1813<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47891<lb/>Unpublished.<lb/>Dating note: dating from postmark.</note></head><opener><salute>Senhora Kedora Niâbarma</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Last night I received your note. My notion as to the manner of discharging the high office<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. the Poet Laureateship.</note> to which it hath pleased the best-drest <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> in Christendom to call me is this: To set forth an ode for which the
                    present state of public affairs affords <del>a subject</del> almost too much subject, – because let the writer do what he will, he
                        <del>will rather</del> &lt;is in danger of&gt; falling short of what <del>the</del> events lead the public to expect: – &amp;
                    to publish this by itself in some such form as the Giaour,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Byron’s oriental tale
                            <title>The Giaour</title> (1813).</note> &amp; prefix to it a blank verse Epistle <del>x</del> to the <del>xxxxx</del><ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent"> Prince</ref>, pitched in somewhat of a solemn key, saying something about the office
                        <del>itself</del>, of those who have held it heretofore, of myself, &amp; of the manner in which it behoves me to address him.
                    This I shall set about immediately on my return.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s first poem as Laureate was the
                        New Year’s ode <title>Carmen Triumphale</title>, published, after much revision, as a quarto of 30 pages on 1 January 1814. It
                        was not accompanied by an epistle to the Prince Regent.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The Levee<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s official presentation at Court as Poet Laureate.</note>
                    is appointed for Thursday, &amp; <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> takes me there. There is a possibility
                    that it may be put off, – the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">P.</ref> being apt to do such things, &amp; there is a
                    fainter possibility that in some unlucky mood of preciousness he may thrust unwelcome honour upon me his Poet, by
                        <del>xxxxxx</del> commanding me to dine with him. Neither of these things are likely, but I dare not take my place till both
                    dangers are over, &amp; this exposes me to the risk of not finding one for Friday evening when I go in the morning to look for
                    it.</p><p rend="indent1"> As for the office you know me well enough to smile at the apprehensions of anyone who fears that I may degrade
                    myself by the manner of discharging it. Common sense would prevent me from doing this, even if <del>x</del> any better principle
                    were wanting. Believez-vous me, Senhora, that however inferior my Laureat verses may be to those poems in which my whole heart
                    &amp; mind have been employed, they will be among those which <del>xxx</del> will do me most honour hereafter.</p><p rend="indent1"> What you say about Roderic<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> had past across my mind, – but the intention which I have formed
                    will render it unnecessary.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am in haste. It is now 9 o clock – I have already written one hasty letter &amp; breakfasted; &amp; among the
                    business of the morning is that of seeing Miss Linwoods pictures,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The needlework pictures
                        of Mary Linwood (1755–1845; <title>DNB</title>), which had been on show in Leicester Square, London, since 1809.</note> – the
                    sun is shining accordingly. I dine at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> &amp; sleep there. Tomorrow I dine with
                    Col Stenor<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> a Spaniard who was in
                        Romanas<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish general Pedro Caro y Sureda, 3rd Marquis of la Romana
                        (1761–1811).</note> army, &amp; shall meet there a party of Spaniards. Tell <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref> I saw <ref target="people.html#LovellRobertJr">Robert</ref> on Saturday, rigged him with
                    great coat to his own liking, &amp; attended to his ways &amp; means. He is as well as he can be. – <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is at Bristol lecturing with great success.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge gave six lectures in Bristol on Shakespeare and two on education, 28 October-23 November
                        1813.</note> – My hair was cut eight weeks ago at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>, &amp; ten days ago by
                    the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctors</ref> hair cutter. I make my appearance in full buckle, bag sword &amp;
                        ruffles,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The formal dress required for the Poet Laureate’s appearance at
                        court.</note> – would that you could see me in this masquerade dress! – The bust<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> A
                        bust of Southey, sculpted by James Smith (1775–1815).</note> is finished to the satisfaction of all who have seen it – The
                    little artist means to send you one, &amp; thus prevents me from doing it. – There is no caviar to hand, no Bolognas. So M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Burgess<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The provisions merchants John Burgess &amp; Son, of 107 The
                        Strand.</note> assured me, &amp; we both joined in execrating the tyranny of Buonaparte which had produced this privation. – I
                    have bought a <del>bed</del> small bed-rug, like a horse cloth, to wrap round me in the mail, &amp; fear neither cold nor fatigue.
                    On the contrary I shall be more at rest when I have fairly seated myself in the corner of the coach, – than at any other moment
                    since I left home.</p><p rend="indent1"> And now God bless you all. I expect a line from <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> tomorrow. &amp;
                    shall write in reply to it.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Edith Southey, 10 November 1813, Letter
                        2326.</note> But of my departure I can say nothing [MS torn]tain, farther than it shall [MS torn] as soon as possible, &amp;
                    that if [MS torn] not see me on Sunday next [MS torn] you will hear from me.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall think of the ceremony of the <del>coronation</del> crowning upon the road.</p><closer><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>