<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1805</idno><idno type="nines">rce3076</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS
                        47891.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1805" type="letter"><head>1805. Robert Southey and <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref> to <ref target="people.html#BrowneMrs">Mrs
                        Browne</ref>, <date when="1810-09-12">12 September 1810</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: Mrs Browne/ Ludlow<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47891<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><epigraph><p>[Start of section in Edith Southey’s hand]</p></epigraph><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1810-09-12">September 12, 1810.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Madam</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It gave me no great pleasure to hear that you had all arrived in safety at your distant-dwelling; &amp; that you
                    received pleasant accounts of the young ladies,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably a reference to Wade Browne’s
                        daughters by his first marriage, Lydia (c. 1789–1864), Elizabeth (dates unknown) and Sarah (c. 1793/1794–1860s).</note> whose
                    sweet dispositions &amp; agreeable manners, make them receive &amp; impart pleasure wherever they go.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am not that all surprized that your <hi rend="ital">meek</hi> Mary<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary
                        Browne (dates unknown), Wade Browne’s only child by his second marriage.</note> disapproved of the numerous faces she
                    encountered upon the road: I dare say such little timid darlings feel a real trouble upon those occasions for I can well remember
                    what my sufferings used to be, at six &amp; seven years old, when <ref target="people.html#Frickerfamily">“dear Mama”</ref> was
                    out of sight; even in the house of our nearest relations. <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">My sister Coleridge</ref> quizzes
                    me about it to this day. </p><p rend="indent1"> We are all very much obliged by your kind inquiries. I left my room much earlier than after my other confinement,
                    &amp; felt no inconvenience from it: – the dear child thrives. they are both to &lt;be&gt; Christianed immediately, &amp; we mean
                    to call the new-born <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Katharine</ref>; after <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hill</ref>, who is to stand for her, with <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">my Sister
                        Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward Littleton</ref>. I have only two pieces of news
                    to relate to you from this neighbourhood; the one is that we are to have a regatta on Thursday, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> White<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mr White (d. 1811), a wealthy man who had retired to Keswick with his mistress.</note> – I
                    believe – is the conductor of it, the other relates to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Janson of the Royal
                        Oak,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mr and Mrs Janson (dates unknown), owners of the Royal Oak inn at Keswick.</note>
                    who having refused to entertain a gentleman who came on foot, concluding he was of no consequence, he swears he will spare neither
                    time, money nor pains to see them punished to the <hi rend="ital">utmost rigour of the law</hi>. We hear he has since commensed
                    his operations, he is the son of Alderman Brown,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a son of Alderman Charles Brown
                        (dates unknown), a retired merchant and Alderman of Leeds (Mayor in 1811 and 1824). Wade Browne had been Mayor of Leeds in
                        1794 and 1804.</note> no doubt he is well informed of the nature of the business &amp; will not prove a <hi rend="ital">Madman</hi> as Mrs Janson, she, poor deluded woman, a few days since turned away a Noble Lord from her own door before she
                    had glanced her eye at the Coronet upon his Carriage which she did not discover untill he was on the wing, but her dispair was
                    witnessed by some of her servants who relate the story with no small glee.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwents</ref> arm gains strength very fast, &amp; he will join <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">his brother</ref> after the regatta. The Ponsonby’s<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lieutenant John Ponsonby of the Royal Navy and his wife (name and dates unknown). They were staying at
                        Ormathwaite. Ponsonby gave Southey some information about the Battle of Copenhagen (1801) for his <title>Life of
                            Nelson</title> (1813).</note> are return&lt;ed&gt; they, with M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Calvert,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly the wife of <ref target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">William Calvert</ref>. Her name and dates are
                        unknown.</note> &amp; Miss Christian,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Christian (1759–1831). A neighbour of the
                        Southeys in Keswick.</note> beg to be kindly remembered to you: the latter feels the want of your company in her
                    neighbourhood, exceedingly. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> will long retain a lively remembrance of the many happy days they have passed
                    in your society. they often talk of their delightful visits to you. Poor Lancaster<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Unidentified.</note> called here a few days since to ask if we had heard from his friends. He is much altered by illness that
                    my Sister<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Either <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sarah Coleridge</ref> or <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> did not know him.</p><p rend="indent1"> My Sisters<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sarah Coleridge</ref> and <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary
                        Lovell</ref>.</note> unite with me in kind remembrances to yourself, <ref target="people.html#BrowneWade">Mr Browne</ref>
                    &amp; the young ladies – believe me dear Madam – very affectionately</p><p rend="indent2"> E. Southey<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> to ask if we … Southey: written upside down on fol 2
                    v.</note></p><p>[End of section in Edith Southey’s hand]</p><p>My dear Madam</p><p rend="indent1"> I have requested <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> to leave me a page of the letter that I may
                    request your assistance in a business wherein I am taking great interest. A Bristol youth by name <ref target="people.html#RobertsWilliamIsaac">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Roberts</ref> died not long since of consumption at the age of
                    19. leaving a collection of poems to two of his friends (to be by them published) for the benefit of an only sister. <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Eliza Roberts (dates unknown).</note> – that being all he had to leave her. At the time of his
                    death he had a salary of 80 or 90£ from one of the Bristol Banks: his father <note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">William
                        Roberts (dates unknown), he had been made bankrupt in 1793.</note> had been a respectable brewer, who failed, &amp; obtained a
                    situation in the Customs, just sufficient with the profits of a lodging house, &amp; <ref target="people.html#RobertsWilliamIsaac">Williams</ref> salary, to support in decent comfort a family accustomed to better things. The death of the son therefore not
                    only cut off all their hopes of again rising in the world, but bereft them of a considerable part of their means of support. Since
                    that event the father has been disabled from discharging the duties of his situation by illness. A grandmother makes part of the
                    family, &amp; they are all sinking fast to absolute poverty &amp; want.</p><p rend="indent1"> Under these circumstances it is easily possible that the poor legacy bequeathed by <ref target="people.html#RobertsWilliamIsaac">William</ref> to his sister, <note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Eliza Roberts.</note> may be made far more valuable than he could have had any expectation. One of the <del>friends</del>
                    &lt;persons&gt; to whose care the<del>y</del> &lt;papers&gt; were left (<ref target="people.html#JamesPaulMoon">P.M. James</ref>,
                    a banker at Birmingham) sent them to me, with a history of the circumstances, – he edites them &amp; will prefix an account of the
                    life of his friend. <note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Poems and Letters, by the Late William Isaac Roberts</title>
                        (1811).</note> My advice was that they should be published by subscription, in this way the sale would depend upon the
                    exertions of a few well-disposed individuals, &amp; if they exerted themselves strenuously, about 300£ might be raised, which
                    would suffice to place the daughter in some way of life that might enable her to support herself &amp; her parents in
                    respectability. I am doing my best to swell the subscription list, &amp; I hope the statement which I have thus plainly &amp;
                    briefly made, will justify me in requesting your assistance.</p><p rend="indent1"> The book will be a half-guinea volume, to be paid for on delivery. What merit it may possess I should now consider
                    was its least claim, but the truth is that <ref target="people.html#RobertsWilliamIsaac">William Roberts</ref> was a youth of the
                    most promising genius, ardently devoted to literary pursuits, &amp; certainly (in my judgement) capable of attaining a very
                    distinguished rank, had it pleased God to prolong his life. In his whole conduct, his hopes &amp; habits, &amp; in every domestic
                    relation, he was as far as I can learn from his most intimate friends, or judge from his letters, as nearly as man can be supposed
                    to be, without spot or stain. I am sure that no person who subscribes to the book will consider its cost as ill-bestowed, even if
                    in bestowing the half-guinea they looked to the half-guineas worth. In its form, arrangement &amp; embellishments it will resemble
                        <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry Kirke Whites</ref> Remains, <note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s
                            <title>Remains of Henry Kirke White</title> (1807).</note> – only I believe no portrait is in existence.</p><p rend="indent1"> I must not conclude without communicating to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Browne some information which will probably
                    surprize him as much as it did me. That pamphlett upon the State of Ireland which he formerly sent me, &amp; from which I have
                    made some extracts in the Edinburgh Annual Register, was written by <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Croker</ref>. <note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Croker’s <title>A Sketch of the State of Ireland, Past and
                            Present</title> (1807). Southey cited it as by ‘far the ablest publication upon this subject’ in <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 9 n. *.</note> This I have from undoubted authority. – The affairs of Ireland have
                    often been discussed in the house of Commons since he has been in Parliament, – &amp; yet not a single section of manly, bold
                    plain truth has ever fallen from him there upon the subject!</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> I beg my respects to <ref target="people.html#BrowneWade">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> B.</ref> &amp; his
                        daughters &amp; am my dear Madam</salute><salute rend="indent2"> very truly yours</salute><signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>