<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2507</idno><idno type="nines">rce3778</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 86.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 87–90 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2507" type="letter"><head>2507. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Robert Gooch</ref>, <date when="1814-11-30">30 November
                        1814</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Dr Gooch/ Aldermanbury/ London<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb/>Postmark: E/ 3 DE 3/ 1813<lb/>Endorsement: November 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1814<lb/>Watermark: DICKINSON &amp; Co/
                        1811<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 86<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 87–90 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1814-11-30">30 Nov. 1814.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Gooch</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your letter reminds me that I have something to ask of you. You may remember telling me of a sailor in Yarmouth
                    hospital, after <del>Duncans victory</del> &lt;Nelsons battle at Copenhagen<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Battle of
                        Copenhagen (1801).</note>&gt; (if I recollect rightly) – whom you attended, – &amp; who died in consequence of neglect after
                    you had ceased to attend him, – but expressed his delight at seeing you before he died. Tho I have not forgotten, – &amp; could
                    not forget – the circumstances, I have <del>had</del> acquired a sort of passion for authenticity upon all points where it is
                    attainable, – &amp; you will oblige me by relating the particulars. I am about to compose a paper for the Quarterly, the text for
                    which will be taken from the Reports of the Poor Society,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Society for Bettering the
                        Condition and Increasing the Comforts of the Poor.</note> &amp; the object of which is to show what has been done in this
                    country towards lessening the quantum of human suffering, &amp; what remains to do.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        essay was a long time in gestation, eventually appearing as ‘The Poor’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816),
                        187–235. It attracted a great deal of attention and was reprinted in Southey’s <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title>, 2
                        vols (London, 1832), II, pp. 159–247. It did not make use of Gooch’s story.</note> In treating of prevention, correction &amp;
                    alleviation, I shall have to treat of schools, prisons &amp; hospitals: &amp; respecting hospitals must quote the saying of a
                    Frenchman whom Louis XVI sent over to England to inquire into the manner in which they were conducted. He praised them as they
                    deserved, but added – <hi rend="ital">mais il y manque deux choses, nos curés et nos hospitaliéres</hi>;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘But there they are lacking two things: our treatments and our care’. Southey did not use this story in
                        his <title>Quarterly</title> article. Louis XVI (1754–1793; King of France 1774–1792) appointed a commission, which reported
                        in 1788, to examine how French hospitals could be improved. Southey probably culled his story of the anonymous Frenchman’s
                        view on English hospitals from John Lingard (1771–1851; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Antiquities of the Anglo-Saxon
                            Church</title> (Newcastle, 1810), p. 146, which follows a similar phrasing. The book is no. 1728 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey’s library.</note> – &amp; here with due caution respecting <hi rend="ital">place</hi> &amp;c. I wish to tell your
                    story.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am fully convinced that a gradual improvement is going on in the world, has been going on from its commencement,
                    &amp; will continue till the &lt;human&gt; race <del>of men</del> shall attain <del>the</del> all the perfection of which
                        <del>they are</del> &lt;it is&gt; capable in this mortal state. This belief grows out of knowledge, – that is it is a
                    corollary deduced from the whole history of mankind. It is no little pleasure to believe that in no age has this improvement
                    proceeded so rapidly as in the present, &amp; that there never was so great a disposition to promote it in those who have the
                    power. The disposition indeed is alloyed with much weakness, &amp; much superstition; &amp; God knows there are many disturbing
                    powers at work. But much has been done, more is doing, &amp; nothing can be of more importance than giving this disposition a good
                    direction. <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Percevals</ref> death was one of the severest losses that England has ever
                    sustained: he was a man who not only desired to act well, but desired it ardently; his heart always strengthened his
                    understanding, &amp; gave him that power which rose always to the measure of the occasion. <ref target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lord Liverpool</ref> is a cold man; you may convince his understanding, but you can only obtain an inert <del>consent</del>
                    assent, where zealous cooperation is wanted. It is however enough for <hi rend="ital">us</hi> to know <hi rend="ital">what</hi>
                    ought to be done. The <hi rend="ital">how</hi> &amp; the <hi rend="ital">when</hi> are in the hands of One who knows when &amp;
                    how it may be done best. Oh if this world of ours were but well cultivated &amp; weeded well how like the Garden of Eden might it
                    be made! – Its evils might almost be reduced to physical sufferings &amp; death; – the former continually diminishing, – &amp; the
                    latter always indeed an aweful thing, but yet to be converted into hope &amp; joy.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am much better pleased with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henrys</ref> choice than if he had made
                    a more ambitious alliance.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Herbert Southey had recently become engaged to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa Gonne</ref>.</note> Give me neither riches nor poverty, said the wise man.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Proverbs</title> 30: 8.</note> Lead us not into temptation<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Matthew</title> 6: 13.</note> is one of the few petitions of that <del>xxxxx</del> prayer which <del>x</del> comprizes
                    all that we need to ask; – riches always lead that way. I have seen very little of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref> since she was a child, but before she was born I knew <ref target="people.html#GonneMrs">her mother</ref>, who
                    was then almost in person what she is in disposition – the ideal of whatever is womanly &amp; lovely. <del>You know xxxx xxxxx it
                        xxxxxx xx xxxx xxx xxxxxxx xxxx xx xxxxx of which I xxxxxx xxxx xx xxxxxxx</del>) – she has as fair a prospect of happiness as
                    could fall to any of her sex. I know not what larger portion of the gifts of heaven can be requird than good sense, good nature
                    &amp; good spirits <del>all w</del> with all which <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> is blest in
                    perfection.</p><p rend="indent1"> Why have you not been to visit <ref target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcott</ref>?<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southcott had announced that she was pregnant with Shiloh (<title>Genesis</title> 49:10); see
                            <title>The Third Book of Wonders, Announcing the Coming of Shiloh</title> (1814) and <title>Prophecies Announcing the
                            Birth of the Prince of Peace</title> (1814). Her supposed condition excited tremendous public excitement and ridicule. She
                        was examined by a number of doctors, whose findings were widely reported. Shiloh failed to appear and Southcott died on 27
                        December 1814.</note> If I had been less occupied I should have requested you to go, – not for the sake of a professional
                    opinion (D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Simms<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The respected accoucheur, botanist and founder
                        member of the Linnaean Society. Dr John Sims (1749–1831) had examined Southcott on 18 August and published a statement in the
                            <title>Morning Chronicle</title> (3 September 1814) that she was not pregnant but labouring ‘under strong mental
                        delusion’. In November 1817 he was involved in another controversial pregnancy. Sims was one of three doctors who attended the
                        labour of Princess Charlotte (1796–1817; <title>DNB</title>). The Princess was delivered of a stillborn son and died shortly
                        afterwards.</note> having satisfied me upon that score) – but that you might have got at some of the mythology, &amp;
                    ascertained how much was imposture and how much delusion. – Gregoire has published a Histoire des Sectes in two volumes, beginning
                    with the last century.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henri Gregoire (1750–1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes
                            Religieuses</title> (1810).</note> I shall review it as a second part to <del>my</del> the article upon the
                        Dissenters.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first part of the article had appeared in the <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 10 (October 1813), 90–139. A second part was not written, and Southey’s review of Gregoire was published
                        in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), 1–46.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> You have in Roderick<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, The Last of the Goths</title>, published in 1814. It was the best-selling of all his long poems.</note> the
                    best which I have done, &amp; probably the best that I shall do, – which is rather a melancholy feeling for the author. My powers
                    I hope are not yet verging upon decay, but I have no right to expect any increase or improvement, – short as they are of what they
                    might have been, &amp; of what I might have hoped to make them. Perhaps I shall never venture upon another poem of equal extent,
                    &amp; in so deep a strain. It will affect you more than Madoc,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> because it is pitchd in a higher key. I am growing old, the grey hairs thicken upon me, my
                    joints are less <del>flexible</del> supple, &amp; in mind as well as body I am less enterprizing than in former years. When the
                    thought of any new undertaking occurs, the question shall I live to compleat what I have already undertaken – occurs also. – My
                    next poem will be ‘A Tale of Paraguay’<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> was published in 1825, dedicated to Edith May Southey.</note> – about 1000 lines only in
                    length, its object will be to <del>dress</del> plant the grave with flowers, &amp; wreathe a chaplet for the Angel of Death. If
                    you suspect from all this that I suffer any diminution of my usual happy spirits you will be mistaken.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> My best wishes to <ref target="people.html#GoochMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gooch</ref> – &amp; God bless
                        you –</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>