<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1924</idno><idno type="nines">rce3195</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Previously  published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    222–224.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1924" type="letter"><head>1924. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1811-05-17">17
                        May 1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esqr M.P./
                        London<lb/>Postmark: FREE/ 20 MY 20/ 1811<lb/>MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb/>Previously published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    222–224.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1811-05-17">May 17. 1811.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Wynn</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I thought to have seen you <del>xxxx</del> before this time, but my journey has been so long delayed that I suppose
                    you will have left London ere I reach it. The cause of this has been the enormous length of the Register for 1809, – whereby I
                    lose three months close labour &amp; have the additional recompense of losing the greater part, if not the whole profits of my
                    twelfth share in the work; for the booksellers are afraid to raise the price &amp; it will be well if the increased bulk does not
                    make it a losing concern.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ballantyne was concerned enough about the length of the
                        historical section to insist that Southey explained himself to the readers in a prefatory note; see <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), [v]–vi.</note> However this has not made me out of heart <del>xxxxxxx xxxx</del>x
                    neither have I slighted it in any manner for the sake of shortening so <del>xxxx</del> unprofitable a task.</p><p rend="indent1"> If you have seen <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> he will have told you that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">my fathers <del>remain</del> last brother</ref> is dead,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey’s death was reported in his local newspaper the <title>Taunton Courier</title> on 18 April
                        1811.</note> &amp; has left his property between his man Tom<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey’s servant
                        Tom (dates and surname unknown).</note> &amp; a person at Bristol, with whose family he was intimate,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly William Oliver (1775–1830) of Hope Corner, Taunton.</note> – his last boast being (like that of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southey</ref> before him) that no one of his own name should ever be a shilling the
                    better for him. I feel with respect to him just as I did to his brother, neither angry nor surprized. It has been beyond all doubt
                    a species of madness, – but one which the law does not reach. We had been upon <del>xxx</del> good terms for many years, &amp; I
                    had never given him the slightest cause of offence. If this news should give you a momentary feeling of disappointment it will be
                    more than it did me. As long as I have health, old Withers motto may be mine. <hi rend="ital">Nec habeo, nec cares, nec
                        curo</hi>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Wither (1588–1667; DNB), <title>Wither’s Motto: Nec Habeo, Nec
                            Cares, Nec Curo</title> (1621). The Latin translates as: ‘I have not, I want not, I care not’.</note> The last two years
                    have brought with them a material improvement in my worldly affairs by means of the Quarterly &amp; the Register. – Kehama<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The quarto first edition of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> has sold
                    better than my former poems. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> tells me he has 109 copies left &amp; that he
                    thinks it time to put a smaller edition to press.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of
                            <title>Kehama</title> appeared in 1811.</note> Madoc<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The third edition of
                            <title>Madoc</title>, published in 1812.</note> is in the press also, it <del>xx</del> was <del>xxxx</del> a very ugly
                    book &amp; I will now take care that its appearance shall not discredit it again.</p><p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#BunburyHenryWilliam">Mr Bunbury</ref> was buried in the church here on Tuesday. This
                    of course brought <ref target="people.html#BunburySirHenryEdward">his son</ref> here. He is the first person I ever met after 19
                    years absence, &amp; the total difference between the boy which I left him &amp; the man which <del>xxx</del> he is now
                        <del>xxx</del> produces a strange &amp; confused feeling when I think of <del>xxxx</del> it. <del>Xxxxxxxxxxxxxxx</del> I have
                    his <del>xxx</del> image as vividly in my mind as if it were but yesterday that we were in Deans Yard together, &amp; there is now
                    no trace of resemblance. I have been exceedingly pleased with him – his situation gives him of course great opportunities of
                    information, but in addition to this I have seldom met with so sensible a man.</p><p rend="indent1"> Shall you be in town three weeks hence? I hope to reach London in that time. My stay there will be about a month,
                    most part of it at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>. From there we go to Bristol &amp; if I do not meet <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> there or at Bath, we shall most likely make <ref target="places.html#Llanthony">Llanthony</ref> in our way home &amp; so from thence to Ludlow &amp; Liverpool, halting a day
                    or two at both places in our progress. I shall probably never see you for more than a morning-call till I make a journey into
                    Wales on purpose &amp; God knows when it will be in my power to do that. This additional length in the years register having
                        <del>cost</del> occupied full three months I am thrown just so much behind hand with other engagements, – &amp; it will be a
                    long time before I shall be able to recover my lee way.</p><p rend="indent1"> The last Quarterly had nothing of mine <del>xxxxxxxxxxx</del> neither is &lt;there&gt; likely to be any thing in
                    the next. I had written a long reviewal of Pasleys book,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Charles William Pasley
                        (1780–1861; <title>DNB</title>) had questioned whether British conduct to Sicily had been unwise and had suggested Britain
                        should have ‘taken possession of Sicily for ourselves’, <title>Essay on the Military Policy and Institutions of the British
                            Empire</title> (London, 1810), pp. 171, 163. Southey undoubtedly agreed with this, making the inventionist case in the
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 99. In contrast, the published version of Southey’s review
                        of the <title>Essay</title>, which had been rewritten by Croker, in consultation with Gifford and Murray, dismissed Pasley’s
                        ideas as ‘fraught with dangerous principles’ (<title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (May 1810) pp. 429–431).</note> which is now
                    under correction that it may not give offence to Castelcicali.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Fabrizio Ruffo, Prince of
                        Castelcicala (1763–1832), Sicilian minister to the Court of St James 1802–1815.</note> Our ministry will not believe any thing
                    against that infamous court of Palermo. I thought this was likely enough but was determined at least to make the trial. The
                    Register I have to myself &amp; will open a battery there, which nobody can silence.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey had to wait until <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 422–437 to express his views.</note>
                    – In other points of view the delay of the article was fortunate, some of it having been superseded by Massenas retreat.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French Marshal André Massena (1758–1815). His army started to retreat from Portugal
                        into Spain in March 1811.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> What part have you taken upon the Bullion question? <ref target="people.html#KosterHenry">Koster</ref> has
                        <del>xxxxxxxxxx</del> &lt;shown&gt; that the consumption of gold has of late increased at least fifty fold while the supply
                    has almost wholly failed: &amp; he has, therewith, established a principle of which Locke<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        John Locke (1632–1704; <title>DNB</title>) had argued that the value of money was inversely related to the amount of money in
                        circulation. He also believed that the economy would suffer if a country’s gold inflow from trade fell relative to those of
                        its trading partners, e.g. in <title>Several Papers Relating to Money, Interest and Trade, et cetera</title> (1696).</note>
                    had a glimpse &amp; at which the Ministerial pamphlet<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a reference to John
                        Charles Herries’s <title>A Review of the Controversy Respecting the High Price of Bullion, and the State of Our
                            Currency</title> (1811).</note> hints without <del>xxx</del> appearing to perceive its importance, – that gold is as
                    incapable of being kept at a maximum <del>xx</del> as any other commodity.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Theodore
                        Koster, <title>A Short Statement of the Trade in Gold Bullion: Shewing the True Causes of the General Scarcity and Consequent
                            High Price on that Precious Metal: Also Demonstrating that the Notes of the Bank of England are Not Depreciated</title>
                        (1810). It went into a second edition in 1811, and Koster followed this with <title>Further Observations on Bullion and Bank
                            Notes</title> (1811).</note> Political oeconomy is much talked of as one of the things to be learnt at Edinburgh, – but I
                    suspect it is almost in as imperfect a state as metaphysics, &amp; that the Scotch are in reality no better versed in one than in
                    the other. When the bullion report<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Bullion Committee, a select committee of the House
                        of Commons, had recommended in 1810 that convertability between paper currency and gold bullion (suspended in 1797) should be
                        restored.</note> was first made public <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; I talked a great
                    deal upon the subject, &amp; the more I have considered it &lt;since&gt; the more am I confirmed in the opinion which we then
                    formed of its errors &amp; its danger.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> I had almost forgot to tell you that <ref target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> applied to
                            <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> to know if I would translate Lucien Buonapartes poem!<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucien Bonaparte (1775–1840), brother of Napoleon and author of <title>Charlemagne, ou
                                l’Eglise Délivrée</title> (1814). Southey refused the request.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>