<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2261</idno><idno type="nines">rce3532</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), II, pp. 58–60.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2261" type="letter"><head>2261. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1813-05-21">21 May
                        1813</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/
                        Surry<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmarks: 10o’Clock / MY 24/ 1813 FN<hi rend="sup">n</hi><lb/>MS: Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), II, pp. 58–60.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1813-05-21">May 21. 1813.</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> You know what I have written upon the Madras disturbances.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A mutiny by
                        European officers in the East India Company’s Madras Army in 1809. <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.1
                        (1812), 260–281, for Southey’s account.</note> The Carnatic Debts<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> An incredibly complex
                        issue. The Nawabs of Carnatic had incurred massive debts to the East India Company and to private British traders. In 1801 a
                        deal was struck whereby the administration of the State was handed over to the East India Company, in return for the Madras
                        Government agreeing to pay the Nawabs’ debts. It soon became clear that many of the Nawabs’ alleged debts were not genuine and
                        were based on forged bonds. The Madras Government’s attempt to prosecute a number of people for these forgeries produced
                        inconclusive and contradictory verdicts; and the Government was accused of high-handed actions against local merchants and
                        officials it suspected of being involved in the forgeries.</note> are not touched upon in that Chapter, – I had however gone
                    thro all the papers concerning them which were laid before Parliament, &amp; my opinion was as much in favour of Sir G. B.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir George Hilaro Barlow (1763–1846; <title>DNB</title>), Governor of Madras 1807–1813. He
                        was recalled in 1812 and there was much controversy about his actions during the mutiny of 1809.</note><del>xx</del> &lt;in this&gt; the beginning of the <del>xx</del> business, as it was &lt;in the rebellion&gt; at the end. But in
                    the progress I thought he acted in more than one instance, oppressively. – You will believe me when I say that I should have been
                    heartily glad to have thought him right throughout.</p><p rend="indent1"> If however Marshs book<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The barrister and MP Charles Marsh (c. 1774–1835;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Review of Some Important Passages in the Late Administration of Sir G. H. Barlow, Bart., at
                            Madras</title> (1813). This attacked Barlow’s conduct as Governor of Madras.</note> applies chiefly to the Carnatic Debts,
                    there is no reason why I should decline to answer him upon that point: &amp; upon the general question – the necessity of
                        <del>xxx</del> suppressing the rebellious spirit of the army, &amp; the vigour with which it was done, too much cannot be said
                    in praise of the Government of Madras. I have therefore no other feeling of repugnance at undertaking this task<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir George Barlow’s brother, William (1759–1839), was a neighbour of Herbert Hill’s in Streatham.
                        In 1813 Southey was commissioned by the Barlows to write a defence of the ex-Governor’s conduct. The result was the
                        anonymously published pamphlet <title>An Exposure of the Misrepresentations and Calumnies in Mr Marsh’s Review of Sir George
                            Barlow’s Administration at Madras. By the Relatives of Sir George Barlow</title> (1813).</note> than that it makes me
                    feel, for the first time in my life, like one whose talents are for sale, &amp; who writes not because he has information to
                    communicate, amusement to offer or opinions to enforce, but wholly &amp; solely because he is paid for writing. In this there is
                    something humiliating. But a feeling of pride ought not to stand in the way if there be no stronger reason. </p><p rend="indent1"> I know Marsh, &amp; if we were Bedouin Arabs he would have a right to expect my protection, – for he once ate bread
                    &amp; cheese &amp; drank porter at some lodgings which I &lt;was&gt; occupying for a week in London. He came uninvited &amp;
                    unwelcome as <del>xx</del> well, &amp; <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> in whose
                    company he introduced himself would fain have been excused from bringing him,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Marsh had
                        been born in Norwich and had moved in the same circles as Taylor. In 1795 both had contributed to the locally-published
                            <title>The Cabinet</title>.</note> – for Marsh is a worthless fellow. He was then going to India,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Marsh had obtained a judicial appointment in Madras in 1804, thus dating his meeting with Southey to around
                        this time. He returned to England in 1809 and became MP for East Retford 1812–1818. Southey’s dislike for him can also be
                        explained by Marsh’s consistent support for Catholic emancipation and his opposition to attempts to impose Christianity in
                        India.</note> &amp; <del>x xxxx xxxxxx xx xx xxxx xxx xxxxx</del> &lt;was not without some fear of being shipt off&gt; in a
                    different direction: &lt;for&gt; Among many dishonesties he had committed one which brought him within reach of the law, – &amp; I
                    believe he had recourse to some shifts &amp; stratagems to get safely on board.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Marsh was
                        a controversial figure. His ‘many dishonesties’ reputedly included misrepresenting himself to the electors of East Retford as
                        a Whig, and thus gaining his parliamentary seat by deceit. He also suffered from persistent financial difficulties.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Let me see the plan which is sketched out, that I may chew the cud upon it. The business of course must be kept
                    secret, – &amp; if it will not occupy much time, it had better be done at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>,
                    where any alterations may be made as soon as they are suggested, &amp; no time lost in a distant correspondence. I can come to you
                        <del>xx</del> a month hence. I have a paper upon the History of the Dissenters<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s review of David Bogue (1750–1825; <title>DNB</title>) and James Bennet (1774–1862; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            History of Dissenters, from the Revolution in 1688–to the Year 1808</title> (1812); Walter Wilson (1781–1847;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>History and Antiquities of Dissenting Churches</title> (1808–1814); <title>Neal’s History of
                            the Puritans</title> (1812), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 10 (October 1813), 90–139.</note> to finish for <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, <del>&amp;</del> &amp; also to conclude the fourth volume of the Register, &amp;
                    with it my labours in that work.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813) was the final volume that Southey wrote for.</note> I have long
                    suspected <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn ">Ballantyne</ref> the bookseller of intending to defraud me, &amp; the
                    intention is now pretty plainly avowed. Of course I have given notice that another Annalist must be provided. Some trouble
                        <del>xxx</del> will probably await me, &amp; some loss, – but I take things of this kind easily, <del>&amp; xxxx xx xxxxxxx
                        xx</del> &amp; they give me no vexation.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will let me know if you can receive me the last week in June, – &amp; indeed if you cannot, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Doctor</ref> can. Coxe has applied for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpoles
                        papers.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Coxe (1748–1828; <title>DNB</title>), historian and Anglican
                        clergyman, had asked Southey for the papers of the diplomat Robert Walpole (1736–1810), Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                        Plenipotentiary to Portugal, 1771–1800. Southey had these papers as John May had asked him to write Walpole’s life. Coxe was
                        rumoured to be planning, though he did not write, a life of Jose I (1714–1777; King of Portugal 1750–1777). He was, however, a
                        royal biographer and his <title>Memoirs of the Kings of Spain</title> was published in 1813.</note> – I must have done with
                    them first, – &amp; if you would like to assist me in this, which will save me some precious time, I will send them off to you. –
                    One of the plans which I think of among <del>xxx</del> the ways &amp; means which are now to be provided for, is that of
                        <del>compleating</del> giving as compleat a picture as I can of what Portugal was before the Revolution: – a sort of
                    supplement to the history of the Court,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s unfinished ‘History of
                        Portugal’.</note> – containing all that information which is not matter for history. For this I have abundant memoranda, as
                    well as materials, – &amp; Mr Walpoles papers will be of considerable use.</p><p rend="indent1"> There will be some profit in this, but more of pleasure &amp; reputation. I think also of making some arrangements
                    when I am in London respecting a history of the war in the Peninsula.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> What I have done in the Register is necessarily very
                    imperfect – &amp; for a regular work I think I could without difficulty procure materials from <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M. Wellesley</ref>, &amp; from Government. I have a good channel open at Cadiz, &amp;
                    think I can find one at Coruña, where Pardo,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manuel Pardo de Andrade (1760–1832), priest,
                        journalist and poet. He had roused the Galicians against the French through his paper, <title>Diario de la Coruna</title>.
                        Southey had met him in 1795–1796, see <title>Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (Bristol,
                        1797), pp. 22–23.</note> my dirty acquaintance at <ref target="people.html#JardineAlexander">Jardines</ref>, has done his
                    devoir most nobly with the pen, &amp; more than any other <del>xxx</del> man contributed to <del>keep</del> rouse &amp; keep up
                    the spirit of the Gallegos. I have MS. materials for the Catalan part, &amp; can procure their continuance &amp; the Countess
                        Bureta<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> María de la Consolación Azlor y Villavicencio (1775–1814), a Spanish
                        aristocrat who took an active role in the two sieges of Zaragoza in 1808–1809.</note> will send me <del>xxxxxxx</del>
                    Zaragozana. <del>xxx</del> She is married to D Pedro Maria Ric,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish aristocrat
                        and politician Pedro Maria Ric y Monserrat, Baron de Valdeolivos (1776–1831). He had married the Countess of Bureta in
                        1808.</note> – &amp; there cannot be better means of acquiring every thing respecting <del>xx</del> Aragon.</p><p rend="indent1"> We have had some sickness among the children. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">The eldest</ref> is
                    dreadfully tormented with ascarides. I have not been well myself, &amp; shall be the <del>xx</del> better for change of air, &amp;
                    a good shaking.</p><closer><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>