<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2264</idno><idno type="nines">rce3535</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian
                        Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 29–31 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2264" type="letter"><head>2264. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1813-05-26">26 May 1813</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [deletion and readdress in
                        another hand] To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ <del>Exchequer</del>/ No 9. Terrace/ Buckingham Gate <lb/>Stamped:
                        [partial] Unpaid/ Bge St Westmin<lb/>Postmark: 4 O Clock/ 29 MY/ 1813 EV<lb/>Endorsement: May 26. 1813<lb/>MS: Bodleian
                        Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 29–31 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1813-05-26">May 26. 1813</date></dateline><salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The half bills are safely arrived.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. a half-banknote – a secure way of
                        sending money in the post, by tearing banknotes in half and sending the two halves separately.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is made quite unhappy by these repeated victories of the Americans, &amp; for my
                    own part I regard them with the deepest &amp; gloomiest forebodings.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> American vessels had
                        inflicted a series of morale-sapping victories on British ships on: 19 August, 11 October, 25 October and 29 December
                        1812.</note> The superior weight of metal will not account for all. – I heard a day or two ago from a Liverpoolian, lately
                        <del>from</del> &lt;in&gt; America,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> that they stuff their wadding
                    with bullets, – this may kill a few more men, but will not explain <del>in what man</del> how it is that our ships are so soon
                        <del>not merely</del> demolished, –not merely disabled. <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; I
                    agreed in suspecting some improvement in gunnery, (Fulton<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The American engineer and
                        inventor Robert Fulton (1765–1815). His inventions included the <hi rend="ital">Nautilus</hi>, the first workable
                        submarine.</note> is likely enough to have <del>readi</del> discovered something) – before I saw the same supposition thrown
                    out in the Times.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Times</title>, 18 May 1813, had assured its readers that when comparing American and British ships, ‘the tonnage,
                        guns, and hands [were] nearly the same’, but it might be worthwhile to enquire whether ‘the Americans are possessed of any
                        secret in the management of their guns, in the fabrication of their powder, or in the size and construction of their
                        shot’.</note> Still there would remain something more alarming to be resolved, – &amp; that is how it happens, that we injure
                    them so little? – I very much fear that there may be a dreadful secret at the bottom, which your fact about the cartridges in the
                    Macedonian points at.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bedford’s letter has not survived, but seems to have contained
                        information about the weaponry of HMS <hi rend="ital">Macedonian</hi>, defeated and dismasted by USS <hi rend="ital">United
                            States</hi> on 25 October 1812. It could be connected to the inadequacy and inaccuracy of the ship’s long-range fire, when
                        compared with that of its opponent.</note> Do you know, or does <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref> know
                        <del>an opini</del> a belief in the navy which I heard from Ponsonby,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lieutenant John
                        Ponsonby (dates unknown), who was in 1813 living at Ormathwaite, near Keswick.</note> – that the crew of the Africaine loaded
                    purposely in this manner, in order that by being made prisoners they might be delivered from Corbetts tyranny?<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The naval captain Robert Corbet (d. 1810), whose brutality to his men was well known. In 1809 his
                        crew brought a complaint against him for cruelty and oppression. Corbet demanded a court martial. This acquitted him of all
                        charges except that of punishing his crew ‘with sticks of an improper size and such as are not usual in his majesty’s
                        service’. He was reprimanded but allowed to resume command of his ship the <hi rend="ital">Nereide</hi> and in spring 1810 he
                        was given command of the <hi rend="ital">Africaine</hi>, part of the fleet at the Cape of Good Hope station. The <hi rend="ital">Africaine</hi> was captured by the French off Mauritius in October 1810. Corbet was killed in the action,
                        along with 35 of his shipmates. It was widely, but falsely, rumoured that the <hi rend="ital">Africaine</hi>’s crew had
                        refused to fight, preferring death to victory under their captain.</note> – When <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> was at Malta, Sir A Ball<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Sir Alexander Ball (1756–1809; <title>DNB</title>), politician and naval officer. Coleridge had worked as Ball’s
                        secretary.</note> received a round-robin from Corbetts crew, many of whom had served under him, &amp; who addressed him in a
                    manner which made his heart ache as he was of course compelled to put the paper into Corbetts hands. – One day <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> was with him when this mans name was announced, – &amp;
                        <del>he</del> turning to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> he said to him in a low voice, – here comes
                    one of those men who will one day blow up the British navy.</p><p rend="indent1"> I do not know that the Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of the Macedonian was a tyrant.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 25 October 1812 the USS <hi rend="ital">United States</hi>, commanded by Stephen Decatur (1779–1820), had
                        dismasted and captured HMS <hi rend="ital">Macedonian</hi>, captained by John Surnam Carden (1771–1858). This followed the
                        capture of HMS <hi rend="ital">Mandarin</hi> on 11 October 1812. Although the <hi rend="ital">United States</hi> was a large
                        ship, Carden was heavily criticised for the loss of the <hi rend="ital">Macedonian</hi> and never held an active command
                        again. He remained in the navy and continued to rise through the ranks, reaching full Admiral before his death.</note>
                        Peake<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Peake (1770–1813), Captain of the 18-gun brig sloop <hi rend="ital">Peacock</hi> which was sunk in action against USS <hi rend="ital">Hornet</hi> off the mouth of the Demerara River, Guyana
                        on 24 February 1813. Peake died in the action. His wife was Mary Wordsworth (1780–1853), a second cousin of William
                        Wordsworth.</note> certainly was not, – he is well known here, having married a cousin of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref>, – his ship was in perfect order, &amp; he as brave &amp; able a man
                    as any in the service. Here it seems that the men behaved well, – but in ten minutes the ship was literally knocked to pieces, –
                    her side fairly staved in, – &amp; I think this can only be explained by some <del>new</del> improvement in the manufactory of
                    powder – or in the manner of loading, – &amp;c – . But as a general fact, &amp; of tremendous application, I verily believe that
                    the sailors prefer the Enemys service to <del>that</del> our own. – It is in vain to treat the matter lightly, – or seek to
                    conceal from ourselves the extent of the evil. – Our naval superiority is destroyed!</p><p rend="indent1"> ____</p><p rend="indent1"> My chief business in town will be to make arrangements for supplying the huge deficit which the termination of my
                    labours in the Register<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813) was the last issue to which Southey contributed.</note> occasions. –
                    I wish to turn to <del>current</del> present account <del>the</del> &lt;my Spanish&gt; materials, &amp; still more the insight
                    which I have acquired <del>in the course of four years employme</del> into the history of the war in the peninsula,
                        <del>&amp;</del> – to recast that portion of the Register, &lt;carry <del>in the</del> it on&gt; &amp; bring it forth in a
                    suitable form.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> This became the <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>
                        (1823–1832).</note> This cannot be done without the concurrence of the publishers, – <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref>, <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>. To the two latter I have written,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The letter to Longman appears not to
                        have survived. For that to Murray, see Robert Southey to John Murray, 23 May 1813, Letter 2262.</note> &amp; am about to write
                    to <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames ">James Ballantyne</ref>, who bears a very different character from <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">his brother</ref>. Should the thing be brought to be bear I must procure an introduction
                    to <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M Wellesley</ref>, – that is to <del>xxx</del> the document which I doubt not he
                    would very readily <del>fa</del> supply; &amp; I should have occasion for all the assistance from the <del>public</del>
                    &lt;foreign&gt; office which my friends could <del>procur</del> obtain. To the <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">Marquis</ref> I have means of access thro <ref target="people.html#Hatherton">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Littleton</ref>, &amp;
                    probably also, <del>thro Giffa</del> via <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> thro <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref>. – It may be of use if you make known my wishes in that quarter.</p><p rend="indent1"> Travelling I doubt not, – or rather change of place of air &amp; of the whole moral atmosphere, will be beneficial
                    to me. I meant to halt one day at Leeds, where I can get letters to a Cicerone,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. a
                        letter of introduction to someone who could act as Southey’s guide in Leeds. The most likely person to provide such an
                        introduction was Wade Browne, who had been a merchant in Leeds.</note> – &amp; again at Sheffield with <ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomery</ref>, who as yet knows me only by letter, <del>&amp; i</del> thence if <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G Beaumont</ref> should be in the country – I shall make my way to him at
                    Coleorton. – I am now going for a week to <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref> with the two Ediths,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May
                        Southey</ref>.</note><ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref>, – whom if you
                    were to see her, you would pronounce far too pretty &amp; too good-natured ever to be in danger of <del>a xxxx</del> condemnation
                    to Killbrat.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your old landlord has sustained a heavy loss in his son poor Daniel,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Bedford’s landlord during one of his visits to Keswick was possibly the family of Peter Crosthwaite (1735–1808), a retired
                        naval commander, publisher of maps and inventor of the aeolian harp. In the 1780s he established the first museum in Keswick.
                        Its treasures included a set of musical stones, a stuffed albatross and a pig with no legs. By 1811 the Museum was run by his
                        son Daniel (c. 1776–1847), a portrait painter.</note> – after long confinement, originating in jaundice, he was suffocated by
                    the breaking of an abscess in the liver.</p><closer><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>