<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2012</idno><idno type="nines">rce3283</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        24.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 323–326 [in part]. </p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2012" type="letter"><head>2012. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1812-01-04">4 January 1812</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>/ [in another hand] Exchequer/ J. C. Herries<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        24<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 323–326 [in part]. </note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1812-01-04">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 4. 1812.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Grosvenor </salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Concerning the Devils Advocate<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Henry Brougham</ref>, whom Southey believed was encouraging parliament to summon
                        him to Westminster to explain comments he had published in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>. These had been drawn
                        to parliament’s attention in a long aside in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 18 (August 1811), 420–423n, which had
                        questioned whether the ‘virulent personal abuse … levelled at the most respectable members of the Legislature’ in the
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> was in breach of Parliamentary privilege and hinted that action against the
                        author and publishers might be taken. In the event, nothing happened.</note> I believe in every instance the text of his
                    speech will justify the comment. You have heard of <del>x xxxxx</del> taking <del>the ear</del> the wrong sow by the ear, – he had
                    better take a wild boar by the ear than hawl me up to London upon this quarrel. I should tell him it was true that I had said his
                    speeches were translated into French &amp; circulated thro all the departments of France, but I had not said what has since come
                    to my knowledge, – that when they were thus circulated nobody believed them genuine, – nobody believed it possible that such
                    speeches could have been uttered by an Englishman. I should ask the House (that is his side of the House &amp; of course in that
                        <hi rend="ital">humble</hi> language becoming a person at the bar) – at what time they would be pleased to let their
                    transactions become matter for history, – &amp; I should give <del>him</del> &lt;the party&gt; a gentle hint not to delay that
                    time too long, for <del>when a few years had reduced their</del> reputations like every thing else find their level, &amp; if he
                    &amp; such as he do not get into history soon, – they may run a risk of not getting into it at all. I should speak of the
                    situation in which Spain &amp; England stand to each other, &amp; contrast my own feelings with those which he has continually
                    expressed. I should appeal to the whole tenour of the book whether the design of the writer was to vilify Parliament, or to bring
                    the Government into contempt. And as an Englishman, – a man of letters – &amp; an historian I should claim my privileges.</p><p rend="indent1"> Phillidor<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified. </note> has made his appearance, &amp; shall be returned in the first parcel, – with the
                    reviewal of Azara.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Felix Manuel de Azara (1742–1821), Spanish solider, engineer and
                        naturalist. Southey was particularly interested in his writings on Paraguay and owned copies of his <title>Essais sur
                            l’Histoire Naturelle des Quadrupedes de la Province du Paraguay</title> (1801) and <title>Voyages dans l’Amerique
                            Meridionale depuis 1781, jusqu’ en 1801</title> (1809), nos 89 and 90 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. He did
                        not review Azara for the <title>Quarterly</title>, but did make use of him in numerous writings, including the <title>History
                            of Brazil</title> and the <title>Tale of Paraguay</title>.</note> Out of pure conscience I have promised <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> to take all their S American travellers myself, because I cannot bear that
                    the Edinburgh should gain credit upon this subject, when I am so much better versed in it than any other man in England possibly
                    can be. I am heartily glad the State of S America is in <ref target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blancos</ref> hands,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Blanco White’s review of William Walton (1783/4–1857; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Present
                            State of the Spanish Colonies; Including a Particular Report of Hispanola, or the Spanish Part of Santo Domingo</title>
                        (1810), appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 14 (June 1812), 235–264.</note> – it will be highly useful to the review,
                    – &amp; I hope to himself also, – for he works hard with little benefit, <del>to h</del> &amp; when he has once tried his strength
                    in the review it will not be difficult to find other appropriate subjects for him. I have a high respect for this mans moral &amp;
                    intellectual character, &amp; earnestly wish it were possible to cure him of his vexation by a pension, which never could be more
                    properly bestowed. <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> has smitten the Q. with a dead palsy upon the Catholick
                        question,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Canning favoured Catholic Emancipation.</note> – or else <ref target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco</ref> could supply such an exposition upon that subject as would entitle him to
                    any thing which <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Perceval</ref> could give.</p><p rend="indent1"> Here is a man at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> who acts upon me as my own Ghost would do. He is
                    just what I was in 1794. His name is <ref target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> – son to the Member for
                        Shoreham,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Timothy Shelley (1753–1844), MP for New Shoreham, Sussex, 1802–1818.</note>
                    – with 6000 £ a year entailed upon &lt;him&gt;, &amp; as much more in his fathers power to cut off. Beginning with romances of
                    ghosts &amp; murder, &amp; with poetry at Eton, – he past at Oxford into metaphysics, – printed half a dozen pages which he
                    entitled ‘the Necessity of Atheism” – sent one anonymously to <ref target="people.html#CoplestonEdward">Copplestone</ref> in
                    expectation I suppose of converting him, – was expelled in consequence<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Necessity of Atheism</title>, published in March 1811. It was co-authored with Thomas Jefferson Hogg (1792–1862;
                            <title>DNB</title>), who was also expelled from the university.</note> – married a <ref target="people.html#ShelleyHarriet">girl of 17</ref>, after being turned out of doors by his father – &amp; here they both are
                    in lodgings, living upon 200 £ a year which her father<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Westbrook (1751–1835), had
                        retired from his main business as a vintner and hotel manager, but still owned a London coffee shop and a tavern.</note>
                    allows them. He is come to the fittest physician in the world – <del>At xxx</del> At present he has got to the Pantheistic stage
                    of philosophy, &amp; in the course of a week I expect he will be a Berkeleyan, for I have put him upon a course of Berkeley.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Berkeley (1685–1753; <title>DNB</title>). Southey had given Shelley a copy of
                            <title>Alciphron: or, The Minute Philosopher</title> (1735), no. 270 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library, a series
                        of dialogues designed to combat unbelief; see Southey to John Rickman, 6 January 1812, Letter 2013.</note> It has surprized
                    him a good deal to meet for the first time in his life with a man who perfectly understands him &amp; does him full justice. I
                    tell him that all the difference between us, is that he is 19 &amp; <del>th</del> I am 38. &amp; I dare say it will not be very
                    long before I shall <del>x</del> succeed in convincing him that he may be a true philosopher &amp; do a great deal of good with
                    6000 £ a year, – the thought of which troubles him a great deal more at present than ever the want of six pence (for I have known
                    such a want,) did me. He is brimfull &amp; overflowing with every thing good &amp; generous, – tho the Oxford-men were as much
                    shocked at him as if he had had hoofs &amp; <del>xxx</del> horns, four &amp; forty iron teeth, &amp; a tail with a sting at the
                    end of it. God help us, the world wants mending tho he did not set about it exactly in the right way. – The worst thing which I
                    hate in the world is a rogue atheist, who talks about <del>xxxxx</del> toleration for the sake of destroying religion – the next
                    thing is a Bigot who makes religion a scare-crow, &amp; by his manner of belief proves that he would have believed in one faith
                    just as well as in another. I do not say that it would have been either right or expedient to keep <ref target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelly</ref> at Oxford, – but this I will <del>xxxxxx</del> swear that when they
                    expelled him they sent away more genius &amp; better principles than they kept behind, – that is better in their <hi rend="ital">root</hi>, &amp; which will one prove themselves so by the fruit which they will bring forth.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you Grosvenor</salute><signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>