<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2107</idno><idno type="nines">rce3378</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 3882.  Previously  published: Wilfred Partington, Sir Walter’s
                            Post-Bag (London, 1932), pp. 86–87 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2107" type="letter"><head>2107. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, <date when="1812-05-30">30 May
                        1812</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Scott Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/
                        Edinburgh<lb/>Stamped: Keswick 298<lb/>Postmark: JU/1812/1<lb/>Watermark: IPING/ 1806<lb/>Endorsement: Southey/ 30 May/
                        1812<lb/>MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 3882<lb/>Previously published: Wilfred Partington, <title>Sir Walter’s
                            Post-Bag</title> (London, 1932), pp. 86–87 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1812-05-30">May 30. 1812.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Scott</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Tho I have long owed you a letter, I should hardly at this time have robbed <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> of the time employed in writing one, if a matter of considerable
                    importance to my own worldly interests had not just now occurred. M. Dutens his Majestys Historiographer is dead, &amp; I believe
                    you know that I have long looked on to the situation which he held, as one might properly be given me, &amp; which
                        <del>secure</del> would secure to me a moderate competence.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The diplomatist and writer
                        Louis Dutens (1730–1812; <title>DNB</title>) had died on 23 May 1812. Southey hoped to succeed him as Historiographer
                        Royal.</note> It is in the <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Lord Chamberlains</ref> gift. – <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> immediately applied for it &amp; his application was favourably received. On such an
                    occasion I would not omit any means in my power which might conduce to my success. I have therefore written to <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref>, on whose good offices I believe I may depend, – &amp; I have written
                    to <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> also, but have sent up the letter to <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> that if he thinks it ill-timed, he may put it in the fire. Had <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> been living, I might have wanted no other interest. I now write to you, being sure that if <del>you</del><del>can</del> there be any channel thro which you can assist me, you will chearfully <del>xxx xxx</del> use your influence for
                    getting me appointed to that good ship the Historiographer.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott actively promoted
                        Southey, writing to Lord Melville on his behalf; see H. C. Grierson (ed.), <title>The Letters of Walter Scott,
                            1787–1832</title>, 12, vols (London, 1932–1937), III, pp. 123–124. Robert Saunders Dundas, 2nd Viscount Melville
                        (1771–1851; <title>DNB</title>), had become First Lord of the Admiralty earlier in 1812.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The poem upon Catalonia<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Hawke Locker, <title>Catalonia, A Poem, with
                            Notes Illustrative of the Present State of Affairs in the Peninsula</title> (1811).</note> which you designed to send me
                    was commuted by a not very fortunate mistake for a collection of sermons, which in addition to a similar present from <ref target="people.html#LundieRobert">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lundie</ref> of Kelso made the whole cargo consist of divinity, –
                    except your letter and its accompaniments. Catalonia however may be in time for next year. I have excellent materials for the war
                    in that province in the years 1808 &amp; 9 – had they existed in time, – two printed portions of a critical-military-memoir by
                        Cabanes,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Xavier de Cabanes (1781–1834), <title>Historia de las Operaciones
                            des Exercito de Catalune en la Guerra de la Usurpacion</title> (1809), all three volumes (two printed and one MS) were no.
                        3816 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> &amp; the third in manuscript, sent over by the author in that state,
                    in the hope that it might reach me in time. Indeed I have many friends at Cadiz who take as much interest as could be wished in
                    procuring materials for me. The Countess of Bureta<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> María de la Consolación Azlor y
                        Villavicencio (1775–1814), a Spanish aristocrat who took an active role in the two sieges of Zaragoza in 1808–1809.</note>
                    wrote to me by the last packet, &amp; enclosed a letter from Zaragoza.</p><p rend="indent1"> You probably heard that the liberal hint in the Edinburgh Review concerning the last years Register was taken into
                    serious consideration by the Party.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A long aside (attributed by Southey to Brougham) in
                        the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 18 (August 1811), 420–423n, had questioned whether the ‘virulent personal abuse …
                        levelled at the most respectable members of the Legislature’ in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> was in breach of
                        Parliamentary privilege and hinted that action against the author and publishers might be taken. If it had, Southey would have
                        been summoned to attend parliament by the serjeant-at-arms (i.e. the chief law enforcement office in the Houses of
                        Parliament). In the event, the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>’s suggestion was not taken up.</note> I received information
                    from various quarters that I might expect to be summoned to the Bar of the House, &amp; I know not to whom they are indebted for
                    preventing them from giving this noble proof of their attachment to the liberty of the press. My appearance there would have been
                    some inconvenience, but no injury. I am as much indebted to <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Jeffrey</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> as if their friendly intentions had taken
                    effect, &amp; certainly shall not fail to show a proper sense of the obligation at a convenient season. Of criticism be it fair or
                    foul I should be the last man in the world to complain, the worst which <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref>
                    could say of me as a writer would never have excited any feeling of anger, – but the man must be a rascal who holds me up as an
                    object for political prosecution.</p><p rend="indent1"> I hope to finish the Register<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title> (1812).</note> in the course of a fortnight, reserving the South American
                    matters for next year when [MS torn] will appear to more advantage from the greater scope of events, &amp; when I shall be able to
                    give to the subject the attention which it demands, – for it will be a work of no little labour.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813), 367–421.</note> – Of the political changes which are going on I
                    have now neither time nor heart to speak. Strong measures are required at home to save us from the second part of the Tragedy of
                    Jack Cade.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The widespread public disorder which followed the rebellion led by John [alias
                        Jack] Cade (d. 1450; <title>DNB</title>).</note> And for the Catholic question – to suppose that it can tame the wild Irish is
                    absurd, – but it is not absurd to <del>fe</del> apprehend that it may lead to a Church-Revolution in England, <del>an event</del>
                    which cannot happen without drawing after it a revolution in the state. – a consummation toward which all things seem tending, –
                    but from which Almighty God preserve us!</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> believe me my dear Scott</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>