<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2278</idno><idno type="nines">rce3549</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42551 .  Previously 
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                        Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
                    60-62.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2278" type="letter"><head>2278. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John
                    Murray</ref>, <date when="1813-07-09">9 July 1813</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle
                        Street/ London<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb/>Postmark: E/ 12 JY 12/
                        1813<lb/>Seal: black wax ‘S’ and motto<lb/>Watermark: C WILMOTT/
                        1807<lb/>MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42551 <lb/>Previously
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
                        Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
                    60-62.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1813-07-09">July 9. 1813.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I should sooner have expressed my own thanks &amp; those of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey</ref> for
                    Nelson in his full dress,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. a copy
                        of <title>The Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> if my house had not been
                    in a melancholy state when the books arrived, &amp; for some days afterwards.
                        <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">My wife’s brother</ref>, who came here at Christmas with the intention of staying a few weeks,
                    was then very near the end of a long &amp; fatal illness.</p><p rend="indent1"> The general sort of dislocation which a long sickness produces in
                    a family, with the perpetual sense of anxiety &amp; discomfort attending it, had
                    for weeks or indeed for months rendered me very little adequate to serious
                    efforts of composition, – I should else have been in London ere this. You will
                    see me I think in about three weeks.</p><p rend="indent1"> Meantime I think the sooner it can be announced that I am
                    employed upon the history of the war,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note>
                    the better; – for this is a fit season to announce it, &amp; if my intention be
                    made public it may <del>probably</del> prevent Stanier Clarke from laying
                    irreverend hands upon a subject, which, as Historiographer he is very likely to
                        <del>think his</del> consider his own.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Stanier Clarke (1765?-1834; <title>DNB</title>). Southey, who
                        had canvassed for the post, disliked Clarke and resented his appointment as
                        Historiographer Royal.</note> I am much inclined to think that this is one
                    of those works which might appear at first with advantage in a splendid form, –
                    with portraits &amp; views as well as plans. In that case the plea of large
                    paper copies &amp; first impressions would remove any objections I
                        <del>might</del> should otherwise feel to a <del>xxx</del> list of
                    subscribers, – &amp; the names with which you could begin the list would draw
                    others after them, &amp; probably secure a greater first crop than could else be
                    calculated upon. This is a matter which you must understand far better than I
                    possibly can do. But I am the more induced to mention it as worthy of
                    consideration, because <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharp</ref> to
                    whom I was <del>xx</del> speaking of my undertaking yesterday, suggested the
                    same thing.</p><p rend="indent1"> Was there ever such a book as <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarksons</ref> life of W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Penn!<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Clarkson,
                            <title>Memoirs of the Private and Public Life of William Penn</title>
                        (1813). Southey did not review it for the <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> I
                    received a copy from him while yours was on the road, &amp; really in respect to
                        <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref>, as a man
                        <del>whom</del> to &lt;whom&gt; for public <del>respect as</del> well as
                    individual regard I would not for the world give the slightest pain, – it is
                    best to leave his volumes unnoticed, – tho I dare say he reckons in full
                    confidence upon a favourable report at my hands. If I could make a life of W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Penn<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> William
                        Penn (1644–1718; <title>DNB</title>), Quaker leader and founder of
                        Pennsylvania.</note> that would be in <del>xx</del> any degree interesting,
                    the better way would be so to do, &amp; to avoid all criticism, – but it must
                    needs be a dull task, &amp; I fear it would prove an invidious one, – for I
                    should have to <del>xx</del> show that Penn was only a good man of considerable
                    talents for business, &amp; little talent for any thing else; – &amp; that his
                    name has become conspicuous in history, almost by mere accident, – certainly not
                    by any greatness or merit of his own. He was a Quaker who being rich by
                    inheritance, vested his property in colonial speculations – those speculations
                    happened to succeed, – &amp; he <del>being xx Quaker</del> necessarily framed
                    his settlement upon the principles of his sect. – I knew he was a mere Quaker in
                    literature, but like the multitude I had given him credit for being a great man
                    till <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> undeceived me. –
                    Such is my feeling upon the subject. Nevertheless if it must be reviewed I will
                    do what I can, &amp; serve <del>him</del> &lt;it&gt; as we do a calf’s or a cods
                    head, – conceal its inspiditty by <del>the xxx xxxx</del> &lt;aid&gt; of the
                    sauce.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have written to Cadiz, to Coruña &amp; to Lisbon, &amp; opened
                    fresh channels of information. Here in England <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> has offered all the
                    assistance his office can furnish, which is considerable. Mr [MS torn] made no
                    doubt of <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">Marquis Wellesley’s</ref>
                    willingness to assist us, – but I should be glad of a direct assurance of this,
                    for the use of which I could make of it abroad. – The battle of Vittoria<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The allied defeat of the French at
                        Vittoria, 21 June 1813, paved the way for eventual victory in the Peninsular
                        war.</note> is what I did not expect: there is yet much to do, but <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> will do
                    it, – &amp; this campaign will according to all probability clear the peninsula.
                    Barcelona has always been victualled with great difficulty &amp; cannot
                        <del>xxx</del> hold out against a long blockade; – that once recovered &amp;
                    the work is done. – I hope <del>Mur</del> Sir J Murray has not been too rash at
                        Tarragona;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In June 1813
                        Lieutenant General John Murray, 8th Baronet (1768?-1827;
                        <title>DNB</title>), despite having superior numbers, failed to capture the
                        Spanish port of Tarragona.</note> – <del>but</del> be that as it may
                        <del>xx</del> we are now masters of the field, &amp; the fortresses must
                    fall unless it were possible for the enemy to recover their superiority. Even a
                    contintental peace would not <del>do that xxx</del> effect that for them when we
                    are so near the passes as in reality to be masters of them, </p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent3"> R Southey. </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>