<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2480</idno><idno type="nines">rce3751</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Harry
                        Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos, The Letters of
                            Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 136–137.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2480" type="letter"><head>2480. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1814-09-10">10 September 1814</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>./ Richmond/ Surry<lb/>Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ 13SE13/ 1814; [partial] 10o’Clo/ SP.1/ 1814F.N<lb/>Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 176
                        1814/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 10 September/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi><lb/>Watermark: J Dickinson &amp; Co/ 1811<lb/>MS: Harry
                        Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb/>Previously published: Charles Ramos, <title>The Letters of
                            Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 136–137.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1814-09-10">10 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1814.</date></dateline><salute>My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I wrote to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> in the beginning of last month, telling
                    him that if I did not hear from him in the course of three weeks I could no longer delay applying to his brothers on behalf of his
                    children. A fortnight after my letter was written a gentleman<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge to Southey, 10
                        August 1814, E. L. Griggs, <title>Collected Letters of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</title>, 6 vols (Oxford, 1956–1971), III, p.
                        521. The bearer of the letter of introduction from Coleridge was Zachariah Henry Biddulph (c. 1792–1842), a young Bristolian
                        who was later Vicar of Old and New Shoreham, 1828–1842.</note> brought a few lines of introduction from him, in which he said
                    that I should have received an answer to my letter before that note would reach me. None however has arrived, &amp; indeed I have
                    no doubt but that my letter has never been opened.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> used to receive an annuity of 150£ from <ref target="people.html#WedgwoodThomas">Thomas</ref> &amp; Josiah Wedgewood,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Josiah
                        Wedgwood II (1769–1843), brother of Thomas Wedgwood. He was a partner in the family pottery business 1790–1841 and took over
                        its management in 1805. The annuity to Coleridge had been paid since 1798.</note> given him <del>on an a xxxx xx</del> for the
                        purpose<del>ng</del> of enabling him to devote himself to such literary pursuits as might be worthy of his powers. <ref target="people.html#WedgwoodThomas">Thomas W.</ref> died having settled his half of the annuity by will <del>by</del> upon
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> the other half was withdrawn by the other brother between three &amp;
                    four years ago, on the plea that it was not convenient for him to continue it longer.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Josiah Wedgwood withdrew his share of the annuity in 1812.</note> In reality the <del>condit</del> purpose for which it was
                    granted was not answered by any performance of the implied condition, &amp; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C. </ref><hi rend="ital"> more suo</hi><note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Latin translates as ‘in his usual manner’.</note> had
                    so neglected these friends, that the only feeling which they entertained toward him <del>was</del> &lt;had long been&gt; that of
                    resentment.</p><p rend="indent1"> When <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> from mere caprice thought proper to live in a state
                    of semi-separation from <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">his wife</ref>, he left her &lt;<hi rend="ital">then</hi>&gt; this
                        <hi rend="ital">whole</hi> annuity, for herself &amp; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her daughter</ref>,
                    promising to support the boys<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent
                            Coleridge</ref>.</note> as well as himself. He insisted also that she should have a house which he could call his own. –
                    This building &lt;which I inhabit&gt; consists of two houses under one roof, with a door of communication; our <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Landlord</ref> used to <del>inhabit</del> &lt;live in&gt; the smaller of these tenements;
                    just before his death I took a lease of the two – (they are partly furnished, –) at the rent of 45 £ for the one, 30 for the
                    other. The former was for myself, the latter for <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C.</ref> We formed
                    but one family, but the houses were considered as distinct in point of rent &amp; taxation.</p><p rend="indent1"> When the Remorse<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Remorse</title> was staged at Drury Lane, London, 23 January-12 February 1813. This made it a moderate success.</note>
                    was acted <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> sent <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">his wife</ref> 100
                    £ the whole of which was consumed in the payment of debts previously contracted.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge
                        to Sara Coleridge [27 January 1813], E. L. Griggs, <title>Collected Letters of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</title>, 6 vols
                        (Oxford, 1956–1971), III, pp. 429–431.</note> The two boys are at school at <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>, the <hi rend="ital">schooling</hi> of the <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">elder</ref> has
                    been given him, on the score of attachment to him for his talents, by the schoolmaster <ref target="people.html#Dawes">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dawes</ref>. 10. 10 £ is paid for that of the other, &amp; both are boarded in the village; – their
                    expences, including their cloathing, consume, tho every economy is used, nearly the whole of the £67- 10/ which is all that <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C</ref> has to receive. <del>In</del> Consequently the rent not only
                    falls on me, but I have also her &amp; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her daughter</ref> to maintain, – &amp;
                    she is also contracting debts, tho it is <del>xxx</del> impossible for any person to manage with more frugality.</p><p rend="indent1"> I say all this to you that you may fully understand the circumstances in which these poor children &amp; their
                    mother are placed. The father must be considered as a man labouring under a kind of moral madness, &amp; I <del>hope</del> should
                    hope that his brothers will not let any feeling of indignation against him <del>prevent</del> operate to their injury: – in that
                    case they will indeed be worse than fatherless. The object for which I am now solicitous is to place <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> at the University, – that being the only destination for which he is
                    qualified either by education or nature. <ref target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMary">Lady Beaumont</ref> has offered 30 £ a year
                        <del>for</del> toward <del>that</del> &lt;this&gt; specific purpose. <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Poole</ref> of
                    Stowey (who is his godfather) 10 £. Wherever he go some College assistance must of course be sought for him, &amp; this requires
                        <del>consultation</del> enquiry: if it be to Cambridge he must inevitably go as a sizer; – at Oxford there is a degree of
                    degradation attending the Servitors which should be avoided.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> A sizar at Cambridge
                        University was a student who received benefits such as lower fees or free meals in return for performing set tasks, originally
                        of a menial nature. Servitors at Oxford University were in a similar position; in the past they had acted as servants to other
                        students. They were distinguished by their plain black gown and round hat.</note><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> owing to an order of his fathers that he should learn Greek first
                    &amp; not be regularly taught Latin, is an irregular scholar. He will astonish the tutor with his Greek, more than he will
                    disappoint him in some minor points. But he is very diligent, &amp; of extraordinary abilities.</p><p rend="indent1"> If <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> makes his way at College, (it must be his own
                    fault if he does not, &amp; he is certainly a boy of good heart &amp; good principles) he will be enabled to <del>he</del> assist
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">his brother</ref> in his turn.</p><p rend="indent1"> That <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> may by some fit of exertion afford occasional
                    assistance to his family is always possible, but every day lessens the probability, &amp; increases his own difficulties, – for he
                    is literally living upon the bounty of his friends for the time being. – What I have said of my own part of the burthen I have
                    said to no one but you; <del>&amp;</del><ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam"> Wordsworth</ref> is the only other person who knows it. You are perfectly acquainted
                    with my circumstances, <del>&amp; know that if my ability was equal to my will</del>. But the point upon which I wish you to
                    address <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeGeorge">his brother</ref> is the situation of the children, &amp; <del>the</del> in
                    particular the pressing necessity of putting the eldest forward in that line of life which will soonest enable him to assist his
                    brother</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>