<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1734</idno><idno type="nines">rce3005</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, RS 146.  Previously  published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 273–275
                        [in part; dated 21 January 1810].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1734" type="letter"><head>1734. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1810-01-17">17–21 January
                        1810</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>Endorsement: From/ RS./ Janry 17: 1810 <lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 146<lb/>Previously published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 273–275
                        [in part; dated 21 January 1810].</note></head><opener><date when="1810-01-17">Wednesday. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 17.</date><salute>My dear Rickman</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I am one of those lucky people who find their business their amusement, &amp; contrive to do more by having half a
                    dozen things in hand at once, than if <del>any</del> employed upon any single one of them. It is the <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Printers</ref> fault that you have not &lt;ere this&gt; seen the best of my labours in a
                    ‘tangible shape,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The phrase had been used by Charles Philip Yorke (1764–1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>) in a Commons debate on 27 January 1809 about the accusations of corruption brought against Frederick,
                        Duke of York (1763–1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander-in-Chief of the Army 1798–1810, 1811–1827, and soon became a political
                        joke.</note> – such however are his delays, that more proof sheets are likely to visit you, before you receive the collected
                        volume<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title>
                        (1810–1819).</note> – <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> does not hurry me with the Register,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810), for which Southey wrote the
                        historical sections.</note> &amp; till <del>me</del> &lt;he&gt; hurries me I let it sleep &amp; work at my second volume, for
                    which I have collected a considerable quantity of materials, have pretty well mapped out the arrangement, &amp; am proceeding with
                    the straight forward narration. There are a few books still wanting which are of more importance to one chapter, &amp; for these I
                    have advertised at the end of my Preface.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3
                        vols (London, 1810–1819), I, p. [vi].</note> So many offers have been made me of books which I did not want, that this method
                    may very probably bring in some of those which I do. – They have printed only five sheets of the Register, &amp; have about five
                    more in their hands, – my part of <del>that</del> &lt;the&gt; labour is half done, – when they jog me with another proof, I, shall
                    take another heat, &amp; without hurrying myself <del>wr</del> can write a sheet a week <del>that</del> &lt;which&gt; is as fast
                    as they will print it, leaving my evenings (the best portion of the writers day) for other calls. You will like what I have said
                    concerning the Catholick Question,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. the question of Catholic emancipation. For
                        Southey’s anti-emancipation views, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), esp. 131–133.</note> &amp;
                    not dislike the way in which I have <del>xx</del> discharged a little of my gall upon the Foxites, the Peace-mongers, &amp; Mr
                        Whitbread.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey’s attack on Samuel Whitbread (1764–1815; <title>DNB</title>)
                        and his allies, see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 37–38.</note> – This is a very profitable
                    engagement. They give me 400 £ – for it, &amp; if it continues two or three years (which I believe rests wholly with myself) it
                    will <del>set me y</del> make me altogether at ease in circumstances, for by that time my property in <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> hands will have <del>cle right</del> cleared itself, – the Constable will
                    come up with me, &amp; we shall travel on I trust to the end of our journey cheek by jowl, – even if I should not be able to send
                    him forward <del>xxx</del> like a running footman.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> To ‘outrun the Constable’ was an old
                        phrase that signified getting into debt. Southey is joking that he hopes to break even, though it is unlikely he will
                        accumulate much in the way of savings, by sending the Constable ahead of him, in the manner of a running footman, who was paid
                        to run in front of a rich man’s carriage.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The Quarterly pays me well, 10 guineas per sheet, – at the same measure the Annual was only four.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had contributed to the <title>Annual Review</title> until its demise in 1809.</note> I
                    have the bulky life of Nelson in hand, &amp; am to be paid double.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey’s review of
                        John Charnock (1756–1806; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Biographical Memoirs of Lord Viscount Nelson, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.;
                            with Observations, Critical and Explanatory</title> (1806); James Harrison (d. 1847), <title>The Life of Lord
                            Nelson</title> (1806); T. O. Churchill (fl. 1800–1823), <title>The Life of Lord Viscount Nelson, Duke of Bronté,
                            &amp;c</title> (1808); and James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765–1834; <title>DNB</title>) and John McArthur (1755–1840;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of Admiral Lord Nelson, K.B. from his Lordship’s Manuscripts</title> (1809); see
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218–262. It was later expanded into a full-scale <title>Life of
                            Nelson</title> (1813).</note> This must be for the sake of saying they give 20 G. per sheet, as I should have been well
                    satisfied with ten, &amp; have taken exactly the same pains. In the last number I have only the American Article of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Holmes<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Abiel Holmes (1763–1837), <title>American Annals; or, a
                            Chronological History of America, from its Discovery in 1492 to 1806</title> (1808), for Southey’s appraisal see
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (November 1809), 319–337.</note> – A load of work for it arrived this
                        <del>quarter</del>, evening, &amp; is at this moment littering my floor, just as it was unpacked. It will distil to the amount
                    of 40 G. at the O. P.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> 40 guineas at the ‘Old Price’ of 10 guineas per sheet, rather than
                        the 20 guineas Southey was paid for reviewing works on Nelson. Southey probably used the abbreviation O.P. in reference to the
                        Old Price or ‘O.P.’ riots of 1809 at Covent Garden Theatre, in opposition to increased ticket prices.</note> in the course of
                    the next six months.</p><p rend="indent1"> The next news of my grey goose quill, is, that as I have one quarto just coming out of the press for you, I have
                    another just going in for <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman</ref>.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, published later in 1810.</note> &lt;Though&gt; I suspect it will be less to her taste than
                    any of my former poems. Kehama has been finished these two months, is more than half transcribed, &amp; the first quarter ought to
                    have reached <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames ">Ballantyne</ref> a month ago, but those rascally carriers have delayed or
                    lost it. The days are now sufficiently lengthened to give me some half a hour before breakfast, &amp; I have begun Pelayo,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early name for <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> conquered
                    the difficulty of the opening, &amp; am fairly afloat. Add to all this, that from the overflowings of my notes &amp; notanda I am
                    putting together some volumes of <title>Omniana</title><note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Published in 2 volumes, with
                        contributions from Coleridge, in 1812.</note> (which will I have no doubt pay better than <del>if</del> any of the works
                        <del>from</del> &lt;of&gt; which they are &lt;in the main&gt; as it were the crumbs &amp; leavings) – &amp; then you will have
                    the catalogue of my works in hand, – unless a drawer-full of materials for D Manuels next travels,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s proposed sequel to <title>Letters from England</title> (1807) was never written.</note> which is
                    constantly receiving <del>of</del> some addition, should be added thereunto.</p><p rend="indent1"><hi rend="ital">Mathetes</hi><note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> A letter signed ‘Mathetes’ (‘Learner’) had appeared in
                            <title>The Friend</title>, 17 (14 December 1809), 257–268. De Quincey provided some ideas for the letter, but it was
                        written by the author and journalist John Wilson (pseud. ‘Christopher North’) and his friend Alexander Blair (dates unknown),
                        Professor of English Literature, University College, London, 1830–1836. Wilson was a Scot, but had graduated from Magdalen
                        College, Oxford in 1807 and was living at Elleray in the Lake District – hence Southey’s comments.</note> is not <ref target="people.html#DeQuinceyThomas">De Quincey</ref>, but a <ref target="people.html#WilsonJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Wilson</ref>, – a very odd homo, – who might be shown at Pidcock’s<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The celebrated
                        menagerie at Exeter Change, London, run by ‘the modern Noah’ Gilbert Pidcock (d. 1810; <title>DNB</title>).</note> for a
                    perfect Kelt, – only that <del>xx luckily</del> by some accident he has just been trained enough to come within the &lt;protection
                    of the&gt; Habeus Corpus Act.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Habeas Corpus Act (1679), strengthened the English
                        legal principle that persons could not be unlawfully imprisoned.</note><ref target="people.html#DeQuinceyThomas">De Quincey</ref> is a singular little man, but better informed than any person (almost)
                    that I ever met at <del>the</del> &lt;his&gt; age. – <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref> I know has unaccountably
                    taken a dislike to him, &amp; despises him, but this is one of <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lambs</ref> crazy humours.
                        <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> reply to Mathetes,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Friend</title>, 17 (14 December 1809), 268–272 and 20 (4 January 1810), 305–318, signed ‘M. M.’</note> has the
                    fault of the letter itself, – both are about nothing at all, – things that you &amp; I have never thought about because they were
                    not worth thinking about. It is beautifully written, but &lt;when&gt; you have done with it it is but a <del>xxxxxxx</del>
                    &lt;mouthful&gt; of moonshine, – ex nihilo nihil fit.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Nothing comes from
                        nothing.’</note> – The vice of the Friend is its round-aboutness – Sometimes it is of the highest merit both in matter &amp;
                    manner, – more frequently its turnings &amp; windings &amp; twistings &amp; doublings provoke my greyhound propensity of darting
                    straight forward to the mark.</p><p rend="indent1"> My visit to London must be delayed till <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> is settled at
                        <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>, &amp; then I shall with much pleasure divide my time between his
                    parsonage, &amp; S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Stephens Court. Tell <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        R.</ref> I shall be very glad to see the little girls,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Martha Rickman (d. 1810) and
                        Ann Rickman (b. 1808).</note> &amp; communicate to their father the secret of a pocket-swing, – for which General Bentham<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Bentham (1757–1831; <title>DNB</title>), Inspector-General of Naval Works
                        (1796–1807) and a prolific inventor, sometimes in conjunction with his brother the philosopher Jeremy Bentham (1748–1832;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> would perhaps take out a patent. In April I purpose going to Durham, &amp; taking with me the
                    two Ediths,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May
                            Southey</ref>.</note> of whom the elder has never been out of sight of these mountains since we came among them in 1803.
                    My reason for going in that month is that Don Manuel may attend at the Long-Main,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Long Main was a famous week long cock-fight that coincided with Newcastle races in the last week of April or first week of
                        May.</note> – he has a number of odd things to relate of the Cock-fighters &amp; Fox hunters of the Bishoprick.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Coalition to which you seem to look on is likely enough to take place – if it should &amp; Dutens<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> The diplomatist and writer Louis Dutens (1730–1812; <title>DNB</title>). Southey hoped to succeed
                        him as Historiographer Royal.</note> were to die I might be the better for it, – the country would not.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey might especially hope to benefit if the Grenville group, which included his friend,
                        Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, joined the government.</note> These people have all been tried &amp; found wanting. Look where I
                    will, I can see no good, – the journey to Falmouth seems the best prospect, &amp; yet at my time of life (the grey hairs are
                    coming) – &amp; with my habits, it would be much more agreeable to me to stay at home. I have no hope from chopping &amp; changing
                    while the materials must remain the same. It signifies little who plays the first fiddle, – tantararara will always be the tune,
                    till <del>be a</del> there be an entirely new set of performers. And God knows where they are to go from. Here is Lord
                        Folkestone,<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> The politician William Pleydell-Bouverie, Viscount Folkestone, 3rd Earl
                        of Radnor from 1828 (1779–1869; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Salisbury 1802–1828. Folkestone was a Radical critic of the
                        administration. At a county meeting in Berkshire on 17 January 1810 he had denounced most aspects of their policies, including
                        the consequences of the British intervention in Spain.</note> whom I used to think well of talking like a fool about Ferdinand
                        7<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ferdinand VII (1784–1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813–1833).</note> as our making,
                    &amp; of the danger of an army of foreigners! God help the man. Are we to be bugbeard by a few poor Germans in these days!<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Kings’ German Legion. A British Army unit 1803–1816, made up of expatriate
                        Germans.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> hinted something about <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa’s</ref> folly. He never spoke a word about it to me, – which is some proof that he is ashamed of such a fools trick.
                        <del>God</del> Was ever any thing so absurd! – It is letting every body know<del>s</del>, he feels his education to have been
                    defective, – but as for remedying it in this manner, – it is just as if a man who had been bred up by hand (as they call it) in
                    his infancy, should fancy when he grew up that his constitution had been hurt by it, &amp; put himself <del>to wet</del> out to be
                        wet-nursed.<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Duppa entered as a student of the Middle Temple on 7 February 1810.
                        Southey’s hostile response is probably connected to his own enforced – and uncompleted – legal studies</note>. I am sorry for
                    it, &amp; if any stranger should mention it to me shall feel half-ashamed.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will serve me during the next sessions by sending as many Parl. Procs. as may be of use towards the Hist. of
                    the year.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1810-01-21">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 21. 1810.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>