<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2453</idno><idno type="nines">rce3724</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from
                            the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856) .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 356–359.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2453" type="letter"><head>2453. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1814-07-01">1 July 1814</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from
                            the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856) <lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 356–359.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1814-07-01">July 1 1814.</date></dateline><salute>My Dear Friend,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Yesterday I received your letter, with its inclosure of 50/., a fresh obligation for which I stand indebted to you.
                    Arriving on Thursday, it could not be acknowledged on the same day.</p><p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Chamberlain’s</ref> office, I perceive, is much more slow in its
                    payments than the Exchequer, where they usually pay one quarter shortly after a second is due.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s salary as Poet Laureate was paid by the Lord Chamberlain’s office.</note> The fees, &amp;c. are
                    within a few shillings of 20<hi rend="ital">l</hi>., which somewhat exceeds the first quarter of the salary, but there is also the
                    wicked commutation for the sack<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Part of the Poet Laureate’s traditional payment was a butt
                        of sack. Southey’s predecessor, Henry James Pye (1745–1813; <title>DNB</title>), exchanged this for £27 p.a.</note> to be
                    received, payable at another place, which will more than answer the deficiency. This is paid by William Nicol,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Nicol (fl. 1800s-1850s), printer and publisher. Nicol was also Assistant Paymaster in the Lord Steward’s office and thus had some responsibility for part of Southey’s salary. The Lord Steward, who has charge of the Royal Household’s domestic arrangements, had traditionally provided the Poet Laureate with the butt of sack, as a supplement to his salary. Even after the wine had been converted into an annual sum of £27, this was still paid by the Lord Steward.</note> whom <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> has seen at <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford’s</ref>, and from Bedford he will learn when the money may be forthcoming. Have you received the bust yet?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A copy of the bust of Southey sculpted in October 1813 by James Smith (1775–1815).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The fault which has been committed about the slave trade arose from the principle upon which we treated, which
                    appears to me to have been radically wrong.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Treaty of Paris, signed on 30 May 1814,
                        fixed France’s boundaries and dealt with the fate of its colonies; formally restored the Bourbon dynasty as rulers of France;
                        and committed France to abolish the slave trade within five years.</note> Unquestionably it was a great point to re-establish
                    the Bourbons, and it was good policy to separate the cause of Bonaparte from that of France; this latter point you know I have
                    often endeavoured to enforce. But the French had no merit to plead in deserting their tyrant; their suppleness and their fear made
                    them stand by him to the last, and their capital was in consequence conquered. Blucher<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Gebhart Leberecht von Blucher (1742–1819), Prussian Field Marshal and commander of the Army of Silesia, which occupied Paris
                        on 30 March 1814.</note> was at the gates when they capitulated. France, therefore, had no claim upon the generosity of the
                    allies, but her negotiators, as usual, have been expert at their business, and flattered the crowned heads into an ostentatious
                    display of what is magnanimity between man and man, but folly between nation and nation, under the present circumstances of
                    Europe. Since the days of Louis XIV<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis XIV (1638–1715; King of France
                        1643–1715).</note> the power and the ambition of France have been the curse of half the world; there was now an opportunity of
                    repairing the blunders committed at Utrecht,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Treaty of Utrecht (1713) concluded the
                        War of the Spanish Succession, and was widely criticised in Britain as too lenient towards France.</note> and stripping France
                    of the acquisitions which Louis XIV made. Ministers say that the cessions which we have made were to purchase certain equivalent
                    arrangements on the continent. To this it may be replied that for any arrangements in which we were directly or indirectly
                    concerned, we made an ample equivalent by restoring Gascony, then subject to the British arms.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> British troops had invaded the south west of France in October 1813 and occupied Bordeaux on 12 March
                        1814.</note> But the real truth is, that terms so favourable to France were granted to render the new Government popular; and
                    that now, as in every former instance, the British negotiators have not fully understood their own strength, nor adequately
                    supported the pride and power of their country. “Whatever we may restore,” they should have said, “ is on our part a mere gift.
                    You have no equivalent to offer, and no possibility of recovering what you have lost by arms. We will give you your sugar
                        islands,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Guadelupe and Martinique had been captured by British forces in 1809–1810
                        and were restored to France under the terms of the Treaty of Paris.</note> &amp;c., if you will assent to the abolition of the
                    slave trade; if you do not like the condition, so be it – the islands shall remain as they are.” What possible reply could have
                    been made to this?</p><p rend="indent1"> The evil, however, is not so great in this instance as the alarm. To prevent the introduction of fresh negroes into
                    our own islands is very practicable, and very easy. No kind of commodity is so difficult, or rather impossible, to be smuggled, if
                    the simple regulation is adopted of making every person register his slaves. There can be no importation to St. Domingo,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Haiti, a former French colony, which had finally expelled French troops in 1803.</note>
                    and the islands which we restore have been long enough in our possession to feel the possibility of advantage of doing without any
                    fresh supply; and demonstrated as the impolicy, as well as the wickedness, of the trade has been, I think there is little reason
                    to doubt that the stipulation in the treaty for its absolute abolishment at the time appointed will be fulfilled, even if it be
                    not affected sooner. There are far greater difficulties to encounter with Spain and Portugal. The Prince<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John VI (1767–1826), Prince Regent of Portugal 1799–1816, King of Portugal 1816–1826.</note> cannot attempt it
                    without inevitably losing Brazil. Whether the same consequences would take place in Cuba, I do not know. When you see in my second
                        volume<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819),
                        published in 1817.</note> the long and persevering struggles which the Jesuits made against the Indian slave trade, and how
                    ineffectual were all the efforts of the Government and the Church, – the latter most zealous in the cause, and with agents the
                    most able and the most virtuous, – you will perceive what difficulties are to be encountered in countries where the only
                    alteration which has taken place is in the growth and enlarged commerce of a few widely distant cities.</p><p rend="indent1"> The good in which the slave trade will terminate seems to me to be that of preparing for those countries in which
                    European constitutions are incapable of that degree of labour which is “healthful and necessary, as well for the soul as the
                    body,” a mixed race, uniting so much of the European mind and African conformation as may render them the fit inhabitants of a
                    tropical climate.</p><p rend="indent1"> I love to trace the moral order of things in the history of the world. The aborigines (as we call them) of the new
                    world seem to me, with few exceptions, to have been either so far sunk into a savage state, that upon the great scale of things,
                    they might be considered as barren fig-trees – to be hewn down:<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Luke</title>, 13:6–9.</note> or they were like the Canaanites, some for their vices, and some for their cruelty, worthy
                    of extermination. If the guilt of misery attendant upon such a process be objected, I feel the weight of the objection; but am, at
                    the same time, satisfied that it resolves itself into the great question of the origin of evil: that, comparing it with the good
                    which there is in the world, the evil seems to me as much lost as the filth and impurity of our navigated rivers is in the sea;
                    that what evil there is is temporary as to individuals, and evanescent as to the species, and that a future state sets all to
                    rights. I thought to have said something respecting Norway, and upon the state of things in Spain, but have left myself no
                        room.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Demark had been allied to France since 1807, but by late 1813 was isolated and
                        bankrupt. Consequently, on 14 January 1814, the Danes signed the Treaty of Kiel with Britain and Sweden. Most importantly, it
                        ceded Norway, which had been under Danish rule, to Sweden. The Norwegians responded with a declaration of independence in May
                        1814, but Swedish troops were poised to invade the country, crossing the Norwegian border on 29 July 1814. Eventually, the
                        Norwegians agreed to union with Sweden. In Spain, Ferdinand VII (1784–1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813–1833) had abolished the
                        liberal Constitution of 1812 on 4 May 1814 and arrested the liberal leaders on 10 May.</note> “Roderick”<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> monopolises me just now; I am in all the bustle and passion of
                    the catastrophe, and my next, as far as it is possible to foresee anything, will, I trust, inform you of its happy
                    termination.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> I hope the sea has entirely removed the whooping cough. God bless you.</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yours, most affectionately,</salute><signed rend="indent3"> R. Southey. </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>