<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1743</idno><idno type="nines">rce3014</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Mitchell Library, Glasgow.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 275–277 [in
                        part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1743" type="letter"><head>1743. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ElliottEbenezer">Ebenezer Elliott</ref>, <date when="1810-02-09">9 February
                        1810</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> E Elliott Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Rotherham<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK 298<lb/>MS: Mitchell Library, Glasgow<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 275–277 [in
                        part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1810-02-09">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 9. 1810</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1">The price of Holmes’s<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Abiel Holmes (1763–1837), <title>American Annals; or,
                            a Chronological History of America, from its Discovery in 1492 to 1806</title> (1808); for Southey’s appraisal see
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (November 1809), 319–337.</note> book if I recollect rightly is 18/. – very little
                    considering its solid contents. It has been reprinted in London, you will find references in it to all the historical authorities
                    which you can want.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is a curious circumstance that in the subject which you seem disposed to adopt you must necessarily allude to
                    &amp; most probably introduce as a conspicuous personage a namesake of your own – John Elliott, the Apostle of the Indians, a most
                    excellent, venerable, &amp; apostolic man.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Eliot (c. 1604–1690), Puritan missionary
                        to Native Americans and translator of the bible and other religious writings into Algonquian. His work earned him the nickname
                        ‘the Indian apostle’.</note> Some account of him is given in the second volume of Bogue &amp; Bennets History of the
                        Dissenters,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> David Bogue (1750–1825; <title>DNB</title>) and James Bennet (1774–1862;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of Dissenters, from the Revolution in 1688 to the Year 1808</title>, 3 vols (London,
                        1809), II, pp. 450–456.</note> but Holmes will probably refer you to a more copious biography.</p><p rend="indent1"> The objections which have been made to the style of Madoc<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> are ill founded. It has no other peculiarity than that of being pure English, which
                    unhappily in these times renders it peculiar. My rule of writing, whether for prose or verse is the same, &amp; may very shortly
                    be stated – it is to express myself 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> as perspicuously as possible, 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> – as concisely as
                    possible, 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> as impressively as possible. This is the way to be understood &amp; felt &amp; remembered. But
                    there is an obtuseness of heart &amp; of understanding which it is impossible to reach, – &amp; if you have seen the reviewals of
                    Madoc, after having read the poem, you will perceive that almost in every part or passage which they have selected for censure,
                    they have mist the meaning. For instance – the Edinburgh sneers at the beginning of the 3 section Part 2. &amp; the words My own
                    dear Mothers child – as inane.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 7 (October 1805), 16: ‘this affectation of babyish gentleness’ as a criticism of
                            <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Part 2, Book 3, line 8.</note> Now as for the speech itself if <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Mr Jeffray</ref> had not good feeling enough in his nature to feel its dramatic truth
                    &amp; fitness in that place, it is his misfortune, – but that particular expression would to any person who reflected upon its
                    meaning with a moments due attention, give it a peculiar force. For in that state of society most of the Kings children were by
                    different mothers, – of course when Madoc addressed his sister as his mothers child, more affecting remembrances &amp; more love
                    were implied in that single expression, than a whole speech could convey with equal expressiveness. – The Eclectic ridicules ‘Wilt
                    thou come hither Prince &amp; let me feel thy face’<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ridiculed in <title>Eclectic
                            Review</title>, 1 (December 1805), 906: ‘meagre unharmonious effusions of inspidity’, as a criticism of
                            <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Part 1, Book 3, lines 233–234.</note> – I am utterly ignorant of the nature &amp; essence of
                    poetry, if that be not one of the finest scenes that I have ever been able to produce.</p><p rend="indent1"> The metre has been criticised with equal incapacity on the part of the critics. Milton &amp; Shakespere are the
                    standards of blank verse, – in these writers every variety of it is to be found, &amp; by this standard I desire to be measured.
                    The redundant verses, (when the redundant syllable <del>be</del> &lt;is&gt; any where except at the end of the line) are formed
                    upon the admitted principle that two short syllables are equal in time to one long one. The truth is that tho the knack of
                    versifying is a gift, the art is an acquirement. I versified more rapidly at sixteen than now at six &amp; thirty. But it requires
                    a knowledge of that art to criticise upon the structure of verse, nor is it sufficient &lt;merely&gt; to understand the regular
                    tune of <del>blank</del> &lt;the&gt; metre, – a parrot might be taught that. In the sweep of blank verse, the whole paragraph must
                    be taken into consideration before the merit or demerit of a single line, or sometimes of a single word, can be understood. Yet
                        <del>one of</del> these critics are everlastingly picking out single lines &amp; condemning their cadence as bad. <del>In
                        xxx</del> This might be true if the line could possibly stand alone, – But were I to cut one of the critics fingers off &amp;
                    tell him it was only fit for a tobacco stopper, – that would be true also, – because the act of amputation <del>had</del> made it
                    so. </p><p rend="indent1"> You appreciate the story with true judgement, &amp; have laid your finger upon its faulty parts. This it is to have
                    the inborn feeling of a poet. Of the language you are not so good a judge because you have not mastered the art, &amp; are not
                        <del>read</del> well read in the poets of Shakesperes age. You cannot read Shakespere, Spenser Milton &amp; the Elizabethan
                    dramatists too much. <del>xxxx</del> There is no danger of catching their faults.</p><closer><salute> Yrs very truly</salute><signed> Robert Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1">The Workington notes of Falcon Hodgeson &amp; Co<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A Workington bank,
                            which failed, leading to speculation in its banknotes.</note> – are current here.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>