<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013-05-27</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2309</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce3580</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                  1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                  only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                  redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                        Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                  that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                  additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                  all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>British Library, Add MS 47888. Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York,
               1965), II, pp. 76-80; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp.
               43-45 [in part].</p>
            <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
            <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript
               Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
               Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University
               Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
               Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University; the John Rylands Library,
               Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
               Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public
               Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
               Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne;
               the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
            <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the English Department of
               Nottingham Trent University.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Southey’s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
               <category xml:id="people">
                  <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
               <category xml:id="places">
                  <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
            <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
            <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
            <list>
               <item>corrections from proofing</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
            <list>
               <item>TEI Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="2309" type="letter">
            <head>2309. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <date when="1813-09-28">28
                  September</date> [<date when="1813-10-01">–1 October] 1813</date>
               <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland <lb/>Postmarks: 7
                  o’Clock/ OC 1/ 1813 N. T; [partial] OC/ 1/ 1813<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 4p.<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth
                  Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 76-80; Charles Cuthbert
                  Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 43-45 [in part].</note>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date when="1813-09-28">Tuesday night. Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 28. 1813.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My dear Edith</salute>
            </opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> I have stolen away from a room-full of people at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Barlows,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  > William Barlow (1759–1839), a merchant and neighbour of Herbert Hill’s in Streatham.</note> that I might spend an hour in writing
               to you instead of wasting it at the card table. On Saturday I sent you <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays </ref>
               <del> xxx</del> check for thirty guineas<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Edith Southey, 25 September 1813,
                  Letter 2308.</note> Sunday <del>at twelve</del> I went by appointment to Lord William Gordon,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"
                  > Lord William Gordon (1744–1823), son of Cosmo George Gordon, 3rd Duke of Gordon (1720–1752). He owned the Waterend estate on the
                  west side of Derwentwater.</note> who wanted to take me to see a young Lady. Who should this prove to be but Miss Booth,<note n="4"
                  place="foot" resp="editors"> The actress Sarah Booth (1789/94–1867; <title>DNB</title>).</note> – the very actress whom we saw at
               Liverpool play so sweetly in Kotzebues comedy of the Birthday.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> August von Kotzebue (1761–1819).
                  The Southeys had seen an English version of his play, <title>The Reconciliation; or The Birthday</title> (1799), translated by Anne
                  Plumptre (1760–1818; <title>DNB</title>).</note> There was I taken to hear her recite Mary the Maid of the Inn!<note n="6"
                  place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s ballad, first published in his <title>Poems</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp. 161–168, as ‘Mary’,
                  and widely reprinted thereafter.</note> &amp; if I had not interfered in aid of her own better sense, Lord W. &amp; her mother &amp;
               sisters would have made her act as well as recite it. As I know you defy the Monster,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. the
                  green-eyed monster; a private joke about Edith Southey’s tendency to be jealous.</note> I may venture to say that she is a sweet
               little girl, tho a little spoilt by <del>xxx</del> circumstances which would injure any body, – but what think you of this old Lord
               asking permission for me to repeat my visit, &amp; urging me to “take her under my protection” – &amp; show her what to recite, &amp;
               instruct her how to recite it? – And all this upon a Sunday! So I shall give her a book, &amp; tell her what parts she should chuse to
               appear in, – &amp; if she goes again to Edinburgh be civil to her if she touches at the Lakes; – she supports a mother a brother &amp;
               two or three sisters. – When I returned to <ref target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q Anne Street</ref> from the visit I found <ref
                  type="m" target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> sitting with the <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert"
                  >Doctor</ref>, &amp; awaiting my return. I could not dine with him tomorrow, having an engagement, but we promised to go in the
               evening &amp; take <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> with us, &amp; <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>, if they would go. It will be a party of Lions, where the <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctor</ref> must for that evening perform the part of Daniel in the Lions Den.<note n="8"
                  place="foot" resp="editors">
                  <title>Daniel</title> 6: 1–28.</note>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I dined on Sunday at <ref target="places.html#HollandHouse">Holland House</ref> with an ill assorted party of some 18
               or 20 persons. However <ref type="m" target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharp</ref> was there who introduced me with all due form to
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#RogersSamuel">Rogers</ref> &amp; to Sir James Macintosh who seems to be in that state of health
               that a certain personage &amp; his grannam will not have very long to kick their heels in waiting for him.<note n="9" place="foot"
                  resp="editors"> Southey’s prediction of Sir James Mackintosh’s imminent demise was wrong – born in 1765, he lived until 1832.</note>
               In the evening <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> came in. He had asked <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharp </ref>
               <del> xx xxx xxx</del> if I was “magnanimous”, – &amp; required him to make for him all sorts of amends honourable for having tried his
               wit upon me at the expense of his discretion: &amp; in full confidence of the success of his apology had been provided with a letter of
               introduction to me in case he had gone to the Lakes as he intended to have done. As for me you know how I regard things of this kind: –
               so we met with all becoming courtesy on both sides, &amp; I saw a man whom in voice, manner &amp; <del>xxx</del> countenance I liked
               very much more than either his character or his writings had given me reason to expect.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  Byron’s response was recorded in two letters, to Thomas Moore, 27 September 1813, and to James Wedderburn Webster, 30 September
                  1813: ‘Southey – the best-looking bard I have seen for some time. To have that poet’s head and shoulders, I would almost have
                  written his Sapphics. He is certainly a prepossessing person to look on, and a man of talent, and all that, and – there is his
                  eulogy’; ‘I met Southey; he is a person of very epic appearance, and has a fine head – as far as the outside goes, and wants nothing
                  but taste to make the inside equally attractive’ (Leslie A. Marchand (ed.), <title>The Letters and Journals of Lord Byron</title>,
                  12 vols (Cambridge, Mass., 1973–1981), III, pp. 122, 127).</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#RogersSamuel">Rogers</ref> wanted me to dine with him on Tuesday (this day) – only
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Ld Byron</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharp</ref> were to
               have been of the party – but I had a pending engagement here &amp; was sorry for it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">
               <ref target="places.html#HollandHouse">Holland House</ref> is a most interesting building. The library is a sort of gallery <del>xx
                  xxx</del> 109 feet in length, &amp; like my study serves for drawing room also. The dinner room is pannelled with wood, &amp; the
               pannels emblazoned with coats of arms, – like the ceiling of the room in the palace at Cintra.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  The Sala dos Brasoes (built 1515–1518) in the Royal Palace at Sintra. The domed ceiling is decorated with 72 coats of arms. Southey
                  and Edith would have seen the palace during their stay at Sintra in 1800.</note> The house is of Henry 8<hi rend="sup">ths</hi>
                  time.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry VIII (1491–1547; <title>DNB</title>). Southey was mistaken, the house,
                  originally named Cope Castle, dated from 1605.</note> I slept there &amp; got back to London the next morning before <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Sir Domine</ref> was awake. I borrowed from <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord H.</ref> two Spanish plays connected with the story of Roderick.<note n="13" place="foot"
                  resp="editors"> Probably Felix Arturo Lope de Vega y Carpio (1562–1635), <title>El Ultimo Rey Godo de Espana</title> (1617) and
                  another play, possibly Bartolomé Palau (fl. 1520s-1550s), <title>Historia de la Gloriosa Santa Orosia</title> (c. 1550).</note> I
               read &lt;thro&gt; both &amp; made notes from them in the course of the morning before <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; I started. This was a good mornings work. We got here to dinner. to day I
               did a good days work &amp; tomorrow shall get a spell before we return to town. I see the end of my business here, &amp; shall probably
               see the first proof tomorrow.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was writing a pamphlet entitled <title>An Exposure of
                     the Misrepresentations and Calumnies in Mr Marsh’s Review of Sir George Barlow’s Administration at Madras. By the Relatives of
                     Sir George Barlow</title> (1813). This was a defence of Sir George Barlow’s (1763–1846; <title>DNB</title>) conduct as Governor
                  of Madras in 1807–1813, especially during the army mutiny of 1809. It was a direct reply to Charles Marsh (c. 1774–1835;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Review of Some Important Passages in the Late Administration of Sir G. H. Barlow, Bart., at
                     Madras</title> (1813).</note> It is entirely to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> B’s satisfaction, &amp; in this case that is enough.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Lord W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> is not a little pleased with appearing to be my patron, &amp; I rather expect that he, from
               his intimacy with the Prince, will procure a private presentation for me &amp; take me <del>xxx</del> to Carleton House,<note n="15"
                  place="foot" resp="editors"> The London home of the Prince Regent.</note> in which case I escape bag, sword and ruffles<note n="16"
                  place="foot" resp="editors"> The dress Southey was required to wear for his official presentation at Court.</note> for the present.
               As for the appointment, there is no doubt about it; most probably in the course of the week I shall pay the fees for it, – it will give
               the children three thousand pounds, with an accumulating interest, so that if I should live fourteen years the three thousand will be
               four. This is going so far toward a provision for them, that I am really sincerely glad of the office which enables me to secure
               it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Thursday we dine with M<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Stael.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anne Louise Germaine de
                  Staël-Holstein (1766–1817), the writer and salonnière, who was much feted during her 1813 visit to England.</note> Friday I return
               &amp; dine with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Davis.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reynold Davies (1752–1822), Curate of Streatham
                  and a neighbour of Herbert Hill’s. He ran a school for small boys.</note> Sunday <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> dines with me at <ref type="m" target="people.html#StuartDaniel"
                  >Stuarts</ref>. Tuesday I &amp; the <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctor</ref> dine at M<hi rend="sup"
                  >r</hi> Legges,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hon. Heneage Legge (1788–1844), MP for Banbury 1819–1826.</note> &amp; the
               Saturday following at D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stangers.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The physician Christopher Stanger
                  (1759–1834; <title>DNB</title>). He was a member of a family that owned estates near Keswick.</note>
               <del>xx</del> by that time I expect to be near the end of my business here, – perhaps to have compleated it. You do not know how I long
               to be at home. I must stay about a fortnight in town after my removal: – &amp; then, if it were not for Lucien Buonaparte,<note n="21"
                  place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucien Bonaparte (1775–1840), brother of Napoleon. Since 1810 he had been living under house arrest in
                  England and writing <title>Charlemagne, ou l’Eglise Delivree</title> (1814), an epic poem which it had been suggested that Southey
                  should translate.</note> I think I should write an excuse to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneWade">Mr Brown</ref> &amp; take
               the mail for Penrith. But it is better to delay my return for a few days, – than to lose the opportunity of seeing Lucien &amp; regret
               it for ever afterwards.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">Mrs Hill</ref> wins upon me a good deal. Today she began a conversation with me about
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> &amp; said it was as much as she could do to bear her. One of her
                  sisters,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Catherine Hill had no fewer than six sisters: Margaret (born 1768); Jane (born
                  1770); Dorothy (born 1771); Elizabeth (born 1773); Alethea (born 1777); Mary-Anne (born 1783).</note> returning from Stanton a
               little before <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">the Man</ref> was born called in to <ref
                  target="places.html#CollegeGreenBristol">College Green</ref> with a letter. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss
                  T.</ref> on hearing that her brother was likely to have a child said she was <hi rend="ital">not</hi> glad to hear it, &amp; indeed
               she had not approved of his marrying. She made <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> very uncomfortable
               while she was here by her intolerable humours. however before she went away he made her make over <del>xx</del> her estate to him; it
               is worth about 200£ a year &amp; whenever she dies he will be able to clear off the mortgage upon it gradually. She told <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#HillCatherine">Mrs Hill</ref> that she had all my play things. When <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> escorted her home to Bristol she actually suffered him to sleep at an inn –
               because she would not make up one of her own beds.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> has to return today. His sister<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  Rickman had two sisters. This is probably a reference to Mary Rickman (dates unknown).</note> enquires for you. <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref> will be in town soon. I tell everybody that I am not yet in town, &amp; make
               this my excuse for an apparent neglect for as yet I have had no possibility of calling on many persons, Boswell<note n="24"
                  place="foot" resp="editors"> James Boswell (1778–1822; <title>DNB</title>), son of the biographer and an erstwhile fellow pupil with
                  Southey at Westminster School.</note> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ThelwallJohn">John Thelwall</ref> among the number, –
               &amp; Miss Linwoods<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Linwood (1755–1845; <title>DNB</title>), artist in needlework. An
                  exhibition of her copies of Old Masters were on display in Leicester Square.</note> pictures, &amp; Heaven knows what beside.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I expect that your seal will be finished about Saturday, &amp; if so I shall seal a letter to <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> with it early in the next week. I should like to see him when he receives it
                  <del>xxxx</del> Time passes with a heavy pace, &amp; yet how many weeks are gone since I left home!</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> We have begun fires at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> today – which was not before I wanted one. I
               write in the drawing room – in the inner part of it where I am quite by myself. Below stairs the young <del>xxx</del> Bears<note n="26"
                  place="foot" resp="editors"> Herbert and Catherine Hill’s sons, Edward, Herbert and Errol.</note> put all my accomplishments in
               requisition. The Marquis has profited greatly by my lesson in articulation but Duke Bruin is not so teachable. I am grown very fond of
               them – but how glad I shall be to see my own <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bruinella</ref>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> M de Stael writes such a foot that in a note of hers which arrived this evening to tell me where she lives &amp; when
               she dines I can only guess that the hour is 7 o clock. – The gate bell rings, – &amp; they are come home from next door. I leave my
               letter open till the post arrives tomorrow, – in case there should come a letter from you as I hope there may, – so good night my dear
               Edith, – dear dear Edith good night. </p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Friday two o clock. – I forgot to fold up this letter on Wednesday, – which is rather fortunate as I have seen <ref
                  type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MorganMary">Mrs
                  Morgan</ref> this morning. She tells me that things are looking better than they had at one time cause to fear,<note n="27"
                  place="foot" resp="editors"> The Morgans were in financial trouble; see Southey to Edith Southey 5[–7] September 1813, Letter
                  2299.</note> – &amp; that she &amp; her sister<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charlotte Brent (dates unknown).</note> will
               go to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> &amp; take lodgings there for some little time, – the more willingly as it
               happens to be directly in the road to that part of Ireland where <ref type="m" target="people.html#MorganJohnJames">John Morgan</ref>
               is. In three weeks or a month they talk of going – &amp; by that time I trust to be at home myself.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> We had a very pleasant dinner at M de Staels. <ref type="m" target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> &amp; <ref
                  type="m" target="people.html#DavyJane">his wife</ref>, Bozzle &amp; her husband,<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a
                  nickname for the writer Fanny Burney (1752–1840; <title>DNB</title>). She was a friend of Madam de Staël. Her husband was
                  Alexandre-Jean-Baptiste Piochard d’Arblay (1754–1818).</note> – a Frenchman whose name I never heard &amp; the Portugueze Ambassador
               the Conde de Palmella,<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro de Sousa Holstein, Conde de Palmela (1781–1850), Portuguese
                  Ambassador to the United Kingdom, 1812–1817. He was later Prime Minister of Portugal, 1834–1835 and briefly in 1842 and 1846.</note>
               a gentleman &amp; accomplished man. I wish you had seen the animation with which she exclaimed against <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> &amp; Macintosh for their notions about peace. <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is returned &amp; walked half way to <ref target="places.html#Streatham"
                  >Streatham</ref> with me this morning. I dine at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Davis’s to day. – It was some disappointment not to find a
               letter from home, – I must console myself with thinking upon the one &amp; twenty ducks<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  Southey’s name for his more dilapidated books.</note> which I bought yesterday, &amp; the corner of <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> room in which they &amp; my other purchases of the same kind are placed
               together waiting for the joyful day of packing up.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I saw <ref type="m" target="people.html#ThelwallJohn">John Thelwall</ref> yesterday. His wife<note n="32" place="foot"
                  resp="editors"> Susan Thelwall (d. 1816).</note> has been very ill &amp; has not yet recovered her looks. Algernon is going to
               Cambridge, &amp; if he goes on cramming his head there as he seems to be doing at home, he will kill himself.<note n="33" place="foot"
                  resp="editors"> Algernon Sydney Thelwall (1795–1863; <title>DNB</title>). He graduated from Trinity College, Cambridge in 1818. In
                  1819 he was ordained and from 1819–1826 served as English chaplain and missionary to the Jews in Amsterdam. He was a prominent
                  evangelical and anti-Catholic. From 1850 he was a lecturer in elocution and public reading at King’s College, London.</note> – I
               thought you would have written to acknowledge the <del>xxx</del> money – God bless you. Next week compleats my work &amp; I begin to
               think of cutting off all visits on my return &amp; taking the mail. Once more farewell. </p>
            <closer>
               <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
