<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1865</idno><idno type="nines">rce3136</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), II, pp. 211–214 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1865" type="letter"><head>1865. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1811-02-05">5 February
                        1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry/
                        Single.<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmarks: E/ 8 FE 8/ 1811; [illegible]<lb/>MS: Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), II, pp. 211–214 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1811-02-05">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 5. 1811.</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> An examination of the Arte de Furtar, which I had not read since I was last at Lisbon, convinces me that it is not
                        Vieyra’s.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Arte de Furtar</title> (1652). Now attributed to the Jesuit Manuel de Costa (1601–1667), but at this time thought to be
                        by the Jesuit missionary, diplomat and writer Antonio Vieira (1608–1697). Southey’s copy was no. 3772 in the sale catalogue of
                        his library.</note> He speaks as an eyewitness of things in Algarve &amp; in Castille, – now it does not appear either from
                    his life or letters that he had been in either country. It has nothing of his character or manner, – I think too that I perceive a
                    mode of expression &lt;which&gt; never occur<del>ring</del> in any of his undisputed works. – The defence of the Inquisition would
                    not have come from Vieyra. On the whole I have not a doubt upon the subject. </p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames ">Ballantyne</ref> watches, with all the anxiety of a printer &amp; publisher over the
                    Register, &amp; serves me as a safety-valve. Not that there can be any political danger, – the <del>section</del> opinions of the
                    book are a sufficient security against that; – but he keeps a keen <del>x</del> eye upon any thing which might by possibility
                    injure the sale. My second vol.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>
                        (1811).</note> makes vigorous war upon the <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdettites</ref>. I do not apprehend any
                    possible inconvenience to myself from the freedom with which it is written, – that which so strenuously supports the Government
                    both Church &amp; State, may be allowed to censure the Administration, – &amp; as for any personal offence which might be taken,
                    if any man were fool enough to challenge me, I should turn over the correspondence to a Lawyer, – first taking the opportunity of
                    delivering in a summary manner my opinions respecting duelling. </p><p rend="indent1"> I urged <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> to double the intended number of
                        Omniana<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Omniana, or Horae Otiosiores</title> (1812), published in two volumes.</note> volumes <del>xxxxx</del> merely for the
                    sake of making him do something for his family, this requiring literally no other trouble than either cutting out of his
                    commonplace books what has for years been accumulating there, – or marking the passages off for a transcriber. He promised to add
                    two volumes, – &amp; has contributed about one sheet, which I <del>xxx</del> dare say, unless he soon returns to Cumberland will
                    be all.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#RobinsonHenryCrabb">Robinson</ref> is the man who introduced me to <ref target="people.html#AbellaManuel">Abella</ref> &amp; Gen. Caroll<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Parker Carrol (1776–1842), liaison officer
                        between the British and Spanish forces. Later promoted to Major-General and Field Marshal in the Spanish Army.</note> who
                    writes to say that he will obtain for me an account of Romanas<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish general Pedro
                        Caro y Sureda, 3rd Marquis of la Romana (1761–1811).</note> operations from R. himself. This portion of the years annals I
                    hope will be far less imperfect than in the former volume. I have also satisfied myself in the Walcheren affair.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Walcheren Campaign, an unsuccessful British expedition to the Netherlands in 1809. The plan
                        had been to open another front in the war against Napoleon. Although there was little actual fighting, the British forces were
                        severely depleted by a sickness quickly dubbed the ‘Walcheren Fever’. For Southey’s account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register,
                            for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 660–692.</note><ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is my right hand in supplying all parl. documents &amp; much private
                    information beside. Some also I obtain from <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, &amp; I have access to the
                    Admiralty thro <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Bedfords brother</ref>, – tho what I wanted was not to be found. </p><p rend="indent1"> With regard to Kehama<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> I was perfectly aware that I was planting acorns while my contemporaries
                    were setting Turkey Beans. The oak will grow, &amp; tho I may never sit under its shade my children will. Of the Lady of the Lake
                    25,000 copies have been printed,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott’s <title>The Lady of the Lake</title> (1810). It
                        sold over 20,000 copies in the year of its publication.</note> of Kehama 500. – &amp; if they sell in seven years I shall be
                        surprized.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was being unduly pessimistic. <title>Kehama</title> went into three
                        editions in two years.</note> It is of no consequence. My annual &amp; quarterly labours now support me &amp; enable me to
                        <del>pay off</del> &lt;lessen&gt; a debt to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">J May</ref> which I expect to pay off entirely
                    in another year.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The debt had been incurred in paying for Henry Herbert Southey’s
                        education; see Southey to John May, 9 August 1810, Letter 1799.</note> Meantime my property in <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> hands is clearing off its mortgages, – &amp; the sale of <del>all</del> the
                    current edition will leave a balance in my favour. So as I feel no want of <del>the</del> &lt;any&gt; profit from those works
                    which are for futurity, I am compleatly indifferent concerning their immediate success. The only effect the total non-sale of
                    Kehama could have would be to make me take measures against the iniquitous laws of literary property, &amp; convert the other
                    poems which I hope to write into so many post-obits. – The fault which you point out in Kehama arose in the way such faults are
                    most likely to arise, – in correction, I had written</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Whereon the wood nymphs lie,</l><l rend="indent3"> Their languid limbs dispread</l><l rend="indent3"> In summers sultry hours, – </l></lg><p rend="indent1">And, having occasion to use the word <hi rend="ital">dispread</hi> elsewhere in the same paragraph struck it out, –
                    without perceiving that this omission made the use of the preceding verb improper.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), Book 16, lines 98–99. As published the lines read: ‘Whereon the Wood Nymphs lie/
                        Their languid limbs in summer’s sultry hours.’</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I go on slowly with Pelayo,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early name for <title>Roderick, the Last
                            of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> – only a few lines before breakfast. <del>Xxxx</del> Other subjects are floating in my
                    head, particularly that upon Philips war,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> King Philip’s War, or Metacom’s Rebellion,
                        1675–1676. An armed conflict between English colonists and the native American inhabitants of New England. Southey’s poem was
                        ‘Oliver Newman’, left incomplete at his death.</note> which was pointed out in the reviewal of Holmes’s American Annals.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Abiel Holmes (1763–1837), <title>American Annals; or, a Chronological History of America,
                            from its Discovery in 1492 to 1806</title> (1808), for Southey’s appraisal see <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2
                        (November 1809), 319–337 (esp. 323 which recommended Philip’s War as ‘peculiarly fitted for poetry’).</note> It has almost
                    matured into a compleat fable, – &amp; you will smile to hear that the principal personage is to be a primitive Quaker, –
                    certainly a character new to heroic poetry. I am undetermined upon the metre, – it has long been a favourite project of mine to
                    write one poem in hexameters written of course by accent, – &amp; formed upon the model of the Greek or German. The thing is
                    practicable, experto crede Roberto.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Believe Robert who has had experience in the
                        matter’.</note> I can write them with as much facility as any other metre; – but they will not suit a subject which requires
                    to have some of its parts pitched in a high key, – for rapidity they are unequalled, they fail in solemnity, they are unfit for
                    the dramatic parts of poetry, &amp; yet will not, I think allow well of any transition to another mode of verse.</p><p rend="indent1"> Tell <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> that, God willing, she will see me early in May. – <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Her god-daughter</ref> is not a thriving child, in fact the season has been unusually sickly,
                    owing perhaps to the very variable weather we have had. One or other of the children has been ailing for the last two months,
                    sometimes two, three, or even all four at once. – I long to see <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Don Duardos</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Capitaneus</ref> need not be much puzzled in finding paper for his third
                        volume,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Burney’s mammoth <title>Chronological History of the Discoveries in the South
                            Sea or Pacific Ocean</title> (1803–1817).</note> as he has to chuse whether it shall be of the size of the first or the
                    second, – he having contrived not to match them by about half an inch.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am going to send for Dulan’s<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The London-based booksellers and publishers
                        A. Dulan &amp; Co., who specialised in books in French.</note> &amp; Cuthell’s<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Cuthell (d. 1818), a bookseller whose premises were in Middle Row, Holborn.</note> Catalogues.</p><closer><salute rend="indent6"> God bless you.</salute><signed rend="indent7"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>