<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>                      
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <title level="a">Appendix 4</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
            <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
            
            <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
               <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Director</resp>
               <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp> Editor</resp>
               <name />
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2024-04-08</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
               University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                  reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                  it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                  and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                  amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                  Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                  accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                  as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                  in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                  editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                  for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                  conditions: 
                  <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                        purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                        forms other than their current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                  to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                  of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                  elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                  edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                  to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                  can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                  to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="edition">Appendix4Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
            <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Appendix 4</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
                  <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/part7/Appendix4"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" />
                  <title level="s" />
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                        University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                  " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                  except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                  have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
               <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                  has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                  etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
               font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
            <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
            <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
            <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
               <term subtype="tags" />
               <term subtype="tags" />
               <term subtype="tags" />
               <term subtype="tags" />
               <term subtype="tags" />
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name />
            <date />
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="paratext">
            <head rend="bold">Appendix 4</head>
           
            <p rend="bold">Southey’s manuscript drafts of his letter to the <title>Courier</title> 1824</p>
            <p>This Appendix makes available annotated transcripts of two manuscripts, Huntington Library, HM 6656, relating to Southey’s letter to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title> (see Letter 4289), published in the <title>Courier</title> on 13 December 1824. Southey’s addition of his own footnotes means that both drafts, especially 4.1, have complex layouts. We have therefore used folio numbers, in square brackets, to show this and Southey’s drafting process.</p>
      <lb/>      
            <div type="letter" n="4.1">
            <head rend="bold">4.1 Robert Southey to the <ref type="a" target="people.html#MudfordWilliam">Editor of the <title>Courier</title></ref>, [1824]</head>
            <p>Watermark: Kingsford/ 1814</p>
            <p>MS: Huntington Library, HM 6656. ALS; 7p.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>[fol. 1r]</p>
            <p rend="center">To the Editor of the Courier.</p>
            <p rend="center">—————</p>
            <p>Sir</p>
            <p rend="indent1">On two former occasions you have allowed me thro the channel of your Journal to contradict a calumnious accusation as publicly as it had been preferred;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 16 June 1815, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Four</title>, Letter 2616; and Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776.</note> &#38; tho in these days of slander, such things hardly deserve refutation, there are reasons which induce me once more to request a similar favour. </p>
            <p rend="indent1">Some <del>An</del> extracts from Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Medwins recent publication of Lord Byrons Conversations<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Medwin (1788–1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron: Noted During a Residence with his Lordship at Pisa, in the Years 1821 and 1822</title> (1824).</note> has been transmitted me by <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">a friend</ref>, who happening to know what the facts are which are there falsified, is of opinion that it would not misbecome me to state them at this time. <del>The</del> &#60;following&#62; <del>words which are given in that volume as</del> &#60;<del>having proceeded from his Ldsp</del>&#62; <del>Lord Byrons are as follows</del> &#60;Now then to the point. The following speech is reported by C<hi rend="sup">pt</hi> Medwin as <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref>&#62;: </p>
            <p rend="indent1">“I am glad M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey owns that article on “Foliage*”, which excited my choler so much. But who else could have been the author? Who but Southey would have had the baseness, under pretext of reviewing the work of one man, insidiously to make it a nest-egg for hatching malicious calumnies against others? – I say nothing of the critique itself on Foliage; – but what was the object of that article? I repeat, to vilify &#38; scatter his dark &#38; devilish insinuations against me &#38; others. – Shame on the man who could wound an already bleeding heart; – be barbarous enough to revive the memory of an event that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> was perfectly innocent of, &#38; found scandal on falsehood! <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> taxed him with writing that article some years ago; &#38; he had the audacity to admit that he had treasured up some opinions of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelleys</ref> ten years before when he was on a visit at Keswick, &#38; had made a note of them at the time.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Medwin (1788–1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron: Noted During a Residence with his Lordship at Pisa, in the Years 1821 and 1822</title> (London, 1824), pp. 149–150.</note></p>
            <p rend="center">——————</p>
            <p>* A volume of poems by <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Leigh Hunt</ref>. The reader who may be desirous of referring to the [MS torn] will find it in the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> vol. of the Quarterly Review. p. 324 [Editors’ note: A review of James Henry Leigh Hunt, <title>Foliage; or, Poems Original and Translated</title> (1818), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 324–355, published 9 June 1818. The reviewer was John Taylor Coleridge.] </p>
            <lb/>
               <p>[fol. 1v]:</p>
               <p rend="indent1">I wish it to be distinctly understood that in <del>noticing</del> &#60;replying to&#62; these impudent falsehoods, I am not influenced by any desire of vindicating myself; – this would be wholly unnecessary considering from what quarter they come. I notice them for the sake of laying before the Public one sample more of the practises of the Satanic school,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (London, 1821), ‘Preface’, pp. xvii–xxii, where Southey denounced ‘the Satanic School’ of modern poetry without naming any one poet. However, this was clearly a riposte to Byron’s <title>Don Juan</title> (1819), whose suppressed ‘Dedication’, mocking Southey, had circulated widely.</note> &#38; shewing what credit is due to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> assertions. For that his Lordship <del>said what is here ascribed to him</del> &#60;spoke to this effect &#38; in this temper&#62;, I have no doubt. Capt Medwin has, I dare say, <del>accurately reported what he heard</del> to the best of his recollection; <del>&#38;</del> faithfully performed the <del>honorable</del> &#60;worshipful&#62; office of retailing all the effusions of spleen, slander &#38; malignity which were <del>uttered</del> &#60;vented&#62; in his presence. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref><del>, like Lord Bolingbroke, left a blunderbuss &#38; the blunderbuss has only let out what it was charged with</del>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Lord ... with: deleted in pencil. Speaking of David Mallet’s (c. 1705–1765; <title>DNB</title>) edition of the <title>Works</title> (1754) of Henry St John, 1st Viscount Bolingbroke (1678–1751; <title>DNB</title>), Samuel Johnson (1709–1784; <title>DNB</title>) declared of Bolingbroke that ‘he was a scoundrel, and a coward: a scoundrel for charging a blunderbuss against religion and morality; a coward because he had not the resolution to fire it off himself, but left half a crown to a beggarly Scotchman, to draw the trigger after his death!’ (James Boswell (1740–1795; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Life of Samuel Johnson</title>, 3rd edn (London, 1799), p. 312).</note></p>
               <p rend="indent1">The reviewal in question <title><hi rend="ital">I did not write</hi></title>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> might have known this if he had enquired of <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Murray</ref>, who would readily have assured him that I was not the author: &#38; he might have known it from the reviewal itself, where the writer declares in plain words that he was a contemporary of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley’s</ref>, at Eton.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 324–355 (327): ‘At Eton we remember him notorious for setting fire to old trees with burning glasses, no unmeet emblem for a man who perverts his ingenuity and knowledge to the attacking of all that is ancient and venerable in our civil and religious institutions.’</note> I had no concern in it directly or indirectly. But let it not be inferred that in thus disclaiming that paper, any disapproval of it is intended. Papers in the Quarterly Review have been ascribed to me (those on Keats’s poems for example)<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of John Keats (1795–1821; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Endymion</title> (1818), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 204–208, published 26 September 1818, was by John Wilson Croker.</note> which I have heartily condemned both for their spirit &#38; manner. But for the one in question, its composition would be creditable to the most distinguished writer; nor is there any thing either in the opinions expressed, or in the manner of expressing them which a man of just &#38; honourable principles would have hesitated to advance <del>in his own person.</del><note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">in … person: deleted in pencil.</note> <del>Most assuredly it</del> contains nothing that I would not have avowed if I had written it, or subscribed as entirely assenting to &#38; approving it. </p>
               <p rend="indent1">It is not true that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> ever enquired of me whether I were the author of that paper, which purporting as it did to be written by an Etonian of his own standing, he very well knew I was not. But in this part of <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> statement there may be some mistake mingled with a great deal of malignant falsehood. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Shelley</ref> addressed a letter to me from Pisa asking if I were the author of a criticism in the Quarterly Review upon his Revolt of Islam,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">In a letter of 26 June 1820, Shelley had accused Southey of writing a hostile review of <title>Laon and Cythna, or the Revolution of the Golden City</title> (1818; published late 1817) and <title>The Revolt of Islam. A Poem, in Twelve Cantos</title> (1818); see Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 358–359. This review had appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 460–471, published 10 September 1819, and its author was, once again, John Taylor Coleridge.</note> – not exactly in <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> phrase <title><hi rend="ital">taxing</hi></title> me with it, for he declared his own belief that I [MS torn] </p>
               <lb/>
                  <p>[fol. 2 r]:</p>
                  <p>but added that he was induced to ask the question by the positive declaration of some friends in England that the article was mine. <del>Disclaiming</del> &#60;Denying&#62; in my reply<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Percy Bysshe Shelley, [c. 29 July 1820], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3517.</note> that either he or any other person was entitled to propose such a question upon such grounds, I nevertheless assured him that I had not written the paper, &#38; that I had never in any of my writings alluded to him in any way. </p>
                  <p rend="indent1">Now for the assertion that I had the audacity to admit having treasured up some of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley’s</ref> opinions when he resided at Keswick, &#38; having made notes of them at the time. What truth is mixed up with the slander of this statement I shall immediately explain: premising only that as the <del>remark</del> &#60;opinion thus implied&#62; concerning the practise of noting down familiar conversation is not applicable to me. I transfer it to Capt Medwin for his own especial use. </p>
                  <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Shelley</ref> having in the letter alluded to thought proper to make some remarks upon my opinions, I took occasion in reply to comment upon his; &#38; to ask him (as the tree is known by its fruits)<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Luke </title>6: 44 and <title>Matthew</title> 7: 16.</note> whether he had found them conducive to his own happiness, &#38; the happiness of those with whom he had been most nearly connected. This produced a second letter from him,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Shelley to Southey, 17 August 1820, Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 361–363.</note> written in a tone partly of justification, partly of attack. I replied to this also;<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Percy Bysshe Shelley, 12 October 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3538.</note> not by any such &#60;absurd&#62; admission as <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> has stated (<del>which would have been both absurd &#38; false</del>) but by recapitulating to him, as a practical illustration of his principles, the leading circumstances of his own life, from the commencement of his career at University College;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Shelley matriculated at University College, Oxford, on 10 April 1810 but was sent down in November 1811 following a furore over his pamphlet, <title>The Necessity of Atheism</title> (1811).</note> the earlier facts I stated upon his own authority as I had heard them from his own lips, the latter were of public notoriety. – There the correspondence ended. On his part it had &#60;been&#62; conducted with the courtesy which was natural to him; on mine, in the spirit of one who was earnestly admonishing a fellow creature. <del>(&#38; a most guilty one!) of death &#38; judgement</del>.</p>
                  <p rend="indent1">This is the correspondence <del>to</del> &#60;upon&#62; which <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> <del>has alluded</del> &#60;misrepresentation has been constructed&#62;: it is all that ever past between us, except a note from <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> – some years before – accompanying a copy of his Alastor, &#38; one of mine in acknowledgement of it.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Alastor; or the Spirit of Solitude</title> (1816), no. 2547 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Shelley had sent Southey a copy on 7 March 1816; see Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. [357]. Southey’s reply does not survive.</note> I have preserved his letters, together with copies of my own: &#38; if I had as little consideration for the feelings of [MS torn] as Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Medwin has displayed, it is not any tenderness toward the * dead that</p>
                  <p rend="center">————</p>
                  <p>[MS torn] the Preface to his Monody on Keats, <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref>, as I have been informed, asserts that I was the<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s footnote continues at the bottom of fol. 2v: ‘author of … communication to himself’.</note></p>
                  <lb/>
                     <p>[fol. 2v]:</p>
                     <p>would withhold me &#60;now&#62; from <del>ever</del> publishing them. </p>
                     <p rend="indent1">It is not likely that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> should have communicated my part of this correspondence to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref>, even if he did his own. Bearing testimony as his heart did to the truth of <del>the</del> &#60;my&#62; statement in every point, &#38; impossible as it was to escape from the conclusion which was there brought home, I do not think he would have dared produce it. How much or how little of the truth was known to his <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lordship</ref>, or with which of the party at Pisa the insolent &#38; calumnious <del>falsehood</del> &#60;misrepresentation&#62; conveyed in <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his Lordship’s</ref> words originated, is of little consequence. <del>I shall not parody the extract &#38; ask who but Lord Byron; or who but Shelley could have had the baseness thus to found a scandal on falsehood, because I believe any Professor of the Satanic school is capable of it, any pupil of that school, &#38; any visitor who has been admitted to the honours of a sitting there, &#38; received the fraternal embrace</del>.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">I shall … embrace: deleted in pencil.</note></p>
                     <p rend="indent1">The charge of scattering dark &#38; devilish insinuations, is one which if <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> were living I would throw back in his teeth. Me he had assailed without the slightest provocation, &#38; with that unmanliness too which was peculiar to himself; &#38; in this course he might have gone on without giving me the slightest <del>pain</del> &#60;uneasiness&#62;, or calling forth one animadversion in reply. When I came forward to attack <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his Lordship</ref> it was upon</p>
                     <p>public, not upon private grounds.<hi rend="sup"> </hi> It was because <del>hxx</del> &#60;<del>x</del>&#62; had brought a stigma upon English literature that I accused him, because he had perverted great talents to the worst purposes: because he had set up for Pander General to the youth of Great Britain as long as his writings should endure: – because he had committed a high crime &#38; misdemeanour against Society, by sending forth a work<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Byron’s <title>Don Juan</title> (1819).</note> in which</p>
                     <p rend="center">——————</p>
                     <p>author of the criticism in the Quarterly Review upon that young mans poems, &#38; that his death was occasioned by it. There was a degree of meanness in this (especially considering the temper &#38; tenour of our correspondence) which I was not then prepared to expect from Shelley, for that he <title><hi rend="ital">believed</hi></title> me to be author of that paper, I certainly do not believe. </p>
                     <p rend="indent1">He was once for a short time my neighbour; I met him upon terms, not of friendship indeed, but certainly of mutual good will; I admired his talents, thought that he would outgrow his errors (perilous as they were) &#38; trusted that meantime a kind &#38; generous heart would resist the effect of fatal opinions which he had taken up in ignorance &#38; boyhood. Therein I was mistaken [MS torn] to regard him with hope, he became to me an object for sorrow &#38; aweful commiseration, not of any injurious or [MS torn] when I expressed myself with just severity concerning him, it was in direct communication to himself.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Percy Shelley, ‘Preface’, <title>Adonais. An Elegy on the Death of John Keats, Author of Endymion, Hyperion, Etc </title>(London, 1821), p. 4, though Southey was not named as the author of the notorious review of John Keats (1795–1821; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Endymion</title> (1818) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 204–208. </note></p>
                     <lb/>
                        <p>[fol. 3r]</p>
                        <p>mockery was mingled with horrors, filth with impiety, profligacy with &#60;sedition &#38;&#62; slander. For these offences I came forward to arraign him. The accusation was not made darkly, it was &#60;not&#62; insinuated; nor even advanced <del>thro</del> &#60;under&#62; the <del>medium</del> &#60;cover&#62; of a <del>public journal</del> &#60;review&#62;: I attacked him openly in my own name, &#38; only not by his, because he had not then publicly avowed the flagitious production by which he will be remembered for lasting infamy. He replied in a manner altogether worthy of himself &#38; his cause.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">In the ‘Appendix’ to ‘The Two Foscari’, <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy. Cain, A Mystery</title> (London, 1821), p. 328, Byron had cautioned: ‘I am not ignorant of Mr. Southey’s calumnies on a different occasion, knowing them to be such, which he scattered abroad on his return from Switzerland against me and others.’ Southey had visited Switzerland in his continental tour of May–August 1817. Byron believed that Southey had subsequently spread rumours that Byron and Shelley engaged in a ‘League of Incest’.</note> Contention with a generous &#38; honourable opponent leads naturally to esteem, &#38; probably to friendship: but next to such an antagonist, an enemy like <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> is to be desired, – one who &#60;by his conduct in the interest&#62; divests himself of every claim to respect, – one whose baseness is such as to sanctify the vindictive feeling that it provokes, &#38; upon whom the act of taking vengeance is that of administering justice. I answered him as he deserved to be answered,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courie</title>r, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776.</note> – &#38; the effect which that answer produced upon him <del>Lordships feelings &#38; countenance</del>, has been described by <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his Lordships</ref> friendly chronicler, Capt Medwin.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Medwin (1788–1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron: Noted During a Residence with his Lordship at Pisa, in the Years 1821 and 1822</title> (London, 1824), pp. 147–149, described Byron’s rage at Southey’s January 1822 Letter to the <title>Courier</title> and his discussion of whether to challenge Southey to a duel.</note> <del>He found the draught bitter in the mouth, &#38; cold in the stomach, but it was of his own brewing</del>.</p>
                        <p rend="indent1">One piece of advice I gave <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his Lordship</ref> on that occasion, which he was prudent enough to follow. I recommended him when he should attack me in future always to do it in rhyme.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776.</note> This accordingly he did,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Byron’s <title>The Vision of Judgment</title> (1822), a parody of Southey’s <title>A Vision of Judgement </title>(1821), was first published in the <title>Liberal</title>, 1 (October 1822), 3–39.</note> &#38; this he might have continued to do till his heart ached, unnoticed by me. To the Poets license of fiction he was entitled in its fullest extent, nor did I care how much he might abuse the privilege. But if what appeared as mere fiction (with whatever venom it was compounded) in verse, had again assumed the plain prose form of calumny &#38; falsehood, <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> would have found me as ready in rejoinder the second time as the first. </p>
                        <p rend="indent1">This is the real history of what the purveyors <del>for xx</del> of scandal for the Public are pleased sometimes to announce in their advertisements as “Byrons Controversy with Southey.” What there was “dark &#38; devilish” in it, belongs to his Lordship: &#38; </p>
                        <lb/>
                           <p>[fol. 3v]:</p>
                           <p>had I been compelled to resume it during his life, he who played the Monster in literature, &#38; aimed his blows at women, should have been treated <del>like a Monster</del> accordingly <del>to his deserts. On my part there was nothing covert, nothing insidious; I dealt neither in insinuations nor calumnies. In assuming that the principles &#38; feelings which actuated his private life were to be found in his writings, I applied to him that test whereby I am willing to be tried myself. There I saw that like Michael Draytons Mooncalf</del></p>
                           <lg><l rend="indent3"><del>He termeth virtue madness, or mere folly,</del></l>
                              <l rend="indent3"><del>He hates all high things &#38; profanes all holy.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Michael Drayton (1563–1631; <title>DNB</title>), ‘The Moon-Calf’ (1627), lines 323–324.</note></del></l></lg>
                           <p><del>There I found the portraiture of one who hated men, despised women, was sated with the vices of this world, &#38; seemed to have no views or hopes beyond it. If any one be disposed to censure me for speaking thus of the departed, let him remember that it is in answer to posthumous slander. I have no pxxxxxs &#60;taste&#62; for morbid anatomy: my pursuits, thank Heaven, are of a cleanlier &#38; healthier kind. Lord Byron was living when “I fastened his name upon the gibbet”,</del><note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the Courier, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776.</note><del>– it is by his professed friends that he is now exhibited there, pendant at full length.</del><note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">On my ... length: deletion is in pencil, two vertical lines.</note></p>
                           <p rend="indent1"><del>No man may hope to pass thro this world, such as the world now is, without enemies, tho his life should be as inoffensive as mine, equally retired &#38; more obscure. But it is a comfort for me to think, as it will be an honour to have it recorded, that living in friendship with xxx many of the best &#38; wisest of my contemporaries, I &#60;have&#62; had for enemies those who were most notorious in their generation for their pernicious principles, &#38; their profligate conduct</del>.</p>
                           <signed rend="indent5">Robert Southey.</signed>
                              
                              <postscript><p rend="indent1">It might have been thought that <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Ld B.</ref> had attaind the last degree of <del>infamy</del> &#60;disgrace&#62; when his head was set up for a sign at one of those preparatory schools for the Brothel</p>
                              <lb/>
                                 <p>[fol. 4r] </p>
                                 <p>&#38; the gallows where obscenity sedition &#38; blasphemy are retailed in drams for the vulgar.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">William Benbow (1787–1864; <title>DNB</title>), radical publisher and pornographer, called his shop in Castle Street, Leicester Square, ‘The Byron’s Head’, and imprints from his press contained this address.</note> There remaind one farther <del>disgrace</del> &#60;shame&#62;; there remaind this exposure of his conversation which has compelled <del>even</del> <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his Ldps</ref> friends <del>xxx x</del> in their own defence to compare his oral <del>statements</del> &#60;declarations&#62; with his written words,<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey may be thinking here in particular of John Murray’s letter of 2 November 1824, which appeared in many papers, including the <title>Courier</title>, 5 November 1824, and compared Medwin’s reports of Byron’s statements with letters exchanged between Murray and Byron.</note> &#38; thereby demonstrate that he was as reckless of truth as he was <del>regardless of every other principle</del> – incapable of sustaining those &#60;<del>better</del>&#62; feelings <del>which sometimes</del> suited to his birth station &#38; high endowment which sometimes came across his better mind –</p>
                                 
                                 <p>[fol. 4v is blank] </p>
                                 <lb/></postscript></div>
                                    
                                   <div type="letter" n="4.2">
                                   <head rend="bold">4.2 Robert Southey to the <ref type="a" target="people.html#MudfordWilliam">Editor of the <title>Courier</title></ref>, [1824]</head>
                                    <p>Watermarks: top part of crest surmounted by a crown (fols 1 and 5); 1822 (fols 2 and 4); Kingsford (fols 3 and 6); lower part of crest, displaying rampant lion (fol. 7). </p>
                                    <p>MS: Huntington Library, HM 6656. AL; 14p. </p>
                                    
                                    <p rend="center">To the Editor of the Courier</p>
                                    
                                    <p>Sir</p>
                                    <p rend="indent1">On two former occasions you have allowed me thro the channel of your journal to contradict a calmunious accusation as publicly as it had been preferred:<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 16 June 1815, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Four</title>, Letter 2616; and Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776.</note> &#38; tho in these days of slander such charges <del>xxx xxxx</del> hardly deserve refutation, there are reasons which induce me once more to request <del>the same</del> &#60;<del>like</del>&#62; &#60;a similar&#62; favour. </p>
                                    <p rend="indent1"><del>The following</del> &#60;An&#62; extract<del>s</del> from Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Medwins recent publication of Lord Byrons Conversations,<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Medwin (1788–1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron: Noted During a Residence with his Lordship at Pisa, in the Years 1821 and 1822</title> (1824).</note> has<del>e</del> been transmitted me by <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">a friend</ref>, who happening to know what the facts are, &#60;which are there <del>xxxxx</del> falsified&#62; is of opinion that it would &#60;not mis&#62; become me to state them at this time. The words &#60;which&#62; are given as <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> &#60;in that volume&#62; are as follows. </p>
                                    <p rend="indent1">“I am glad M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey owns that article on “<title><hi rend="ital">Foliage</hi></title>” which excited my choler so much. But who else could have been the Author? Who but Southey would have had the baseness, under pretext of reviewing the work of one man, insidiously to make it a nest-egg for hatching malicious calumnies against others? – I say nothing of the critique itself on “Foliage”; – but what was the object of that article? I repeat, to vilify &#38; scatter his dark &#38; devilish insinuations against me &#38; others. – Shame on the man who could wound an already bleeding heart, – be barbarous enough to revive the memory of an event that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> was perfectly innocent of, – &#38; found scandal on falsehood! – <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> taxed him with writing that article some years ago; &#38; he had the audacity to admit that he had treasured up some opinions of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley’s</ref> ten years before, when he was on a visit at Keswick, &#38; had made a note of them at the time.”<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Medwin (1788–1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron: Noted During a Residence with his Lordship at Pisa, in the Years 1821 and 1822</title> (London, 1824), pp. 149–150.</note></p>
                                    <p rend="indent1">I wish it to be distinctly understood that in <del>giving the broadest &#38; most unqualified contradiction to</del> &#60;noticing&#62; these impudent falsehoods, I am not influenced by any desire of vindicating myself – this would be wholly unnecessary <del>on my part</del> considering from what quarter they <del>abuse</del> come<del>s</del>. I notice them only for the sake of laying before the Public one sample more of &#60;the practice of the Satanic&#62; <del>Lord Byrons honour &#38; veracity</del> &#60;school&#62;,<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (London, 1821), ‘Preface’, pp. xvii–xxii, where Southey denounced ‘the Satanic School’ of modern poetry without naming any one poet. However, this was clearly a riposte to Byron’s <title>Don Juan</title> (1819), whose suppressed ‘Dedication’, mocking Southey, had circulated widely.</note> &#38; shewing <del>thxx</del> what credit is due to &#60;<ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord B.s</ref>&#62; his assertions. For that <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his Lordship</ref> said what is here ascribed to him I <del>can</del> have no doubt. Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Medwin has I dare say accurately reported what he heard to the best of his recollection, – &#38; faithfully performed the honourable office of retailing all the effusions of spleen, slander &#38; malignity which were uttered in his presence. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> like &#60;Lord&#62; Bolingbroke left a blunderbuss, &#38; the blunderbuss has only let out what it was charged with.<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors">Speaking of David Mallet’s (c. 1705–1765; <title>DNB</title>) edition of the <title>Works</title> (1754) of Henry St John, 1st Viscount Bolingbroke (1678–1751; <title>DNB</title>), Samuel Johnson (1709–1784; <title>DNB</title>) declared of Bolingbroke that ‘he was a scoundrel, and a coward: a scoundrel for charging a blunderbuss against religion and morality; a coward because he had not the resolution to fire it off himself, but left half a crown to a beggarly Scotchman, to draw the trigger after his death!’ (James Boswell (1740–1795; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Life of Samuel Johnson</title>, 3rd edn (London, 1799), p. 312).</note></p>
                                    <p rend="indent1">The reviewal in question <title><hi rend="ital">I did not write</hi></title>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> might have known this if he had enquired of <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Murray</ref>, who would readily have assured him that I was not the author; – - &#38; he might have known it also from the reviewal itself, where the writer declares in plain words that he was a contemporary of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelleys</ref> at Eton.<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 324–355 (327): ‘At Eton we remember him notorious for setting fire to old trees with burning glasses, no unmeet emblem for a man who perverts his ingenuity and knowledge to the attacking of all that is ancient and venerable in our civil and religious institutions.’</note> I had no concern in it, directly or indirectly. <del>After this it would be superfluous to say that I never owned </del>it. &#60;But&#62; Let</p>
                                    <lb/>
                                       <p>[fol. 2r]: </p>
                                       <p>X It is not true that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> ever enquired of me whether I were the author of that paper, – which purporting as it did to be written by an <del>schoolfellow</del> &#60;Etonian of his own standing&#62;, – he very well knew I was not. But in this part of <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> statement there <del>is</del> &#60;may be&#62; some <del>error</del> &#60;mistake&#62; mingled with a great deal of malignant falsehood. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> S &#38;c –</p>
                                       <lb/>
                                          <p>[fol. 2v blank] </p>
                                          <lb/>
                                             <p>[fol. 3r]: </p>
                                             <p>it not <del>however</del> be inferred that in thus disclaiming that paper, any disapproval of it is intended. Papers in the Quarterly Review have been ascribed to me (those on Keats’s poems for example)<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of John Keats (1795–1821; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Endymion</title> (1818), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 204–208, published 26 September 1818, was by John Wilson Croker.</note> which I have heartily condemned both for their spirit &#38; manner But &#60;for&#62; the one in question its composition would be creditable to the most distinguished writer nor is there any thing either in the opinions expressed, or in the manner of expressing them <del>that xx x</del> which a man of <del>honorab would</del> &#60;just &#38;&#62; honourable principles would have hesitated to <del>subxx</del> advance in his own <del>name</del> &#60;person.&#62; Most certainly it contains nothing which I would not have <del>acknowledged</del> &#60;avowed&#62; had I written it, or subscribed as entirely assenting to, <del>it</del> &#38; approving it. </p>
                                             <p rend="indent1">X <del>It is true that</del> <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Shelley</ref> addressed a letter to me from Pisa asking if I were the author of <del>that paper</del>, &#60;a criticism in the QR. upon his Revolt of Islam,<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors">In a letter of 26 June 1820, Shelley had accused Southey of writing a hostile review of <title>Laon and Cythna, or the Revolution of the Golden City</title> (1818; published late 1817) and <title>The Revolt of Islam. A Poem, in Twelve Cantos</title> (1818); see Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 358–359. This review had appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 460–471, published 10 September 1819, and its author was, once again, John Taylor Coleridge.</note> &#62;- not exactly <title><hi rend="ital">taxing</hi></title> &#60;in <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Bs</ref> phrase&#62; me with it, for he declared his own <del>persuasion</del> &#60;belief&#62; that I was not, – <del>which declaration I have at this time in his own handwriting</del>. &#60;but added that he was induced to ask the question by <del>declaration</del> the positive declaration of some friends in England that the article was mine.&#62; Denying in my reply<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Percy Bysshe Shelley, [c. 29 July 1820], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3517.</note> that either he or any other person was entitled to propose such a question &#60;upon such grounds -&#62;, I nevertheless assured him that I had not &#60;written that paper&#62;, &#38; that I had never in any of my writings alluded to him, in any way. <del>Lord Byron says I owned the paper: whether that falsehood was originally his own, or Mr Shelleys, I neither know, nor care, believing them to have been equally destitute of veracity</del>.</p>
                                             <p rend="indent1">Now for the <del>last part of the charge</del> &#60;assertion&#62;, that I had the audacity to admit <del>the</del> having treasured up some of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelleys</ref> opinions when he resided at Keswick, &#38; <del>making</del> &#60;having made&#62; notes of them at the time. What truth is <del>disguised under</del> &#60;mixed up with the slander of&#62; this statement I shall immediately explain, – premising only that <del>I hand over</del> the remark concerning the practice of noting down &#60;familiar&#62; conversation &#60;is not applicable to <del>myself</del> me xxxxxxxxxxxxx transfer&#62; – to Capt Medwin, for his &#60;own&#62; especial use.</p>
                                                <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Shelley</ref> having in the letter alluded to thought proper to make some remarks upon my opinions, I took occasion in reply to comment upon his, &#38; to ask him (as the tree is known by its fruits)<note n="39" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Luke </title>6: 44 and <title>Matthew</title> 7: 16.</note> whether he had found them conducive to his own happiness &#38; the happiness of those with whom he had been most nearly connected. This produced a second letter from him,<note n="40" place="foot" resp="editors">Shelley to Southey, 17 August 1820, Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 361–363.</note> written in a tone partly of justification, partly of attack. I replied to this <del>epistle</del> also:<note n="41" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Percy Bysshe Shelley, 12 October 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3538.</note> – not by any such admission as <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> has stated (which would have been both absurd &#38; false) but by recapitulating to him, as a practical illustration of his principles, the <del>xxxxxx principal events</del> &#60;leading circumstances&#62; of his own life from the commencement of his career at University College:<note n="42" place="foot" resp="editors">Shelley matriculated at University College, Oxford, on 10 April 1810 but was sent down in November 1811 following a furore over his pamphlet, <title>The Necessity of Atheism</title> (1811).</note> the earlier facts were stated <del>to him</del> upon his own authority as I had heard them from his own lips; the latter were of public notoriety, <del>or within my own certain knowledge</del>. There the correspondence <del>xx</del> ended. On his part it had been conducted with the courtesy which was natural to him; – on mine, in the spirit of one who was earnestly admonishing a fellow creature, (&#38; a most guilty one!) of death &#38; judgement.</p>
                                                   <p rend="indent1">This is the correspondence to which <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> has alluded It is all that ever past between us, except a note from <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> &#60;some years before,&#62; accompanying a copy of his Alastor, &#38; one of mine in acknowledge-</p>
                                                   <lb/>
                                                      <p rend="indent1">How much or how little of the truth was known to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his Lordship</ref>, – or <del>to his</del> will which of the <del>xx</del> party at Pisa the impudent &#38; calumnious <del>falsehood</del> &#60;misrepresentation&#62; conveys in <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his Lordship</ref> <del>account of</del> words, originated, is of little consequence. I shall not parody the extract, &#38; ask who but <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord B</ref> – or who but <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> –</p>
                                                      <lb/>
                                                         <p>[fol. 4v blank] </p>
                                                         <lb/>
                                                            <p>[fol. 5r]: </p>
                                                            <p>-ment of it.<note n="43" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Alastor; or the Spirit of Solitude</title> (1816), no. 2547 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Shelley had sent Southey a copy on 7 March 1816; see Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. [357]. Southey’s reply does not survive.</note> – I have preserved his letters, together with copies of my own; &#38; if I had as little consideration for the feelings of the living as Capt Medwin has displayd, it is not any tenderness toward the † dead that would withhold he from &#60;now&#62; publishing them <del>at this time</del>.</p>
                                                            <p rend="indent1">It is not likely that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> should have communicated my part of the correspondence to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref>. &#60;even if he did his own.&#62; Bearing testimony as his heart did to the truth of the <del>whole</del> statement in every <del>part</del> &#60;point&#62;, &#38; impossible as it was to escape from the <del>inference</del> &#60;conclusion&#62; which was &#60;then&#62; brought home, I do not think he would have dared produce it. <del>Touching the manner in which his Lordship has represented the matter, xx I shall not parody his own words &#38; ask who but Lord Byron</del> could have had the baseness &#60;thus&#62; to found scandal on falsehood, because I believe any Professor of the Satanic school is capable of it, any pupil of that school, &#38; any visitor, who has been admitted to the honour of a sitting &#60;there&#62; &#38; received the fraternal embrace. </p>
                                                            <p rend="indent1">The charge of scattering dark &#38; devilish insinuations is one which if <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> were living, I would throw back in his teeth. </p>
                                                            <p rend="center">———————————————————</p>
                                                            <p>&#9768; In the Preface to his Monody on Keats,<ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe"> Shelley </ref>as I have been informed, asserts that I was the author of the <del>critique</del> criticism in the Quarterly Review upon that young mans poems, &#38; that his death was occasioned by it. There was a degree of meanness in this (especially considering the temper &#38; tenour of our correspondence) which I was not then prepared to expect from <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref>; – for that he <title><hi rend="ital">believed</hi></title> me to be the author of that paper, I certainly do not believe.<note n="44" place="foot" resp="editors">Percy Shelley, ‘Preface’, <title>Adonais. An Elegy on the Death of John Keats, Author of Endymion, Hyperion, Etc </title>(London, 1821), p. 4, though Southey was not named as the author of the notorious review of John Keats (1795–1821; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Endymion</title> (1818) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 204–208. </note></p>
                                                            <lb/>
                                                               <p>[fol. 5v]: </p>
                                                               <p>Me he had <del>repeatedly</del><note n="45" place="foot" resp="editors">repeatedly: deleted in pencil. </note> assaild without the slightest provocation, – &#38; <del>sometimes</del><note n="46" place="foot" resp="editors">sometimes: deleted in pencil.</note> with that unmanliness &#60;too&#62; which was peculiar to himself; &#38; in this course he might have con<del>tinued</del> &#60;gone on&#62; without <del>exciting in</del> &#60;giving&#62; me the slightest <del>feeling of</del> pain, or calling forth one animadversion in reply. When <del>at last</del><note n="47" place="foot" resp="editors">at last: deleted in pencil.</note> I came forward to attack <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his Lordship</ref>, it was upon public not upon private grounds.<note n="48" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (London, 1821), ‘Preface’, pp. xvii–xxii, where Southey denounced ‘the Satanic School’ of modern poetry without naming any one poet.</note> It was because he had brought a stigma upon English <del>poetry</del> &#60;literature&#62; that I accused him, because he had perverted great talents to the <del>basest &#38; most pernicious</del> &#60;<del>worst foulest</del>&#62; purposes, – because he had set up for Pander general to the youth of Great Britain – as long as his writings should endure, – because he had committed a high crime &#38; misdemeanour against society, by sending forth a work<note n="49" place="foot" resp="editors">Byron’s <title>Don Juan</title> (1819).</note> in which mockery was mingled with horrors, filth with impiety, profligacy with slander. For these <del>xxxxx</del> offences I came forward to arraign him; the accusation was not made darkly, not insinuated, nor even advanced thro the medium of a <del>review</del> &#60;public journal&#62;; I attacked him openly, in my own name, &#38; only not by his, because he had not then publicly avowd the flagitious production by which he will be remembered for lasting infamy. He replied in a manner altogether worthy of himself &#38; his cause.<note n="50" place="foot" resp="editors">In the ‘Appendix’ to ‘The Two Foscari’, <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy. Cain, A Mystery</title> (London, 1821), p. 328, Byron had cautioned: ‘I am not ignorant of Mr. Southey’s calumnies on a different occasion, knowing them to be such, which he scattered abroad on his return from Switzerland against me and others.’ Southey had visited Switzerland in his continental tour of May–August 1817. Byron believed that Southey had subsequently spread rumours that Byron and Shelley engaged in a ‘League of Incest’.</note> <del>Next to being opposed to</del> a &#60;contention with a&#62; generous &#38; honourable <del>enemy</del> &#60;<del>foe</del> opponent <del>x xxxxxx</del>&#62;, <del>with whom any contention</del> leads naturally to esteem &#38; probably to friendship, &#60;<del>but next to such an enem</del>&#62; such an antagonist, &#60;an enemy like&#62; <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> is to be desired. – one who divests himself of <del>all</del> &#60;every&#62; claim to respect, – one whose baseness is such as to sanctify the vindictive feeling that it <del>excites</del> &#60;provokes&#62;, &#38; upon whom the act of taking vengeance, is that of administering justice. I answered him as he deserved to be answered,<note n="51" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776.</note> &#38; the effect which that answer produced upon his <del>Lordships</del> feelings &#38; countenance has been described by <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his &#60;Lordships</ref>&#62; friendly chronicler Capt Medwin.<note n="52" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Medwin (1788–1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of the Conversations of Lord Byron: Noted During a Residence with his Lordship at Pisa, in the Years 1821 and 1822</title> (London, 1824), pp. 147–149, described Byron’s rage at Southey’s January 1822 Letter to the <title>Courier</title> and his discussion of whether to challenge Southey to a duel.</note> He found the draught bitter in the mouth &#38; cold in the</p>
                                                               <lb/>
                                                                  <p>[fol. 6r]: </p>
                                                                  <p>stomach, – but it was of his own brewing</p>
                                                                  <p rend="indent1">One piece of advice I gave <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his Lordship</ref> on that <del>letter</del> &#60;<del>time</del> occasion&#62; which he was prudent enough to <del>take</del> &#60;follow&#62;. I recommended him when he <del>xxx</del> should attack me in future always to do it in rhyme.<note n="53" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776.</note> This accordingly he did,<note n="54" place="foot" resp="editors">Byron’s <title>The Vision of Judgment</title> (1822), a parody of Southey’s <title>A Vision of Judgement </title>(1821), was first published in the <title>Liberal</title>, 1 (October 1822), 3–39.</note> &#38; this he might have continued to do till his heart ached, unnoticed by me. <del>It would have been otherwise if he had ventured again into the field of prose</del>. To the Poets license of fiction he was entitled in its fullest extent, <del>&#38; however much he might have abused the privilege it would never have concerned me</del><note n="55" place="foot" resp="editors">&#38; however … concerned me: deleted in pencil.</note> &#60;nor did I care how much he might abuse the privilege&#62;. But if what appeared as mere fiction, (with whatever venom it was compounded&#62; in verse, had again assumed the plain prose form of calumny &#38; falsehood, <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> would have found me as ready in rejoinder the second time as the first. <del>I must have been as poor a creature as his own Devil in the Alps</del><note n="56" place="foot" resp="editors">Lord Byron’s <title>Manfred: a Dramatic Poem</title> (1817), Act 2 scene 3, where Manfred resists a pact with the Devil.</note><del> if I could have been intimidated or silenced by him. Hate me he did, &#38; always would have done unless a radical change had been effected in his whole character &#38; nature; but despise me (in spite of his bravados) he never did, nor should, nor could have done. So rancorous a feeling as that with which he regarded me cannot coexist with contempt. And on my part tho I considered his empty insults as unworthy notice, &#60;being&#62; disgraceful as they were to no one but himself, it was not with contempt that I regarded Lord Byron. When I set my heel upon a vipers head, it is not in contempt that I tread upon the venomous &#38; writhing reptile</del>.<note n="57" place="foot" resp="editors">I must … reptile: deleted in pencil.</note></p>
                                                                  <p rend="indent1">This is the <del>whole</del> &#60;real&#62; history of what is called my controversy with <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref>, what there was “dark &#38; devilish” in it belongs to his Lordship, &#60;And had I <del>xxxxxxx</del> it were xxxxxxxx the xxxxxxxx during his life&#62; He who played the Monster in literature, &#38; aimd his blows at women <del>was to be</del> &#60;should have been&#62; treated like a Monster &#60;<del>xx xxxxxxx</del> xxxxxxxx xx xxx xxxxx&#62;. On my part there was nothing covert – nothing insidious. I dealt neither &#60;in&#62; insi-</p>
                                                                  <lb/>
                                                                     <p>[fol. 6v blank] </p>
                                                                     <lb/>
                                                                        <p>[fol. 7r]: </p>
                                                                        <p>- nuations nor calumny In assuming that the principles, <del>opinions</del> &#38; feelings which actuated his private life were to be found in his writing, I applied to him that test whereby I am willing to be tried myself. There I saw that like Michael Draytons Mooncalf</p>
                                                                        <lg><l rend="indent3">He termeth virtue madness or mere folly,</l>
                                                                           <l rend="indent3">He hates all high things &#38; profanes all holy.<note n="58" place="foot" resp="editors">Michael Drayton (1563–1631; <title>DNB</title>), ‘The Moon-Calf’ (1627), lines 323–324.</note></l></lg>
                                                                        <p>there I found the portraiture of one who hated men, despised women, was sated with the vices of this world, &#38; seemed to have no views or hopes beyond it. – If any one be disposed to censure me for speaking thus of the departed, let him remember that it is an answer to posthumous <del>calumny</del> &#60;slander&#62;. I have no passion for morbid anatomy – my pursuits thank Heaven are of a cleanlier &#38; healthier kind. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord B.</ref> was living when I fastened his name upon the gibbet:<note n="59" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776,</note> it is by his professed friends that he <del>has been</del> &#60;is now&#62; exhibited there – <del>after death</del> &#60;pendant&#62; at full length. </p>
                                                                        <p rend="indent1">No man may hope to pass thro this world, such as the world now is – without enemies, tho his life should be as inoffensive as mine, equally retired, &#38; more obscure. But it is &#60;a comfort&#62; for me <del>a satisfaction</del> to think, as it will be an honour to have it recorded that living in friendship with many of the best &#38; wisest of my contemporaries, I had for enemies those who were most notorious &#60;in this generation&#62; for their pernicious principles &#38; their profligate conduct</p>
                                                                        <lb/>
                                                                           <p>[fol. 7v]: </p>
                                                                           <p>the Purveyors &#60;of scandal&#62; for public <del>scandal</del> are pleased sometimes to announce in their advertisements as <del>my</del> <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Byrons</ref> controversy with Southey</p>
         </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
