<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.959</idno><idno type="nines">rce2081</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="959" type="letter"><head>959. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1804-07-02">2 July
                        1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Mr Danvers/ Bristol./ Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb/>Postmark: [partial] E/ JUL 5<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1804-07-02"> July 2. 1804.</date></dateline><salute>Dear Danvers</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> First I have to tell you that Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> D &amp; W.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Danvers
                        and White (first name and dates unknown): the wine merchants from whom Southey received his wine. Four bottles of wine in his
                        last order had been broken in transit; see Southey to Charles Danvers 1 March 1804, Letter 905.</note> have done too much in
                    deducting the whole price of the broken bottles. the loss should be shared – be pleased therefore to settle it accordingly upon
                    this fair footing.</p><p rend="indent1"> Some thing was said in my last (which crost yours upon the road) respecting your coming here.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Danvers, 12 June 1804, Letter 952.</note> We expect &amp; intend to remain
                    here another summer – but Dear Danvers you know how little any man ought to calculate upon the stability of his plans, &amp; I
                    least of all men. So do not depend upon aught so uncertain, but come at once. About the <ref target="people.html#SmithThomas">Smiths</ref> I know nothing. you can easily find them out &amp; know their plans, &amp; regulate your own accordingly. Autumn
                    is of course the weather for colouring, but summer has the great advantage of longer days, &amp; of warmer weather for the Lake –
                    which is a main thing to be considered. I should almost advise you to set off without delay for the country is indeed in its
                    glory. Oh that you could have seen <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> on Friday evening last! I never saw such an
                    effect of sunset, many as I have seen.</p><p rend="indent1"> The books arrived, &amp; in admirable order, that box is my best traveller. my folios now assume a formidable
                    appearance when it is considered that they have all travelled three hundred miles by land – &amp; have another journey as long
                    before they will be finally at rest. I get on steadily &amp; <hi rend="ital">con amore</hi>,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning ‘with love’.</note> – indeed so much so that nothing less than the arrival of a proof sheet will be
                    sufficient to turn my attention to Madoc.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem <title>Madoc</title>, which Southey had
                        written in 1797–1799 and since then had been intermittently revising. It was completed in October 1804 and published in
                        1805.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">The child</ref> grows well – kicks bravely, takes notice &amp; begins to occupy some of
                    my time in playing with her. I am uneasy to observe how frightfully she starts at any sudden noise. She is dreadfully troubled
                    with wind – so as to throw her into strange agitations during sleep – sudden starts, &amp; uneasy sounds, &amp; flinging about the
                    arms. Ask <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> by what regimen of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">the mother</ref>
                    – or child this can be relieved. it is worse after she has taken the breast, than after any other food, – for we let her eat. Ask
                    him too to tell me some carminative which we may keep at hand &amp; give often with least injury. her digestion goes on well, –
                    which was rarely the case with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">her poor sister</ref>. these uneasinesses usually
                    end in her throwing up the milk – all other food stays with her. She grows finely however. her eyes are growing very bright –
                    &amp; when you have seen her two or three times you will begin to think she is not ugly.</p><p rend="indent1"> Bring down with you the little Romances del Cid<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Juan de Escobar (dates
                        unknown), <title>Romancero e Historia del Cid Ruy Diez de Bivar en Language Antigo</title> (1632), no. 3449 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey’s library, where it is described as a ‘fine copy, in green morocco’.</note> which Barry<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bartholomew Barry (dates unknown), a Bristol bookseller and stationer.</note> had to bind, any
                    new numbers of the Missionary Transactions from him<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Transactions of the
                            Missionary Society</title> were first issued as separate numbers, each dealing with a specific mission, from 1798 onwards.
                        They were gathered into volumes, the first including the transactions for the years 1795–1802 in the Pacific and South Africa,
                        the second beginning with further South African transactions (London, 1804) and containing <title>The Rev. Mr Kicherer’s
                            Narrative of the Mission to the Hottentots, and Boschemen; with a General Account of the South African
                        Missions</title>.</note> – &amp; any of the Baptist Missions Report since I left Bristol, from James.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac James (b. 1759) was the son of Samuel James (1716–1773), Baptist minister at Hitchin. He came to Bristol
                        in 1773 as a student at the Baptist Academy. During the late 1790s and early 1800s, James collaborated with <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref> in selling numerous works, mostly by dissenters. Among James’s own
                        works were <title>Providence Displayed: or, The Remarkable Adventures of Alexander Selkirk</title> (1800). He also tried his
                        hand at poetry, including <title>The Pilgrim’s Progress. The First Part: Rendered into Familiar Verse</title> (1815), as well
                        as a polemical work, <title>An Essay on the Sign of the Prophet Jonah</title> (1802). An associate of the members of the
                        Baptist Missionary Society Committee, James was well placed to supply the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist
                            Missionary Society</title>, 6 vols (1800–1817). These were published as a periodical beginning in 1793, but then as bound
                        volumes beginning in 1800. Southey reviewed <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title>
                        (1800–1801), in the <title>Annual Review for 1802</title> (1803), 207–218.</note> tell James too that Cape Gardefui should
                    properly be called Garde<hi rend="ital">fan</hi> which means the Straits of Burial. So says Bruce at the end of his first
                        volume,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Bruce, <title>Travels to Discover the Source of the Nile, In the Years
                            1768, 1769, 1770, 1771, 1772 and 1773</title>, 5 vols (Edinburgh, 1790), I, p. 443.</note><del>&amp; promises a reason afterwards which I have not yet found</del>. I know not that this interpretation will be of any use
                    to him, but it will show that I remember his projected work, &amp; take an interest in its progress. It was probably there, says
                    Bruce, Book 2. Chap. 4. where the East Wind drove ashore the bodies of such as had been shipwrecked in the voyage.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Bruce, <title>Travels to Discover the Source of the Nile, In the Years 1768, 1769, 1770, 1771,
                            1772 and 1773</title>, I, p. 443.</note>he will find
                    other etymologies in the same chapter which may turn to good account in his hands.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am uneasy about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. no letter for ten weeks, – &amp; I know he would
                    not lose any opportunity of writing. It does not appear whether or not the Galatea was at Surinam.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey’s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, was a fifth-rate 32-gun frigate. It did not
                        participate in the invasion of Surinam, the Dutch colony lying between French Guyana and Guyana, which took place in May 1804
                        when a British expedition led by Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762–1814; <title>DNB</title>)
                        attacked and took possession of the colony. Surinam was returned to the Dutch later that year.</note> – there are some
                    excellent remarks upon the capture in the Iris.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Iris; or, Norwich and Norfolk Weekly Advertiser</title> was the Norwich newspaper edited, from 1803–1804, by
                        Southey’s friend <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>.</note> I wish you saw that paper regularly. its
                    politics are more far-sighted than those of any London edition. – <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> not
                    yet come. I suppose that in his Highland walk the Scotch have either given him a very good reception – or that he has caught the
                    itch. he does not write &amp; we are daily or rather hourly expecting him. – Where is your brother Dan? he will fall in with <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> at Malta – &amp; may enquire for him if he does not, at <hi rend="ital">Doctor</hi> Stoddarts.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John Stoddart (1773–1856; <title>DNB</title>):
                        brother-in-law, from 1808 of <ref target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">William Hazlitt</ref> and from 1803 to 1807 the king’s
                        and the admiralty’s advocate at Malta, in which capacity he was an associate of Coleridge, who had recently taken up a
                        temporary post there as private secretary to Sir Alexander Ball (1757–1809), the naval officer governing Malta. Later he was
                        editor of <title>The Times</title> and <title>The New Times</title>, in which capacity he was satirised, alongside Southey, by
                        William Hone (1780–1842), in <title>A Slap at Slop</title> (1821).</note> &amp; how is your other brother going on? tho it is
                    a question I ask with little hope.</p><p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#TobinJamesWebbe">Tobin</ref> ! I was very sorry for his disappointment, &amp;
                    somewhat provoked at the absurdity of breaking it off upon a money question. poor fellow, he must find somebody who will [MS
                    obscured] to the blind. – Have you received the Henrys History from Cork?<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Henry
                        (1718–1790), <title>The History of Great Britain, From the First Invasion of it by the Romans under Julius Cæsar</title>
                        (1771–1793), was delayed in the post, its despatch having been entrusted by Southey’s brother Tom to the bookseller in Cork.
                        See letter 893 of this edition.</note> – &amp; what tidings of the books from Leghorn<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Livorno, on the western coast of Tuscany, Italy.</note> which were on their way a year ago? remember me to <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">Sam Reid</ref> of whom this reminds me – &amp; to William<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> – &amp; the Hort<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Jillard Hort
                        (1764–1849), Unitarian minister and writer.</note> – &amp; <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">Estlin</ref> – &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Roe<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably John Rowe (1764–1832), assistant minister at the
                        Unitarian chapel in Lewin’s Mead, Bristol, from 1798 until his death.</note> –. I have no prospect of seeing Bristol again,
                    except for a single day or so, if I should spend a few weeks at Bath before I settle, which is not unlikely, for the Baths would
                    probably be very useful to me. – <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> I conclude is very busy – remember me to him &amp;
                    the Queen. &amp; tell me how the Princess goes on.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> King’s child had been born in July
                        1803; his wife contracted childbed fever and was not fully recovered by November of that year.</note> &amp; how his physic
                    agrees with Joe. &amp; what news of Cupid.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joe and Cupid were dogs in Danvers’ care. Joe
                        was Thomas Southey’s dog, Cupid formerly Southey’s.</note> My dog Dapper is the veryest coward that ever carried a tail. the
                    very sucking pigs frighten him – but he is a good fellow for all that – &amp; I shall be very happy Sir to have the pleasure of
                    introducing you to him.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>