<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.978</idno><idno type="nines">rce2100</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849–1850), II, pp. 302–306 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="978" type="letter"><head>978. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1804-09-12">12 September
                        1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Galatea./ Barbadoes/ Or
                        Elsewhere/ Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ SEP 17/ 1804<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb/>Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849–1850), II, pp. 302–306 [in part].</note></head><opener><salute>Dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It is a heartless &amp; hopeless thing to write letter after letter when there seems so little probability of their
                    ever reaching you. How the Devil it is that all your letters seem to find me, &amp; none of mine to find you I cannot comprehend.
                    I write &amp; write &amp; write always directing Barbadoes or elsewhere – &amp; suppose that according to direction they go any
                    where elsewhere than to the Galatea.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey’s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, a fifth-rate 32-gun frigate.</note> Patience! &amp; once more to tell you what I have already told you in
                    half a score letters. All well. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">the
                        Edithling</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; myself. the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">young Edith</ref> is four months old, a thriving, good natured, lively girl, of whom you
                    would be very fond. What will surprize you <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is actually growing fat, – my own
                    skin &amp; bones remain in the same state as you left them, but bating an occasional diabetes, I am in sound health. my intention
                    is, God willing, to remain here till another year, &amp; in the autumn of 1805 to go once more to Lisbon, &amp; there remain one
                    two or three years, till my history be well &amp; effectually compleated.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                        ‘History of Portugal’, which was never completed.</note> Meantime these are my employments; to finish the correction &amp;
                    printing of Madoc,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was correcting proofs of <title>Madoc</title> (1805) while
                        still revising sections of the manuscript not yet sent to the printer.</note> to get thro my Annual work of reviewing – &amp;
                    to bring my history as far onward as possible. In the press I have 1. Metrical Tales &amp; other poems – being merely a corrected
                    republication of my best pieces from the Anthology.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s poems from the <title>Annual
                            Anthology</title> (1799–1800) reappeared in his <title>Metrical Tales and Other Poems</title> (1805).</note> 2. Specimens
                    of the Later English Poets – i.e. – of all who have <hi rend="ital">died</hi> from 1685 to 1800. this is meant as a supplement to
                        <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">George Ellis’s</ref> Specimens of the Early Poets, a book which you may remember at
                        Bristol.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, which he
                        jointly edited with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref>, was published with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807 as a companion to George Ellis’s, <title>Specimens of the Early
                            English Poets</title> (1790, 2nd edn. 1801, 3rd edn. 1803).</note> It will <del>xxx</del> fill two volumes in crown octavo
                    – the size of Ritsons English Romances<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Ritson (1752–1803; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Ancient Engleish Metrical Romanceës</title> (1802).</note> if you recollect them. 3. Madoc. in quarto. whereof 22
                    sheets are printed. one more finishes the first part, which ends with his return to America, formerly <del>xxx</del> contained in
                    six books, now split &amp; enlarged into 18 sections – 1150 lines having been added. the most important of these additions were
                    copied out in three letters for you by <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> – &amp; all went either to the French or
                    to the Sharks. Of how many sections the second part may consist I cannot yet tell. I expect to finish the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                    this evening, bringing me to the end of the old tenth book, about 1100 lines have been inserted between the old 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &amp; 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, &amp; there are yet about 500 of new story to be introduced. in about two months my
                    work will be done. <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Mr Ballantyne</ref> my Scotch Printer will do his by Xmas. he printed
                    the Minstrelsy of the Scotish Border<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Scott, <title>Minstrelsy of the Scottish
                            Border</title> (1802).</note> which perhaps you saw at Bristol. the vignettes are these – one in the title page designed
                    as emblematic of the main matter of the Poem, a Cross planted upon a rock, a palm tree hanging over it, &amp; a spring gushing at
                    its foot. the motto <hi rend="ital">in hoc signo</hi>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning ‘in this sign’, alluding to
                        the early Christian tradition that the Emperor Constantine I (272–337) had a vision of the sun with a cross above it and the
                        words ‘εν τούτῳ νίκα’ (meaning ‘by this, may you conquer’), which is
                        often translated in Latin as ‘In hoc signo vinces’. Constantine adopted the phrase for his battle standards.</note> in – or
                    under this sign or banner. then each of the two parts will have a separate black letter half title (i.e. a title page in every
                    respect except that neither my name, nor the publisher appear) for the first Pocock has drawn Madocs ship making to land, the ship
                    copied from one of William the Conqueror, going out with a fair breeze. for the second a Great Snake, some 25 feet long, sunning
                    himself at the mouth of a Cavern.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Madoc</title> (1805) has only three illustrations: the engraved titlepage with <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn’s</ref> shield upon a <title>trophée</title>; the palm and cross upon the rock (after the Table of Contents); and
                        the snake before the cave, engraved on the titlepage for the second part, ‘Madoc in Aztlan’ (bound incorrectly after 320
                        instead of after 184). It is probable that the image of the ship by Nicholas Pocock (1740–1821; <title>DNB</title>) was
                        omitted because Southey was displeased with the vessel’s anachronistic modernity; see Southey to Joseph Cottle, 25 August
                        1805, Letter 1097.</note> This Snake, who is a God, I have killed very ingeniously. do you remember the cave in Lea
                        Woods?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Leigh Woods, on the Avon gorge, near Clifton, Bristol. The cave is now part of
                        the grounds of Burwalls, a large house currently used as a conference centre by the University of Bristol.</note> with the
                    chasm above – the opening in the second or inner chamber? such a cave with such a sky light have I given this snake for his temple
                    – &amp; then dropt down a great stone upon him just to break his back &amp; fasten him down. To the notes, I design a fourth half
                    title with a groupe of armour Welsh &amp; Azteca – for the notes are to be all printed at the end. How am I to send you out a
                    copy? will it not be the best way to consign it to some Bristol Merchants agents? which can easily be done. <ref target="people.html#TobinJamesWebbe">Tobin</ref> could send it to Nevis,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> An island in
                        the Caribbean Sea, located near the northern end of the Lesser Antilles archipelago, about 350 km east-southeast of Puerto
                        Rico and 80 km west of Antigua.</note> if that lies at all within your reach. Probably by the time you can answer this
                    question the volume will be ready to send. – <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>, as you should ere then
                    have learnt either from himself or me, has been here since the beginning of July &amp; will yet remain about six weeks longer. We
                    mountaineerify together, &amp; bathe together, &amp; go on the lake together, &amp; have contrived to pass a delightful summer.
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> set off to go on board the Salvador del Mundo<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Salvador del Mundo</hi> was a 112-gun ship of the line, captured from the Spanish at the
                        battle of Cape St Vincent in 1797.</note> about two months ago, there to remain till Admiral Colpoys<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Colpoys (c. 1742–1821; <title>DNB</title>), British naval officer who achieved notoriety for inciting the
                        mutiny at Spithead in 1797. He was promoted to full Admiral in 1801 and appointed as Commander-in-Chief at Plymouth in 1803.
                        In 1804 he gave up his command to take a seat in the Admiralty.</note> shipped him off to some foreign station. he has since
                    written to let me know his arrival. <ref target="people.html#ThomasDr">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Thomas</ref> has given him money to
                    fit himself out with so little discretion that he makes that &amp; his expences for a month <del>xxx</del> amount to 140£! I have
                    put <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> affairs into a Lawyers hand &amp; trust that they will now be
                    managed <del>xxx</del> with more prudence &amp; more care, for the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> has most scandalously suffered them to
                    go to wreck &amp; ruin, neither acting like a friend, nor a man of business. Thus you have all the family news.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> left us this morning. he came with Saxton <del>xx</del> a son of the Portsmouth
                        commissioner<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> A son of Sir Charles Saxton Bart (1732–1808): Resident Commissioner of
                        his Majesty’s Navy at Portsmouth.</note> &amp; we made a pleasant four days. I expect <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> every day. Your old friends M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Halliday<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> are on a visit to <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel Peachey</ref> here, who
                    lives on the Island. we dined there a few days ago, &amp; they claimed acquaintance with me on the strength of their acquaintance
                    with you. I mean to write by them to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">Aunt Molly-Melinda</ref>, &amp; tell her how we are all
                    going on in the world. To the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">old Gentleman</ref> I think of sending Madoc in a respectable
                    cover, carriage paid, &amp; to announce its coming in a frank. I shall give him in the letter the latest news of you &amp; see how
                    he will take it, as probably he will think fit to acknowledge the book, if he chuses to accept it as I suppose he will. the volume
                    will be exceedingly handsome – of course his will be a large paper copy – &amp; it may flatter him to see the family name appear
                    so respectably.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am learning Dutch – &amp; wish you were here to profit by my lessons at the breakfast table &amp; to
                        Mynheerify<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dutch title of respect, originating in the phrase ‘Du mijn heer’ meaning
                        ‘my lord’.</note> with me, as you like the language. my reason for attaining this language is that as the Dutch conquered, or
                    rather destroyed the Portugueze empire in Asia, the history of the downfall of that empire is of course more fully related by
                    Dutch than by Portugueze historians. how get you on with your Spanish? I am thinking that if peace take place &amp; you get paid
                    off while we are at Lisbon (which God grant) that you may join us there, &amp; in that case you will find Spanish may soon change
                    into Portugueze – so think of that, &amp; let it be an additional motive for going on. – You ask for politics. I can tell you
                    little; – but as for invasion it still continues the same humbug &amp; bugbear as when it was first bruited abroad to gull the
                    people on both sides the water. Bonaparte dare not attempt. would to God he did, defeat would be certain &amp; his ruin
                    inevitable. as it is he must lose reputation by threatening what he cannot execute, &amp; I believe that the Bourbons will finally
                    be restored. At home politics look excellently well. the coalition of <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox</ref> &amp;
                    the Grenvilles<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The followers of <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William Wyndham,
                            Baron Grenville</ref>, who had formed a political coalition with Charles James Fox.</note> has been equally honourable to
                    all parties, &amp; produced the best possible effect, in rooting out the last remains of that political violence which for many
                    years so divided the country. The death of the King,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738–1820, King of Great
                        Britain 1760–1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> or another fit of madness which is very probable, or his abdication which most
                    people think would be very proper, or the declining health of Pitt,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Pitt (1759–1806;
                        <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783–1801, 1804–1806.</note> or the actual strength of the opposition, are things <del>singly or collected</del> of which every one is
                    very likely to bring this coalition to power, &amp; in that case neither you nor I should want friends. So live in hope, as you
                    have good cause to do. steer clear of the sharks &amp; the land-crabs, &amp; be sure that we shall both of us one day be as well
                    off as we could.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Hallidays are visiting <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel Peachey</ref> whose wife I find was also
                    of Bishops Lediard<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bishop’s Lydeard: a town near Taunton, Somerset.</note> a <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Miss Charter</ref>. both she &amp; her sister knew you well by name &amp; all your Taunton
                    friends. We are getting upon excellently good terms, for they are very pleasant &amp; truly womanly women, which is the best
                    praise that can be bestowed upon woman. Will you not laugh &amp; cry zounds to hear that I have actually been employed all this
                    evening in making arrangements for a subscription ball at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>? I – very I – your
                    brother R.S. to what vile purposes may we come! It was started by <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp;
                    Miss Charter<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The sister of <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, her
                        first name and dates are unknown.</note> at the theatre (for we have a strolling company at an alehouse here) – &amp; he &amp;
                    I &amp; General Peche<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Peche (dates unknown), who had served in the East India
                        Company’s army, gazetted as Colonel in 1796 and Major-General in 1798.</note> have settled it – &amp; all Cumberland will now
                    envy the gaieties of <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. Mrs General<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">The wife
                        of General Peche; her first name and dates are unknown.</note> insisted upon my opening the ball with her – I advised her as
                    she was for performing impossibilities to begin with turning the wind – before she could hope to turn me – so I shall sup my tea,
                    &amp; talk with the old folks some hour or so – &amp; then steal home to write Madoc – drink my solitary glass of punch – &amp;
                    get to bed at a good Xtianlike hour – as my father, &amp; no doubt his fathers, did before me. Oh Tom that you were but here – for
                    in truth we lead as pleasant a life as heart of man could wish. I have not for many years taken such constant exercise as this
                    summer. Some friend or acquaintance or other is perpetually making his appearance – &amp; out then go I to lacquey them on the
                    lake or over the mountains. by the Lord I shall get a character for politeness!</p><p rend="indent1"> I have so far altered my original plan of the history to resolve upon not introducing the Life of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Francesco<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> St Francis of Assisi (Giovanni Francesco di Bernardone;
                        1181/1182–1226): the founder of the Order of Friars Minor, more commonly known as the Franciscans.</note> &amp; the chapters
                    therewith connected, but to reserve them for <del>xxx</del> a separate History of Monachism, which will make a very interesting
                    &amp; amusing work. a good honest quarto may comprise it. the whole historical labours will then consist of three separate works.
                    1. Hist. of Portugal – the European part, 3 Vols. 2. Hist. of the Portugueze Empire in Asia 2 or 3 Vols. 3. Hist of Brazil. 4.
                    Hist. of the Jesuits &amp; Japan. 5. Literary History of Spain &amp; Portugal. 2 Vols. 6. Hist of Monachism. In all 10 – 11 – or
                    12 quarto volumes &amp; you cannot easily imagine with what pleasure I look at all this labour before me.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Only the <title>History of Brazil</title>, of these projected works, was finished and published, in
                        1810–1819.</note> God give me life – health – eyesight – &amp; as much leisure as even now I have – &amp; done it shall
                    be.</p><closer><salute rend="indent0"> God bless you.</salute></closer><postscript><p>Sept 12. 1804. I send this off in the middle of a month – to see if it will have a better chance<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> This postscript is written at the top of the first page of the letter.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>