<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1666</idno><idno type="nines">rce2788</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Scotland, MS
                        3878.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251 [dated 6 Aug].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1666" type="letter"><head>1666. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, <date when="1809-08-08">8 August
                        1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Scott Esq<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>/ [deletion
                        and readdress in another hand] <del>Edinburgh</del>/ &lt;Achesteel/ Selkirk&gt; <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: AU/
                        1809/ 10<lb/>Endorsement: Southey/ 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. August/ 1809<lb/>MS: National Library of Scotland, MS
                        3878<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251 [dated 6 Aug].</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Scott</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The Quest is over.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In July 1809, Southey was informed by <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Richard Sharp</ref> that the stewardship of the Derwentwater Estates (which were owned
                        by Greenwich Hospital) would soon become vacant on the death of the incumbent. Southey asked several friends, including
                        Senhouse and <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">George Beaumont</ref> to intercede on his behalf, but in the end it
                        was considered to be unsuitable for him.</note> I believe the Stewardship would have been promised me had I been fit for it,
                    but Lord Mulgraves<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The politician Henry Phipps, 1st Earl of Mulgrave (1755–1831;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> words are – ‘a knowledge of agriculture, a practical experience in the management of mines,
                    knowledge in the cultivation &amp; profit of woods, – in short a man born, bred, educated, &amp; occupied in the superintendance
                    of such property as the Greenwich estates, must be sought for when a vacancy occurs’. This answer <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G. Beaumont</ref> has communicated to me. I learn from another quarter too that the
                    present possessor ‘with all his knowledge, assiduity &amp; rapidity in the mode of transacting business, has always been employed
                    for 17 or 18 hours out of every 24 together with his first Clerk.’ – All therefore that I have to regret is – having relied so
                    implicitly upon <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharps</ref> information, <del>&amp;</del> as to apply for the post before
                    I had thoroughly ascertained my own competency for it. – This was only one blunder. Another was in supposing there was no English
                    Historiographer – Old Dutens has had the office, with a salary of 400 £, for many years,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Louis Dutens (1730–1812; <title>DNB</title>), a French Protestant, held the post of Historiographer Royal until his death on
                        23 May 1812. Southey’s campaign for the post proved unsuccessful and it was given to James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765–1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> – upon what plea they who gave it him can best tell. My aim mu[MS torn]ow<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Text given as ‘must now’ in Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251.</note> be to succeed him whenever he pleases to move
                    off, obtaining, if possible, [MS torn]crease<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Text given as ‘increase’ in Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251.</note>
                    of salary so as to make it equivalent to what it originally was. And toward[MS torn]<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Text
                        given as ‘towards’ in Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251.</note> this I hope some way is gained by what has already been done. – I go to [MS
                        torn]wther<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Text given as ‘Lowther’ in Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251. Lowther Castle, the residence of
                            <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref>, near Penrith in Cumbria.</note> this day week, &amp;
                    according as I feel my footing, will contrive to have my views &amp; wishes explained.</p><p rend="indent1"> There came last night a letter from <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis</ref>, communicating the result of
                    his conversation with <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref>. I have thanked him for his friendly interference
                    &amp; told him how things stand.</p><p rend="indent1"> I will do my best for <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref>, &amp; going to work with clear
                    views of the subject, &amp; a thorough knowledge of the Spanish &amp; Portugueze character, – I shall come to it with great
                        advantages.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had agreed to provide historical material for Ballantyne’s
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> That lamentable ground over which poor Sir J Moore retreated (as one of
                    his own officers expresses it) ‘faster than flesh &amp; blood could follow him’<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John
                        Moore (1761–1809; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish General with a long and varied military career. He was also MP for Lanark
                        Burghs 1784–1790. After the controversial Convention of Cintra (1808), Moore was given the command of the British troops in
                        the Iberian peninsula. He was fatally wounded at the Battle of Corunna on 16 January 1809. Moore’s actions were posthumously
                        defended by his brother, James Moore (1763–1860; <title>DNB</title>), in <title>A Narrative of the Campaign of the British
                            Army in Spain, Commanded by His Excellency Sir John Moore. Authenticated by Official Papers and Original Letters</title> (1809). For Southey’s account, see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 442–459. Although he
                        praised many of Moore’s personal qualities, Southey suggested that he was not ‘equal to the difficulties of his situation’
                        (458).</note> – I paced on foot, loitering along that my footpace might not outstrip a lazy coach &amp; six. &amp; my
                    recollection of passes where five hundred Englishmen could have stopt an army is as vivid as if I had just seen them. Bonaparte
                    owes more to the blunders of his enemies than to his own abilities, – &amp; he has no surer allies than those writers who prepare
                    our very Generals to fear him, by constantly representing him as not to be conquered. Oh for Peterborough!<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Mordaunt, 3rd Earl of Peterborough and 1st Earl of Monmouth (1658?–1735;
                            <title>DNB</title>), renowned for his daring tactics in an earlier war in Spain.</note> Oh ‘for a single hour of
                        Dundee.’<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Line 11 of Wordsworth’s sonnet ‘In the Pass of Killiecranky’ (1803),
                        referring to John Graham, 1st Viscount of Dundee (known as Bonnie Dundee; 1648?–1689;<title> DNB</title>), Jacobite army
                        officer.</note> – Sir John Moore was as brave a man as ever died in battle, – but he had that fear upon him, – his imagination
                    was cowed &amp; intimidated, – tho his heart was not. And now because the Galicians did not turn out &amp; expose themselves to
                    certain destruction by or attempting to protect an army, – whom he would not suffer to protect themselves – a party in this
                    count[MS torn]<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Text given as ‘Country’ in Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251.</note><del>attempted</del> &lt;are labouring&gt; to prove that we ought to abandon the Spaniards! Assuredly if I am [MS torn]rite<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Text given as ‘to write’ in Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence
                            of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251.</note> the history of the campaign not a syllable
                    shall be set down in malice, but [MS torn]<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Text given as ‘by Heaven’ in Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251.</note>
                    Heaven I will nothing extenuate. – the retreat shall be painted in its true colours [MS torn]<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Text given as ‘of’ in Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                        Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251.</note> shame &amp; horror, – accurately to the very life, – or
                    rather the very death, – for [MS torn]eath<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Text given as ‘death’ in Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251.</note>
                    it was, – not only to the wretched women &amp; children – who never should have been permitted to enter Spain, but to man &amp;
                    beast, – both marched till <del>death</del> flesh &amp; blood failed them, &amp; the men broken-hearted to think that their lives
                    were thus ignominiously wasted.</p><p rend="indent1"> If I thought you repeated the Retainers wish in sober earnest, – I could not in conscience wish your Old Man of the
                    Sea were off your shoulders,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> An allusion to Scott’s own allusion to the story of Sinbad
                        in the <title>Arabian Nights’ Tales</title> in which the Old Man of the Sea was a burden carried on the shoulders of his
                        companions. In a note to <title>Marmion</title> (Edinburgh, 1808), Scott describes ‘the relics of St. Cuthbert. The Saint was,
                        however, a most capricious fellowtraveller: which was the more intolerable, as like Sinbad’s Old Man of the Sea, he journeyed
                        upon the shoulders of his companions. They paraded him through Scotland for several years’ (p. xlvii). Scott’s burden in this
                        case was the editing work on <title>English Minstrelsy. Being a Selection of Fugitive Poetry from the Best English Authors;
                            with some Original Pieces Hitherto Unpublished</title> (1810).</note> – but I believe whenever he is laid down, doing what
                    you please will be doing much, &amp; that we shall have more Marmions<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott’s
                            <title>Marmion</title> (1808).</note> &amp; William of Delorains.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott’s
                            <title>The Lay of the Last Minstrel: A Poem</title> (1805).</note><ref target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> waggery was new to me<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Byron’s
                            <title>English Bards and Scotch Reviewers</title> (1809).</note> &amp; I cannot help wishing you may some day have an
                    opportunity of giving him the retort as neatly as you have given it to that poor envious old Cumberland.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Scott had reviewed Richard Cumberland (1732–1811; <title>DNB</title>), <title>John de Lancaster: A
                            Novel</title> (1809) in the <title>Quarterly Review</title> 1 (May 1809), 337–348.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I have fixed myself here by a lease of one &amp; twenty years, which after many weary procrastinations was executed
                    a few days ago.</p><p rend="indent1"> I had nearly forgotten to say something concerning Morte Arthur. [MS torn]<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Text given as ‘It is’ in Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251.</note> now more than a year that I have been playing the dog in the [MS torn]nger<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Text given as ‘manger’ in Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence
                            of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251.</note> towards you, – but the fault is not in me.
                        <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has been to blame in adjourning the printing the work sine die.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning ‘indefinitely’.</note> I will in my next letter state to him that in making me use
                    you ill, – &amp; [MS torn]<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Text given as ‘that’ in Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 248–251.</note> if there be
                    any farther delay I shall feel myself bound to throw up the business<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s edition of
                        Thomas Malory’s (c. 1415–1471; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Birth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur: Of his Noble Knyghtes of
                            the Rounde Table, they’r Merveyllous Enquestes and Aduentures ... : and in the end, Le Morte D’Arthur, with the Dolourous
                            Deth and Departyng out of thys Worlde of them Al</title> was finally published by Longman in 1817.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1809-08-08">Tuesday Aug 8. 1809.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>