<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013-05-27</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1371</idno>
            <idno type="nines">rce2493</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                  1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                  only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                  redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                        Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                  that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                  additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                  all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Huntington Library, RS 118. Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
               (London, 1856), II, pp. 20–22 [in part].</p>
            <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
            <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript
               Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
               Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University
               Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
               Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University; the John Rylands Library,
               Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
               Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public
               Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
               Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne;
               the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
            <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the English Department of
               Nottingham Trent University.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Southey’s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
               <category xml:id="people">
                  <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
               <category xml:id="places">
                  <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
            <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
            <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
            <list>
               <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
            <list>
               <item>corrections from proofing</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
            <list>
               <item>TEI Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="1371" type="letter">
            <head>1371. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1807-10-05">5 October
                  1807</date>
               <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Harting/ near/ Petersfield/
                  Hampshire/ Single<lb/>Endorsement: RS./ 5 Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1807<lb/>Postmark: E./ OCT 8/ 1807<lb/>MS: Huntington Library,
                  RS 118. ALS; 4p.<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4
                  vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 20–22 [in part].</note>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
            </opener>
            <p rend="indent1">
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa’s</ref> father was a man of some property, who was resident either in or near
               Leominster, in Herefordshire; his family is I believe very distantly connected with my own, I having heard Bishop Duppa claimed as
               kinsman on my mother’s side, – a relationship of which I am not very proud, holding the said Bishop to have had a hand in the
               manufactory of the Eikon Basilike.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Brian Duppa (1588–1662; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of
                  Winchester, and favoured cleric of the royal household of Charles I, whose spiritual meditations as execution approached were
                  published as <title>Eikon Basilike, The Pourtrature of His Sacred Majestie in His Solitudes and Sufferings</title> (1649). Duppa is
                  not thought by modern scholars to have had a hand in the book’s authorship.</note>
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> has two elder brothers the one a clergyman in good circumstances; the elder
               a country gentleman I believe – he himself by the late death of his father inherits some small independence, – little, but enough for
               an independant man.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I have known him since the Installation at Oxford, in 1793, where he was introduced to me by his relation &amp; my
               nearest &amp; dearest friend, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund Seward</ref>. Of his Education I can tell you
               little, – it was in this country &amp; I suspect not very good. He learnt the art of engraving from Heath<note n="2" place="foot"
                  resp="editors"> James Heath (1757–1834; <title>DNB</title>), engraver of illustrations for many literary works.</note> I believe, –
               but never practised it as a trade, – went abroad &amp; continued there for three years, – &amp; since his return has published those
               heads, his Subversion of the Papal Government, &amp; his life of Michael Angelo.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  <title>A Selection of Twelve Heads from the Last Judgment of Michael Angelo</title> (1801), <title>A Brief Account of the Subversion
                     of the Papal Government in 1798</title> (1799) and <title>Literary Works of Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with His Poetry and
                     Letters</title> (1806), the latter including translations by Southey and <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam"
                     >Wordsworth</ref>.</note> – I guess his age at from 5 to 7 &amp; 30. <ref type="m" target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony"
                  >Carlisle</ref> has known him longer than I have &amp; can probably tell you more of his history previous to his going abroad.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> He knows the Arts well, &amp; loves them disinterestedly; – they have been his pursuit rather than his profession.
               Whatever is connected with them he has studied seriously, – anatomy in particular &amp; I believe he has a good knowledge of
                  <del>xxxxx</del> other branches of science.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">
               <hi rend="ital">Medriociter</hi> we must rank his classical knowledge.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> was seeking preferment to a post at the British Museum vacated by the
                  death of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace Bedford</ref>.</note> to this he never makes any
               pretensions; – &amp; if he would not aim at style, <del>he xx</del> he would, like another <ref type="m"
                  target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">good friend of ours</ref>, write better. Now I know nothing more, &amp; all this amounts to very
               little; – of his soundness, &amp; his knowledge of what odd things there are in the world which make him so pleasant a companion, you
               know as much as myself. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> told me long since of a marriage engagement
               pending, between him &amp; Miss Page,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Page (dates unknown).</note> – a xxx cousin of the
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Bedfords</ref>, who lived with them. I should be glad if it was carried into
               effect. The Lady is an acquaintance of mine, suitable to him in age. &amp; one whom, for her thoroughly happy temper I like so well,
               that it would give me pleasure to hear she had found a comfortable home before the total wreck &amp; ruin of that family takes place,
               as it must do upon the death of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>, which is, I very much fear
               to be expected.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s fears were prompted by the recent death of Bedford’s brother, <ref
                     type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref>, and a liver complaint from which Bedford had been suffering; see
                  Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 2 January 1807, Letter 1255.</note> Very likely it is this engagement which makes him wish for
               the situation in request. Would it be of any use if <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> were to
               interest <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">his brother</ref> &lt;for&gt; <del>xxx</del> him, he being of
               authority at Lambeth?<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Christopher Wordsworth had influence as a chaplain at Lambeth Palace,
                  home of the Archbishop of Canterbury, because he had tutored the Archbishop’s son Charles Manners Sutton (1780–1845;
                     <title>DNB</title>). Wordsworth’s son John (1805–1839; <title>DNB</title>) was born at Lambeth, where Christopher was granted the
                  living of St Mary’s in 1816.</note> If so, lose no time in telling me.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I have received lately several works of the ex-Jesuits, concerning South America. This body of men seem to have been
               useful to the last, &amp; to have employed their old age, cruelly as they had been treated, in leaving all their knowledge to
               posterity. Among them is a famous catalogue of all existing languages, by Hervas, originally published by him in Italian in 1784, but
               now greatly enlarged &amp; extended in Spanish, his native <del>language</del> tongue.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lorenzo
                  Hervás y Panduro (1735–1809), <title>Catalogo de las Lenguas de las Naciones Conocidas</title> (1800–1805).</note> It is to be
               followed by grammars &amp; vocabularies, – the whole treasure of their missionary school. From this catalogue I have collected some
               curious facts respecting S America, – among others the singular one that none of the languages there have any affinity to those spoken
               in N America. He believes in the tales of Atlantis, &amp; thinks this half of the new world was peopled from thence, &amp; so
               originally from Africa, – his proofs of the latter fact are from etymology, – which cannot be appreciated till his vocabularies appear;
               – of the former, the chain of soundings, from Brazil to Africa. The Araucans<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Indian nations
                  that dominated what is now the central part of Chile. They fought successfully against conquest by the Spanish in the sixteenth
                  century and against subjugation within independent Chile for much of the nineteenth century. Southey praised them in his ‘Song of
                  the Araucans During a Thunder Storm’, published in the <title>Morning Post</title>, 1799. See <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works
                     1793–1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), V, <title>Selected Shorter Poems</title>, ed. Lynda Pratt, pp.
                  372–374.</note> speak a language more excellently artificial than any other even than the Greek: &amp; in some of the islands off
               their coast the language is Spanish adapted to the Araucan grammar. – The Mexicans &amp; Peruvians (like the Romans) spread their
               language with their arms, &amp; consequently each extended over a prodigious extent of country, – thus greatly facilitating the
               conquests of the Spaniards. But the Jesuits found it better to learn the savage dialects of the different tribes than to teach them
               Spanish, – for this obvious reason, that thus they kept them to themselves. This Paraguay hist. will be very curious, never yet having
               been touched upon with decent impartiality.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I have collected the titles of many other works relating to S America, which I will send for to Italy whenever I can
               find out how to do it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I wish this may be true about Portugal &amp; Brazil, – but doubt it.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> That the
                  royal family of Portugal would take the court to Brazil to escape Napoleonic conquest of the mother country, thus giving Southey’s
                     <title>History of Brazil</title> greater currency with the publishers of <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow">Paternoster
                     Row</ref>, London. This came to pass on 29 November 1807, when a British squadron escorted the Prince Regent and the Queen, his
                  mother, across the Atlantic.</note> If it should, my book will be worth something in the <ref target="places.html#PaternosterRow"
                  >Row</ref>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Thank <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Mrs R.</ref> for her good wishes, I have about four days work
               only to finish the body of the Cid.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the
                     Cid</title> (1808).</note> The notes &amp; introduction are more than half done. I go soon to reviewing, &amp; think of appearing
               in London as soon as that shall be over, – probably in January: – or perhaps may wait a few weeks to see the arrival of a son or
               daughter – expected about that time.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
               <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <date when="1807-10-05">Oct 5. 1807.</date>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
