<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1496</idno><idno type="nines">rce2618</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 162–164 [in
                        part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1496" type="letter"><head>1496. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1808-08-16">16 August 1808</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey./ H. M. S. Dreadnought/ Plymouth Dock/ or
                        elsewhere <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 162–164 [in
                        part].</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> is gone to Spain! to fight as a private in the Spanish army, &amp; he
                    has found two Englishmen to go with him. A noble fellow this is something like the days of old as we poets &amp; romancers
                    represent them, something like the best part of chivalry, – old honours, old generosity, old heroism are reviving, – &amp; the
                    career of that cursed monkey nation is stopt, I believe &amp; fully trust, now &amp; for ever. A man like <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> cannot long remain without command, – &amp; of all things in this world I
                    should most rejoice to hear that King Joseph<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph-Napoléon Bonaparte (1768–1844) was the
                        elder brother of Napoleon, who made him King of Naples and Sicily (1806–1808), and King of Spain and the Indies as Joseph I of
                        Spain (1808–1813).</note> has fallen into his hands: – he would infallibly hang him upon the nearest tree, first as a
                    Bonaparte by blood, secondly as a Frenchman by adoption, thirdly as a King by trade.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is vexatious that he did not get the second batch of Kehama<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                        poem <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, which he was sending to <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> in
                        instalments.</note> before his departure, – which he would have done had you been here to have copied it. I get on regularly,
                    an hour in the morning before breakfast, slow &amp; sure. The 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Section (a very long one – 358 lines) is
                    finished, &amp; I am 50 lines on in the next, – in all 1933 – an increase of something more like 1000 since the poem has been
                    resumed. I am about the Enchantress who helps Arvalan to his travelling air-car, for which in my conscience I think I deserve a
                    patent, the invention being wholly my own. In the course of a week I hope to rib him in ice at the North Pole, &amp; then I shall
                    proceed to revolutionize the Swerga.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Events in <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>, Book
                        11.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The first proof of the Appendix with <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Freres</ref> translation reached me
                    last night, – it will fill about three sheets &amp; a half.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Three of Frere’s translations
                        from the <title>Poema del Cid</title> were appended to Southey’s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title>.</note> In
                    a fortnight the book may be expected to make its appearance, &amp; then your copy will set off for Plymouth. <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">King Arthur</ref> is deposed from the Annual Review. – I am as you know, <del>xx</del> very
                    well disposed to see such personages cashiered when they misbehave. <ref target="people.html#ReesThomas">Thomas Rees</ref>, a
                    dissenting clergyman, brother to the Rees of [MS obscured]eeds in his stead,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Rees
                        (1777–1864; <title>DNB</title>), Unitarian minister and writer on theological history, brother of <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Owen Rees</ref>, partner with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>,
                        publisher of the <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> – a change greatly for the better, &amp; with which I am [MS obscured]
                    pleased.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Miss Sewards</ref> criticism has appeared in the Gentlemans Magazine,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘A Letter written by Anna Seward to one of her Literary friends, Feb. 15, 1806, on the subject of Mr.
                        Southey’s “Madoc” and before she had any acquaintance, personal or by pen, with that gentleman’ appeared in <title>The
                            Gentleman’s Magazine</title>, 78.2 (1808), 577–581.</note> – her verses have not been inserted in the Courier, which is
                    rather odd. She reads Madoc to all her acquaintance, &amp; must be the means of selling several copies.</p><p rend="indent2"> ___</p><p>Another Island came up on Saturday last which I shall visit the first fine day, probably with <ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref> &amp; Jonathan Ottley,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jonathan
                        Otley (1766–1856), geologist, clockmaker, map maker, mountain guide.</note> who is going to measure it, &amp; catch a bottle
                    of the gas, – Jonathan being as you know our <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> philosopher. We are having a spell of
                    wind &amp; rain.</p><p rend="indent1"> We have got the prettiest kitten you ever saw, – a dark tabby, &amp; we have christened her by the heathenish name
                    of Dido. You would be very much diverted to see her hunt <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> all round the
                    kitchen, playing with his little bare feet, which she just pricks at every pat, &amp; the faster he moves back, the more she paws
                    them, while he squealls &amp; fights, &amp; cries naughty Dido, &amp; points to his feet &amp; says hurt – hurt – naughty Dido, –
                    presently he feeds her with poppin bits, which Dido plays with awhile, but soon returns to her old game. You have lost the amusing
                    part of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herberts</ref> childhood, – just when he is trying to talk, &amp; endeavouring to
                    say every thing.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#JacksonWilliam">Jackson</ref> is making a bathing-house down there at the bottom of the orchard, – which
                    I suppose nobody will ever use. I have been in the water very seldom since you went, – but the last time I accomplished the great
                    job of fairly swimming on my back, – which is a step equal to that of getting ones first commission. We drank tea out a few nights
                    ago with the Wolseleys,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reverend Robert Wolseley (d. 1815), son of William Wolseley, 6th Baronet (1740–1817). The family seat was at Wolseley Park, Rugeley in Staffordshire.</note> – &amp;
                    they were so well pleased with it that we shall probably take them again when the weather permits.</p><p rend="indent1"> I boggle at your third section of Kehama, because that must be turned into rhyme. the two first are transcribed, –
                    the first with many alterations, &amp; I have written (by this post) to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 16 August 1808,
                        Letter 1494.</note> to know whether I cannot contrive to frank by his means, thro his friend <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>, &amp; <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref>, – for
                    the second inclosures may perhaps make them above weight for an ordinary frank, &amp; till Parliament meets I have no way of
                    procuring <del>xx</del> Imperial ones.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, franks obtained through Rickman, who
                        worked in the office of the ‘Emperor of the Franks’ Speaker of the House of Commons <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbot</ref>.</note> – The story opens upon me in its progress, – every seed &amp; bud in the embryo plan
                    ripening, &amp; blossoming fairly out. – I hope too that the opening of Pelayo<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> An early
                        name for the poem which became <title>Roderick, Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> is pretty well arranged, but I will
                    not begin upon it till I come to a stop in Kehama. You will not perhaps be surprized to hear that two of my old dreams are likely
                    to be introduced with powerful effect in this poem: – good proof that it was well worth while to keep even the imperfect register
                    which I have. The fact is that what happens to Nebuchadnezzar is perpetually happening to me, – I forget my dreams, &amp; have no
                    Daniel to help out my recollection;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the Book of Daniel 2, Daniel is alone able to
                        interpret King Nebuchadnezzar’s dreams.</note> – &amp; if by chance I do remember them, unless they are instantly written
                    down, the impression passes away, almost as lightly as the dream itself. – Do you remember the story of Mickle the Poet<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Mickle (1735–1788; <title>DNB</title>), poet and translator from the Portuguese of
                        the <title>Lusiads</title> of Luís Vaz de Camões (c. 1524–1580), <title>The Lusiad, or, The Discovery of India</title>
                        (1776).</note> who always regretted that he could not remember the poetry which he composed in his sleep, – it was, he said,
                    so infinitely superior to any thing which he produced in his waking hours. – One morning he awoke, &amp; repeated the lamentation
                    over his unhappy fortune, that he should compose such sublime poetry – &amp; yet lose it for ever! – what, said his wife, who
                    happened to be awake, – were you writing poetry? – yes, <del>said</del> he &lt;replied&gt;, – &amp; such poetry that I should give
                    the world to remember it. Well then, <del>xx</del> said she, I <del>xx</del> did luckily hear the last lines, &amp; I am sure I
                    remember them exactly – they were –</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> by Heaven I’ll wreck my woes</l><l rend="indent3"> Upon the cowslip &amp; the pale primrose. </l></lg><p rend="indent1">This is one of <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharpes</ref> stories, it is true, – &amp; an excellently good
                    one it is. – I am not such a dreamer as Mickle, for what I can remember is worth remembering, – &amp; one of the wildest scenes in
                    Kehama will prove this.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1808-08-16">Aug. 16. 1808.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>