<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1307</idno><idno type="nines">rce2429</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, HM 4855 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life
                            and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 189–195.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1307" type="letter"><head>1307. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1807-04-13">13 April
                        1807</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ William Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich/ Single<lb/>Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 21 May<lb/>Stamped:
                        KESWICK/298<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, HM 4855 <lb/>Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life
                            and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 189–195.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1807-04-13">April 13. 1807</date></dateline><salute>My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Just as your letter arrived I was about to begin a Keswick Extraordinary Gazette for you. Great news from my little
                    world.</p><p rend="indent1"> When the last Ministry saw that out they must go, <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> thought of
                    saving some thing for me out of the fire. He could only get an offer for a place in the Island of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        Lucia,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The post of Register of the Vice-Admiralty Court of St. Lucia.</note> worth
                    about 600 £ a year, – there was no time to divine my answer,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn, [25 March 1807], Letter 1298.</note> but he divined it rightly, &amp; refused. Instead, one of <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord G.s</ref><note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Wyndham Grenville, 1st Baron
                        Grenville (1759–1834; <title>DNB</title>), Wynn’s maternal uncle, Prime Minister. His administration fell in March
                        1807.</note> last acts was to give me a pension of 200 £ to which the King “graciously assented” – – You cannot be more amused
                    at finding me a pensioner than I am at finding myself so. – I am not however a richer man than before. Hitherto <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> has given me an annuity of 160, – which I felt no pain in accepting from the
                    oldest friend I have in the world, with whom my intimacy was formed before we were either of &lt;us&gt; old enough to think of
                    differences of rank &amp; fortune. But <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> is not a rich man for his rank, – so
                    little so that he could not marry till he got a place, – &amp; of course I shall receive this no longer from him, now that it is
                    no longer necessary. Of 200 £, the taxes have the modesty to deduct 56, &amp; the Exchequer pays irregularly. he is in luck who
                        <del>xx</del> &lt;has&gt; only one quarter arrears – so <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> tells
                    me – who has an office there. I therefore lose 16 £ per year during war, &amp; gain 4 £ whenever the income tax is repealed;
                        <del>x</del> having the discomfort always of uncertain remittances. – <del>xxxx</del> – it is but wearing a few more grey
                    goose quills to the stump <del>during</del> in the course of the year: &amp; in the course of one year I have better hope than I
                    ever yet had of getting a head, as you will presently see.</p><p rend="indent1"> The last copy of MSS. for Espriellas Letter sets out this night on its way to Richard Taylor,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been sending copy for <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella.
                            Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807) to the printer Richard Taylor (1781–1858; <title>DNB</title>).</note> – &amp;
                    it is his fault that the book is not already published, but he has not given me one sheet a week. I have just a fortnights close
                    work to compleat the revisal of Palmerin, – about which I was in fact taken in. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> spake to me with admiration of the
                    language of Palmerin of England – as the most rhythmical prose they had ever seen. I knew <del>what</del> the original romance,
                    &amp; when <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> (during my last stay in London) said that <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis</ref> had recommended him to reprint it, consented to preface &amp; revise it,
                    correcting the costume so as to give it in that respect its original value.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Published as
                            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> Well the book was procured, &amp; when I came to set about it – I found that the translator neither understood
                    French, English, nor the story which he was murdering.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The [First-] Seconde Part, of the ... Historie, of the ... Princes Palmerin of England, and Florian du Desart his
                            brother ... Translated out of French, by A. M</title>. [Anthony Munday (1560?-1633; <title>DNB</title>)] (1596).</note> In
                    consequence I have had full three fourths to translate, – for having put my hand to the plough I would not turn back. By this
                    additional labour I gain nothing, my original agreement having been, as for Madoc, to share the eventual profits. The cause of
                    mistake seems to have been that <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> had seen the <hi rend="ital">third</hi> part, with which I have
                    nothing to do.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Third and Last Part of Palmerin of England ... Written in Spanish, Italian, and French and Translated into English
                            by A. M</title> [Anthony Munday] (1602).</note> This heavy drudgery is nearly off my hands. – Lastly, I have been
                    arranging for the press the remains of <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry White</ref>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White, of Nottingham</title> (1807).</note> – a truly admirable young man, of first rate
                    powers as a poet, – who killed himself by incessant application, having brought on such a state of nerves by this &amp; by
                    Evangelicelism – that if he had not died he would have been probably deranged. He was at one time articled to Enfield of
                    Nottingham whom I suppose you know.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Enfield (1775–1845); attorney and town clerk of
                        Nottingham between 1816 and 1845. As a young man, <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry Kirke White</ref> had worked
                        for a time in the law offices of Coldham and Enfield. Enfield’s partner, George Coldham (1766–1815), was William Taylor’s
                        cousin.</note> You will be affected by his letters, &amp; will greatly admire some of his latter poems. I tell his story
                    plainly, &amp; then arrange extracts from his letters in such a way as to make him his own biographer. Upon his religion I can do
                    no more than simply enter a protest against the supposition that I assent to it, because I do not controvert it – for the book may
                    probably get into an Evangelical circulation, &amp; should that be the case the profits will be useful to his family, for whom he
                    has taught me to take a very great interest. This is nearly done – a few days will compleat it; &amp; when this &amp; the Palmerin
                    are off my hands, as they will both be in three weeks (God willing) I shall be at full leisure for things of more importance.</p><p rend="indent1"> What I then devote myself to is that branch of the Portugueze history which will come under the title of Brazil
                    &amp; Paraguay,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> This title was not adopted. The first volume of Southey’s <title>History
                            of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> – &amp; which, tho it would otherwise have appeared last in the series, I
                    publish first, as having a temporary interest, &amp; conveying more intelligence respecting that side of South America than can be
                    communicated by any other person in Europe except perhaps one Frenchman<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The identity of
                        this French cleric is unclear. It is likely that he was Abbé Francois Garnier (1722–1804), the long-standing chaplain to the
                        French factory in Lisbon. Abbé Jean-Antoine Dubois (1765–1848), was a French Catholic missionary in India, whose long sojourn
                        in the southern districts brought him into contact with the legacy of Portuguese Catholic colonialism there. Dubois’s
                        manuscript history of Indian religion was purchased by the East India Company and published in English as <title>Description
                            of the Character, Manners and Customs of the People of India, and of their Institutions, Religious and Civil</title>
                        (1816).</note> who has duplicates of most of my materials, in many instances taken from them. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> has for about five &amp; twenty years collected materials concerning
                    Brazil, &amp; at his desire, I offered the late administration such information as they contained.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, [15 December 1806], Letter 1243.</note> Will you believe that
                        <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord G.s</ref><note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s offer to prepare a
                        report on South America for the benefit of government intelligence was politely declined by Grenville.</note> answer was that
                    it related to the wrong side of South America? –– Talleyrand<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Maurice de
                        Talleyrand-Périgord, prince de Bénévent, then prince de Talleyrand (1754–1838), French foreign minister.</note> would have sent me &amp; my papers to Paris, &amp; have learnt all
                    their contents without a minutes delay. I offered specific information respecting Brazil, its mines &amp;c from indisputable
                    documents, – &amp; it was not wanted – because <del>it did not</del> our buccaneering schemes are probably directed against the
                    other side &lt;of that continent&gt;, &amp; England has never, <del>since I have</del> in our days had a minister who looked
                    beyond his nose. About a fourth part of the first volume is done, – &amp; I shall perhaps print it volume by volume.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> appeared in three volumes from 1810 to 1819.</note>
                    Two quartos are the probable extent. I might doubtless obtain five hundred guineas for the copyright, but I will not sell the
                    chance of greater eventual profit. – This work will supply a <del>xxxx</del> chasm in history.</p><p rend="indent1"> This is not all. I cannot do one thing at a time. so sure as I attempt it my health suffers. the business of the
                    day haunts me in the night, &amp; tho a sound sleeper otherwise, my dreams partake so much of it as to harrass &amp; disturb me. I
                    must always therefore have one train of thought for the morning, another for the evening, &amp; a book not relating to either for
                    half an hour after supper, &amp; <del>xxxx</del> thus neutralizing one set of associations by another, &amp; having (God be
                    thanked) a heart at ease, I contrive to keep in order a set of nerves as much disposed to be out of order as any mans can be. The
                    Cid is therefore my other work in hand.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the
                            Cid</title> (1808).</note> I want only an importation of books from Lisbon to send this to the press, &amp; shall have
                    full time to <del>the</del> compleat the introduction &amp; notes, while the body of the work is printing. It will supply the
                    place of preliminaries to the Hist. of Portugal,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s ‘History of Portugal’ was
                        never completed.</note> &amp; exhibit a compleat view of the heroic age of Spain. If I am not greatly deceived this will be
                    one of the most interesting chivalrous pieces of history that has ever appeared. – I had almost forgot to say that the reason why
                    you have not received a copy of my Specimens<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> is that it is delayed for some cancels. Sad work has been
                    made [MS torn] by <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, – he has (between ourselves) played the very
                    Devil, Changed my selections, mutilated my sketches – interpolated them – superseded them with his own; – &amp; to crown the whole
                        <del>ma</del> omitted so many authors that I am obliged to make a supplementary volume.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Though planned, a supplementary volume did not appear.</note> When it comes to you to be reviewed you can find
                    enough matter in the preface <del>for</del> to serve you for a text. It is <del>a xxxx</del> an outline of our poetical
                    history.</p><p rend="indent1"> Lastly I have to tell you that <del>(</del>before this change of Ministry took away all my expectations<del>)</del>
                    I was weary of them: &amp; as some arrangements of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> made it
                    necessary that I should either decide upon removing from hence at a fixed time, or remaining with <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">the house</ref>, had chosen the latter alternative. Here then I am settled – Am planting
                    currant trees, – purchasing a little furniture – making the place decent as far as scanty means will go, &amp; sending for
                        <del>by</del> my books by sea, – perfectly well contented with my lot, &amp; thankful that it has fallen in so goodly a
                    land.</p><p rend="indent1"> I will not ask you to visit me here till <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> passes his next
                    summer here which will perhaps be next year, but come once I trust you will. – his direction is with the <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Revd Herbert Hill</ref> Lisbon, – <del>xxxxxx</del> – Of the Severembians I
                        <del>only</del> know nothing having only often seen the title of the book in catalogues.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Denis Vairasse d’Allais (?1630–1672),<title> The History of the Sevarites or Sevarambi, a Nation Inhabiting
                            Part of the Third Continent called Terræ Australes Incognitæ: with An Account of their Admirable Government, Religion,
                            Customs, and Language, Written by one Captain Siden</title> (1675), published in an expanded edition in 1738.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The change of ministry is abominable – tho I am an enemy to Catholic emancipation the last men had done something,
                    &amp; would have done more – they were redeeming the character which <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox</ref> had lost
                    for them.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Grenville’s ministry fell because the King would not accede to its intention to
                        introduce a law removing civil restrictions against Catholics. Charles James Fox (1749–1806; <title>DNB</title>), a great opposition orator and leader but
                        also a notorious gambler, drinker and womaniser, had been Foreign Secretary in the ministry, after many years of retirement
                        from politics, and had introduced a bill to abolish the slave trade before dying in September 1806.</note> Their successors
                    are <del>a set of xxx</del> men of tried &amp; convicted incapacity. The opinion of a <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">friend
                        of ours</ref> who knows much about S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Stephens<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The chapel of St
                        Stephen’s, where the House of Commons sat until the chapel was destroyed by fire in 1834.</note> is <hi rend="ital">Tantara-rara</hi>,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s disparaging term for the noisy MPs in the House of
                        Commons. <title>Tantara-rara, Rogues All</title> was the title of a 1786 play by John O’Keeffe (1747–1833;
                        <title>DNB</title>); see <title>The Dramatic Works of John O’Keeffe Esq.</title>, 4 vols (London, 1798), III, pp. 349–90.
                        ‘Tantara-rara, Fools All Fools All’ was also a popular song from Henry Fielding’s (1707–1754; <title>DNB</title>) play
                            <title>The Lottery</title> (1732).</note> – &amp; from this opinion I am not disposed to differ. You will see that D
                        Manuel<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The putative author of Southey’s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel
                            Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> gives reasons why there always be a want of talent
                    in the English Government, &amp; you may smile when you read them at thinking that it has pleased his most gracious majesty to
                    give me a pension.</p><p rend="indent1"> I pray you remember me very kindly to your mother. I am not without hope of seeing her again. if peace would let me I should go to Holland to look for books
                    about the E Indies &amp; Brazil –</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you </salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p>poor Opie!<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Opie (1761–1807; <title>DNB</title>), painter, was buried in St Paul’s
                            Cathedral on 20 April.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>