<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1365</idno><idno type="nines">rce2487</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Previously  published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    457–458.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1365" type="letter"><head>1365. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1807-09-28">28
                        September 1807</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        M. P./ Wynnstay/ Wrexham<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb/>Previously published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    457–458.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Wynn</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Where can <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> be! I dread his arrival – having such
                    intelligence to communicate to him.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> While Grosvenor Charles Bedford was en route to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, following a visit to Wynn’s estate in Wales, his brother <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> died.</note> – &amp; yet dread still more the probability that he
                    is laid up somewhere on the road. How is that family going to wreck &amp; ruin! – <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> will – I very much fear – soon follow <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref>, the old people drop off half-broken hearted, &amp; very likely in a
                    twelvemonths time <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> will be the only one left! –</p><p rend="indent1"> As for coming to you it is impossible. My summers are much interrupted –which is good for my health, – indeed
                    essential to it, for I feel the benefit of vigorous exercise – but then labour is accumulating for the winter, &amp; I am obliged
                    to become avaricious of time. I have received my account from <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, – the total
                    profit upon Madoc is 25£. – There is little likelihood that the remaining quarto copies will ever sell, unless at trade sales for
                    a fourth part of their price.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first edition of <title>Madoc</title> (1805) was
                        published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in a luxurious quarto, costing two guineas.</note> The
                    small edition will go off drop by drop.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A cheaper duodecimo edition of <title>Madoc</title>
                        had recently been published.</note> – by <hi rend="ital">leakage</hi> not by a run; – in about two years time it will perhaps
                    begin to send in some returns, &amp; then <del>perhaps</del> produce some yearly five or ten pounds. The laws of copy-right
                        <del>x</del> are singularly hard, twenty or thirty years hence it is probable that this poem will have made its way, &amp;
                    settled into a steady &amp; regular sale: – &amp; then when the returns would be valuable, the property becomes common. ‘Sic vos
                    non vobis!’<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Attributed to Virgil, meaning ‘Thus do ye, but not for yourselves’.</note> –
                    Surely this deserves to be amended, &amp; men of letters ought not to be the only persons whose children are not to reap the fruit
                    of their fathers labours.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Specimens, thanks to poor <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>, cannot possibly
                    get me any thing except heartily-deserved abuse.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807), co-edited with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, and published, to Southey’s dismay, with numerous errors.</note> The sale of this
                    edition of Espriella will right my account with Longman up to <del>xxx</del> midsummer: should it go thro another with any
                    rapidity it would smooth my way fairly, &amp; float me into quiet water.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807). The book went into a
                        second edition in 1808; but a third was not called for until 1814.</note> I have had unusual expences in settling myself here
                    this year, &amp; the edition of the Cid<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>Chronicle of the Cid, from the
                            Spanish</title> was published by Longmans in 1808. It comprised translations from the <title>Crónica particular del
                            Cid</title> (1593), with additions from the <title>Crónica de España</title> of Alphonso the Wise (1541) and
                            <title>Romancero e Historia del Cid</title> (1632).</note> is mortgaged &amp; gone for them, &amp; for current out-goings.
                    – When my first quarter was considerd due, &amp; consequently what is at present due from thence, I know not. – but this temporary
                    failure <del>xxxxxx</del> is embarrassing. I used just to make both ends meet, as the phrase is; – at present I am half a year
                    behind hand. May I ask you to supply me, &amp; receive the pension – till I can make a start, &amp; enable myself to wait for it.
                    This will probably be soon, – for there is a great likelihood that Espriella <del>xx</del> alone will do it. On this however I
                    know nothing., but am now covenanting to revise the old translation of D Quixote, prologize &amp; annotate it &amp;c.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey intended to, but in the event did not, edit and update Thomas Shelton (fl. 1598–1629;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the Valorous and Witty Knight-Errant, Don Quixote of the Mançha</title>
                        (1612–1620).</note> This extra work will bring up my lea way. Next year too I shall be ready with Brazil in spite of all
                        interruptions.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first edition of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> was not
                        published until 1810.</note> – &amp; then I may hope to be before hand with the world, &amp; easily to continue so.</p><p rend="indent1"> In this statement of income I had overlooked Palmerin,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> for which I am to share the profits. About 700 of Amadis<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                        translation of the Spanish romance <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> have sold, if the same number of this should
                    go off my share will be short of 100£, – about fourscore may probably be looked for in the course of a year &amp; half; – &amp; it
                    may be more. Easily earned if there had been no more trouble in reediting it than I expected. – but very hardly as the thing
                    proved to be. Your copy is ordered to George Street. There is a longish preface, most part of which is very bibliological &amp;
                    dull. Cervantes over-rates the book,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Palmerin of England</title> is praised in chapter 6 of <title>Don Quixote</title>.</note> – still it is a striking
                    romance, &amp; I confess I would rather be ill paid for such employ then get more by less congenial work.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am very very anxious about Portugal. The removal of the Court to Brazil will be the best event that possibly
                    could happen for this country, &amp; for that general interest which one who lives out of the world may be permitted to think of
                    more importance than any temporary or merely national advantage.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is here
                        speculating as to whether the royal family of Portugal would take the court to Brazil to escape the Napoleonic conquest of the
                        mother country. This came to pass on 29 November 1807, when a British squadron under the command of Sir William Sidney Smith
                        (1764–1840; <title>DNB</title>) escorted the Prince Regent, John VI (the Duke of Braganza) (1767–1826), and the Queen, his
                        mother, across the Atlantic.</note> Copenhagen is as you say a dreadful business.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> In
                        summer 1807 the British, believing that France would gain possession of Denmark and its fleet, amassed ships and troops and on
                        2 September launched a pre-emptive attack on Copenhagen, causing the deaths of over two thousand townspeople.</note> the
                    general feeling seems to me, I am sorry to say, in favour of it. The damnable doctrine of expediency will never want advocates. –
                    Is not your party likely to split upon the question of peace? – My own opinion is that it is the worst <del>xxx</del> thing which
                    can betide us. – but that any ministry is likely to make it for the sake of purchasing a short popularity and putting off its
                    embarrassments.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1807-09-28">Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 28. 1807</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>