<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1172</idno><idno type="nines">rce2294</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 47888 .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters
                            of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 419–424.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1172" type="letter"><head>1172. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <date when="1806-04-05">5 April
                        1806</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To Mrs Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland/ Single<lb/>Stamped:
                        [partial] THETFORD 81<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 47888 <lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters
                            of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 419–424.</note></head><opener><address><placeName>Thetford.</placeName></address><date when="1806-04-05"> Saturday April 5 1806</date></opener><p rend="indent1"> My last was from Newark<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> This has not survived.</note> – it was too late for
                    the post-office tho in time for the mail, if the ostler has properly delivered it. Now then for my subsequent adventures. We went
                    in the Coach – which took us up at half after four. two stages on I got some tea, &amp; very good it was – I drank three large
                    cups – for which I had afterwards reason to be sorry, &amp; found myself disposed to be sick from riding backwards. So I asked my
                    opposite traveller to change – the sickness went off but left me ventose, &amp; when I dozed I had <del>xxx</del> nervous
                    startings <del>xxxx</del> which at length made me think it better to keep quite awake. There was a <del>young</del> Lady in the
                    coach <del>xx</del> bound for Norfolk &lt;as well as myself&gt;. We both alighted at Alconbury Hill<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Near Huntingdon, thirty miles north of Cambridge.</note> at two in the morning, roused up the ostler &amp; got
                    chaise to Fen-stanton. It was bright moonlight. We were not very cold till we changed chaises between four &amp; five,
                        <del>xx</del> the coldest time of the whole day or night – &amp; then the cold room in which we waited about twenty minutes
                    &amp; the cold chaise afterward chilled us – my companion had nothing either agreable or disagreable about her – she was about
                    thirty, neither ugly nor otherwise – &amp; I liked her well enough till when we were at Cambridge she would have washed in my
                    dirty water if I would have let her. I merely breakfasted at Cambridge, left my companion to wait for the Fakenham stage, &amp;
                    posted to Bourne Bridge thinking to be there in time for the day coaches &amp; accordingly – there I got by nine in the morning.
                    Guess my satisfaction at learning there would be no coach till between one &amp; two the following night. I was by this hour
                    fairly tired &amp; in a highly nervous state – partly occasioned perhaps by the unusual quantity of strong green tea which I had
                    drank without eating anything. So I had the bed warmed, &amp; for the first time in my life went to bed in the morning. My feet
                    were cold so that I was obliged to put on stockings – I dozed about half an hour &amp; had dreadful startings, – I lay awake till
                    two, &amp; then feeling my self rather worse than better, rose to see what a good dinner would do for me. The larder furnished
                    nothing better than beef stakes, – &amp; because I had not ordered potatoes the rascally Landlady thought proper to give me none.
                    The stakes were very bad &amp; nauseated my sickly palate – I began to be apprehensive of being taken ill – to wait till past
                    midnight in this house was a gloomy thought – a single inn in a desolate country – my spirits were never worse – hardly ever so
                    bad – &amp; then another night without sleep would effectually lay me up. It came suddenly into my head that I might get on to
                    Thetford before dark – I asked the distance – thirty two miles – in my state of feeling expense seemed nothing – in fact it was
                    nothing – I ordered chaise &amp; felt revived as soon as I got into it by the thought of seeing somebody who knew me. Nothing can
                    be so excellent as the Norfolk roads – the man drove admirably – twelve miles to Newmarket within the hour &amp; half. Off in
                    about ten minutes – the rain (for it rained when I set off) cleared off but the country was covered with a thin sheet of snow. You
                    can conceive nothing so desolate as this country – flat &amp; open. But I had a fine view of all the racers (I dare say at least
                    thirty) exercising against next week upon the Newmarket heath, flying like the wind – till they seemed no bigger than rabbits. One
                    hour brought me the nine miles to Barton Mills – luckily for the inn-keeper for in the room into which I was shown a red poker lay
                    upon the floor in the act of setting fire to it. – Eleven to Thetford in about ten minutes above the hour. I got out of the chaise
                    quite a different being from that I was in the morning. That woman at Bourne Bridge was so brutal &amp; impudently selfish that to
                    have been sick in her house would have been fearful. My spirits were getting up – Where does Mr Wilkinson<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Wilkinson (1764–1831), clergyman, and amateur landscape painter and illustrator. After serving as canon
                        in Carlisle he became Rector of Wretham, Norfolk in 1803. He published <title>Select Views in Cumberland</title> (1810) and
                            <title>The Architectural Remains of Thetford</title> (1822).</note> live? – just by Sir – but the family are in London,
                    the little boy Charles has met with an accident which they are afraid will cost him the sight of one of his eyes. he was playing
                    with a knife which he had stuck into the crevice of a table, the blade snapt and fled up into his eye – Mr W. was in London at the
                    time, &amp; Mrs W. is gone up with the child – I was very much shocked – very much indeed. However as I really was better it was
                    still a matter of great satisfaction to feel myself sure of a nights rest – for the coaches pass between half past six &amp; eight
                    in the morning – within thirty miles of Norwich &amp; with civil people about me. I ordered a roast fowl, called for pen &amp;
                    ink, &amp; was beginning to write when the Landlord came in &amp; said Mr Wilkinson was at home – he had just seen his servant. He
                    had returned last night to serve his church that day being Good Friday. He called the servant in &amp; off I set.</p><p rend="indent1"> Whether Wilkinson was more glad to see me or I to see him – I cannot tell – he had a brother clergyman &amp; an
                    Eton boy dining with him, &amp; had been drinking wine enough to warm his heart &amp; to make him shake my hand ten times as often
                    as he would else have done. I had cold meat set before me – &amp; then joined the party – three glasses of madeira were truly
                    medicinal to me – tea after this, &amp; before tea I got to bed in a comfortable room, with a good fire in it. I fell asleep
                    immediately, had such a nights rest that I would have given fifty guineas to have been sure of it only half a day before, &amp;
                    awoke this morning quite well. To day I stay here, &amp; tomorrow take the coach to Norwich where I hope to be before dinner time.
                    I have no other sense of fatigue now than the motion of a carriage in my head – like what a voyage leaves – &amp; an upper lip so
                    hideously swolen as to be like the neck of a turkey cock – this the cold has done. – but I am quite well thank God, &amp; verily
                    believe that by posting on here from that doleful house &amp; damnable Landlady I have escaped a serious illness – which assuredly
                    half a day &amp; night then – &amp; half a night &amp; day in the coach (had there even been room) must have occasioned me in the
                    state I then was.</p><p rend="indent1"> I never had a warmer welcome. Wilkinsons heart overflows after dinner with the very cream of human kindness – never
                    did wine make a man happier – nor better pleased with every body around him – his friend the clergyman was in a high state of
                    enjoyment – his whole face perfectly relaxed with animal happiness – the cheeks hanging down, &amp; an under lip more like a
                    horses than ever Townsends<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Joseph Townsend (1739–1816; <title>DNB</title>),
                        geologist, author of <title>A Journey Through Spain in the Years 1786 and 1787; with Particular Attention to the Agriculture,
                            Manufactures, Commerce, Population, Taxes, and Revenue of that Country</title> (1791), whom Southey met in London in 1797.
                        See Southey’s letter to Joseph Cottle, 9 April 1797, Letter 210.</note> was stretched up like a purse, covered the upper one
                    &amp; then turned down with a flap. He is a worthy old boy who has no other fault says Wilkinson than that whenever he finds a
                    bottle he must get to the bottom of it. To day he is to dine here – &amp; Fellowes (the famous writer against the
                        Evangelicals)<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Fellowes (1770–1847; <title>DNB</title>), who took orders but
                        never held a position with the Anglican Church, though he published several books on religious topics, such as <title>A
                            Picture of Christian Philosophy</title> (1799) and <title>Religion without Cant</title> (1801). He was the editor of the <title>Critical
                            Review</title> from 1804 to 1811.</note> has been sent to to come &amp; meet me – It seems <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Miss Seward</ref> corresponds with him &amp; has written him an enormously long letter full of
                    enormous praise of Madoc.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s poem <title>Madoc</title>, published the previous
                        year.</note> So I shall have a pleasant day &amp; get thoroughly refreshed. Thank God that I have escaped illness – I never
                    before was in such dread of it – &amp; never in my life – not even at that cursed Comporta<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        On the southwest coast of Portugal.</note><del>xx</del> felt so thoroughly &amp; miserably un-comfortable as for six hours
                    yesterday.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have neglected my journal for the sake of writing to you – &amp; shall therefore run over my memory for the
                    remainder of the road. Lincoln Cathedral is in good order within – they have been obliged in some places to lay a beam from one
                    column to another to support them – but have so ornamented the beam with Gothic work – that tho it looked unlike any thing I had
                    ever before seen – my notion was that it was a continuation of one of the passages <del>xxxx xxx</del> above. In the cloisters a
                    fine Roman pavement was discovered, not many years ago – they have built a brick building over it with commendable care, but with
                    abominable taste – the place being more like a <hi rend="ital">pavilione</hi> than any thing else – Something in keeping might
                    have been put there – a Library forms one side of the cloister quadrangle in detestable taste. The Cathedral wants painted glass
                    sadly – we felt the light quite unpleasant – &amp; where three old windows remained the effect of the colourd light upon the
                    little crockets &amp; pinnacles within crowning them &amp; playing upon the columns with red &amp; purple &amp; saffron shade of
                    light – made me the more regret that all were not in the same state of beauty. Peters who painted that vile Angel &amp; Child
                    which has been so popular is a Prebend here &amp; has stuck up a picture of the annunciation. He is a worthless fellow – who has
                    studied his Virgins &amp; Angels in the vilest brothels – and his picture is a disgrace to the choir.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> William (Matthew) Peters (1742–1814; <title>DNB</title>), portrait and genre painter and Church of England
                        clergyman. Painting in the Italian style in the 1770s, Peters favoured classical and biblical scenes, many of which featured
                        female nudity. These pictures were reproduced in engravings and became popular. He took up a career in the church in 1781,
                        becoming prebendary of Lincoln Cathedral in 1795. In this post he painted numerous religious works, including <title>An Angel
                            Carrying the Spirit of a Child to Paradise</title> (1783), and a large-scale representation of the Annunciation for
                        Lincoln Cathedral (1799).</note> Had you been with me when we ascended the Tower, that it is &amp; if you could have borne the
                    fatigue of the ascent which is very great, you would have seen passages &amp; turnings to have given you an adequate idea of my
                    adventure <del>at Ely</del>. Great Tom is a noble fellow.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lincoln Cathedral’s large bell,
                        Great Tom, cast in 1610.</note> as <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> said, it pleased me to feel
                    how the first disappointment at its size wore off – &amp; we became satisfied that it was quite as great a thing as it is said to
                    be – one might stand under it &amp; the mouth measure one &amp; twenty feet. It must be a large tree which would be the size of
                    its middle – the hours are struck upon it with a hammer. No other bell of nearly this size is ever moved: this is &amp; it is
                    tolled on Whitsunday, &amp; when the Judges come to town it has been (I think it should be used at executions – to which it would
                    give great solemnity). It has been disused on other occasions because it shook the tower &amp; endangered it. They have secured
                    the tower now with iron cramps. The west part of Lincoln is wonderfully rich – look for a print in one of the Beauties of
                        England<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Beauties of England and Wales</title> (1801–1818) was a series of
                        lavishly-illustrated accounts of the historical features of Britain, produced by John Britton (1771–1857; <title>DNB</title>),
                        an antiquary, with his friend Edward Wedlake Brayley (1773–1854; <title>DNB</title>). Southey’s 25 volumes of this edition
                        were included in the sale catalogue of his library. The ninth volume of <title>The Beauties of England and Wales</title>
                        (London, 1807) contains a print of the west front of Lincoln cathedral, opposite page 627.</note> – if it be not unluckily in
                    the few numbers which are at <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref>. – There are some parts more resembling the
                    stile of Belem<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Belém Tower, in Lisbon, built in 1515 as a fortress to guard the harbour
                        entrance.</note> than I have seen elsewhere but this is not the finest view of the whole – tho it is the most characteristic –
                    No other building which I have ever seen stands so admirably. Indeed Lincoln is one of the most striking places you can conceive,
                    &amp; it well repaid the journey with all its expences &amp; inconveniences.</p><p rend="indent1"> The road to Newark is straight – an old Roman way<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Fosse Way, which
                        runs from Lincoln to Exeter.</note> – look at the print of Newark Castle in the <hi rend="ital">Beauties</hi><note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> A print of Newark bridge and castle appears in the twelfth volume of <title>The Beauties of
                            England and Wales</title> (London, 1813), part 1, opposite page 233.</note> – you perhaps may remember the place as we
                    past it by day light. There is nothing to see more than you catch in passing. I noticed the name Ordoyno<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The name Ordoyno was once common in Newark. Thomas Ordoyno (dates unknown), a nurseryman and author of
                            <title>Flora Nottinghamiensis</title> (1807), owned several properties in the town.</note> on a shop – which is the very
                    old Spanish name Ordoño – or Ordonho – a name so old as to be obsolete in Spain. Newark is famous in history as the place where
                    the Scotch sold Charles 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> but one sees all such places quite sufficiently in passing thro.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles I (1600–1649, King of England, Scotland, and Ireland 1625–1649; <title>DNB</title>)
                        surrendered to the Scots besieging Newark in 1646 and in 1647 they handed him over to the English Parliament.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The whole country from Penrith to this place with the exception of a few spots about Penrith itself &amp; Appleby
                    is so utterly without beauty that I verily believe if you were compelled to live in any part of it – you could wish yourself at
                    Lisbon. <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> has quite spoilt us for living any where else – a flat land is quite
                    insupportable to me now. Wilkinson says he has had but one regret at the thought of Ormathwaite<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The small village near Keswick in the Lake District in which Wilkinson had lived before moving to
                        Norfolk.</note> – which has lasted ever since &amp; Mrs W. never looks at the drawing of it but the tears come in her eyes.
                    Thetford was once an important place with nearly 20 churches – now only three are left. It has nothing to recommend it but its
                    vicinity to Norwich – &amp; easy distance from London. Yet when I saw it before, it left a pleasant impression on my memory. It
                    was at sunset in June &amp; &amp; several fields of lucerne were in full blossom so that the earth was as purple as the sky – And
                    all the houses in Norfolk &amp; Suffolk have an appearance of cleanliness which is very delightful – the soil is admirably dry. In
                    the dirtiest weather you might ride without splashing a silk stocking. – We past near the place of Sir Isaac Newtons birth<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac Newton (1642–1727; <title>DNB</title>) was born at Woolsthorpe Manor, in Woolsthorpe
                        by Colsterworth, Lincolnshire.</note> – there is a bust of him on the house – public monuments in such occasions would have a
                    good affect &amp; give to a journey a new interest. So also thro Huntingdon where Cromwell was born.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Oliver Cromwell, (1599–1658, 1653–1658 Lord Protector of England, Scotland, and Ireland; <title>DNB</title>),
                        was born in Huntingdon, Cambridgeshire.</note> – I must tell you a good thing which <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> did – at Penrith he left the key of his own trunk &amp; carried off
                    one of Miss Monkhouses.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Elizabeth Monkhouse (1750–1828), maternal aunt and foster mother
                        of Wordsworth’s wife Mary Hutchinson (1770–1859).</note> You must know he flattered himself that his breeches were very
                    genteel – but unluckily I happened to say the buttons required covering – &amp; still more unluckily discovered that he had torn a
                    hole in them. I shall hardly know him London when he has got a new set of black. – Dear Edith I am in hopes of finding a letter at
                    Norwich tomorrow – or the next day surely one will come. You do not know what good it would do me to hear all was well. God bless
                    you my dear dear love! Upon my soul I do not think I can bear to go abroad without you – at least I shall be thoroughly unhappy if
                    I do. Give <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> a kiss – I would give I know not what if I could do it myself –
                    God bless you xx.</p></div></body></text></TEI>