<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1659</idno><idno type="nines">rce2781</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>University of Rochester, Rare Books Library, A.S727 1:2.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1659" type="letter"><head>1659. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref>, <date when="1809-07-25">25 July
                    1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Humphrey Senhouse Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Castle Hill/ Maryport/ Cockermouth<lb/>Seal: Red Wax<lb/>Watermark: [partially obscured by seal] 1803/ T
                        BOTFIELD<lb/> Endorsement: July 25. 1809/ Rob<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey to HS./ Relative to your estimation of Steward/ to
                        the Derwentwater Estates<lb/>MS: University of Rochester, Rare Books Library, A.S727 1:2<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute>Dear Senhouse</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Some little while ago I received a letter from <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> telling me
                    that <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Canning</ref> had expressed a wish to serve me, that he would have
                    offered me a situation of 200 £ a year in his own department, but on consideration it was thought not worth my acceptance as
                    requiring more time &amp; attendance than were equivalent to the salary, &amp; that in consequence he, Scott, was desired to
                    communicate with me upon the subject, &amp; learn in what manner I could be benefitted most conformably to my own pursuits &amp;
                    inclinations. Now the Stewardship for the Derwentwater Estates, held by a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walton,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicholas Walton (d. 1809).</note> is expected soon to be vacated by his death, – the whole would be
                    thought too much for me I apprehend, but this objection might easily be remedied by seperating the Cumberland from the
                    Northumberland property.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Although Southey asked various friends to intercede on his
                        behalf for this post, in the end it was considered unsuitable for him; see Southey to Walter Scott, 8 August 1809 (Letter
                        1666) and Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 12 August 1809 (Letter 1669).</note> This therefore I mentioned to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>, – his reply is that the thing seems feasible, but that <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdales</ref> recommendation will probably command it, that at any rate his
                    countenance would be in the highest degree important &amp; therefore he urged me to make what interest I could in that quarter,
                    stating the grounds upon which I applied, – that is, the disposition on the part of the <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Canning</ref> towards me. </p><p rend="indent1"> I should like this office because it would give me the care of these woods, &amp; the power of planting &amp;
                    beautifying this neighbourhood. I should like the salary because it would enable me to follow without interruption <del>such</del>
                    &lt;those&gt; literary pursuits for which I am best qualified. I have written to <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir
                        George Beaumont</ref> requesting his recommendation at <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lowther</ref>, &amp; I have
                    requested <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>  to do the same to Lord Bute,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Stuart, 4th Earl of Bute (1744–1814; <title>DNB</title>).</note> with whom he is
                    sufficiently well acquainted.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> For these letters, see Southey to Sir George Beaumont, 17
                        July 1809 (Letter 1656) and Southey to Herbert Hill, 24 July 1809 (Letter 1658).</note> A word from you would perhaps be of
                    more avail than from either; for tho <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref> appears sensible of the credit
                    which is gained in these times by patronising literature, he is far more likely to have election purposes in view. If however from
                    any just cause or impediment you are unwilling to address him upon the subject, tell me so as freely as I have now applied to you.
                    The chance is important enough to make it my duty to omit no likely means of success. My circumstances would be materially
                    bettered by obtaining it, – but I shall suffer neither expectation nor failure in the slightest degree to diminish my
                    tranquillity.</p><p rend="indent1"> Miss Wood<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isabella Wood (dates unknown), cousin of Humphrey
                        Senhouse.</note> informed us a few days ago of <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachys</ref>
                     death, an event which I had always foreseen. To us she is a great loss, nor shall I ever cast my eyes towards
                        <del>yound</del> yonder beautiful Island without remembering &amp; regretting her. Since last you heard from me we have lost
                    the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">little girl</ref>  who was named after her – by a disease more resembling
                    cholera morbus than any thing else, but with anomalous &lt;symptoms&gt; which seemed to me to indicate some organic disease. My
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">little boy</ref>  had just before been saved from the croup. At
                    present, thank God, all are well, except that I have my summer catarrh upon me, it is now about eight weeks old, &amp; I suppose
                    will soon take its departure. – I was at Durham last month to visit <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother</ref>
                     on his marriage he is getting into practise there, &amp; at the death of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">his wifes</ref>  father<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Sealy (dates unknown), a wealthy Lisbon merchant.</note> will probably have enough to do without it.</p><closer><salute> Remember us at <ref target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref> &amp; to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Senhouse. I hope
                        your young Humphrey is doing well</salute><salute rend="indent1"> yours very truly</salute><signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1809-07-25">July 25. 1809.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>