<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.923</idno><idno type="nines">rce2045</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="923" type="letter"><head>923. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1804-04-10">10 April 1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M. P./ Chester.<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute>Dear Wynn</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Of Roberts’s book I had not heard till your letter spoke of it. I will find out among the Welshmen in London whether he is a man who can be employed as you propose,
                    &amp; whether if so circumstanced he is also so qualified.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Peter Roberts (1760–1819), cleric, biblical scholar and antiquarian who
                        published several Welsh histories, including <title>A Sketch of the Early History of the Cymry</title> (1803).</note> Davis’s Celtic Antiquities are at length advertised, to
                    which, if my memory do not deceive me I put my name as a subscriber eleven years ago.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Davies (1756–1831), <title>Celtic Researches
                            on the Origin, Traditions, and Language of the Ancient Britons</title> (1804). Although Southey’s name is not included in the List of Subscribers, he did own a copy of this
                        work no. 796 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> In London I shall look after it, &amp; see whether any thing fit for Madoc can be gleaned from these new
                    researches.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have lately received a cargo of books which will almost enable to fit the first part of my history for the press.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s projected ‘History of Portugal’, which he never completed.</note> among other treasures is the Collection of Castilian Poems anterior to the fifteenth century<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 3720 of the sale catalogue of Southey’s library was <title>Romances Sueltos en Verso Espanola</title>. Published in Alicante, Seville
                        and Valladolid, the date of publication is unknown.</note> – a work which has not been compleated for want of sale to my bitter regret &amp; great misfortune. The oldest of all
                    is the Cid – which I do not open till my return from town when I can enjoy it fully &amp; leisurely.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had access to the story of
                        the Cid in several books listed in the sale catalogue of his library: no. 3449, Juan de Escobar (dates unknown), <title>Romancero e Historia del Cid Ruy Diez de Bivar en
                            Language Antigo</title> (1632); no. 3344, Rodrigo Diaz de Vivar (c. 1043–1099), <title>Chronica de la Famoso Cavallero Cid
                                Ruy Diez Campeador</title> (1593); no. 3338,
                        Alfonso X of Castile (1221–1284; King of Castile 1252–1284), <title>Chronica de Espana</title> (1541). Southey’s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title>, including an introductory
                        discussion of the origins of the tale, was published by Longman in 1808.</note> there is also a Romance of Alexander<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Romance of
                        Alexander is a collection of mythical tales about the deeds of Alexander ‘the Great’ (356–323 BC), dating from a third-century AD Greek manuscript. It was translated into most
                        European vernaculars in the medieval period. In Spanish it formed the basis of the epic poem <title>Libro de Alexandre</title>, attributed to Alfonso X of Castile, and dating
                        from the late twelfth, or early thirteenth, century.</note> which ought to be compared with Adam Davies<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In George Ellis,
                            <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790, 2nd edn. 1801, 3rd edn. 1803), the English version of the Romance of Alexander – ‘the Life of Alexander’ – was
                        ascribed to Adam Davy (fl. early 14th cent.), author of a verse account of five prophetic dreams (in Bodleian MS Laud misc. 622), who described himself as ‘Adam, the marshal’,
                        ‘of Stratford-atte-bowe’ (London) (<title>DNB</title>).</note> – which it is said Park<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Park (1758/9–1834; <title>DNB</title>):
                        antiquarian, bibliographer and editor, who was praised by Southey to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> as the best editor for the projected
                            <title>Bibliotheca Britannica</title>. Park’s editions of poetry included <title>Works of the British Poets</title> (1805–1808), John Dryden’s (1631–1700;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Fables from Boccaccio and Chaucer</title> (1806) and Thomas Percy’s (1729–1811), <title>Reliques of Ancient English Poetry</title>, 5th edn
                        (1812).</note> is to edite under <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Elliss</ref>  direction.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ellis edited, with Park’s
                        help, <title>Specimens of Early English Metrical Romances</title> (1805).</note> &amp; a poem or rather series of Poems which by the table of Contents seems to resemble the
                    Confessio Amantis.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Gower (1330–1408; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Confessio Amantis</title> (1390).</note> The Volume on which I
                    have begun consists wholly of saintly &amp; miraculous poems, but I am gleaning from them many facts &amp; corollaries. I am also upon the Fuero Juzgo – the Laws of the
                        Wisi-Goths.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 3463 of the sale catalogue of Southey’s library was J. A. Llorente (dates unknown), <title>Leyes del Fuero-Juzgo ó
                            Recopilacion de las Leyes de los Wisi-Godos Españoles</title> (1792).</note> a small quarto contains them – &amp; I have half got thro with profit abundantly equivalent to
                    the patience required, in fact old laws are never tiresome. the next Code in order – the Fuero Viejo – has not yet reached me<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> This book
                        did reach Southey: no. 3387 of the sale catalogue of his library was D. Ignatius Jordan de Asso y del Rio (1742–1804), and D. Miguel de Manuel y Rodriguez (fl. 1780),
                            <title>El Fuero Viejo de Castilla, con Notas Historicas, y Legales</title> (1771).</note> – the third Las Partidas<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 3610 of the sale catalogue of Southey’s library was Gregorio Lopez (1496/7–1560), <title>Partidas (las Siete) del Sabio Rey Don Alonso el Nono Glosadas</title> (1789).</note> – in
                    four folios, is awaiting me in town. All these are anterior to the oldest Portugueze Code, &amp; I must go thro all – for I will leave nothing undone.</p><p rend="indent1"> Madoc<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poem <title>Madoc</title>, which Southey had written in 1797–1799 and since then had been intermittently
                        revising. It was completed in October 1804 and published in 1805.</note> meantime stands still – <del>perhaps</del> partly because I have run myself out of breath &amp; still
                    more because the daily expectation of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref>  confinement<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, the Southeys’ second child, was born on 30 April 1804.</note> does not leave my mind sufficiently at ease for
                    composition. As soon as she is out of danger – if so it please God that it should turn out – I shall prepare for my journey to London.</p><p rend="indent1"> Remember when we meet to ask me for a story of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; Nicols the M.P.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly John Nicholls (1745?–1832): M.P. for the rotten borough of Tregony and author of <title>Reflections, Personal and Political as Connected with
                            Public Affairs</title> (1822). The story Southey refers to has not come to light.</note> – Coleridge is on the seas – for Malta. – Is <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> in town?</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Farewell. I hope to write again soon – &amp; if within the week – shall direct to Chester.</salute><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you –</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1804-04-10">Tuesday. April 10. 1804.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>