<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1698</idno><idno type="nines">rce2820</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Morgan Library, Call Number: Bound MA 4500 0045, Record ID 221063: Accession Number MA 4500
                        (45).  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1698" type="letter"><head>1698. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1809-10-20">20 October 1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> / Richmond/ Surry./ Single<lb/>Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmarks: E/ OCT23/ 1809; [partial] 10o’Clock/ OC.2[MS torn]/ 1809[MS torn]<lb/>Watermark:
                        1808<lb/>Endorsements: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 144 1809/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.<lb/>MS: Morgan Library, Call Number: Bound MA 4500 0045, Record ID 221063: Accession Number MA 4500
                        (45)<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1809-10-20">Oct 20. 1809.</date></dateline><salute>My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It is so long since I have written to you that my conscience would rise up in judgement against me, – if the
                    silence on your part had not been longer than mine. During this interval one or two things have occurred to me which you will not
                    be displeased to hear. – For two or three years past I have occasionally interchanged letters with <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, – originating in an interchange of books. Some three months ago he wrote
                    to tell me that <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> had a great desire to serve me, – that he talked the matter over
                    with him (W Scott) &amp; <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis</ref>, – that he would have offered me the situation
                    of <hi rend="ital">precis</hi>-writer in his own office, but on considerations its emoluments were not thought equivalent to the
                    sacrifice of time &amp; the change of abode required, – &amp; that he left it to Scott to find out by consulting me in what manner
                    I could be served most conformably to my own wishes &amp; pursuits. Diplomatic situations, or professorships at the Universities
                    were mentioned. – Concerning the former my reply was, that the time in which such a situation was desirable was gone by. (<ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref>  being in England &amp; I myself settled with my books
                    about me.) – concerning the latter, – they are fenced round about with tests, – I cannot go thro the door, &amp; will not leap
                    over the hedge. Moreover my way of life was determined, – it was my deliberate &amp; unrepented choice, &amp; no prospects however
                    flattering could induce me to change it. I asked however to have the office of Historiographer created for me, with a respectable
                    salary. – While things were in this state I learnt that the Stewardship of the Derwentwater Estates was likely soon to be vacated,
                    &amp; I was advised to ask for this. Accordingly I wrote to Scott, &amp; at the same time to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> (my constant privy Counsellor) asking his advice.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> For these letters, see Southey to Walter Scott, 6 July 1809 (Letter 1648) and Southey to Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn, 8 July 1809 (Letter 1651).</note> Both thought it the best thing that could be sought for, – &amp; both urged
                    me to obtain <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdales</ref>  recommendation for it, as paramount
                    . – Well – behold me place-hunting, – I write my plain story to my twenty-mile-off-neighbour <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref> (the only <hi rend="ital">friend</hi> whom I have made in the
                    county) – requesting him to apply to Ld Lonsdale, – &amp; I write also to <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G.
                        Beaumont</ref> to the same effect.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey’s letters to Beaumont and Senhouse,
                        see Southey to Sir George Beaumont, 17 July 1809 (Letter 1656) and Southey to Humphrey Senhouse, 25 July 1809 (Letter
                        1659).</note> Both take the matter up warmly, – Ld Lonsdale enters very handsomely into my views, – &amp; formal application
                    is made for it <del>xxx</del> by Sir G Beaumont, sanctioned by his name, to Ld Mulgrave,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Phipps, 1st Earl of Mulgrave (1755–1831; <title>DNB</title>): diplomatist and politician who was appointed First
                        Lord of the Admiralty in 1807.</note> in whose gift it is to be, &amp; with whom Sir G. is very intimate. The answer under a
                    plea that very peculiar qualifications are required for the situation, implied that he meant to give it to one of his own
                    relations or immediate dependants, – <del>x xxx</del> other information tended to corroborate the first part of his statement,
                    &amp; I declined soliciting farther, as Lord L. would have had me do.</p><p rend="indent1"> So ended this quest. With respect to the Historiographers place Canning said there was a great objection to
                    creating any new place, however just the occasion; – when lo! to the great surprize of all parties I discovered that the place
                    already existed &amp; was held <del>by</del> &lt;of&gt; all men in the world by Dutens the Frenchman.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Dutens (1730–1812; <title>DNB</title>), a French Protestant, held the post of Historiographer Royal
                        until his death on 23 May 1812. Southey’s campaign for the post proved unsuccessful and it went to one of his particular <hi rend="ital">bêtes noires</hi>, James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765–1834; <title>DNB</title>).</note> So C. promised all his
                    influence for it whenever the said Dutens should go to Heaven, – &amp; you know the least thing <del>you can</del> to be expected
                    from a Frenchman is that he should go <hi rend="ital">there</hi> to oblige <del>you</del> one. – The topsy-turvy changes in
                    Administration which have just taken place, put an end to the story.</p><p rend="indent1"> Meantime the <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref>, who projected some twelve months ago an
                    Edinburgh Annual Register with their Magnus Apollo<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning his mentor or
                        luminary.</note> W Scott, applied to me to write the history of Spanish affairs for the year (1808) – this, liking the
                    subject, I undertook. They found themselves woefully disappointed in the sample of the other part of the history which was sent
                    them, – so much so that they cancelled it, &amp; applied to me to undertake the whole, – for which they offered me 400 £ a year. I
                    have accepted it for one year on trial, – hoping &amp; indeed expecting to continue it, – less in love with the employment than
                    with the ‘sweet remuneration’ that awaits it.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> From 1810 to 1812 Southey contributed to
                        the ‘History of Europe’ for 1808–1810 in James Ballantyne’s <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> – My books do not
                    sell, &amp; leave me behind hand with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, – tho the property in his hands when
                    sold would give a balance in my favour. But if in this Register I should suit Ballantyne’s purpose, – as well as <del>the</del>
                    his terms suit mine, I shall very speedily get above the world. 100 £ of the first years payment shall be remitted to you. As yet
                    there is but little progress made, – one sheet printed, &amp; not above four written, but they are in haste, &amp; so am I, &amp;
                    the volume will be published in the spring, the second will follow as speedily as possible, &amp; I have good &lt;hope&gt; of
                    paying you a second hundred in the course of <del>the ensuing</del> &lt;next&gt; year.</p><p rend="indent1"> You need not be told that what I write will be done with perfect sincerity &amp; perfect freedom. Aloof from all
                    parties &amp; thoroughly despising all, my two <del>x</del> main principles are, the necessity of reform at home, &amp; the
                    necessity of continuing the war as long as Buonaparte &amp; his system are in existence. My first chapter has astonished
                    Ballantyne. He is exceedingly delighted with it, – looking bookseller-like to its effect upon the sale of his work, – &amp;
                    submits to see his own party censured because there is a heavier condemnation of the Talents.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The ‘Ministry of All the Talents’ was in government during 1806–1807.</note> Some passages he requested
                    might be expunged, – I copied them fairly out to reinsert hereafter, – &amp; whenever you visit me at the Lakes (which I hope
                    &amp; trust you will one day do, &amp; <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> with you) you will
                    be amused at seeing the Castrations.</p><p rend="indent1"> There will be nothing of mine in the fourth Quarterly, except Holmes’s American Annals, which were post-poned in
                    the last number.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed Abiel Holmes (1763–1837), <title>American Annals; or,
                            a Chronological History of America, from its Discovery in 1492 to 1806</title> in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2
                        (November 1809), 319–337.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My first volume will be thicker than I wish it to be.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume
                        of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1810.</note> 496 pages are printed &amp; I think it will not be
                    comprized in less than 700. The whole copy is at <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">the printers</ref>, except the
                    supplementary notes. These contain a great deal of very curious matter. – I want to transmit <del>your</del> some questions to
                    your brother William,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Henry May (1785–1849), John May’s youngest brother and
                        business partner in Brazil.</note> when I have time to write them, chiefly respecting the mixture of languages &amp; races
                    which has taken place. My second volume will be more interesting than the first,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        second volume of his <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1817.</note> but this first is a good book, &amp;
                    whatever be its immediate reception (of which I augur very little) will <del>x</del> do me honour hereafter.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Remember us to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May &amp; believe me</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yours very affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent5"> R Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> Should you in the course of the next ten days or fortnight be near New Cavendish Street, you may see at Miss
                        Bethams N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 14, – the pictures of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">your god-daughter</ref>, <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">her mother</ref>  &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">brother</ref>, – all good likenesses, <del>&amp;</del> the children most remarkably so, – together with one of
                        myself, which is not so fortunate.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The postscript is inserted at the top of the
                            first page of the letter.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>