<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1015</idno><idno type="nines">rce2137</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos
                        (ed.), The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 91–93.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1015" type="letter"><head>1015. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1805-01-09">9 January 1805</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry/
                        Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmarks: E/ JAN12/ 1805; 10o’Clock/ JA.12/ 1805F.N.n<lb/>Endorsement: No. 105 1805/
                        Robert Southey/ Keswick 9th Jany/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 12 do/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 21st d<hi rend="sup">o</hi><lb/>MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb/>Previously published: Charles Ramos
                        (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 91–93.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1805-01-09">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 9. 1805.</date></dateline><salute>My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The main reason of so long a silence on my part has been that having some tidings of my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> to communicate, &amp; being daily in expectation of a letter from him – I waited in
                    hope of receiving it. – The boats of the Galatea attempted to cut out a sloop called the Lilly from Guadaloupe, <del>&amp;</del>
                    the attempt proved very disastrous, &amp; so has never been gazetted. We heard this from London – in consequence I made enquiry by
                    a friend at the Admiralty who saw a private letter from one who had been in the action &amp; fairly inferred that as <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> name was not mentioned in it, he was safe. Shortly after, a paragraph appeared in
                    our Whitehaven paper<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Cumberland Pacquet and Ware’s Whitehaven Advertiser</title>.</note> stating the death of the Master of the Galatea
                    who was a native of that town. he was killed in this affair – &amp; the paragraph <del>stated</del> &lt;added&gt; that the First
                    Lieutenant fell also. I read this myself – &amp; you may guess how it went thro me like an electric shock however it is never my
                    custom to accredit things lightly. it was mentioned that the Surgeon was killed – I argued that neither Surgeon nor Master could
                    be in the boats – consequently the <del>xxx</del> paragraph was erroneous in part &amp; possibly in the whole – so I wrote again
                    to London – tho I confess persuaded in my heart that my brother had fallen, knowing that he would be foremost in any attempt which
                    required exertion &amp; could lead to promotion. the answer was that a Lieutenant was slain – but of a different name – for the
                    official account had arrived. In a few days came a letter from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> to tell me that he
                    had been brought to a Court Martial for disobedience of orders, neglect of duty &amp; contempt of his Captain.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain (later Admiral) Henry Heathcote (1777–1851), in command of HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi> 1803–1805.</note> the two first charges were not proved. the last was &amp; he was sentenced to be dismissed
                    the ship. The contempt proved was that when the Captain had charged him with the offences which were disproved clearly on the
                    trial, he had replied I beg your pardon Sir – I must contradict you. Mark the providence – I do not use the word superstitiously –
                    but such things induce an aweful sort of feeling – being thus under arrest he could not go in the boats, &amp; the Lieutenant who
                    went in his stead fell.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 14 August 1804, the boats of Thomas Southey’s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, made an unsuccessful attempt to cut out the French privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi>
                        (formerly the British sloop of war <hi rend="ital">Lilly</hi>) lying at the Saintes near Guadeloupe. Of the 90 men sent on the
                        mission 65 were killed or wounded. Southey suspected that his brother was among the dead. Thomas had been the first lieutenant
                        but was absent from the raid because had been placed under arrest. Charles Hayman (d. 1804) was made first lieutenant in his
                        stead and died in the attack.</note> – I have waited in hopes of adding the sequel to the story. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother</ref> wrote from Antigua. he had that morning breakfasted with Commodore Hood<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet (1762–1814;
                        <title>DNB</title>), in command of the fleet in which Thomas Southey served.</note> – who told him to wait in the West Indies
                    till he had seen the minutes of the trial, for the sentence only had reached him – if he thought proper. this was sufficient
                    encouragement – as a frigate was sailing for England the next day, &amp; no other opportunity would offer till April. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> of course remains, knowing that the minutes which state the whole evidence are in
                    his favour, &amp; therefore expecting an appointment the more likely as the Commodore is the brother of Captain Hood – <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> first friend – who fell in the Mars.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Captain Alexander Hood (1758–1798), who died of a wound to the thigh, on 2 April 1798, sustained when his ship the <hi rend="ital">Mars</hi> engaged the French ship <hi rend="ital">Hercule</hi> off the coast of Brittany. Nearly 400 men, and
                        both captains, died in the fight; Thomas Southey, on board the <hi rend="ital">Mars</hi>, was wounded.</note> he has money
                    enough to support him with oeconomy six weeks, before <del>which</del> the expiration of which term the minutes would in all
                    probability arrive from Antigua. where he had been tried, &amp; where he had immediately gone to the Commodore. – I wrote
                    immediately to bid him draw on me<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Thomas Southey, 17 December 1804, Letter
                        1004.</note> – &amp; before I wrote a second letter lest the first should miscarry – <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> to whom I had related the story – very kindly put fifty pounds at my disposal for him. So that if his hopes fail
                    him he will at least be enabled to clear himself from the Islands, &amp; should he be obliged to return home for employment, I
                    have a home for him, &amp; some interest with one of the Lords of the Admiralty.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have written to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> about his mad wishes to be at
                    Cambridge, in such a style as will, or ought to, effectually put an end to them.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> See
                        Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 8 January 1805, Letter 1013.</note> You are very kind in what you say of him. if need were
                    the proposed income would amply suffice him for the whole years expences – but the bargain <del>xxx</del> concerning our house is
                    broken off, &amp; we are of course at liberty to remain. – Should an army be sent to Portugal it would be of infinite advantage to
                    me if I could procure a<del>n</del> civil office in the establishment. I could do the official business &amp; my own with ease –
                    &amp; be enabled by living with <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> to save nearly the whole of the salary.
                    There is not much chance of this under the present administration but I shall try my own strength, &amp; also write to my Uncle –
                    who most likely will think of it himself.</p><p rend="indent1"> If I had known in time of &lt;young&gt; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpoles intention I would have retranslated the Ode
                    of Luis de Leon<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Fray Luis Ponce de León (1527–1591), the Spanish lyric poet whose ode on
                        King Roderick (in Spanish Rodrigo), the last Visigothic king of Spain (d. 711) and the conflict with the Moors was translated
                        by Southey in <title>Letters Written during a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp. 292–302.
                        Robert Walpole (1781–1856) was preparing materials for his publication of <title>Specimens of Scarce Translations of the
                            Seventeenth Century, from the Latin Poets</title> (London, 1805), which includes a translation into Greek of de León’s
                        Spanish ode on the introduction of the Moors into Spain (p. 129). Walpole credits Southey’s translation of this work (p.
                        viii).</note> for him – for it was done when I was nine years younger, &amp; is done badly.</p><p rend="indent1"> I also am a loser by the Critical Review. something from 10 to 30 £ the balance of a long account, which Hamilton
                    for two years after I had ceased to write for him delayed to settle, &amp; now it is gone.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Samuel Hamilton (dates unknown), owner of the <title>Critical Review</title> 1799–1804. Hamilton’s departure from the
                            <title>Critical</title> left Southey unpaid for reviews he had written.</note> – I am busy for the Annual – but my
                    articles this year will neither be so many nor so interesting as the last.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        reviewed, in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805): John Barrow (1764–1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An
                            Account of Travels into the Interior of Southern Africa, in the years 1797 and 1798, including Observations on the Geology
                            &amp; Geography, the Natural History ... and Sketches of the Various Tribes Surrounding the Cape of Good Hope</title>,
                        Vol. II (1804), 22–33; Robert Percival (1765–1826), <title>An Account of the Cape of Good Hope</title> (1804), 34–41; Daniel
                        Mackinnen (1767–1830), <title>A Tour Through the British West Indies, in the years 1802 and 1803 giving a Particular Account
                            of the Bahama Islands</title> (1804), 50–56; John Barrow, <title>Travels in China: Containing Descriptions, Observations
                            and Comparisons Made and Collected in the Course of a Short Residence at the Imperial Palace of Yuen-min-yuen, and on a
                            Subsequent Journey from Pekin to Canton</title> (1804), 69–83; <title>Sir John Froissart’s Chronicles of England, France,
                            and the Adjoining Countries, from the Latter Part of the Reign of Edward II to the Coronation of Henry IV</title>, trans.
                        Thomas Johnes (1748–1816; <title>DNB</title>) (1804), 189–194; George Heriot (1766–1844), <title>The History of Canada, From
                            its First Discovery: Comprehending an Account of the Original Establishment of the Colony of Louisiana</title>, 194–197;
                            <title>Part the First of An Address to the Public from the Society for the Suppression of Vice, Instituted, in London,
                            1802, Setting Forth, with a List of the Members, the Utility and Necessity of such an Institution, and its Claim to Public
                            Support</title> (1803), 225–231; Edward Ledwich (1738–1823), <title>The Antiquities of Ireland</title> (1804), 398–413;
                            <title>Original Correspondence of Jean Jacques Rousseau, with Mad. La Tour de Franqueville and M. Du Peyrou</title>
                        (1804), 485–488; Anna Seward, <title>Memoirs of the Life of Dr. Darwin, ... with Anecdotes of his Friends and Criticisms on
                            his Writings</title> (1804), 488–93; David Irving (1778–1850),<title> The Lives of the Scotish Poets; with Preliminary
                            Dissertations on the Literary History of Scotland and the Early Scotish Drama</title> (1804), 493–499; Walter Scott,
                            <title>Sir Tristram: A Metrical Romance by Thomas of Ercildoune</title> (1804), 555–563; Charles Abraham Elton
                        (1778–1853), <title>Poems</title> (1804), 564–565; William Day (dates unknown), <title>The Shepherd’s Boy: being Pastoral
                            Tales</title> (1804), 567–568; E. Warren (dates unknown), <title>The Poet’s Day, or, Imagination’s Ramble</title> (1804),
                        568; <title>Cupid turned Volunteer: in a Series of Prints, Designed by her Royal Highness the Princess Elizabeth; and Engraved
                            by W. N. Gardiner, B.A., with Poetical Illustrations by T. P</title> [Thomas Park (1758/9–1834; <title>DNB</title>)]
                        (1804), 568–580; Thomas Green Fessenden (1771–1837), <title>Original Poems</title> (1804), 571; John Blair Linn (1777–1805),
                            <title>The Powers of Genius</title> (1801), 571; Thomas Clio Rickman (1761–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Ode in
                            Celebration of the Emancipation of the Blacks of Saint Domingo, November 29, 1803</title> (1804), 572; Robert Bloomfield,
                            <title>Good Tidings</title> (1804), 574; William Robert Spencer (1770–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Year of
                            Sorrow</title> (1804), 574–575; <title>British Purity: or, the World we Live in. A Poetic Tale, of Two Centuries…By Lory
                            Lucian and Jerry Juvenal, … Assisted by S. Scriblerus, etc.</title> [pseud.] (1804), 575; William Falconer (1732–1769),
                            <title>The Shipwreck</title>, (1804), ed., James Stanier Clarke (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>), 577–580; William Tooke
                        (1777–1863), ed., <title>The Poetical Works of Charles Churchill: with Explanatory Notes and an Authentic Account of his
                            Life</title>, (1804), 580–585; J. Amphlett (dates unknown), <title>Invasion: a Descriptive and Satirical Poem</title>
                        (1804), 585; Joseph Jefferson (1766–1824), <title>Horae Poeticæ. Poems, Sacred, Moral and Descriptive</title> (1804), 586–587;
                        Alexander Campbell (1764–1824; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Grampians Desolate, a Poem in Six Books</title> (1804),
                        587–591; William Crowe (bap. 1745, d. 1829; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Lewesdon Hill</title> (1804), 593–594; John Finlay
                        (1782–1810), <title>Wallace, or, The Vale of Ellerslie, and other Poems</title> (1804), 594–596; Jessie Stewart (dates
                        unknown), <title>Ode to Dr. Thomas Percy</title> (1804), 597; John Belfour (1768–1842), <title>Fables on Subjects Connected
                            with Literature. Imitated from the Spanish of Don Tomas de Yriarte</title> (1804), 597–598; <title>Transactions of the
                            Missionary Society</title> (1804), 621–634; Edward Davies (1756–1831; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Celtic Researches, on
                            the Origin, Traditions, &amp; Language, of the Ancient Britons; with some Introductory Sketches, on Primitive
                            Society</title> (1804), 634–644; [Anon.] <title>No Slaves - No Sugar: Containing New and Irresistible Arguments in Favour
                            of the African Trade by a Liverpool Merchant</title> (1804), 644–648; William Tennant (1758–1813), <title>Indian
                            Recreations, Consisting Chiefly of Strictures on the Domestic and Rural Economy of the Mahommedans and Hindoos</title>
                        (1803), 658–670; John Gardiner (fl. 1758–1792), <title>Essays Literary, Political and Economical</title> (1804), 670–674;
                        Richard Duppa, <title>Heads from the Fresco Pictures of Raffaele in the Vatican</title> (1802), 918–923.</note> No text could
                    be found for a <del>Cath</del> Anti Catholic essay which must therefore be deferred <del>for</del> &lt;to&gt; my quartos. – They
                    loiter with the notes to Madoc – my part has long been done. – Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Jones was a wonderful man – but he is
                    over-rated. latterly he abandoned himself to vague speculations, &amp; all his life long he was envious. Witness his treatment of
                    Anquetil Du Perron, &amp; his twice translating what he knew Wilkins had already undertaken – from a paltry desire of being first
                    instead of cooperating with a man as learned as himself to communicate as much knowledge as they could.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir William Jones (1746–1794; <title>DNB</title>), the Orientalist scholar whose <title>Institutes of Hindu
                            Law, or, The Ordinances of Menu</title> appeared in 1794. In his 1771 <title>Lettre à Monsieur A*** du P***</title>, Jones
                        criticised Abraham-Hyacinthe Anquetil Du Perron (1731–1805), the French Orientalist who in 1771 translated the
                            <title>Avesta</title> from Persian into French and thus introduced Zoroastrianism to Europe. ‘Stung to patriotic anger by
                        the Frenchman’s criticisms of Oxford scholarship’ (<title>DNB</title>), Jones suggested Du Perron had been fooled with
                        forgeries by the Parsi priests on whom he had relied for his Persian texts. In Bengal, Jones collaborated with Sir Charles
                        Wilkins (1749–1836; <title>DNB</title>); together the two men helped establish the Asiatick Society of Bengal in 1784. Wilkins
                        translated the <title>Bhagvat-geeta, or Dialogues of Kreeshna and Arjoon</title> (1785). Southey’s remark about Jones’s
                        competitiveness with Wilkins, scarcely warranted, was probably based on Jones’s ‘Preface’ to his translation of
                            <title>Sacontalá</title>: ‘I think it proper to say, that I have already translated four or five other books, and among
                        them the Hitópadésa, which I undertook merely as an exercise in learning Sanscrit, three years before I knew that Mr. Wilkins,
                        without whose aid I should never have learned it [Sanskrit], had any thought of giving the same work to the publick’
                            (<title>The Works of Sir William Jones</title>, 6 vols (London, 1799), VI, p. 208).</note> I have studied his Ordinances
                    of Menu for the purpose of a chapter on the Hindoos, – &amp; indeed all his works &amp; all others concerning Hindostan that I
                    could procure for materials for my next poem<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>
                        (1810), Southey made extensive use of translations of Hindu texts.</note> – which is to exhibit their mythology in the manner
                    of Thalaba<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), Southey ‘exhibits’ the
                        ‘mythology’ of Islam; he also draws upon William Jones’s <title>Poesos Asiaticae Commentariorium</title> (1777) and<title>
                            Essay on the Poetry of the Eastern Nations</title> (1772). See <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793–1810</title>,
                        gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), III, pp. 221 and 337.</note> – If poetry were a marketable article I would
                        <del>xxxxx</del> no longer waste that time in criticising bad books which would be so much more pleasantly occupied in writing
                    better, but as I make no other sacrifice than that of time I am well off.</p><p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> has been vaccinated &amp; is well.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">To provide inoculation from smallpox in the light of the publication, in <title>An Inquiry Into the
                        Causes and Effects of the Variolæ Vaccinæ</title> (1798), of the experiments of Edward Jenner (1749–1823; <title>DNB</title>) on vaccinating against smallpox using cowpox serum.</note> I am in excellent
                    good health, &amp; wish for nothing but to be with all my books about me. If my next years schemes turn out well I shall come near
                    you &amp; gather them together but I find it more easy to acquire fame than fortune. Madoc will soon be ready &amp; the book a
                    very beautiful one. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> joins me in remembrances to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you </salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>