<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1605</idno><idno type="nines">rce2727</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1605" type="letter"><head>1605. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, [started before and continued on] <date when="1809-03-27">27 March [1809]</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Staunton upon Wye/ Hereford
                        <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb/>Unpublished. </note></head><p rend="indent1"> Your description of the Falls of the Yguazu has been partly wrought into the text, partly inserted in the
                        notes.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), I,
                        p. 112.</note> I thought I had acknowledged it, &amp; also that I had said something concerning the Life of Pombal.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sebastião José de Carvalho e Melo, 1st Count of Oeiras, 1st Marquess of Pombal (1699–1782;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Minister of the Kingdom of Portugal from 1750 to 1777. Southey narrates his period of government in
                        the third volume of the <title>History of Brazil</title>.</note> My part shall travel to you with the next portion of MS. the
                    whole may then go to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, &amp; get bound before I make use of it. There is a
                    good deal of time lost in referring to unbound manuscripts. As for Pinkerton I have no intention of adding any thing to his book,
                    but merely of correcting his blunders.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had arranged with John Pinkerton
                        (1758–1826; <title>DNB</title>) that his brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>
                        would provide translations and abridgements of travel accounts for his edition of <title>A General Collection of the Best and
                            Most Interesting Voyages and Travels in All Parts of the World</title> (1808–1814).</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref> may be written to under cover to ‘<ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Rt. Honble the Speaker</ref>’ . <del>xxx</del> Rickman is the most useful of all my friends, &amp; one of the men in the
                    world for whom I have the most thorough &amp; unalloyed liking. My proofs come to me thro his hands, &amp; are the better for his
                    remarks. He has lately sent me Arrowsmiths map of S America<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aaron Arrowsmith (1750–1823;
                            <title>DNB</title>), cartographer of Soho Square, London, renowned for his 1790 large chart of the world. Among
                        Arrowsmith’s other productions were <title>A Map of America</title> (1804), which depicted North and South America.</note> to
                    correct the orthography as far as I can before my own be made.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second volume of
                        Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819) contained this map.</note> As I have no business, at least none of any
                    importance, south of the Plata, he &amp; Arrowsmith &amp; <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        Burney</ref> agree with me that it will be better to cut off the knuckle of the shoulder of mutton just below that river, by
                    which means we shall be able <del>x</del> materially to enlarge the scale of the map. Proofs, when it is ready, may be sent both
                    to you &amp; to me, as often as they are needed, by help of the Speaker – who is Emperor of the Franks.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rickman’s employer, <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbot</ref>, was dubbed ‘Emperor of the
                        Franks’ because of his power to frank mail, which <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, used on Southey’s
                        behalf.</note> Arrowsmith has copied Johs’s map,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Perhaps the c. 1720 map of the whole
                        of America by Joh. Baptist Homann (1664–1724).<title>Totius Americae, Joh. Baptist Homann</title>.</note> &amp; has also at my
                    recommendation hunted out Dobrizhoffers.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717–1791), <title>Historia
                            de Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariæ</title> (1784).</note> Solreviela’s in the Mercurio Peruano,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Mercurio Peruano</title> was a newspaper published in Peru between 1790 and 1795,
                        renowned for its scientific content. Southey probably had access to the twelve-volume edition of <title>Mercurio Peruano, de
                            Historia, Literatura y Noticias Públicas que da á luz la Sociedad Academica de Amantes de Lima</title> (1791–1795).
                        Solreviela y Girba (dates unknown), who was associated with this publication was responsible for reproducing the map Southey
                        refers to.</note> of which there <del>was</del> &lt;is&gt; probably no other copy in England, I put into his hands when John
                        Allen<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Allen (1771–1843; <title>DNB</title>), a journalist and historian who was
                        an intimate of <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord</ref> and <ref target="people.html#FoxElizabethVassall">Lady
                            Holland</ref> and an expert on Spanish history.</note> lent me the book, – from thence he would get the Ucayali,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Ucayali River in Peru is the main headwater for the Amazon River.</note> better than
                    it has yet been laid down. We shall be able by combining these, hitherto uncombined, materials make a better map than has
                    appeared. <del>xx</del> I think it will be advisable to get the skeleton engraved as soon as may be, but reserve the map for the
                    second volume, because I shall certainly be able to made it fuller then than can possibly be done now.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have got at Falkner<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Falkner (1707–1784), an English Jesuit whose
                        papers were published as <title>A Description of Patagonia and the Adjoining Parts of South America</title> (1774).</note> by
                    means of Arrowsmith, from Sir Joseph Banks’s Library,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Banks, Baronet (1743–1820;
                            <title>DNB</title>), naturalist and patron of science, whose house in Soho Square, London contained Europe’s best library
                        of natural history and voyage narratives.</note> – By way of obtaining this book for myself I shall recommend it for insertion
                    in Pinkertons Voyages – which the Booksellers give me.</p><p rend="indent1"> ———</p><p><date when="1809-03-27">Monday March 27.</date></p><p rend="indent1"> Thus far I had written last night when a call to supper interrupted me, &amp; this morning soon after day break
                        <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> was safely delivered of a <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">daughter</ref>. All hitherto, thank God, is as well as could be wished. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Your
                        namesake</ref>, who is, we think, as like you as he could be were he your own child, – is exceedingly astonished at his new
                    sister. Little <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma</ref> is hardly old enough for wonder. I have, now four living, &amp;
                    one in heaven. Few things would give me so much pleasure as to hear that they had a cousin in Herefordshire.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hill’s son, <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref>, was born later in
                    1809.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> From Lackingtons<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The publishing firm run by George Lackington
                        (1777–1844).</note> I have got the Hist. delle Guerre di Portagallo – da Alessandro Brandano.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alessandro Brandano (dates unknown) <title>Historia delle Guerre di Portogallo: Succedute per l’Occasione della
                        Separazione di quel Regno dalla Corona Cattolica Descritte, e Dedicate alla Sacra Reale Maestà Di Pietro II, Re di Portogallo</title>
                        (1689). The book as described by Southey was no. 417 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> The Braganzan war down to
                    1656. another of the same family published a continuation.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francesco Brandano (dates
                        unknown), <title>Dell’Istoria delle Guerre di Portogallo: che Continua quella di Alessandro Branda; Parte Seconda (-terza) ...
                            Descritta, e Dedicata alla Sacra Real Maestà Di Giovanni V, Re di Portogallo</title> (1716–1724).</note> Whether the Book
                    be a good one I know not. – the copy is a fine one, in old Morocco binding, &amp; was purchased by a Mr Stearne Tighe at Florence
                    in 1787.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Stearne Tighe (1760–1835).</note> the Tighes are an Irish family of some
                    distinction there is a poem by a Lady of that name in which the story of Psyche is well told<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Tighe (née Blachford; 1772–1810; <title>DNB</title>), poet whose major work <title>Psyche; or The Legend
                            of Love</title> (1805) was admired by several of her literary contemporaries.</note> in Spensers manner, &amp; another of
                    the family has still more lately published a respectable poem which he calls The Plants.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        William Tighe (1766–1816), <title>The Plants: A Poem, Cantos the First and Second, with Notes; and Occasional Poems</title>
                        (1808).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I have sent to Bristol for Atkyns’ Voyages to Brazil.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to
                        Charles Danvers, 20 March 1809, Letter 1603.</note> His voyage to Africa Brazil &amp; the W Indies I purchased from a
                    Catalogue years ago, &amp; found that all it contained about Brazil was a reference to this separate volume. It will be a prize if
                    it should prove as good a book as the other.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Atkins (bap. 1685–1757;
                            <title>DNB</title>) published <title>A Voyage to Guinea, Brazil and the West Indies in His Majesty’s Ships the Swallow and
                            Weymouth</title> (1735), but did not write a separate account of a voyage to Brazil.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>