<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1090</idno><idno type="nines">rce2212</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Huntington Library, RS 76.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 339–340 [in part];
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        387–390.Dating note: dating from JR’s endorsement. </p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1090" type="letter"><head>1090. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1805-07-31">[July-August
                        1805]</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>Endorsement: RS./ July Aug. 1805<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 76<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), II, pp. 339–340 [in part];
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        387–390.<lb/>Dating note: dating from JR’s endorsement. </note></head><opener><salute>Dear Rickman</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Have you not been somewhat precipitate in commencing the house hunt for me? – there are ugly contingencies still in
                    the way, – the prizes may still miscarry,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was hoping to move with the financial
                        assistance of his brother, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas</ref>, whose ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, in
                        which he was a lieutenant, had captured the Spanish brig <hi rend="ital">Isabella</hi> and the ship <hi rend="ital">Conception</hi>, both laden with wine and brandy, and the ship <hi rend="ital">Commerce</hi>, laden with cotton. It was
                        customary for naval officers to be allotted a share of the value of ships and cargo captured in armed conflict.</note> – the
                    bills not arrive, – not be honoured when they come, or prove good for nothing, like those of which you speak.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your objections to the exordial lines are not valid:<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is referring
                        to the exordial lines of his poem <title>Madoc</title> (1805). See <title>Robert Southey. Poetical Works 1793–1810</title>,
                        gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), II, p. 8.</note> I say there of what the poem is to treat, not affirming that it
                    is historically true. Just as I might have said in an introduction to Thalaba<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> that he destroyed the Domdaniel &amp; so put an end to all sorcery. – The
                    want of numerals is a fault – I confess. not so the namelessness of the divisions – nor indeed are they nameless, for in the notes
                    they are referred to as <hi rend="ital">Sections</hi>, – &amp; that each has not its <hi rend="ital">specific</hi> name, from its
                    subject matter &lt;affixed to it,&gt; is you know the effect of your own advice. However call them Sections, Cantos, Canticles,
                    Chapters – what you will, &amp; then consider in what is the mode of division objectionable? it differs only from that of other
                    poems in having shorter sections – in travelling by miles instead of leagues the primary division into parts is unavoidable.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am not surprized at your little-liking the poem. – on the contrary I am more surprized <del>that</del> at those
                    who like it, – because what merit it has is almost wholly that of execution, which is infinitely better than the subject, – now
                    every body can feel if a story be uninteresting or flat, whereas there are very few who can judge the worth of the language &amp;
                    versification. I have said to somebody – perhaps it was to you yourself – that had this been <hi rend="ital">written</hi> since
                    Thalaba, (for as you know the plan was formed &amp; the key pitched before Thalaba was begun or dreamt of) I should have thought
                    it ominous of declining powers, it is in so sober a tone, its colouring so autumnal, its light every where that of an evening sun.
                    But as only the last finish of language, the polishing part is of later labour, the fair inference is that instead of the poets
                    imagination having grown weaker, he has improved in the mechanism of his art. A fair inference it is – for I am no self-flatterer
                    Heaven knows. – That you may see what is my own deep &amp; intimate conviction about the poem I send what I had written as the
                    beginning of a preface: – the remarks are <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref>. I acceded easily to the
                    common-sense which they contained &amp; readily forbore telling the reader what he was likely enough to find out. But the truth it
                    is. – I had chosen my subject ill, &amp; nothing could ever overbalance that radical &amp; constitutional defect.</p><p rend="indent1"> Having confessed thus much I ought to add that the poem is better than you think it, &amp; is certainly not of the
                    patchwork-texture you describe. Compare it with the Odyssey – not the Iliad – King John or Coriolanus, not Macbeth or the
                        Tempest.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Plays by Shakespeare.</note> The story wants unity, &amp; has perhaps too
                    Greek – too Stoical – a want of passion, – but as far as I can <del>judge</del> &lt;see&gt; with the same eyes wherewith I read
                    Homer &amp; Spenser &amp; Shakespere &amp; Milton, it is still a good poem, &amp; must live. – You will like it better if ever you
                    read it again.</p><p rend="indent1"> You speak of <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Gobwin</ref> as you should speak.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s habitual misspelling of Godwin’s name was meant to suggest his mouthiness. For the affair that occasioned Southey’s distaste – Godwin’s objection by letter to Southey’s tone in reviewing Godwin’s books – see Southey to John Rickman, 18 May 1805 (Letter 1067).</note> Certainly I would not have
                    spoken of him in the Malthusian article as I did speak, had I supposed he would have ever known me to be the author<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Godwin’s argument, in <title>An Enquiry Concerning Political Justice</title> (1793), that human
                        society might advance towards perfectibility was opposed by Thomas Malthus (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>), in <title>An Essay
                            on the Principle of Population, as it Affects the Future Improvement of Society; with Remarks on the Speculations of W.
                            Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title> (1803). Southey’s review of Malthus appeared in <title>The Annual Review
                            for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 292–301.</note> – but as certainly <del>xxx</del> I would <del>xxx</del> have written the same
                    reviewal of his Chaucer.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had reviewed Godwin’s <title>Chaucer ... Including
                            Memoirs of ... John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster; with Sketches of the Manners, Opinions, Arts and Literature of England in
                            the Fourteenth Century</title> (1803) in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 462–473.</note> You seem to
                    over-rate our former acquaintance – I never liked the man, &amp; he never liked me. I <hi rend="ital">did</hi> like his <ref target="people.html#WollstonecraftMary">wife</ref> – I did like &amp; do like what is good in his first book.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>An Enquiry Concerning Political Justice</title> (1793).</note> but in proportion as I value what is true there, do I
                    abominate the cursed mingle-mangle of metaphysics &amp; concubinism &amp; atheism with which he polluted it. Once I dined at his
                        <ref target="people.html#WollstonecraftMary">wifes</ref> by her invitation – except this a half a dozen morning calls <hi rend="ital">out</hi>sums all my visits, &amp; those I &lt;had&gt; discontinued, thinking him intolerably dull, &amp; tho
                    without any harm equally good-for-nothing. As for any violation of decorum, he is the aggressor, &amp; he knows it, &amp;
                    assuredly if it could be proper for him to speak contemptuously of me to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, it cannot have been otherwise in me to write him down a fool. The plea in formâ pauperis is valid,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A Latin legal term meaning ‘in the form of a pauper or poor man’, used to refer to
                        defendants who have no money to pay for a trial.</note> were the effect possible. But all that criticism can do against a man
                    so notorious is to beat him down from biography or history – to his proper work, that of manufacturing novels, – a manufactory in
                    which such journeymen will never lack employment. Enough – You have seen all the ink he shall cost me, &amp; may admire the self
                    denial which I exercised in forbearing from answering his letter as I could have answered it.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> See note 5.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The History of Portugal fits me better than that of my own country.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s projected ‘History of Portugal’ was never completed, but he used much of the material he researched for it in his
                            <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> England will not for ever want a worthy historian, – but it is not
                    likely that Portugal would ever again find one so qualified, – for if a foreigner possess the knowledge of a native he is better
                    qualified. – My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> – if he ever does any thing – will write the
                    history of the Crusades. he has it in his mind, &amp; I have just at a country sale provided him with an Arabic grammar to [MS
                    obscured] upon. this is a worthy subject. he does not want talents, &amp; has only too much ambition. if it should settle in this
                    channel, much might be expected from him. that &amp; the history of the Caliphate are works worth living for. <del>xxxxxx</del> My
                    work is cut out. – I shall write more poetry – because I also have certain wants to supply, &amp; being obliged to do something
                    for money will do that which I can do best. Therefore will I give over reviewing after this current year, &amp; instead finish my
                    series of romances, of which Thalaba is the first. Each will not cost much more labour than a years drudgery at dull publications,
                    certainly not more than the <del>xxx</del> proportion of profits will answer. for the sale of 500 &lt;within the year&gt; is
                    certain, &amp; the after profits, tho if slow coming in, would always be something, whereas the labour of reviewing once paid is
                    paid for ever.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have just received from Lisbon <del>a collection of</del> the Barbarorum Leges Antiquae with notes glossaries
                    &amp;c. in five thin but full folios, edited between 1781 &amp; 1793 at Venice by F. Paulus Canciani, a Monk, – &amp;
                        <del>xxxxx</del> one who does honour to Monachism.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 483 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey’s books is Paulus Canciani (dates unknown), <title>Barbarorum Leges Antiquæ, cum Notis et Glossariis, acccendunt
                            Formulari Fasciculi et Selectæ Constitutiones</title> (1781–1792).</note> Had this arrived in time I would have sent it to
                        <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> for his last volume<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Volume four
                        of Turner’s <title>History of the Anglo-Saxons</title> was published in 1805.</note> for it contains the laws of all the
                    Gothic branches. – His volume has not yet found its way here. I shall urge him to add to it a Welsh history. – if he would rewrite
                    his first volumes, adding thereto all that his present increased knowledge would enable him, – no <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Gobwin</ref> nor any body else could ever profit by pillaging him, his reputation would
                    stand too high.</p><p rend="indent1"> Thank you for Aylesbury, Ilchester &amp; Knaresborough. I should still like to have Nottingham, – for tho D Manuel
                    cannot enter into any detail of either, the more matter of fact there is in his general picture, or rather in the particular part
                    of it the better<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was collecting material on elections in these constituencies for
                        inclusion in Letter 48 of <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title>
                        (1807).</note> – &amp; the Spensering should be taken from the life. Is the Middlesex 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> report any ways
                        remarkable?<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is referring to the recent election of a Member of Parliament for
                        the county of Middlesex. In the general election of 1802 <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Sir Francis Burdett</ref> stood as
                        a Whig candidate on the platform of penal reform. His return was declared void on 9 July 1804, and in the by-election of 23
                        July he was defeated by a small margin. On 5 March 1805, after challenging this outcome, Burdett was elected, only for the
                        decision to be reversed again soon after. The financial cost to Burdett was huge and he declared that he would never stand for
                        parliament again. The Middlesex election is discussed in <title>Letters from England</title>, Letter 48.</note> – I will wait
                    awhile for the Feyjoo<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s fictional traveller refers to Benito-Gerónimo Feyjoo y
                        Montenegro (1676–1764), <title>Teatro Critico</title> (1726–1739) in Letters 49 and 54 of <title>Letters from
                        England</title>.</note> &amp;c – in case any thing should induce me to carry D Manuel myself to town, which indeed is not
                    likely, but still not impossible. – You did not send me my beginning of a Catalogue – it would be well to have it to add-in what
                    additional books are here. light labour now, &amp; lightening what will be heavy hereafter. thank you for the journey from
                        Salisbury<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rickman’s description of the journey from Salisbury to London is included
                        in Letters 4 and 5 of <title>Letters from England</title>.</note> – it enables me to finish the first journey – which I shall
                    now do without farther delay &amp; send off to you to interpolate. – It is not impossible that I may be urged to write upon the
                    Slave Trade this summer. I made a promise to that effect some year &amp; half ago – if it should be thought useful. if so I shall
                    consult you about it. – Send back – or lay by for me – my unborn preface which is a proof with how foolish an unreserve a man will
                    sometimes write after ten years experience.</p></div></body></text></TEI>