<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1020</idno><idno type="nines">rce2142</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Eng. Lett.
                        c. 23.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1020" type="letter"><head>1020. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1805-01-15">15 January 1805</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster/ Single<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E / JAN18/ 1805<lb/>Endorsement:
                        15 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1805; [in another hand] Wrote to J Moore Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 22.<lb/>MS: Bodleian Eng. Lett.
                        c. 23<lb/>Unpublished. </note></head><opener><salute>Dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Let Hyems<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A Latin soubriquet of John Winter (dates unknown), a printer who
                        frequently worked on books published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</note> when he goes to <ref target="places.html#QueenHithe">Queen Hithe</ref><note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The place of residence of <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Thomas Hill</ref>, book collector and editor.</note> again (&amp; if I thought Hyems never
                    went there I would go live there myself.) – copy from Clarke’s edition of Falconers Shipwreck P xxiii. The Midshipman, beginning
                    ‘Deep in that Fabric’ &amp; on to the end to be the specimen of Falconer.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed
                        James Stanier Clarke’s (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>) 1804 edition of the poem <title>The Shipwreck</title> (1762) by William
                        Falconer (1732–1769) in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 577–580. Here, he wishes Bedford to derive from
                        it the passage from Falconer to be included in their anthology <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>, 3 vols,
                        (London, 1807). The selections appeared in vol. II, pp. 397–400.</note> The book will certainly be there as being the most
                    beautiful edition I ever saw of any work whatsoever. And do you yourself add to our list Captain Thomson who died in 1786. In the
                    Naval Chronicle Vol 6 p. 237 &amp; Vol 7.93 you will see what he wrote &amp; where to find the specimens – of which <hi rend="ital">The Top sails shiver in the Wind</hi> should be one.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain Edward
                        Thompson (1738–1786; <title>DNB</title>), naval officer and author of satires including <title>The Demi-Rep</title> (1756) and
                            <title>The Meretriciad</title> (1763). His career was featured in the new magazine <title>The Naval Chronicle</title>
                        (founded 1799): Southey’s citation is correct, with volume 6 appearing in 1801 and volume 7 in 1802. Thompson authored sea
                        songs including ‘The topsails shiver in the wind’. Selections from his poems appeared in the <title>Specimens of the Later
                            English Poets</title>, II, pp. 407–412, but this one was not included.</note> Say of him what you will, only let this make
                    a part of what you say, that ‘having very immorally abused his talents, he made some atonement by editing the works of that true
                    Englishman Andrew Marvell.’<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thompson’s edition of the writings of fellow Hull poet Andrew
                        Marvell (1621–1678; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of Andrew Marvell ... Containing Many Original Letters, Poems and
                            Tracts, Never Before Printed, with a ... Life of the Author by Capt. E. Thompson</title>, was published in 1776. The sentence suggested by Southey did not appear in Thompson’s biography.</note>
                    You will see in the Biog. Dramatica that he boasted of writing obscenely.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thompson’s boast
                        was: ‘I am the bard (the <hi rend="ital">Naso</hi> of my time)/ Born on the Humber, famed for luscious rhime’, in
                            <title>Biographia Dramatica or, a Companion to the Playhouse</title>, edited by Isaac Reed (1742–1807;
                        <title>DNB</title>), 2 vols (London, 1782), I, p. 445.</note></p><p rend="indent4"> –––</p><p rend="indent1">Now Grosvenor I have something of a very different character to say. I am very desirous of getting a civil
                    appointment in the expedition to Portugal, &amp; am trying for it in all directions. You know some of General Moores
                        relations,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Moore (1761–1809; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish General with a long
                        and varied military career. He was also MP for Lanark Burghs 1784–1790. After the controversial Convention of Cintra (1808),
                        Moore was given the command ofthe British troops in the Iberian peninsula. He was fatally wounded at the Battle of Corunna. In
                        December 1804 he was sent to review the practicability of defending Portugal from a French invasion. His favourable report was
                        widely leaked to the press, e.g. <title>Aberdeen Journal</title>, 9 January 1805. Moore was part of a large and well-known
                        family that included his younger brothers, Dr James Moore (1763–1860; <title>DNB</title>) and the Royal Navy officer Graham
                        Moore (1764–1843; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; it might very possibly be of some use if you could get my name mentioned to
                    him, – that is that he should know what I wish, &amp; why I wish it for he is one of those men with whom my object would be likely
                    to have some weight &amp; my knowledge of the country &amp; the people constitutes a certain fitness which is not to be found in
                    every body. – If you have no objection to do this for me – do it soon, for time is precious, &amp; it is to me a very material
                    thing. I should be enabled to &lt;do&gt; all I wish &amp; accumulate a few hundreds besides, which would settle me comfortably on
                    my return.</p><p rend="indent1"> My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> would have been in the action – had he not been under
                    arrest. he has been tried by a Court Martial – found guilty of contempt towards his Captain<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain (later Admiral) Henry Heathcote (1777–1851), in command of HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi> 1803–1805.</note> –
                    dismissed the ship – &amp; appointed First Lieutenant to a finer frigate by the Commodore in consequence so that he is the fair
                    way to promotion – if he escapes the yellow fever, which is raging dreadfully on board the Amelia.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 14 August 1804, the boats of Thomas Southey’s ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi> made an unsuccessful
                        attempt to cut out the French privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi> (formerly the British sloop of war
                            <distinct>Lilly</distinct>) lying at the Saintes near Guadeloupe. Of the 90 men sent on the mission 65 were killed or
                        wounded. Southey had suspected that his brother was among the dead, having read in the newspapers that the first lieutenant
                        had been killed. Thomas had been placed under arrest and his replacement on the raid, Lieutenant Charles Hayman (dates
                        unknown), died. After the court martial, Thomas was made lieutenant of HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, a finer ship than the
                            <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, because she was a 38-gun Hébé-class frigate of the French navy captured in 1796 and then
                        commissioned into the navy.</note> He wishes me when I visit London to see the minutes of his trials – having gained some
                    credit for his defence.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1">What news of <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> – if he be successful he will be
                        Horatius Cocles – quasi Cockle-shell shewer.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> A pun: the one-eyed Publius Horatius
                            Cocles (6th century BC) was the Roman hero who, in c. 505/6 BC, prevented an Etruscan army pursuing the fleeing Romans
                            over a bridge, by defending it until it was destroyed behind him. Horace Bedford was to be in charge of the Museum’s
                            collection of shells.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>