<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1393</idno><idno type="nines">rce2515</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>.  Previously  published: in E. L. Griggs, ‘Robert Southey and the Edinburgh Review’,
                            Modern Philology, 30 (August 1932), pp. 101–103. </p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1393" type="letter"><head>1393. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1807-12-09">9
                        December 1807</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ S.T. Coleridge Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Courier Office/ Strand/ London/ Single<lb/>Postmark: E/ Dec 12/ 1807<lb/>Endorsed: R. Southey Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>MS:
                        Houghton Library, Harvard<lb/>Previously published: in E. L. Griggs, ‘Robert Southey and the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>’,
                            <title>Modern Philology</title>, 30 (August 1932), pp. 101–103. </note></head><opener><date when="1807-12-09">Dec 9. 1807.</date><salute>My dear Coleridge</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Overtures have been made me thro <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> to bear a part in the
                    Edinburgh review ‘chusing my own books, &amp; expressing my own opinions’. This is the answer which I have returned, – I send it
                        <hi rend="ital">only</hi> to you; – not to be shown &amp; talked of.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> For the original,
                        see Southey to Walter Scott, 8 December 1807, Letter 1392.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> ‘I am very much obliged to you for the offer which you make concerning the E. Review &amp; fully sensible of your
                    friendship, &amp; the advantage which it holds out. I bear as little ill-will to <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> as he does to me; &amp; attribute whatever civil things he has said of me to especial civility; &amp; whatever
                    pert ones, (a truer epithet than severe would be) to the habit he has acquired of taking it for granted that the Critic is, by
                    virtue of his office, superior to every writer whom he chuses to summon before him. The reviewals of Thalaba &amp; Madoc<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jeffrey reviewed <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> in the<title> Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 1 (October 1802), 63–83; his review of <title>Madoc</title> appeared in volume 7 (October 1805),
                        1–29.</note> (<ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> had alluded to them) do in no degree influence me. Setting all
                    personal feelings aside the objections which weigh with me against bearing any part in the Journal are these. I have scarcely one
                    opinion in common with it upon any subject. Jeffrey is for peace, &amp; is endeavouring to frighten the people into it. I am for
                    war as long as Bonaparte lives. He is for Catholick emancipation. I believe that its immediate consequence would be to introduce
                    an Irish Priest into every ship in the navy. My feelings are still less in unison with him than my opinions. On subjects of moral
                    or political importance no man is more apt to speak in the very gall of bitterness that I am; &amp; this habit is likely to go
                    with me to the grave. But that sort of bitterness in which he indulges, which tends directly &amp; purposely to wound a man in his
                    feelings, &amp; injure him in his fame &amp; fortune (<ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomery</ref> is a case in
                        point<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Edinburgh</title> belittled the third edition of James Montgomery’s
                        1806 poem <title>The Wanderer of Switzerland</title> in volume 9 (January 1807), 347–54.</note>) appears to me utterly
                    inexcusable. Now tho there would be no necessity that I should follow this example, yet every seperate article in the review
                    derives authority from the merit of all the others &amp; in this way whatever of any merit I might insert there would aid &amp;
                    abet opinions hostile to my own, &amp; thus make me <hi rend="ital">art &amp; part</hi> in a system which I thoroughly disapprove.
                    This is not said hastily. the emolument to be derived from writing at ten guineas a sheet Scotch measure, instead of seven pounds
                    annual, would be considerable; the pecuniary advantage resulting from the different manner in which my future works would be
                    handled, <del>xxxx</del> probably still more so. But my moral <del>character</del> feelings must not be compromised. To <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> as an individual I shall ever be ready to show every kind of individual
                    courtesy: but <del>to</del> of Judge <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref><note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Here Southey deliberately portrays Francis Jeffrey, severe critic, as George Jeffreys, 1st Baron Jeffreys of Wem (1645–1689;
                            <title>DNB</title>), known as ‘The Hanging Judge’ for the severity of the sentences he handed down after the Monmouth
                        rebellion of 1685.</note> of the E. review, I must ever think <del>xxxx</del> &amp; speak, as of a bad politician, a worse
                    moralist, &amp; a critic in matters of taste equally incompetent &amp; unjust.’</p><p rend="indent1"> Now Coleridge tho <del>xxxx</del> &lt;this&gt; be plain English, it may not be quite understood in Scotland. Why
                    have I transcribed it <del>xxxx</del> for you? – that you may chew the cud upon it. Perhaps the late reviewal of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref><note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jeffrey reviewed Wordsworth’s
                            <title>Poems in Two Volumes</title> in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 11 (October 1807), 214–231.</note> may revive
                    in you old resolutions of putting out your strength against this poor crab who goes on biting Morgante in the heel.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>Morgante</title> (1483), the epic poem by Luigi Pulci (1432–1484), the eponymous giant
                        is killed by a crab bite.</note> – because Morgante will not tread upon him. <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> abominates that review. If you are disposed to attack it in good earnest, the Courier would be the most
                    efficacious engine, &amp; I am ready to cooperate with you in any way you please.</p><p rend="indent1"><hi rend="ital">Run down </hi><ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam"> Wordsworth</ref> cannot be, – but he will be <hi rend="ital">run hard</hi>. I think
                    him injudicious in publishing many of these poems, – some few of them seem even to me, absolutely worthless. But I lose patience
                    at the blindness of heart which dwells upon these &amp; the greater the outcry is the more desirous I am of lifting up a louder
                    voice in opposition to it. A man named Merrival abused him in the Critical<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Herman
                        Merivale (1779–1844), lawyer, translator of Italian, German and Greek poetry, contributor to many journals. A review of
                        Wordsworth’s <title>Poems in Two Volumes</title> appeared in the <title>Critical Review</title>, ns 11 (August 1807), 399–403;
                        which Southey had earlier attributed to Charles Le Grice – now it seems he had changed his mind. For the authorship of this
                        review; see <title>William Wordsworth: The Critical Heritage. Volume 1 1793–1820</title>, ed. Robert Woof (London and New
                        York, 2001), pp. 170–171.</note> – who he is I know not; – tho I have a dim sort of guess that he is the same person who puts
                    portions of Greek tragedy into rhyme in the Athenaeum.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Merivale’s translations from the
                        Greek appeared as ‘Extracts from the Grecian Drama’, <title>Athenæum</title>, 1 (1807), 484–488, 591–594 and in volume 2
                        (1807), 37–40, 152–155, 266–269, 368–371, 483–490.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> There are two ways in which <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> should be attacked. by an
                    exposure of all his errors, moral political &amp;c &amp;c &amp; by a stinging satire – I think I have a sting in my tail long
                    enough to run him thro. You may remember an old notion of mine that the Man in the Moon was dead? – I would go to the Moon express
                    upon a Night Mare just when the election for his successor was to take place – &amp; among other candidates bring up <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref>. – I have floating fancies enough to make this a poem of some length &amp;
                    plentiful oddity.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> This satire was not written.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> will give you Espriella, &amp; with it Palmerin &amp; the small edition of
                    Madoc if you think it worth asking for.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807), <title>Palmerin of
                            England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title> (1807) and the second,
                        duodecimo edition of <title>Madoc</title> (1807).</note> Concerning Palmerin you need feel no ruth &amp; compassion for my
                    fingers; – it is a book which deserved to be tinkered into a decent translation for its reputation – not for its merit – &amp; if
                    you had any liking for Romance you would perceive that this, tho beyond all measurement below Amadis,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s translation of the Spanish romance <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> deserved what labour
                    I bestowed upon it. – Espriella sells, – they tell me that it will probably be expedient to send it again to press in about a
                        month.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> A second edition of <title>Letters from England</title> was published in
                        1808.</note> The sale of a second edition would right me in Longmans books &amp; leave me profits enough to expect from the
                        <del>xxxx</del> duodecimo Madoc<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The 1807 small (and cheaper) edition of
                            <title>Madoc</title>.</note> – Palmerin &amp; the unborn Cid,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s edition
                        of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note></p><p rend="indent1">for the [MS torn] &amp; means of the ensuing year. – during which I shall bring forward the first vol. of Brazil,
                    &amp; most likely my travels in Portugal.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of
                            Brazil</title> was published in 1810. Southey did not produce this projected book; but his 1797 <title>Letters Written
                            During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> were reprinted in an expanded form in 1808 as <title>Letters
                            Written During a Journey in Spain, and a Short Residence in Portugal</title>.</note><ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> must have served the book much. I design to write two additional volumes,
                    bringing D Manuel to England again.</p><p rend="indent1"> I wish you to review Wordsworths Poems for two especial reasons – the first that you will do it more to <hi rend="ital">my</hi> satisfaction &lt;than I myself should&gt;. – the second that you will do it more to <hi rend="ital">his</hi>. For tho I should bestow praise upon him as high as his deserts – that is as high as I have language to convey, I
                    should without scruple blame what I disapprove. This might be the best way of serving the book. but it would not be the best way
                    of pleasing him, &amp; tho I would not go an inch to the left hand to please <del>any one</del> &lt;all the men in the world&gt; I
                    would go a yard to the right to avoid displeasing <del>xxxx</del> any one. If you are too busy – (– yet be you as busy as you may
                    you <hi rend="ital">must</hi> have more time than I have) write me a letter upon the subject &amp; I will fill up any skeleton you
                    may send.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Neither Coleridge nor Southey published a review of Wordsworth’s <title>Poems
                            in Two Volumes</title>. Southey’s review, intended for <title>The Annual Review</title>, was rejected by the editor, <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Arthur Aikin</ref>; see Southey to Thomas Southey, 9 September 1808, Letter
                    1504.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> has probably talked to you about a new review. Were it possible that you could undertake the management (oh that I thought this were possible!)
                    you might secure to yourself an income of 500 £ a year. <note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge did not become editor
                        of a new review.</note> My cooperation might be drawn on to any extent. With my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> I <del>xxxx</del> challenge all England at eating gooseberry pye. by
                    myself I challenge all England for good spirits, &amp; making a noise. with you I would <del>xxxx</del> &lt;challenge&gt; all the
                    critics in England &amp; make open war upon them. – Setting this aside as a thing not to be hoped for, my main object for
                    obtruding a letter <del>xxxx</del> upon you, who neither like to receive nor to write <del>xxxx</del> one – was the business of
                    the Edinburgh. If you will attack it in a series of letters, exploring all its falshood &amp; ignorance, I will bear a full part
                    in this good work: – &amp; if you will join with me in my Man of the Moon I will <del>xxxx</del> be in earnest about it, &amp;
                    send you the plan for your attention. The Devils Thoughts<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘The Devil’s Thoughts’, the
                        jointly-authored political ballad first published in the <title>Morning Post</title>, on 6 September 1799. For the complex
                        later publication history of the poem, see <title>The Poetical Works of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</title>, ed. J. C. C. Mays, 3
                        vols (London and Princeton, 2001), I.ii, pp. 726–750 and <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793–1810</title>, gen. ed.
                        Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), V, <title>Selected Shorter Poems</title>, pp. 451–474.</note> is some little specimen of
                    what we can do together. I am sure we should make as much noise as Two Men in the Moon could do, &amp; that we should make teach
                    better manners to a set of coxcombs who, because we have hitherto acted as if we were literary Quakers, think they may insult
                    &amp; injure us with impunity. – At all events do not talk about this; to threaten &amp; not to strike would be to expose
                    ourselves to deserved contempt. – all well</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>