<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1648</idno><idno type="nines">rce2770</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 3878.  Previously  published:
                        Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp.
                        240–242.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1648" type="letter"><head>1648. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, <date when="1809-07-06">6 July
                        1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] Keswick July Six 1809/ Walter Scott
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Edinburgh/ R Sharp <lb/>Postmark: JY/ 1809/ 8<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Watermark: shield/
                        1807/ T BOTFIELD<lb/>Endorsement: Southey/ 6 July 1809<lb/>MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 3878<lb/>Previously published:
                        Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp.
                        240–242.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Scott</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have just been informed that the Stewardship for the Derwentwater Estates (belonging to Greenwich Hospital) now
                    held by a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walton,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicholas Walton (d. 1809).</note> is expected
                    soon to be vacated by his death.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey asked several friends to intercede on his behalf
                        for this position, including <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">George Beaumont</ref>, but in the end it was considered unsuitable for him; see
                        Southey to Walter Scott, 8 August 1809 (Letter 1666) and Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 12 August 1809 (Letter
                        1669).</note> It is a situation which would give me a respectable income, perfectly suit my present <del>situation</del> place
                    of abode, &amp; not impose upon me more business than I could properly perform with comfort to myself. <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sharp</ref> tells me this, &amp; from him I learn that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Long<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Untraced.</note> is one of the Directors. Could this be
                    obtained for me I should be well provided for – &amp; in a pleasant way, – so I have thought it right to mention it, in
                    consequence of your last letter, &amp; having so done shall dismiss the subject from my thoughts. <hi rend="ital">Pelle timorem,
                        spem que fugato</hi>, is a lesson which I learnt early in life from Boethius,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A
                        paraphrase of part of a passage from Anicius Manlius Severinus Boethius (c. 475–525), <title>De Consolatione
                            Philosophiæ</title>. The complete passage reads: ‘Tu quoque, si vis/ Lumine claro/ Cernere rectum,/ Gaudia pelle/ Pelle
                        timorem/ Spemque fugato/ nec dolor adsit’ and translates as ‘If you desire/ To look on truth/ And follow the path/ With
                        unswerving course,/ Rid yourself/ Of joy and fear,/ Put hope to flight,/ And banish grief’, Boethius, <title>The Consolation
                            of Philosophy</title>, trans. Victor Watts (Harmondsworth, 1969; rev. edn 1999), p. 21.</note> &amp; have been a good deal
                    the happier for practising.</p><p rend="indent1"> The second Quarterly is better than the first. The affairs of Austria are treated with great power, great spirit
                    &amp; clear views.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref>, <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">George Canning</ref>, and <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">William
                            Gifford</ref> (possibly with the German statesman Friedrich von Gentz (1764–1832)) reviewed <title>Proclamation of the
                            Archduke Charles to his Army; Declaration of War by the Emperor of Austria; Address of the Archduke to the German
                            Nation</title> (1809) in the <title>Quarterly Review</title> 1 (May 1809), 437–455.</note> I expected the utter overthrow
                    of the house of Austria, &amp; my fears have happily been disappointed – they have profited by experience, &amp; tho every thing
                    is now upon the balance, &amp; one cannot open the newspaper without great anxiety &amp; many doubts, still it does appear that
                    the chances are in our favour. One defeat will not destroy the Emperor if he is only true to himself, but one defeat would destroy
                    Bonaparte. His authority out of France is maintained wholly by force; in France wholly by the opinion of his good fortune &amp;
                    the splendour of his successes. One thorough defeat will dissolve the spell. – His colossal power then falls to pieces like the
                    image in Nebuchadnezzars dream.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See <title>Daniel</title>, 2.</note> I am afraid our
                    expedition will be too late to turn the scale.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Walcheren expedition was an
                        unsuccessful British attempt to open another front in the Netherlands in support of the Austrian Empire’s struggle with
                        France. Approximately 40,000 soldiers with supporting horses and artillery landed at Walcheren on 30 July 1809. There was
                        little fighting but the army sustained heavy losses from sickness, and in December 1809 the rest of the force withdrew.</note>
                    If it were now in Germany it might do wonders – but we are always slow in our measures, &amp; <del>xxxx</del> game so timorously
                    that we are sure to lose. Why not twice forty thousand men? – It has been proved that we can always beat the French with equal
                    numbers, or at any time when we are not grievously out-numbered. Why then send <del>ou</del> a force that can so easily be
                        <del>outnumbered</del> &lt;doubled or trebled by the enemy? –&gt; – for allied armies cannot act together, &amp; whatever
                    battles we have to fight must be fought alone. Marlborough<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Churchill, 1st Duke of
                        Marlborough (1650–1722; <title>DNB</title>), victor of the battle of Blenheim in which British troops fought alongside troops
                        from Austria, the Dutch Republic, Denmark, and Brandenburg-Prussia.</note> was the only General who could ever wield a
                    confederacy.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have made offer of my services to <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> to undertake <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Freres</ref><del>Defence</del> justification against the friends of Sir John Moore, if
                    it be thought advisable.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The diplomatist John Hookham Frere was sent to Spain as
                        minister-plenipotentiary to the Central Junta on 4 October 1808 and when the French marched on Madrid he urged Sir John Moore
                        (1761–1809; <title>DNB</title>), the Commander of the British forces in northern Spain, also to advance upon Madrid, despite
                        his inclination to retreat through Portugal. After the disastrous British retreat to Corunna, Frere was blamed for this advice
                        and recalled by the government.</note> I have offered also to provide for the fourth Number a paper upon Methodism which would
                    be in all things unlike Sidney Smiths, except in having as much dread of its progress.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Sydney Smith (1771–1845; <title>DNB</title>), one of the founders of, and leading contributors to, the <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>. who reviewed John Styles (1782–1849), <title>Strictures on Two Critiques in the Edinburgh Review on the
                            Subject of Methodism and Missions</title> (1809), <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 27 (April 1809), 40–50. Southey
                        responded in his review of [James Sedgwick (1775–1851; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Hints to the Public and the Legislature,
                            on the Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title> (1809), in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>,
                        4 (November 1810), 480–514.</note> I should examine the causes of its progress, the principles in human nature to which it
                    appeals, &amp; by which it succeeds, its good &amp; its evil, the means of preventing the one, &amp; of obtaining the other at
                    less risqué, &amp; instead of offending the whole religious public, as they call themselves, by indiscriminate ridicule I should
                    endeavour to show of what different parties that public is composed, how some of them may be conciliated &amp; made useful, &amp;
                    others suppressed, for there are limits which common sense must appoint to toleration.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have finished an English Eclogue which is at <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref> service
                    either for his Annual Register or his Minstrelsey, &amp; which shall be transcribed &amp; sent him forthwith.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s poem ‘The Alderman’s Funeral, an English Eclogue’ was not included in <title>English
                            Minstrelsy. Being a Selection of Fugitive Poetry from the Best English Authors; with some Original Pieces Hitherto
                            Unpublished</title> (1810), but it was published in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.2 (1810)
                        along with Southey’s other poems, ‘King Ramiro’ and ‘Queen Orraca’ (i-xiii). Both these works were published by
                        Ballantyne.</note> I have never yet thanked you for Lord Somers, – a very acceptable addition to my Library, – a very valuable
                    collection, &amp; made far more so by your arrangement &amp; additions.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1809 <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> published the first volume of Baron John Somers (1651–1716;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Collection of Scarce and Valuable Tracts on the Most Interesting and Entertaining Subjects
                            But Chiefly Such as Relate to the History and Constitution of These Kingdoms, Selected from an Infinite Number in Print
                            and Manuscript in the Royal Libraries</title> (1809–1815). Southey owned 12 volumes of this work by Scott, published
                        between 1809 and 1815, no. 2613 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> I am sorry my life of D Luisa de
                    Carvajal is printed,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luisa de Carvajal y Mendoza (1568–1614), was a Spanish missionary
                        who devoted herself to the cause of the Catholic faith in England during the reign of James VI and I (1566–1625, King of
                        Scotland, England, and Ireland 1603–1625; <title>DNB</title>). An account of her life was written by Luis Muñoz (d.1646) as
                            <title>La Vida Y Virtues de la Venerable Virgin Dona Luisa de Carvajal y Mendoza</title> in 1632, and was summarised by
                        Southey in the third edition of his <title>Letters from Spain and Portugal</title> (1808). Southey contributed a ‘Memoir of D.
                        Luisa de Carvajal’ to the<title> Athenæum: a Magazine of Literary and Miscellaneous Information</title>, 1 (April/May 1807),
                        270–277, 391–399, 495–500.</note> or I would have offered it you, as worthy of being inserted among the Tracts of James 1<hi rend="sup">sts</hi> time.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> James I (1566–1625; <title>DNB</title>), King of Scotland
                        (as James VI) from 1567, and from 1603 to 1625 King of England and Ireland.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S</ref>. joins me in remembrances to <ref target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Scott</ref> –</salute><salute rend="indent2"> believe me</salute><salute rend="indent3"> yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1809-07-06">July 6. 1809.</date></p><p rend="indent1">I do not know the value of the Stewardship, but if it be thought in <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Mr
                            Fox’s</ref> phrase ‘too good a thing for me’<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Southey’s letter to Walter Scott,
                            dated 16 June 1809 (Letter 1645), he recounts his attempt to get a diplomatic position in Portugal through Charles James
                            Fox who was Foreign Secretary in the ‘Ministry of all the Talents’ before his death in 1806, reporting that Fox considered
                            the ‘Consulship’ to be ‘too good a thing for me’.</note> it might be seperated from the Northumberland estates.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>