<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1185</idno><idno type="nines">rce2307</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of
                        Wales MS 4812D.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1185" type="letter"><head>1185. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1806-05-21">21
                        May [1806]</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.
                        P./ Whitehall/ London/ private<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: [partial] FREE/ MAY/ 1806<lb/>MS: National Library of
                        Wales MS 4812D<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> The papers say nothing about Portugal. – their alarms come and go like ague fits, &amp; this is one of the
                    intervals. But <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> seems to think that some mischief is going on – my
                    opinion, he says, is that we shall not have any Envoy Consul or Chaplain here many months longer. I am much of the same opinion,
                    but if the question were put out of doubt, it would relieve me from a not very comfortable state of indecision. A little time will
                    show: if the country be not seized in revenge for Mirandas <del>exped</del> strange expedition,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1806 the South American revolutionary Sebastián Francisco de Miranda Ravelo y Rodríguez de Espinoza
                        (1750–1816), who had been resident in London and had received unofficial encouragement from ministers, launched a private
                        expedition aimed at liberating Venezuela from Spanish colonial rule. Since Spain was an ally of France, this action risked
                        provoking Napoleon to seize, in retaliation, Britain’s ally Portugal.</note> or to try the system of shutting the ports
                    against us <del>xx</del> on a great scale, which if done must be done soon.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Napoleon
                        introduced this measure, ‘the Continental System’, in November.</note> Then I shall feel persuaded that the same causes which
                    have thus long <del>xxx</del> operated to prevent the seizure of Portugal, will continue so to do. </p><p rend="indent1"> I perceive in one of Cobbetts numbers an assertion that the duties on the importation of books for private use –
                    &amp; not for sale – have sometimes been remitted, on application; &amp; that this was done in his case, tho he did not avail
                    himself of it, having previously paid the money, &amp; finding it too much trouble to get it back.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Weekly Political Register</title> compiled and published by William Cobbett (1763–1835;
                            <title>DNB</title>) from 1802–1835.</note> Now in case <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> should be
                    obliged to send his books home, I shall certainly endeavour to discover thro what channel this application must be made.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am working as hard as this fine weather will let me, for there is a perpetual temptation to be in the open air,
                    at D Manuel first, running a race as usual with the printer; &amp; secondly at the Chronicle of the Cid – so I design to call
                        it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella; Translated
                            from the Spanish</title>, published in 1807; the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title>, published in 1808.</note> You will I
                    think be much pleased with this. I give the whole story at full in Chronicle language, with all its fabulous ornaments, compiled
                    from the original Chronicle, the metrical romances &lt;or history&gt; which was probably the foundation of that, the Ballads,
                    &amp; all the other histories which I can command, &amp; which are not few in number. The respective authorities will be stated
                    step by step, &amp; appreciated in the notes, wherein also I shall point out, as far as possible, what is true, &amp; what
                    fictitious, where that needs to be done: insert the more curious passages from the different poems, &amp; be as learned &amp; as
                    amusing as I can. The whole will give a striking picture of what may be called the heroic age of Spain, &amp; thus shall I dispose of much matter collected for any historical
                    preliminaries, but for which there will be there no room. It is not unlikely that while thus employed I may yield unto temptation
                    &amp; make more ballads after the manner of Queen Orraca<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Queen Urraia and the Five
                        Martyrs of Morocco’, published in in the <title>Morning Post</title> in early September 1803, in the <title>Iris</title>, 3
                        November 1804, also in <title>English Minstrelsy. Being a Selection of Fugitive Poetry from the Best English Authors; with
                            some Original Pieces hitherto unpublished</title>, 2 vols (Edinburgh, 1810), in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1808</title> (Edinburgh, 1810), in <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and <title>Poetical Works</title>
                        (1837–1838). See <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793–1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt (London, 2004), V, pp.
                        406–413.</note> &amp; Garci Ferrandez,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Garci Ferrandez’, was published in the
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title> (1811), in <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and
                            <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837–1838). See <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793–1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda
                        Pratt (London, 2004), V, pp. xxiv and 517.</note> so as to fill a little volume with Tales &amp; Poems founded upon the
                    Spanish &amp; Portuguese history. It will be hard if I cannot get as much for writing upon subjects which interest me as for
                    reviewing; I shall try the experiment, but am not sanguine as to its success.</p><p rend="indent1"> Let me know whether <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has sent you the Joan of Arc.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The third edition of <title>Joan of Arc</title>, printed by <ref target="people.html#BiggsNathaniel">Nathaniel Biggs</ref> in Bristol, was published in 1806, with some alterations. It
                    included the ‘Vision of the Maid of Orleans’, originally published in the second volume of <title>Poems</title> (1799), at the
                        end of the poem. For the alterations, see <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793–1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5
                        vols (London, 2004), I.</note> The first edition of the Poems I found &amp; sent you from <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref>.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Poems</title> (1797).</note> The small set will soon form so respectable a length upon the shelf that you should have
                    them all; they are now eleven in number, &amp; the Spaniards, the small edition of Madoc, the edition of Kehama &amp; the Cid –
                    all of which will be added within the next twelvemonths will make them twenty.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second
                        edition of <title>Madoc</title> (1805) was published in 1807; the <title>Curse of Kehama</title> was published in 1810.</note>
                    If I live long enough I shall outvolume Voltaire.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> François-Marie Arouet, ‘Voltaire’
                        (1694–1778), wrote more than 2000 books and pamphlets.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1806-05-21">May 21. Wednesday.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>