<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.977</idno><idno type="nines">rce2099</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="977" type="letter"><head>977. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1804-08-25">25 August 1804</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster/ Single <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb/>Postmark: E/ AUG28/
                        1804<lb/>Endorsements: 25 August 1804; Friday morn at 6/ Saturday D<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 4/ up all Sun<hi rend="sup">y</hi>
                        night/ Monday morn<hi rend="sup">g</hi> 4½/ Monday night 12/ Wednesday morn<hi rend="sup">g</hi> 4½/ Thursday morn 5<lb/>MS:
                        Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute>Dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Such another semi-letter as yours which arrived this evening has been lying some time in my desk unanswered – for
                    what with supplying <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">a Scotch printer</ref>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        James Ballantyne, whose printing house printed Southey’s <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> attending on Lakers, nursing <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my little girl</ref>, writing history, correcting my poem,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s ‘History of Portugal’ was never completed. He was correcting proofs of <title>Madoc</title> even while still revising the sections of the manuscript
                        not yet sent to the printer.</note> &amp; occasionally getting out for exercise I never felt myself so little at leisure. But
                    in that first letter you say you wish me to write to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> – now long before
                    that letter of yours could have been indited I had written – indeed written a fortnight or three weeks after my return, chiefly to
                    the purport of persuading him to visit <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. the letter required no answer &amp;
                    received none.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> This letter has not survived.</note> perhaps he was disappointed at
                    perceiving how resolutely I avoided those idle &amp; worthless speculations to which he seems to have abandoned himself. I only
                    refer to it to let you see that there was no neglect on my part. his company would have been pleasant to me, – that mine would
                    have been useful to him I see little reason to believe.</p><p rend="indent1"> Now to the second letter &amp; to business.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey proceeds to discuss the
                        anthology of minor verse on which he and Bedford were engaged. It was published by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807 as <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>.</note> I
                    design to prefix some preface – precious tautology – that is, to write a sketch of the history of our poetry from the Restoration,
                    its <del>progression</del> decline &amp; corruption, to what length this will extend above six or eight pages must depend upon the
                    humour in which it is undertaken, my then state of leisure, &amp; whether it trickles from heart to head &amp; thence to the
                    fingers &amp; thence dribbles onto the paper daintily, or not. But there will be nothing intermediate more than those scraps of
                    notices. – As soon as you have enough for three or four sheets <hi rend="ital">put to press</hi> the haunting of a Printers Devil
                    will be an excellent stimulus. needs must go when he drives. but seriously begin as soon as you can for – for even if you should
                    be obliged sometimes to stop the press, it will be an advantage to clear off as you go on &amp; the desiderated are not so many as
                    to occasion any material delay – especially if you apply to <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref>. the Devil must be
                    in the poor author who is not be found either with him, Isaac Reid<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac Reed (1742–1807):
                        a conveyancer, editor and literary historian, author of <title>Biographia Dramatica, or, a Companion to the Playhouse</title>
                        (1782) and editor of Shakespeare’s plays. The fifth edition of his <title>Plays of William Shakespeare</title> was published
                        in 1803.</note> or <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Hill</ref>. their collections are perfect hospitals. </p><p rend="indent1"> I am mistaken if you do not feel more interest than you expect when you look at our lucubrations in printers ink
                    instead of the best Japan<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Japan ink, like Indian ink, made from lampblack and used with a
                        quill pen.</note> or Record,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A kind of ink sufficiently durable to be used for
                        record-keeping.</note> which wants the unction of the typographical. You need no directions, only in your brief prolegomenas
                    round your sentences, or point them if there be little information to communicate &amp; never let slip a joke if it lies in your
                    way. People like to be amused, &amp; where the poetry be dull we ought to make the prose its antidote, &amp; be sure none of the
                    specimens be the same as <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis</ref><note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Ellis,
                            <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790, 2nd edn 1801, 3rd edn 1803), the anthology on which Southey’s
                        own was modelled.</note> has given of those few authors whom we also are obliged to introduce. by the by I should be glad if
                    you could send me my copy of <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">Ellis</ref> from <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> by <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Now good Grosvenor or <hi rend="ital">bone Bedford</hi> which means the same thing or has the same alliterative
                    excellence, – do set soon to work. when your shoulders are to it it is nothing. remember what we got thus at <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Hills</ref>. Get Isaac Reid to fill up the list to the best of his recollection, &amp;
                    never mind if two or three or half a score ragamuffins be omitted now – let them wait for the second edition, to make such a work
                    perfect at once is impossible. London printers make quick work. It may be ready during the winter with no exertion, with great
                    ease during the spring.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am <hi rend="ital">neger</hi>-ring<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, slaving.</note> at Madoc –
                    you will like the story of the Great Serpent &amp; the way in which he is killed.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        snake god features in <title>Madoc</title>, Part 2, books 6 and 7.</note> &amp; I must neger at my history. for go abroad I
                    will in the autumn of next year if possible. this <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Scotch printer</ref> does his work
                    most excellently for accuracy &amp; beauty. It will be ready for Xmas.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> is coming next week. my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is here – a very promising young man. I am going to set up a Jack Ass for <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>. &amp; there is all the news. unless I spoke ill of my Kidneys. Was I born under Aquarius or Orion? &amp; are the
                    stories of nymphs converted into rivers only allegories of diabetes. diabetes quase diaboletes.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning ‘diabetes as if devils’.</note> a devilish bad pun upon a devilish bad thing –</p><p rend="indent1"> God bless you. I would fill the sheet if I could save the post.</p><p rend="indent1">Write – if but to tell me how your mother is – </p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RSouthey.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1804-08-25">Aug. 25. 1804.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>