<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1692</idno><idno type="nines">rce2814</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text is taken from William Knight (ed.), Memorials of
                            Coleorton, 2 vols (London, 1887).  Previously  published: William Knight (ed.), Memorials of Coleorton:
                            Being letters from Coleridge, Wordsworth and his sister, Southey, and Sir Walter Scott to Sir George and Lady Beaumont of
                            Coleorton, Leicestershire, 1803 to 1834, 2 vols (London, 1887), II, pp. 78–81.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1692" type="letter"><head>1692. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont</ref>, <date when="1809-10-12">12
                        October 1809</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from William Knight (ed.), <title>Memorials of
                            Coleorton</title>, 2 vols (London, 1887)<lb/>Previously published: William Knight (ed.), <title>Memorials of Coleorton:
                            Being letters from Coleridge, Wordsworth and his sister, Southey, and Sir Walter Scott to Sir George and Lady Beaumont of
                            Coleorton, Leicestershire, 1803 to 1834</title>, 2 vols (London, 1887), II, pp. 78–81.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1809-10-12">Oct. 12, 1809</date></dateline><salute>My Dear Sir, </salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Having gone thus far through life – not indeed without receiving kind offices, but without ever having solicited
                    them, – it requires some effort to expose myself to the hazard of being thought obtrusive by you, for a second application. I have
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">a brother</ref>  in the Navy, and it has been advised me by <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Williams Wynn</ref> (who in all things concerning my welfare has long been my privy
                    counsellor) to make application in his behalf, and get him, if possible, in the list of post-captains, he having been ten years a
                    lieutenant. Wynn wished me to avail myself of <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Mr. Canning’s</ref> expressed good-will to this
                    effect; but it appears to me from what passed respecting the Derwentwater stewardship<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        In July 1809, Southey was informed by <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Richard Sharp</ref> that the stewardship of the
                        Derwentwater Estates (which were owned by Greenwich Hospital) would soon become vacant on the death of the incumbent. Southey
                        asked several friends to intercede on his behalf, including <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George
                            Beaumont</ref>, but in the end it was considered unsuitable for him; see Southey to Walter Scott, 8 August 1809 (Letter
                        1666) and Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 12 August 1809 (Letter 1669).</note> that Mr. C. has little influence at the
                    Admiralty, and indeed were it otherwise, and I a bolder asker than I have yet learned to be, this would not be a time to trouble
                    him with my concerns. It is said that Lord Mulgrave<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Phipps, 1st Earl of Mulgrave
                        (1755–1831; <title>DNB</title>): First Lord of the Admiralty from 1807, diplomatist and politician.</note> intends soon to
                    make a large promotion of admirals, and this is the circumstance which made Wynn exhort me immediately to make application. What I
                    have further to state will, I hope, justify me for applying to you, and requesting your influence in a matter which interests me
                    so nearly.</p><p rend="indent1"> My brother is at present first lieutenant of Admiral Sotheby’s ship.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Thomas Southey was serving on HMS <hi rend="ital">Dreadnought</hi>, a 98-gun second rate ship of the line launched in 1801.
                        She had fought at the battle of Trafalgar (1805) and was now under the command of Rear Admiral Thomas Sotheby (1759–1831),
                        younger brother of the author, William Sotheby (1757–1833; <title>DNB</title>), who was Southey’s acquaintance.</note> His
                    lieutenancy he earned by his services, having distinguished himself in the action between the Mars and L’Hercule, an important
                    action upon the whole for him, because Captain Hood, who was his friend, was killed in it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The battle in 1798 between HMS <hi rend="ital">Mars</hi> (a 74-gun third-rate ship of the line) against the French
                        seventy-four gun <hi rend="ital">Hercule</hi> ended in the French ship’s surrender, it having lost over three hundred men. On
                            <hi rend="ital">Mars</hi> 31 men were killed and 60 wounded, including the captain, Alexander Hood (1758–1798), who died
                        of a wound to the thigh, on 2 April 1798.</note> Twice he has been disappointed of promotion when he had every prospect of it,
                    first by the recall of Sir Samuel Hood<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Commodore (later Vice-Admiral) Sir Samuel Hood,
                        1st Baronet (1762–1814; <title>DNB</title>).</note> from the West Indies, afterwards by the displacement of <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Mr. Grenville</ref>. There is now no chance of getting forward in the course of
                    service; all opposition upon the sea is at an end. Nothing is to be done except by personal interest.</p><p rend="indent1"> Admiral Sotheby’s ship is likely to go into dock, and in that case will be paid off. My brother’s situation cannot
                    be altered for the better in his present rank, and it unfortunately happens that the longer a man remains in that rank, the worse
                    does his situation become, for this reason, that most captains have their own first lieutenants, and as there are few ships in
                    which one of ten years’ standing would not take that place by seniority, old lieutenants are usually disposed of in gun-brigs and
                    small craft, the least reputable and the most uncomfortable part of the Navy. There is one circumstance which renders me
                    peculiarly anxious to obtain promotion for him. We have <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">an uncle</ref>, a
                    wealthy man, possessing property, which in the common course of inheritance would have devolved upon us instead of him, as
                    children of an elder brother. He is a man of that sort of disposition that the less his relations wanted his estates, the more he
                    would be disposed to bequeath them as he ought to do. If Tom were Captain Southey he would in all probability be appointed his
                    heir; if he remains what he is, the whole, there is every reason to believe, will be left to strangers. I have little doubt that a
                    captain commission would secure to my brother an estate of a thousand a year. I could mention another circumstance more important
                    to his happiness, and little less so to his welfare, to which the want of professional rank, and the prospect which it opens, is
                    the obstacle; and this consideration it is which induces me, reluctant as I am, once more to solicit your good offices with Lord
                    Mulgrave.</p><p rend="indent1"> I do not wish to have him employed, confident as I should be that if he were on the Spanish coast he would
                    eminently distinguish himself. To promote him and send him ashore would be conferring upon me the highest obligation. Family ties
                    grow stronger as we advance in life, and they become fewer in number. There are few persons who are so rich in friends as I am.
                    But among them all there is not one who loves me so dearly and entirely as he does. Nor is there that possible circumstance which
                    would contribute so greatly to my happiness as to have him settled here beside the Lake.</p><p rend="indent1"> I know not, Sir George, in what manner to apologise for an application which I am so little entitled to make. Yet I
                    should have reproached myself had I not made it. The motive must plead for me, and I will rely upon your goodness to excuse me, if
                    it should not be in your power to do more. – Your health, I hope, is better than it was. Present my respects to <ref target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMary">Lady Beaumont</ref>, and believe me, yours respectfully, and very thankfully for your
                    late interference,</p><closer><signed rend="right">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>