<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Contingent Romanticism --></title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume</title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">"Writing Romanticism at the End of the world: Love and Loneliness in Mary Shelley's <hi rend="italic">The Last Man</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Matilda</hi>"</title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Chris Washington</name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor">Padma Rangarajan</editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Paul Youngquist</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor</resp>
                    <name>Orrin N. C. Wang</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Electronic Editions Editor</resp>
                    <name>Michelle Speitz</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- TJ AND JESSICA CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Paul Youngquist</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>paul.youngquist@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE PAUL'S NAMING CONVENTIONS IN THE "toc_file_names_for_links" DOC THAT IS LINKED TO THE SLACK CHANNEL-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2023.contingent.washington</idno> <!-- use the file name above as a reference, but do not include .xml -->
                <idno type="resource">contingent</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">"Writing Romanticism at the End of the World: Love and Loneliness in Mary Shelley's <hi rend="italic">The Last Man</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mathilda</hi>"
                        </title>
                        <!-- ONLY CHANGE THE FINAL PART OF THE <IDNO> TAG. REFERENCE THE NAMING DOC -->
                        <ptr target="praxis/contingent.2024.psychosis.washington"/>
                    </analytic>
                  
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Psychosis</title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- JESS AND TJ CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags">imperialism</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">selfhod</term>
                    <term subtype="tags">the novel</term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Add Editor Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>January 31, 2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p>This essay reflects, via sorities, on what it means to write Romanticism during a pandemic in relation 
                    to the alienation and loneliness that lastness is in Mary Shelley’s <hi rend="italic">The Last Man</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mathilda</hi> and the 
                    recuperative power of ghostly love in her “On Ghosts.” Romanticism is always writing at and about the 
                    end of the world. Shelley wants, in time . . . changes over time at the end of the world. </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>     
            <div type="essay">
                <quote>"If I am destined to be happy with you here, how short is the longest life. 
                    John Keats to Fanny Brawne"</quote>
                <quote> Deh, vienti ti aspetto </quote>
                
                <p>It is a truth universally acknowledged that being a scholar is a lonely, solitary pursuit and profession, full of long days reading in the silent 
                    communion (one hopes) with oneself, perhaps with the companionship of some books in want of 
                    a critical analysis, or perhaps secluded in library rare books rooms, or chasing down some half-forgotten 
                    (or is it half-remembered) quote - or, just as often, sequestered in a room of one's own at home 
                    chasing that flighty, fluttering, friable, flying thing we call writing. Of course, while this, 
                    shall we say, romanticized description glints with truth, scholars also know this "self-evident" truth
                    to be largely self-evident rubbish even as the briefest of glances, at, say, any monograph's acknowledgements movingly testifies
                    top the it-takes-a-village ethos of all scholarly writing endeavors. In fact, in my first book, <hi rend="italic">Romantic Revelations</hi>
                    about the post-apocalyptic visions Romanticism conjures up in a reaction to fears about the changing climate writers of the period 
                    witnessed as a result of 1816's year without a summer, found a dense colloquy of fellows in its converse with not only the voices long 
                    past of the period but with scholars writing in what we might with some honesty call the dread despair 
                    of here and now. </p>
                <p> For what once was in 1816, in terms of climate change disasters and global pandemics, seems to now be again (if it ever were not)
                    and Romantic writing, creative and critical, from then to now, continues to tarry with horrific visions and realities about both 
                    the end of the world and the end of the human species. In some ways, Mary Shelley's pandemic novel, 
                    <hi rend="italic">The Last Man</hi> (1826), prefigures, or, if you like, prophesies, the moment we are living through with the COVID-19
                    virus and the disaster of climate change evidenced in, to choose but one example, the mass wild fires in California, Oregon, and Washington
                    in the summer of 2020 that made the sun appear dim red, like in John Martin's <hi rend="italic">The Last Man</hi> (1849)
                    painting, surrounded by a burnt orange coronal sky. Isolated in our homes for months, we 
                    might all even begin to sympathize with Lionel at novel's end who, alone and at the species' 
                    amort, with vague prospects of finding a companion, takes it upon himself to write down the events 
                    of the plague that wiped out, mostly, the human species with the exception, of course, of Lionel himself who sets sail at novel's end into the 
                    ocean's vast unknown. He sets sail all alone aside from some books, a dog, and a companionate loneliness
                    that compels him to seek out others, to fly forth into a world seemingly well lost to the pandemic's decimating destruction. 
                </p>
                <p>It is in this theorization of lastness that, I want to argue, Romantic writing of the sort we see in the novel indexes this
                ontological, singular, accommpanying loneliness as life itself. <note place="foot">See also Khalip's <hi rend="italic">Last Things,</hi> where he characterizes 
                Romanticism as "already extinct," which, for him, generates its productive fecundity and generativity (12).</note>
                The  dilemma of last-person-ness is the dilemma of both epistemological and ontological uncerntainty, an uncertainty that stems from what it 
                would mean to know you are the last person. How could one be so sure? One would need to be omnipotent, 
                omniscent, and omnipresent, which would mean one were not terrestrial at all, but a god of some variation.
                <note place="foot">I develop this point at greater length here: Washington, 69-76. See also Peter Melville, 144.</note>
                Concurrently, since a condition of being alive is that one may become the last person, then being human contains within it the condition
                that we are all already extinct. If this were not so, then we would be sempiternal. 
                In other words, lastness, the condition of lastness, means we are all already the last man, the last woman, the last generfluid, or last non-binary person. <note place="foot">Emily Steinlight writes of Verney that "as soon as he is last, he is no longer man" because 
                to be a human man requires a fellow species (71). While I agree with this estimation, at the same time, to be human always 
                previously contains the possibility of lastness so, in a sense, we have all already "become" last. Nonetheless, Steinlight's 
                argument comports with the idea that Lionel may, in fact, not be a man, but rather, as Johnson's and Fisch's works variously
                suggests, that Lionel is the last woman. On the other hand, Lionel says that as soon as he begins writing his narrative, 
                he becomes an Adam: "suddenly I became as it were the father of all mankind (#) Or, as Melville
                put it still differently, the question for Lionel is "how to announce the end of 
                man, when he himself is still a man (144). Andrew Sargent, meanwhile, trends somewhere
                else entirely, that a sort of human life will remain, however unrecognizable: "aand though the no futures of this 'now' may still 
                include something akin to 'us,' it might only be as fossils or ghosts (323). Sargent's powerful
                sense of ghosts here registers a bit differently than my reading of Shelley's ghosts below.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
    

