<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Title</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <p>Digital Publisher</p>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="paratext">
                <head>Places</head>
                <p>This page gives further information about the key places that Southey lived in,
                    visited or was connected to during the period 1798-1803. </p>
                <lb/>
                <list type="simple">
                    <item n="1">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="BalliolOxford">Balliol:</term>
                        <gloss target="#BalliolOxford"> Southey was a student at Balliol College, Oxford in 1792-1794,
                            though he left without taking a degree.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="2">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="BridgeSt">25 Bridge St, Westminster:</term>
                        <gloss target="#BridgeSt"> the London residence of Southey and his family from c. November
                            1801- late January 1802. His mother died there on 5 January
                            1802.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="3">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Brixton">Brixton, a village just outside London:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Brixton"> the country home of the Bedford family, Southey spent several weeks
                            there in September–October 1793, during which time he wrote the first
                            draft of Joan of Arc.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="4">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Burton">Burton:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Burton"> village in Hampshire, where Southey stayed in June–September 1797.
                            He returned in October–November 1799 and rented a house found for him by
                            his friend, Charles Biddlecombe.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="5">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="ChristChurch">Christ Church:</term>
                        <gloss target="#ChristChurch"> town, just along the coast from Burton, Hampshire. Southey stayed
                            there briefly in June 1797 and again in October 1799, while supervising
                            renovations to the house he was renting at Burton.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="6">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Cintra">Cintra [Sintra]:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Cintra"> town in Portugal, where Southey’s uncle, Herbert Hill, kept a summer
                            home. Southey visited the house in June–October 1800, calling it ‘a spot
                            the most delightful I have ever yet known’.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="7">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="CollegeGreenBristol">College Green, Bristol:</term>
                        <gloss target="#CollegeGreenBristol"> the home of Southey’s aunt, Elizabeth Tyler. He spent several years
                            of his childhood living there and often returned in 1792-4. In October
                            1794 Miss Tyler threw Southey out of the house when she learned of his
                            relationship with Edith Fricker and involvement in Pantisocracy.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="8">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Congreve">Congreve, Staffordshire:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Congreve"> the home of Mary Barker. Southey and his wife stopped there on their
                            way to Keswick in August 1803, a journey precipitated by the death of
                            their only child Margaret.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="9">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Cottles">Cottles:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Cottles"> Joseph Cottle’s bookshop in Bristol. This was at 48 High St from
                            April 1791 to March 1798. Cottle then moved to 5 Wine St until financial
                            troubles forced him to close his business in July 1799.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="10">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Crickhowel">Crickhowel:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Crickhowel"> small town in Powys. Southey visited it in October 1798 on his
                            walking tour of South Wales with Charles Danvers.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="11">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="DanversKingsdown">Danvers’s, Kingsdown, Bristol:</term>
                        <gloss target="#DanversKingsdown"> the home of Southey’s old friend Charles Danvers and his mother.
                            Used by Southey as postal address on his return to Bristol from Portugal
                            in 1801.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="12">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Dublin">Dublin:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Dublin"> Southey visited the Irish capital for about 10 days in October 1801
                            at the beginning of his employment as secretary to Isaac Corry.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="13">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="DukeSt">Duke St, London:</term>
                        <gloss target="#DukeSt"> the city home of Isaac Corry, Southey’s employer in
                            1801–1802.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="14">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="GraysInn">Gray’s Inn:</term>
                        <gloss target="#GraysInn"> Southey was seeking to qualify as a barrister between 1797 and 1801.
                            This required him to register at one of the Inns of Court and
                            occasionally attend formal dinners there. Southey chose Grays Inn, at
                            the intersection of High Holborn and Grays Inn Road.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="15">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="GretaHall">Greta Hall/ Greeta Hall:</term>
                        <gloss target="#GretaHall"> House on the outskirts of Keswick. From 1800, the home of Samuel
                            Taylor Coleridge and his family. Southey and his wife visited in August
                            1801 and made it their permanent residence from September 1803.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="16">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Keswick">Keswick:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Keswick"> market town in the Lake District. From 1800, the home of Samuel
                            Taylor Coleridge and his family. Southey and his wife visited in August
                            1801 and made it their permanent residence from September 1803.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="17">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="KingsdownParade">Kingsdown Parade, Bristol:</term>
                        <gloss target="KingsdownParade"> Southey lived there December 1799–February 1800, close to Charles
                            Danvers.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="18">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="LambsConduitSt">12 Lambs Conduit Street:</term>
                        <gloss target="#LambsConduitSt"> Southey’s lodgings in London, December 1797–February 1798.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="19">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Lanthony">Lanthony:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Lanthony"> ruined priory in Powys. Southey visited it in October 1798 on his
                            walking tour of South Wales with Charles Danvers. The estate was later
                            owned by Walter Savage Landor.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="20">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="MaesGywn">Maes Gywn, Neath:</term>
                        <gloss target="#MaesGywn"> house in the Vale of Neath, near Swansea, that Southey attempted –
                            but failed – to rent in autumn 1802.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="21">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="MartinHall">Martin Hall:</term>
                        <gloss target="#MartinHall"> Southey’s name for the house in Westbury, near Bristol, which he
                            rented June 1798–June 1799.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="22">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="MerthyrTidvil">Merthyr Tidvil:</term>
                        <gloss target="#MerthyrTidvil"> home of George Maber, who was the local Rector. Southey visited him
                            on October 1798 on his walking tour of South Wales with Charles
                            Danvers.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="23">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Norwich">Norwich:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Norwich"> Southey visited William Taylor at his home at Surry St in Norwich
                            May-June 1798.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="24">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="StJamesPlace">12 St James’s Place, Kingsdown, Bristol:</term>
                        <gloss target="#StJamesPlace"> the house, near to Charles Danvers, rented by Southey and his wife
                            from May 1802–August 1803. Their first child, Margaret, was born and
                            died there. Her death prompted them to leave Bristol for good. In future
                            years, Southey only returned on occasional visits.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="25">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="StokesCroft">Stokes Croft:</term>
                        <gloss target="#StokesCroft"> area of Bristol, north of the city centre. Southey briefly lived
                            there March–April 1800.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="26">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Stowey">Stowey:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Stowey"> the village of Nether Stowey in Somerset. Home of Tom Poole, who
                            found a cottage there for the Coleridge family between 1797 and 1799.
                            Southey visited in August 1799, after his reconciliation with
                            Coleridge.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="27">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Strand">35 Strand, London:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Strand"> the home of Southey and his family from Southey from late January
                            until late May 1802.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="28">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Westbury">Westbury:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Westbury"> village just outside Bristol, Southey rented a cottage, which he
                            named Martin-Hall, between June 1798 and June 1799.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="29">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="WestgateBuildings">8 Westgate Buildings, Bath:</term>
                        <gloss target="#WestgateBuildings"> the boarding house run by Margaret Southey from 1793 to
                            1798.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="30">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Wynnstay">Wynnstay, near Ruabon, Denbighshire:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Wynnstay"> the home of the Wynn family.</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item n="31">
                        <term rend="bold" xml:id="Yarmouth">Yarmouth:</term>
                        <gloss target="#Yarmouth"> town on the Norfolk coast; Southey visited his brother Henry Herbert
                            Southey, who was studying with George Burnett, there in late May
                            1798.</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
