<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3034</idno><idno type="nines">rce4305</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3034. Robert Southey to Wade Browne, 4 November
                  1817</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3034.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>British Library, Add MS 47891. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the
                     Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 72–74.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3034" type="letter"><head>3034. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BrowneWade">Wade Browne</ref>, <date when="1817-11-04">4 November
                  1817</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To Wade Browne Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Ludlow<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb/> MS: British Library, Add MS 47891. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the
                     Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 72–74.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1817-11-04"> 4 Nov. 1817.</date></dateline><salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> After a long journey, &amp; a succession of company since my return, I am at last quietly settled to my winters work,
               with the probability of as few interruptions from without, as Bruin has when he rolls himself up in his cave, &amp; trusts to his paws
               till the spring. You probably heard of my travels. My companions were <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Senhouse</ref> of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref> (near Maryport), &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nash</ref> the artist who was with me at Waterloo.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s journey to the Netherlands in 1815 to see the site of the Battle of Waterloo (18 June 1815).
                  Nash provided the drawings for seven of the eight engravings in <title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note>
               Switzerland &amp; the Alps were our object. We staid five days at Paris &amp; then proceeded by way of Dijon &amp; Besançon to
               Neufchatel, meaning to have crossed Mount S. Gothard<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The St Gotthard Pass connects the northern,
                  German-speaking area of Switzerland with the southern, Italian-speaking part, and opens the route to Italy.</note> &amp; to have
               returned into Switzerland by the Simplon;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Simplon pass, in the Swiss Alps, between Brig and
                  Domodossola in Italy.</note> – but finding that this pass was not practicable for a carriage without taking it to pieces, which
               involves a heavy expense, &amp; moreover that it was <del>xxx xxxxx</del> by no means advisable to enter upon it so early in the year
               as the beginning of June, when the season also happened to be remarkably backward, – we changed our route, &amp; visiting the Grande
                  Chartreuse<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Head monastery of the Carthusian order, founded 1084; located high in an Alpine
                  valley north of Grenoble.</note> on the way, entered Italy by way of Mount Cenis.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A mountain
                  pass between France and Italy.</note> This deviation from our first purposed course I regard as very fortunate; for we saw nothing
               finer than the Chartreuse, – indeed in its kind it cannot be surpassed; &amp; the Mount Cenis road, of which it has not been the
               fashion to say anything, is much more strange &amp; impressive than the Simplon. As you advance up the valley of the Maurienne, the
               Alps are around are crumbling to pieces; the Arco which rushes down the valley with a force &amp; fury beyond anything which I had ever
               before witnessed carries with it nearly as much earth, or rather decomposed stone, as water; &amp; the towns &amp; villages on the way
               are as ragged as the scenery about them. On the summit of M. Cenis, where we breakfasted, I could have fancied myself in Cumberland had
               not richer flowers been under my feet than our climate will produce. There is a tarn opposite the inn, with all the features of our own
               mountain scenery. The first part of the descent is more ruinous than any thing on the Savoy side. Indeed the mountains are in so
               crumbling a state, that it has been found necessary to abandon the new line of road (only a year or two since it was made at enormous
               expense), &amp; follow the old line, &amp; this line leads you four times over the same waterfall, one turn <del>xxxxxxx</del> as
               closely under another as it can possibly be made. But when you get beyond this desolation, where you have nothing but masses of loose
               earth &amp; perishing stone on every side, the descent into Piedmont is beyond description delightful. We went no farther than Milan; –
               from thence to the Lakes of Como &amp; Lugano, then across the Lago Maggiore, &amp; back by the Simplon into Switzerland, turning aside
               on the way for three days to visit the vale of Chamounix, &amp; the Mer de Glace.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncles</ref> brother-in-law<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Awdry
                  (1766–1844), solicitor in Reybridge and husband of Jane, née Bigg-Wither (1770–1845), sister of Herbert Hill’s wife, Catherine.
                  Southey’s party visited them at Echichens, Switzerland on 1–3 June 1817 and returned on 29 June–3 July.</note> happened to be
               residing with his family not far from Lausanne, – this was a very agreeable circumstance, &amp; we halted with him two nights on our
               way out, &amp; four on our return. Having reached Bern we sent the carriage on to Zurich, &amp; struck into what is called the
               Oberland, making our way as we could, sometimes by land – sometimes by water, on horseback or on foot. Thus we spent the most
               adventurous ten days of our journey, &amp; the most delightful. From Zurich our way was to Schaffhausen &amp; Donauschingen, where the
               Danube rises: thence through the Black Forest to Friburg in the Brisgau. We crost the Rhine to look at Strasburg, &amp; returned the
               same night into Germany; &amp; so by way of Heidelberg, Manheim &amp; Frankfort to Mentz, – &amp; then down the left bank to Cologne,
               &amp; so to Brussels, Lisle &amp; Calais. The whole journey was the work of thirteen weeks, about three of which we were stationary at
               different places. I made a copious journal, which was no slight exertion, &amp; my companions were very diligent in the use of the
               pencil; – so that few persons could have brought back more.</p><p rend="indent1"> I returned of a rich sun colour, &amp; according to all my friends, with more flesh upon my bones than I took out, –
               though I am sure that such a journey performed in such a manner would be an excellent recipe for one who had some to spare. Certain
               however it is that the continual <del>xxxx</del> exercise, change of air, &amp; excitement agreed admirably with me, to say nothing of
               the wine which everywhere about the Rhine is the true Amreeta,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The immortality-giving drink
                  prepared by the Hindu gods, that features in Southey’s <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), Book 24. </note> &amp; deserves to
               be called the liquor of life.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> was directed to send you the second volume of the Hist. of Brazil as
               soon as it was published.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> I hope
               he did not neglect this order. The concluding volume is in the press, &amp; I am now fairly employed upon it.</p><p rend="indent1"> Here is Barrow to be let &amp; I cannot but wish old Pocklington had been translated from his bed to his vault seven
               years ago.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1778 Joseph Pocklington (1736–1817), son of a Nottinghamshire banker, bought
                  Derwent Isle, in Derwentwater near Keswick (then known as Vicar’s Island) and built a house, fort and ‘Druid’ stone circle on the
                  land. On the lake shore he built Barrow House, overlooking a waterfall which he diverted and enlarged.</note> It is curious enough
               that I first heard of his death at a Table d’hote in Switzerland. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calvert</ref>
               also wants to let his house, being bent upon going to the continent. Ponsonby<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant John
                  Ponsonby of the Royal Navy and his wife (name and dates unknown) had been residing at Ormathwaite, just north of Keswick. </note>
               has removed to Maryport: so we are losing the few neighbours which we had. <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">This
                  property</ref> is in a wretched state: the owner is in Carlisle jail;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Greta Hall’s owner
                  Samuel Tolson Jnr (dates unknown) was in Carlisle jail, for debt. </note> a mortgage has foreclosed the estate, an injunction has
               been obtained by the widow of the last possessor to stop the sale, – contending parties have pestered me about my rent, &amp; a Bailiff
               comes regularly once a year to distrain upon me for annuities charged upon the estate.</p><p rend="indent1"> Public affairs I trust are looking better, thanks to the suspension of the H. Corpus,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Habeas corpus, preventing detention without trial, was suspended in February 1817 and renewed in February 1818.
               </note> &amp; to this blessed season. You would recognize me in the QR upon Parliamentary Reform &amp; upon the Causes of
                  Discontent.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>Quarterly Review</title> articles ‘Parliamentary Reform’, 16
                  (October 1816), 224–278, and ‘Rise and Progress of Popular Disaffection’, 16 (January 1817), 511–552.</note> In the last number I
               reviewed the Tonga Islands<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 17 (April 1817), 1–39, Southey
                  reviewed James Burney, <title>A Chronological History of the Voyages and Discoveries in the South Sea or Pacific Ocean; Illustrated
                     with Charts and Plates</title> (1803–1817); John Martin (1789–1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Account of the Natives of the
                     Tonga Islands, in the South Pacific Ocean, with an Original Grammar and Vocabulary of their Language</title>; and the
                     <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title> (1817).</note> &amp; in the forthcoming one there will be (or ought to be)
               an account of Lope de Vega.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The article, a review of Lord Holland, <title>Some Account of the
                     Lives and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio, and Guillen de Castro</title> (1817), appeared in <title>Quarterly
                  Review</title>, 18 (October 1817), 1–46.</note> – Is there any hope of seeing you in this country next summer? – after the small fry
               of a midlands river you would delight in landing some of the great fish of the Lakes. Remember us most kindly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Browne</ref> &amp; your daughters; – to Wade<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Wade Browne (1796–1851) and his sisters Lydia (c. 1789–1864), <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneElizabethdau">Elizabeth</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneSarah">Sarah</ref> and Mary (dates unknown). </note> also whom I should
               to meet &amp; recognize as a man.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">Believe me, my dear Sir, </salute><salute rend="indent2"> yrs very sincerely, </salute><signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>