<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2833</idno><idno type="nines">rce4104</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2833. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 31 August 1816</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2833.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>.  Previously  published: John
                  Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4
                  vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 33–35.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2833" type="letter"><head>2833. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1816-08-31">31 August 1816</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer<lb/> Endorsement: 31 August 1816.<lb/> MS:
                  Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: John
                  Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4
                  vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 33–35.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1816-08-31">Sunday 31 Aug. 1816</date></dateline><salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I begin to wish for solitude &amp; long evenings – Winter it were
               needless to include in the wish, for we have <del>been</del> {had} it almost
               uninterruptedly <del>xxxxx xxxx xxxxx</del> since last Christmas. I am weary of
               visitors, &amp; want leisure. The Beaumonts<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMargaret">Lady Beaumont</ref>.</note> are here, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#RogersSamuel">Rogers</ref> is here, – &amp; the Lord knows who has been here, –
                  <del>&amp; the Lord knows who</del> more of the Lord knows who’s family are
               coming. Here is Glover<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Glover
                  (1767–1849; <title>DNB</title>), the watercolour painter who owned Blowick Farm in
                  Patterdale, on Ullswater.</note> in town, &amp; the younger <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref>, &amp; – the Secretaries of the Bible
                  Society<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Secretaries of the British
                  and Foreign Bible Society (founded 1804): John Owen (1766–1822;
                  <title>DNB</title>), Curate of Fulham 1795–1813; and Joseph Hughes (1769–1833;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Baptist Minister who held various posts at Bristol’s
                  Broadmead Baptist Church 1791–1796, where he met Southey.</note> have been here,
               &amp; the King of Prussias Librarian<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel
                  Heinrich Spiker (1786–1858). An English translation of his account of his
                  experiences in Britain was later published as <title>Travels through England,
                     Wales, &amp; Scotland, in the Year 1816</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820). His meeting
                  with Southey was described on I, pp. 269–272. Naturally, Spiker was most interested
                  in Southey’s library.</note> has been here, – &amp; what with one &amp; another I
               am well nigh walked off my legs, &amp; talked out of my life. Am I the better for all
               this, you will ask. Every body will tell you that I am in good spirits, – but – my
               spirits are not what they were, – nor will they ever again be.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert Southey</ref> had died on 17
                  April 1816.</note><hi rend="ital">hæret lateri</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Publius
                  Vergilius Maro (70–19 BC), <title>Aeneid</title>, Book 4, line 73: ‘[it] clings to
                  my side’, in the sense of an arrow in a deer.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I have begun this letter forgetting that an unfinished one has been
               long lying in my desk; – so as I can frank this, I will cut off the fragment. <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> is at his old work of castrating my reviews,
               against which I must resolutely &amp; decidedly remonstrate. He has likewise without
               ceremony or any apology whatsoever wholly supprest a short article which I believe
               you saw, upon a Frenchmans history of Massenas campaign in Portugal,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">André Delagrave (1774–1849), <title>Campagne de
                     l’Armée Francaise en Portugal, dans les années 1810–11, &amp;c. par Mr A. D. L.
                     G., Officier Supérieur employé dans l’État-Major de cette Armée</title> (1815),
                  dealing with the French Marshal, André Massena’s (1758–1817), campaign in Portugal
                  1810–1811. This review was not published in the <title>Quarterly
                  Review</title>.</note> &amp; which certainly has not been omitted to make room for
               better matter. It would be curious if I should be so disgusted as to throw up the
               review at a time when it pays me <del>so</del> {more} liberally than I have ever
               before been remunerated for any kind of labour But I am strongly disposed to suspect
               foul play with which <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> is unacquainted. Judge for
               yourself – <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> propounds to me among others subjects
               a paper upon the West Indies, – there is none which I am more competent to treat: I
               accepted it, &amp; intimated an intention of making it conclude with reference to the
               Registry Bill;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The Registry Bill (1815),
                  backed by Wilberforce, proposed the registration of all slaves in British
                  colonies, but was vehemently opposed by supporters of slavery. For the proposed
                  article, and the books Southey requested Murray to send him, see Southey to
                  Murray, 29 June 1816, Letter 2818.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> is well pleased, – collects abundant pamphletts,
               – takes <del>for</del> it for granted that I must take part with the Planters &amp;
               Slave Smugglers because he “took<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Initially
                  ‘takes’.</note> it for granted that I should think differently from Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi><ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref>, “
               – &amp; finding that on this point (which is in effect the question of the Abolition)
               I agree with them, he writes to solicit as a matter in which his personal interest is
               deeply concerned, – that I will write upon any other subject. There are two modes of
               accounting for this, – he may have West Indian property or connections, &amp;
                  <del>t</del> in that case have formed a fools opinion, upon a mistaken notion of
               self interest, – or – he has submitted his journal to some undue influence – I
               pretend not to say what. Money has been lavished in purchasing newspapers &amp;c –
               yet he can hardly have been so imprudent as <del>well as xx</del> to sell his review
               – &amp; damn its character &amp; his own should this truth be suspected. I of course
               have laid the subject aside, – but as I made no secret of my intention to write thro
               that medium upon the question, I have warned him to beware how he takes the other
               side.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> calls him the <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand
                  Murray</ref>. I have preserved all his letters, – their hints &amp; their
               flattery would amuse you much. When next you come to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> we will turn over these papers upon a rainy day, &amp; put them in
               some order.</p><p rend="indent1"> By accident I have seen a number of the Examiner containing a parody
               upon the Proem to the Lay; I could not have desired it to be more silly or more
               stupid. You are included in it <hi rend="ital">nominatim</hi> as my <hi rend="ital">wise</hi> friend, in <del>reference to</del> burlesquing the stanza wherein I say
               the friendship of the wise &amp; good is mine.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Leigh Hunt</ref> used the paper he jointly ran,
                  the <title>Examiner</title>, to attack Southey as a political turncoat. The
                     <title>Examiner</title>, 449 (4 August 1816), 489–490 carried Hunt’s parody of
                  Southey’s <title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen Nuptiale</title> (1816), ‘The
                  Laureate Laid Double’, including the lines ‘Here I enjoy, amidst my haws and
                  hips,/ The friendship of wise Grosvenor and good Croker: –/ The battles of the
                  Kings and Priests I fought ye ‘em,/ And so at last they’ve crowned my caput
                  mortuum.’ Southey felt this parodied <title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen
                     Nuptiale</title> (1816), ‘Proem’, stanza 9, line 4, ‘The friendship of the good
                  and wise is mine’.</note> It is hardly worth while to allude to such attacks
                  <del>or</del> seriously – but if you will send me back the chapters of the prophet
                  Jehephary,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s parodic attack on
                     <ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref>, the ‘Book of the Prophet Jehephary’,
                  was, on the advice of his friends, not published in his lifetime. It appeared in
                  John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                     Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 35–42.</note> I will
                  <del>xx</del> alter &amp; adapt them to the present <del>state</del> {date}, &amp;
               secure their appearance in the Courier by sending them to <ref type="m" target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> myself.</p><p rend="indent1"> Recover if you can the MS of my two last articles.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed in <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 1–69, a series of memoirs of the French
                  Revolutionary wars and, in the same number, wrote an article ‘On the Poor’, 15
                  (April 1816), 187–235.</note> – Remember me to all at home.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>