<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3108</idno><idno type="nines">rce4379</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3108. Robert Southey to James
                  Montgomery, 2 April 1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3108.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Beinecke Library,
                  GEN MSS 298, Series I, Box 1, folder 21. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John
                  Holland and James Everett, Memoirs of the Life and Writings of James
                     Montgomery, 7 vols (London, 1854–1856), III, pp. 134–137.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3108" type="letter"><head>3108. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">James
                  Montgomery</ref>, <date when="1818-04-02">2 April 1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  James Montgomery./ Iris Office/ Sheffield/ Paid<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
                  Seal: red wax, with ‘S’, ‘In Labore Quies’ motto below<lb/> MS: Beinecke Library,
                  GEN MSS 298, Series I, Box 1, folder 21. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: John
                  Holland and James Everett, <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of James
                     Montgomery</title>, 7 vols (London, 1854–1856), III, pp. 134–137.</note></head><opener><salute> My dear Montgomery</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the Iris.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Sheffield Iris</title>, a weekly newspaper that ran 1794–1848.
                  Montgomery was its editor and owner 1794–1825.</note> I inclose a one pound bill
               (more according to my means than my will) for the poor Greenlanders,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Montgomery, a Moravian by education, campaigned
                  for support for the Moravian missions in Greenland. In 1818 there was severe
                  hardship among the Greenlanders and Montgomery published in the
                     <title>Iris</title> an appeal for funds which raised £130 as well as numerous
                  gifts of clothing.</note> &amp; I will endeavour to do them better service by
               sketching (if I am permitted) a history of the Mission in the Quarterly Review.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">An article on ‘Ancient and Modern Greenland’
                  appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 480–496
                  (published 9 June 1818). Its author was not Southey, but <ref type="m" target="people.html#PalgraveFrancis">Francis Palgrave</ref>.</note> I have
               Egede &amp; Crantz<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Hans Egede (1686–1758),
                     <title>Description et Histoire Naturelle du Groenland</title> (1763), no. 3068
                  in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library; David Crantz (1723–1777),
                     <title>History of Greenland</title> (1767), no. 762 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey’s library.</note> at hand, &amp; will write for the Periodical
                  Accounts.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The regular reports of the
                  Moravian missionaries, published from 1790 onwards as <title>Periodical Accounts
                     Relating to the Missions of the Church of the United Brethren Established Among
                     the Heathen</title>.</note> I have frequent cause to regret that the first
               volumes of these most interesting records are not to be procured.</p><p rend="indent1"> Thank you also for your little publication on the death of
                  Reynolds.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Fragments to the
                     Memory of the Late Richard Reynolds, Esq., the Philanthropist</title> (1817).
                  Richard Reynolds (1735–1816; <title>DNB</title>) was born in Bristol, but moved to
                  Shropshire in 1756, only returning to his native city in 1804. He was a Quaker who
                  became immensely wealthy through his ownership of the Coalbrookdale ironworks, but
                  gave much of his money to good causes, including, in Bristol, the Samaritan
                  Society, an orphan asylum, the Royal Infirmary and almshouses.</note> I believe he
               did not become a resident at Bristol till after I had left that city, – but I have
               seen his daughter (so at least I suppose her to be) M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                  Rathbone,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Hannah Mary Rathbone
                  (1761–1839), Reynolds’s daughter, married William Rathbone IV (1757–1809), a
                  Liverpool ship-owner, merchant and abolitionist. Southey met her in Liverpool in
                  1811; see Robert Southey to Thomas Southey, 8 September 1811, <title>The Collected
                     Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 1952.</note> &amp; she
               perhaps owes something of her sweetness of character, to inheritance, – for assuredly
               we bring with us predispositions good &amp; evil, which the followers of John
                  Locke<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Locke (1632–1704;
                     <title>DNB</title>), empiricist philosopher who argued in his <title>Essay
                     Concerning Human Understanding</title> (1689) that there was nothing in the
                  mind not derived from sense impressions and therefore it was a ‘white sheet’ at
                  birth.</note> &amp; of John Calvin<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">John
                  Calvin (1509–1564), Protestant theologian who argued the proposition that, before
                  birth, the nature and fate after death of each individual’s soul was already
                  decided by God; and emphasised the central importance of the doctrine of original
                  sin, according to which all people were born with a propensity to disobey God’s
                  commands.</note> would find it difficult to reconcile with their respective
               systems.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is very long since I have written to you, – forgive me, – &amp;
               tell me so soon.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am closely employed, &amp; as usual upon many things: the chief of
               these is the concluding volume of Brazil, a work of great ardour, &amp; corresponding
               delight to myself in its progress. This volume will contain much matter respecting
               the Jesuits which is little, if at all, known to the English public; &amp; accounts
               of savage life more curious than any in the former volumes. It is getting on in the
               press, &amp; I fully expect to publish it in the course of the summer.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The third and final volume of the <title>History
                     of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> – Another work which interests me greatly
               at present is upon a subject which you may perhaps regard with more curiosity, – the
               Life of Wesley, upon such a scale as to comprise the history of Methodism {abroad
               &amp; at home}, with no inconsiderable part of the religious history of this country
               for the last hundred years.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s
                     <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>
                  (1820).</note> You know enough of my intellectual habits to know my love of
               pursuing a subject in its ramifications. Just at this time I am drawing up a succinct
               account of the origin &amp; economy of the establishment at Herrnhut,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The village in Saxony, Germany that, after 1722,
                  became the centre for the Moravian revival. The Moravian Church was described in
                  Chapter 5 of <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of
                     Methodism</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820), I, pp. 175–208.</note> – a necessary
               part of that chapter which is entitled “Wesley in Germany.” No part of Wesleys
               conduct is so little creditable to him as that which relates to the Moravians. At
               first he submitted himself to them in a manner unworthy of his understanding, – as in
               the affair of his intended marriage with Sophia Causton, &amp; still more with regard
               to William Law.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>The Life of
                     Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820),
                  I, pp. 106–123, Southey accused Wesley of a lack of courage in allowing the
                  Moravian elders to decide for him that he should not marry Sophia Hopkey (b.
                  1708), the niece of Thomas Causton (c. 1692–1746) of Savannah, Georgia. Wesley’s
                  conduct in dropping a woman he had led to understand he might marry caused local
                  outrage and even a court case. At I, pp. 160–167 Southey suggested that the
                  influence of a Moravian preacher led Wesley rudely to criticise the teachings of
                  his former mentor William Law (1686–1761; <title>DNB</title>).</note> And when he
               separated from them, he did not for a long time render them common justice, – but
               even in some degree sanctioned the abominable calumnies with which they were
               assailed. He became wiser &amp; more charitable as he grew older. I have traced the
               progress of his mind with great care throughout his writings, – he outgrew all his
               extravagancies, but it was not easy for him to disown them all. When you see this
               book I think you will be satisfied with the diligence of the writer, I believe that
               you will not often dissent from his way of thinking, &amp; I am sure that you will
               entirely sympathize <del>in</del> {with} his feelings.</p><p rend="indent1"> Is there no hope of tempting you into this country? Spring is coming
               on, &amp; you would render me a bodily service by drawing me away from the desk &amp;
               the fire-side, to the mountain vallies &amp; the hill tops. I am not a man to make
               insincere professions, – it would give me a heartfelt pleasure to see you here. The
               Leeds Coach runs to Kendal, &amp; from Kendal there is a morning stage every day to
                  <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Last summer I crost the Alps from Savoy, got as far as Milan, saw the
               three lakes Como, Lugano &amp; Maggiore, &amp; recrost the Alps into Switzerland,
               went over the finest part of that [MS torn] country, &amp; then travelling thro the
               Black Forest to Friburg, came to Heidelberg &amp; Frankfurt, &amp; so by the Rhine to
               Cologne. I made a minute journal, which was no slight effort, for we travelled fast,
               &amp; were <del>incessantly</del> indefatigable in seeing every thing. I brought back
               a store of images which <del>no</del> books had never taught me to call up; – perhaps
               no three months of my life were ever past so profitably. And I returned with a stock
               of recruited health which has lasted till now, unimpaired; – &amp; with spirits as
               much improved as they are ever likely to be, – after the severest of all earthly
                  losses.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s only son Herbert
                  had died on 17 April 1816.</note> Come &amp; see me Montgomery, – that we may talk
               together of this world, &amp; of the next.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you –</salute><signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1818-04-02">2 April 1818</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>