<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2836</idno><idno type="nines">rce4107</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2836. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 8 September 1816</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2836.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 202–204 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2836" type="letter"><head>2836. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1816-09-08">8 September 1816</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9. Stafford Row/ Buckingham
                  Gate/ London<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: E/ 11 SE 11/ 1816 <lb/> Seal: black wax, with ‘S’, ‘In Labore Quies’ motto
                  below<lb/> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 202–204 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1816-09-08">Sunday morning. 8 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1816</date></dateline><salute> My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent2"> I have seldom taken up a pen with so little knowledge of what was to proceed from it as on this occasion, – for after
               sleeping upon your letters,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford had written transmitting ministerial proposals that Southey
                  edit a journal supporting the government.</note> &amp; thinking upon them, – breakfasting upon them I am at a loss how to reply, or
               how to act. – If it be necessary I will certainly go to London, – do you <del>xx</del> after what I may say, <del>xx</del> talk with
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>, <del>with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref></del><del> &amp; with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Docstor</ref></del>, &amp;
               determine whether it be so. I shall mention the affair to no person but <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> in
               this part of the world, – &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> are the only persons who need know it any where else, <del>but xxxx &amp;</del><ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn"><del> Rickman</del></ref> {But} If I go to London I shall make <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> of my privy Council.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is very obvious that a sense of danger has occasioned this step. Look at my <del>fiparst</del> paper upon the Poor
               in the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Quarterly,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812),
                  319–356 (this was issue no. 16).</note> – had the Ministry opened their eyes four years ago, <del>or rather had they not</del> had
               they seen what was passing before their eyes, – the evil might have then been checked. The event of a successful war would have enabled
               them to pursue a vigorous policy at home. It will be more difficult now &amp; requires more courage. And less is to be done by
                  <del>calling in</del> administering antidotes, than by preventing the distribution of poison. Make by all means the utmost use of
               the press in <del>xxxx</del> directing the public opinion, – but impose some curb upon its license, or all efforts will be in vain.</p><p rend="indent1"> In any way that may be thought advisable I will do my best, – but alas Grosvenor what <hi rend="ital">can</hi> I do
               more than what I have been doing? – A journal with the same object in view as the Anti-Jacobine,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Anti-Jacobin Review and Magazine, or, Monthly Political and Literary Censor</title> (1798–1821).</note> but conducted
               upon better principles, might be of good service. I could contribute to it from a distance. – But to <hi rend="ital">you</hi> it must
               be obvious that as my head &amp; hands are not like Kehamas<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The supernatural anti-hero of
                  Southey’s <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> multipliable at pleasure, I can exert myself only in one place at a
               time: &amp; Government would gain nothing by transferring me from the Quarterly to any thing else which they might be willing to
               launch. It may be said that that Q R. is established, – that this Engine is at work &amp; will go on, &amp; that it is desirable to
               have more engines than one. – I admit this. And if there be a Journal started which admits of it I will read lectures in live anatomy
               upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Hunt</ref>
               &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Sir Richard Phillips</ref>. In short, whether openly or covertly as may be
               deemed expedient, whatever ought to be done I am ready to do, &amp; to do it fearlessly. The best thing seems what I stated last night,
               – to write a small book or large pamphlett upon the State of the Nation.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey considered
                  writing, but never wrote, this book.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> In all this I see nothing which would require a change of residence, – that measure would induce a great sacrifice of
               feeling, – of comfort, &amp; of expence, – &amp; draw on a heavily increased expenditure. <del>The advantage to myself might perhaps
                  consist</del> They would provide for this, – but in what manner? A man is easily provided for who has a profession, or is capable of
               holding any official character; this is not my case – &amp; such things as might be given me, from the Lottery or stamp office<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey suggests he might be offered a post in the Board of Stamps, which administered stamp duty
                  on a range of items; or the Lottery Office, which ran the 126 state lotteries authorised between 1769 and 1826. Both organisations
                  employed a large number of officials and appointments could be used to reward supporters of the government; Wordsworth had been
                  appointed Distributor for Stamps in Westmorland in 1813 at a salary of £400 p.a.</note> for instance which would require me to live
               near London, would not be <del>so des</del> more advantageous <del>on the whole</del>, as a mere point of income, – &amp; in all other
               respects far less desirable than an increase of my pension to half the amount of such a situation as might be thought of. – To you I
               write without reserve. Perhaps they would give me a situation of 7 or 800 £ a year: – it would serve me more effectively if what comes
               thro your hands were made a clear <del>xxxx</del> five.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had received a government
                  pension of £200 p.a. since 1807, but tax reduced this to £144. He also received £100 p.a. as Poet Laureate, which tax reduced to
                  £92. Here he asks for £500 p.a. ‘clear’ i.e. after tax, more than double his government income in 1816.</note></p><p rend="center"> ____</p><p rend="indent1"> I was going to send Jehephary<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s parodic attack on Francis Jeffrey, the
                  ‘Book of the Prophet Jehephary’, was, on the advice of his friends, not published in his lifetime. It appeared in John Wood Warter
                  (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 35–42.</note> to the Courier, –
               or to enlarge it &amp; let it off thro the <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand Murray</ref> in a small pamphlet, but it
               shall lie by for the present in case a <del>newspaper</del> {journal} be started in which it might find place. Woe be to him, if this
               be! I will handle him in a severer stile than ever <del>he be</del> such a scoundrel was handled yet.</p><p rend="indent1"> No Lady has appeared with a letter from you, &amp; the review of M. with the half dozen initials has never been
                  inserted;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">André Delagrave (1774–1849), <title>Campagne de l’Armée Francaise en Portugal, dans
                     les années 1810–11, &amp;c. par Mr A. D. L. G., Officier Supérieur employé dans l’État-Major de cette Armée</title> (1815),
                  dealing with the French Marshal, André Massena’s (1758–1817), campaign in Portugal 1810–1811. This review was not published in the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> – you fancy so because you read the proof sheets I consider its rejection as a great
               piece of incivility &amp; disrespect.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will understand that I will hasten to London if it be thought necessary, – but that <del>I</del> in my own calm
               judgement it is quite unnecessary. – I even believe that any conversation which the men in power might have with me would operate to my
               disadvantage. I should appear confused &amp; visionary, – an impracticable sort of man. – On the whole too I do not think I <hi rend="ital">could</hi> leave this country, where I am now in a manner attached to the soil, by a sort of moral &amp; intellectual
               serfage which I could not break if I would, – &amp; would not if I could. And <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is to be considered even more than myself. Would that it were in my power to buy <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">this property</ref>, – which I dare say might at this time be purchased, – for we have a needy
               Landlord, in suspicious circumstances.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Greta Hall suffered from the complicated financial and
                  legal entanglements of its owner, Samuel Tolson, Junior (dates unknown), Southey’s landlord, who was, by April 1817, in Carlisle
                  jail for debt.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> It is better that I should write either to you or to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries </ref><del>xxxx</del> a letter <hi rend="ital">to be shown</hi>, than that I should show myself. Good may undoubtedly <del>may</del> be done
               by exposing the anarchists, &amp; awakening the sound part of the country to a sense of their danger. This I can do; but it will be of
               no avail unless it be followed by {an} effective measure, – by appointing a punishment for sedition (such as <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Hunts</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbetts</ref>)<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Leigh Hunt was imprisoned for two years in 1813 for libelling the Prince Regent; Cobbett received two
                  years in prison in 1810 for treasonous libel for criticising the flogging of local militiamen at Ely.</note> which shall prevent a
               repetition of the offence: – transportation is that punishment. Unless this is done, or something which shall produce the same salutary
               effect, I do not think it possible<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Initially ‘possibly’.</note> that we shall escape from a <hi rend="ital">Bellum Servile</hi>.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A civil war between classes.</note> – The immediate
               distress can best be alleviated by finding employment for the poor, – &amp; one easy mode of doing this {to a great extent} is to form
               raised foot paths beside our <del>horse paths</del> roads, wherever the soil does not render them unnecessary. – And I am very desirous
               that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Owens plan for employing paupers in agriculture should be tried;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Owen (1771–1858; <title>DNB</title>), the humanitarian industrialist, who provided improved living conditions for the
                  workers at his mills at New Lanark, Scotland. Owen had visited Southey in August 1816 and the two men had discussed Owen’s plan to
                  house the poor in groups of 500–1,000 people, each with access to 1,000–1,500 acres of land. Owen explained his ideas in
                     <title>Report of the Committee of the Association for Relief of the Manufacturing and Labouring Poor</title> (1817). He hoped
                  these plans might lay the basis for a future utopia.</note> – he writes like a madman, – but his practice ought<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Initially ‘might’.</note> not to be confounded with his metaphysicks; the experiment is worth trying – I
               do not doubt its success, – &amp; the consequences which he so foolishly anticipates with triumph should be regarded as the dreams of
               an enthusiast, – not as reasons to deter Government from the most feasible means of abolishing the poor rates which has been (or in my
               judgement can be) proposed. I have seen Owen, &amp; talked him at great length.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2">RS</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>