<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2843</idno><idno type="nines">rce4114</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2843. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, [begun before and continued on 15
                  September 1816] </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2843.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng.
                  Lett. c. 25. ALS; 3p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2843" type="letter"><head>2843. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1816-09-15">[begun before and continued on 15
                  September 1816] </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9. Stafford Row/ Buckingham Gate./ [in another hand]
                  W.G<lb/> Endorsements: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 19 Sept. 1816; Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 19. Sep<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1816<lb/> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng.
                  Lett. c. 25. ALS; 3p.<lb/> Unpublished.<lb/> Dating note: The endorsement
                  indicates Bedford received the letter on 19 September 1816. Southey himself
                  indicates the second section was written on ‘Sunday evening’, probably 15
                  September 1816.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear G.</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I shall write you a melancholy letter, – if a summons to supper do
               not call me off. <hi rend="ital">Non sum qualis eram</hi>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Quintus Horatius Flaccus (65–8 BC), <title>Odes</title>, 4.1:
                  ‘I am not that which I was’. Herbert Southey had died on 17 April 1816.</note> –
               nor shall I ever be again. Whenever I am unoccupied I feel the wound, – &amp; like a
               schoolboy who wishes that the months which must intervene before the holydays, – were
               over, – I detect <del>him</del>{my}self in wishing that the time were fairly past
               which separates me from eternity. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> has
               a severe cough &amp; cold which disposes me more particularly to such feelings, – or
               rather renders me less able to contend against them. – I can stand aloof &amp;
               contemplate these things like a stoic, – I can feel how beneficial they are, like a
               Xtian, – yea how necessary to the perfection of our moral nature: – but it is neither
               inconsistent with philosophy nor with religion while I am strenuously doing my work,
               to wish that the day were over, – &amp; look on with hope towards the night.</p><p rend="align(center)"> ____</p><p rend="indent1"><date when="1816-09-15">Sunday evening</date></p><p rend="indent1"> The Courier of yesterday brought the speeches at the Palace Yard
               meeting, which as coming pretty strongly in aid of my last letters, are
                  well-timed.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A meeting of householders in
                  the borough of Westminster at Palace Yard on 11 September 1816. It passed a series
                  of resolutions denouncing the government and demanding Parliamentary reform. An
                  account appeared in the <title>Courier</title>, 12 September 1816.</note> It would
               not be amiss if <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> were to reprint my two papers
               upon the Poor, in a little volume; – by restoring the castrations in the first, &amp;
               making some additions to the second, they might be rendered tolerably compleat for
               their purpose.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s articles from the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319–356, and 15 (April
                  1816), 187–235. The 1812 article contained (320–327) a denunciation of Thomas
                  Malthus (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on the Principle of
                     Population</title> (1798) and in particular Malthus’s proposal in the second
                  edition of 1803 to abolish poor relief for children born after a certain date. The
                  pamphlet Southey proposed to write was not forthcoming.</note> Indeed if the
               ministry would but read mark &amp; inwardly digest ten pages in that first paper,
               &amp; act upon them, the {immediate} danger would be put an end to, &amp; leisure be
               gained for those measures of prevention &amp; amelioration which I have so often
               &amp; so earnestly <del>xx</del> advised.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s article, ‘Inquiry into the Poor Laws’,<title> Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319–56, especially 340–351 on the dangers of
                  revolution and the radical press.</note> Were the <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand
                  Murray</ref> to do this I would procure the last Edinburgh which <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> says has stirred up all his bile by
               reviving Malthus’s proposal about the poor,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey loathed Malthus’s argument that population was bound to outstrip
                  resources. In <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 26 (June 1816), 235–280 (276),
                  rural poverty was blamed, in part, on the Poor Laws leading to agricultural
                  labourers, secure in the knowledge they would receive a dole from the parish,
                  having large families. The same article revived Malthus’s proposal to abolish poor
                  relief for children born after a certain date. </note> – &amp; either in notes
               preface or postscript, I would deal with that precious journal according to its
               deserts.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am now about to begin an article for this the next number, the
               motive of which is the solid sum of 100 £ (which you will allow to be a good reason)
               – the text books a heap of <del>foreign</del> travels by Frenchmen in England, –
               &amp; the object a comparative estimate of <del>xx</del> our national character &amp;
                  institutions.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 15 (July 1816), 537–574, Southey reviewed a series of works by
                  travellers in England, under the title ‘Works on England’.</note> In this I shall
               repeat my warning, &amp; exhortations, – &amp; the hope (however faint) that by thus
               repeating again &amp; again the same strain some effect may ultimately be produced
               reconciles me to the employment of irreparable time in such ephemeral occupations, –
               while works which should extend &amp; perpetuate my reputation, are lying unfinished
               on the shelf.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>