<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2953</idno><idno type="nines">rce4224</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2953. Robert Southey to [William Wilberforce] [begun
               before and concluded on] 23 March 1817 </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2953.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Princeton University Library,
                  Robert H. Taylor Collection, Box 17, Folder 27. ALS; 4p. .  Previously 
                  published: R. I. Wilberforce and S. Wilberforce, The Correspondence of
                     William Wilberforce, 2 vols (London, 1840), II, pp. 362–366 [dated 23
                  March]. </p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2953" type="letter"><head>2953. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">William Wilberforce</ref>] [begun
               before and concluded on] <date when="1817-03-23">23 March 1817 </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: Rob Southey on his/
                  ungenerous treatment/ in Case of Wat Tyler<lb/> MS: Princeton University Library,
                  Robert H. Taylor Collection, Box 17, Folder 27. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously
                  published: R. I. Wilberforce and S. Wilberforce, <title>The Correspondence of
                     William Wilberforce</title>, 2 vols (London, 1840), II, pp. 362–366 [dated 23
                  March]. </note></head><opener><signed>My dear Sir</signed></opener><p rend="indent1"> In the year 1794 &amp; in the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>- year of my
               age, I wrote Wat Tyler.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Wat
                     Tyler</title> had been published without Southey’s consent in February
                  1817.</note> It was immediately taken to London by poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> (afterwards my brother-in law) &amp; put into Ridgeways
               hands. Soon afterwards (a few weeks) I went to London myself {for a few days} &amp;
               saw Ridgeway in Newgate; &amp; was informed that he &amp; Symonds would publish
                  it.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">James Ridgway (1755–1838), radical
                  publisher. Southey had visited him in Newgate Prison on 12 January 1795 to arrange
                  publication of <title>Wat Tyler</title>; see Southey to Edith Fricker [c. 12
                  January 1795], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>,
                  Letter 123. Ridgway shared his rooms at Newgate with his fellow-publisher Henry
                  Symonds (1741–1816), and William Winterbotham. Ridgway and Symonds had been
                  imprisoned for four years in 1793 for publishing Thomas Paine’s <title>The Rights
                     of Man</title> (1791–1792), but continued to publish works from Newgate, including
                  Winterbotham’s <title>An Historical, Geographical, Commercial, and Philosophical
                     View of the American United States </title>(1795).</note> They never informed
               me that they afterwards changed their opinion, &amp; I never enquired concerning it;
               – first because my heart as well as my mind was fully employed; secondly because I
               perfectly acquiesced in the fitness of suppressing it, &amp; lastly because I
               considered it unworthy a farther thought. – Had I been in town I might perhaps have
                  <del>xx</del> reclaimed the mss, but not going there till the year 1797,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had returned to London in February 1797 to
                  embark on his legal studies at Gray’s Inn.</note> I reckoned it among the follies
               of my youth, &amp; was contented to forget it. My youth has no worse follies with
               which to reproach me. – I was then a republican &amp; a leveller; &amp; stated such
               principles broadly in this dialogue, – the hasty overflow of my spirits, in
                  <del>xxx</del> two or three mornings. – My counsel have done me more wrong than my
               enemies. I feel no <hi rend="ital">shame</hi> respecting the work, – I acknowledge no
                  <hi rend="ital">wickedness</hi> in it. I was a boy, who wrote as he felt &amp;
                  <del>he</del> {as he} believed in his ignorance, &amp; inexperience; &amp; I was
               as ready to dare all danger in promulgating those opinions then, as I am in
               counteracting them now.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s claim for
                  an injunction against the publishers of <title>Wat Tyler</title> was denied on
                  18–19 March 1817, on the grounds that he had not clearly established his copyright
                  to the work. But Southey was particularly aggrieved at the case made by his
                  lawyers, Sir Anthony Hart (c. 1754–1831; <title>DNB</title>) and Sir Lancelot
                  Shadwell (1779–1850; <title>DNB</title>), as reported in e.g. <title>Morning
                     Post</title>, 19 March 1817, ‘it was of the utmost importance that the
                  dissemination of a work, professing such wicked and mischievous sentiments, both
                  as it regarded the public welfare, and the character of the individual, who had
                  long since disavowed the sentiments contained in it, should be immediately
                  stopped’.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Upon seeing the work announced I lost no time in making oath to the
               circumstances, &amp; applying for an injunction.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">As part of his legal action, Southey had gone to Cockermouth on
                  8 March 1817 to swear an affidavit before a Master of Chancery.</note> The
                  <del>xxx</del> delay which has intervened has not been my fault; &amp; my
                  <del>sole</del> object in so doing was <del>xxxxxxx</del> to acknowledge the work,
                  <del>&amp; secure my</del> (that I might <hi rend="ital">not</hi> seem to be
               ashamed of it) &amp; stop its sale because I know how mischievous it is at this time.
               I have been defeated by perjury. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">Winterbottom</ref>, a
               dissenting Minister, has sworn that I <hi rend="ital">gave</hi> the book to him &amp;
               to D. I. Eaton, &amp; gave them a fraternal embrace when they <del>agreed</del>
               promised to publish it.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Daniel Isaac Eaton
                  (1753–1814; <title>DNB</title>), radical publisher. Winterbotham claimed in his
                  affidavit that when Southey had visited Newgate in January 1795 he had given the
                  manuscript of <title>Wat Tyler</title> to Eaton and Winterbotham, and surrendered
                  his copyright to them.</note> I <hi rend="ital">gave</hi> the book to no person,
               but was to have had a share of the profits. The persons who engaged to publish it
               were Ridgeway &amp; Symonds. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">Winterbottom</ref> was in the
               room, – D I Eaton I never saw in my life, – &amp; as for fraternal embraces; – if you
               knew me my dear Sir, you might as soon expect to see my dancing a hornpipe upon the
               stage now as believe that at any part of my life I could play the fool in this
                  <del>manner</del> way, – so utterly discordant is it to my <hi rend="ital">constitutional</hi> habits &amp; manners.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have addressed two letters to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith</ref>, which if they are not disapproved by my old
               friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Wynn</ref> will appear in the Courier.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had written two letters which he
                  originally hoped to publish in the <title>Courier</title>: Southey to William
                  Smith, 17 March 1817 (Letter 2943) and Southey to the Editor of the
                     <title>Courier</title> [19 March 1817] (Letter 2946). These two letters were
                  sent to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, on 17 and 19 March 1817 (Letters 2944 and
                  2948), for him to approve and forward to the newspaper. In the event, Wynn’s
                  absence from home led to a delay in his receiving the letters. By the time he did
                  so, the public debate had moved on and Southey therefore decided not to publish
                  them in the <title>Courier</title>, but instead to incorporate them into his
                  pamphlet <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title> (1817).</note> The
                  provocation<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Smith had denounced Southey
                  in the House of Commons on 14 March 1817 during the debate on the Seditious
                  Meetings Bill, condemning ‘the settled, determined malignity of a renegado’ and
                  comparing Southey’s arguments against radical views in the <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 227 with those expressed in <title>Wat
                     Tyler</title> (1817), Act 2, lines 103–112.</note> will excuse their warmth,
               &amp; indeed demanded it. To proceed farther in legal courses, would only {draw} upon
               me fresh expences; &amp; of vexation I should not speak as regarding myself, – for I
               have felt too many real afflictions, to be <del>sensible of such unkindnesses</del>
               hurt by any arrows which malice can direct against me. But if <del>xx</del> it be any
               satisfaction to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi>
                  Smith</ref>, he may be told that he has made <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">my
               wife</ref> ill. It is well for him &amp; for me that I <del>xx</del>
               know the wickedness of duelling; How is it that the spirit of faction can have thus
               possessed him! – Had I ever concealed my sentiments, or attempted to conceal them?
               Because I was a republican, or rather as I called myself a <hi rend="ital">pantisocrat</hi>, at the time Wat Tyler was written I had abandoned all my
               prospects in life for the purpose of going to the wilds of America. Those same
               opinions are expressed in poems which I have never felt a wish to alter, – because I
               never was ashamed of having in such times &amp; such circumstances <del>xxxxxx</del>
               formed vain imaginations of a new system of society, – or rather as I then believed
               of restoring the system of Xtian society. I have merely affixed to those pieces the
               date of the year when they were written, – &amp; left others which accompany them to
               explain that as the author grew older, he grew wiser also.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A rather misleading statement: Southey had first added dates of
                  composition to his shorter poems in <title>Poems</title> (1799), published when he
                  was still a radical. The datings marked his poetical, rather than his political or
                  religious, development.</note> So far have I carried this feeling that I have not
               even suppressed a poem upon <del>public worship</del> Sunday morning, because
               erroneous as it is <del>in feeling</del>, the feeling is not such as will make any
               person of sense reproach the man who could thus feel in his youth.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s ‘Written on Sunday Morning’,
                     <title>Poems</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp. 129–131 and reprinted in subsequent
                  collections of his shorter works, including <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815). It
                  was an explicitly non-Christian poem that acquired the date ‘1795’ in
                     <title>Poems</title>, 2 vols (Bristol, 1799), I, p. 60.</note> Nor would I have
               sought to suppress Wat Tyler, had not the verses which I <del>xxxx</del> wrote when
               the mob were ferocious in their loyalty, &amp; the spirit of Anti Jacobinism was
               reigning in full vigour of intolerance, – <del>appeared to myself most</del> {become
               most} mischievous {now} when the sentiments – long since discarded by men of my stamp
               &amp; class in society, have been taken up by the rabble, &amp; are threatening the
               utter overthrow of <del>xxxxx xxxxx xxx xxxxxx</del> {all our institutions}. I
               heartily condemn the piece, – because the principles which it contains are
               misapplied, &amp; put in a mischievous form, – if addressed to a mob prepared for
               them, which they were not when written. They could <hi rend="ital">then</hi> have
               been injurious only to myself. My feeling would be very different, if there were any
               thing irreligious or licentious there, <del>xxxxx</del> there was no error from the
               heart; – – &amp; when I pray for forgiveness of my sins – the political aberrations
               of my youth have never been reckond among them.</p><p rend="indent1"> Believe me I feel very sensibly the kindness of your letter, – &amp;
               to show <hi rend="ital">how</hi> I feel it I could find in my heart to give you a
               brief sketch of my Pilgrimage in this perilous world, &amp; lay open not only the
               outward circumstances, but the inner man. It is my intention, whenever I can afford
               time, to do this at length for posthumous publication; – but when this season of
               leisure may arrive, or whether it will ever be allowed me – who can tell?</p><p rend="indent1"> If no unforeseen evil should occur to prevent my purpose, I shall
               arrive in London on Thursday the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of next month. – It will
               give me great pleasure to see Lord Calthorpe,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">George Gough-Calthorpe, 3rd Baron Calthorpe (1787–1851). He controlled one
                  seat at Bramber, for which Wilberforce was returned as MP 1812–1825.</note> –
               &amp; also if I should find Lady Olivia<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Olivia Sparrow (c. 1778–1863), daughter of the Irish peer Arthur
                  Acheson, 1st Earl of Gosford (c. 1745–1807). She had married Robert Sparrow
                  (1773–1805) on 14 March 1797. </note> in town.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent1"> with great respect</salute><salute rend="indent2">yrs faithfully &amp; thankfully</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1817-03-23">23 March 1817. </date><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>