<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2857</idno><idno type="nines">rce4128</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2857. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 29 October 1816</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2857.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 157.
                  ALS; 4p..  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2857" type="letter"><head>2857. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1816-10-29">29 October 1816</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb/> Postmarks: [partial] o’Clock/ NO 1/ 18 FN<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; E/ 1 NO 1/ 1816<lb/> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 157.
                  ALS; 4p.<title><lb/></title>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1816-10-29">29 Oct. 1816.</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> The Jornal de Coimbra<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey owned an 8–volume set of the <title>Jornal de
                     Coimbra</title> (1812–1820), no. 3498 in the sale catalogue of his library. </note> supplies <del>xxx</del> but a scanty list of
                  <hi rend="ital">desiderata</hi>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">See the list at the end of this letter. The desired materials
                  were to aid Southey’s researches for his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> – as you will perceive on the
                  <del>last</del> other leaf. But I find in it promise of good things which will in due time appear in the publications of the
                  Academy.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The publications of the Royal Academy of Portuguese History (founded 1720).</note>
               They have had presented to them O Livro da Virtuosa Benfeitoria – a work by the Infante D Pedro<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Pedro, Duke of Coimbra (1392–1449), <title>Livro da Virtuosa Benfeitoria</title> (1418).</note>: three volumes of Dissertaçoens
               sobre a Hist Ecclesiastica de Portugal, por Joam Pedro <del>xxx</del> Ribeiro<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">João Pedro Ribeiro
                  (1758–1839), <title>Dissertações Cronológicas e Criticas sobre a Historia e Jurisprudência Ecclesiástica e Civil de Portugal</title> (1798–1810), no. 3713
                  in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – a letter from Pedro vaz Camenha to King D Emanuel relating the discovery of
                  Brazil,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">One of the earliest surviving documents describing the discovery of Brazil, Pêro Vaz
                  de Caminha’s (c. 1450–1500) letter of 1 May 1500 to Manuel I (1469–1521; King of Portugal 1495–1521) was placed in the Portuguese
                  national archives, the Torre do Tombo.</note> &amp; a ms. <del>concerning as xxx</del> Hist das cousas do Brazil by Pedro de
               Magalhaens Gandavo.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Pêro de Magalhães Gândavo (1540–c. 1580), <title>História da Província de
                     Santa Cruz que Vulgarmente Chamamos Brasil</title> (1576).</note> – I must find out some person who has connections with the Rio
               to procure for me the Patriota,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>O Patriota, Jornal Litterario, Politico, Mercantil &amp;c
                     do Rio de Janeiro</title> (1813–1814), no. 3641 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. In <title>History of Brazil</title>,
                  3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, pp. v–vi, Southey thanked John May for procuring the third volume of <title>O Patriota</title> for
                  him, ‘when it was not to be obtained at Lisbon’.</note> – perhaps <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoodenJames">Gooden</ref> can do
               it. </p><p rend="indent1"> This evening I send off to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> a farther portion of copy. I am
               now in the miscellaneous chapter which concludes the volume,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 30 of <title>History of
                     Brazil</title>, 3 vols (1810–1819), II, pp. 632–692.</note> – One volume of the Pinheiro Collection (as for <del>xxx</del>
               convenience I call the set in nine volumes from the name of the Desembargador to whom they originally belonged)<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly the 9 volumes of manuscript material described as ‘Papeis Varias Politicos’ (1674), no. 3852 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – is rich in papers respecting Maranham, &amp; from these I have collected much information
               for this concluding chapter, as well as for the general history. A good deal of matter will be found in it gathered from very various
               sources. <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoodenJames">Gooden</ref> lent me a life of Gomes Freyre<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Gomes Freire de Andrada (1636–1702), Governor of Maranhao 1685–1687.</note> (the best of the name) in two {small}
               volumes, – by Fr. Domingo Teyxeyra<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Domingos Teixeira (d. 1726), <title>Vida de Gomes Freyre de
                     Andrada </title>(1724–1727).</note> author of a folio life of the Grande Condestatore which I have here.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Vida de Nuno Alvares Pereyra, Segundo Condestavel de Portugal</title> (1723), no. 3795 in the sale catalogue
                  of Southey’s library. This was a life of St Nuno Alvares Pereira (1360–1431), hero of Portuguese independence, known as the ‘Great
                  Constable’ from the office he held in the Portuguese Court.</note> The author is an imitator of Jacintho Freyre de Andrada,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacinto Freire de Andrade (1597–1657), priest, poet and biographer, who wrote <title>Vida de Dom
                     João de Castro Quarto Viso-Rei da Índia</title> (1651), no. 3385 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note><del>xxx</del> an original <del>the xxx</del> whose reputation is much beyond his deserts. But this life of G. Freyre tho written in a
               very affected stile has been very useful to me, &amp; contains some interesting matter.</p><p rend="indent1"> The volume will I think, sans doubt, be published in January, &amp; I shall go to press forthwith with the concluding
               one. <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Koster</ref> may very probably be of use in collecting some documents of later
               times, – tho Pernambuco is perhaps the worst place for finding them. However if nothing should come from that quarter I have materials
               enough to carry on a connected narrative. – I think I mentioned <del>to you</del> in my last that there is a collection of laws
               respecting the Indians which it is indispensable to have, – &amp; which I cannot have too soon.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Rules of the Missions were promulgated in 1686 and set out the terms on which the Jesuit mission stations (‘Reductions’) would
                  operate in Brazil. They were published as <title>Regimento e Leis Sobre as Missões do Estado do Maranhaõ e Parà e Sobre a Liberdade
                     dos Indios</title> (1724). </note></p><p rend="indent1"> My affairs with <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> are in a good state, &amp; for the first
               time the yearly account <del>xxx</del> exhibits me on the right side of his books. The edition of the Pilgrimage<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> was exhausted in two months, – giving me
               a profit of 215£. I shall probably have the Tale of Paraguay for publication in the spring,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                     <title>Tale of Paraguay</title> was not completed and published until 1825.</note> – which will form a volume of the same
                  size,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825) ran to 217 pages, compared to 232 pages for
                     <title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816) and both books were retailed for 10<title>s</title>. 6<title>d</title>.
                  Only 1500 copies of the <title>Tale</title> were printed, though, and the book sold slowly.</note> – &amp; by the help of some
               drawings which <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref><note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Tale of
                     Paraguay </title>(1825) featured two illustrations by Richard Westall (1765–1836; <title>DNB</title>) but none by Nash, who died
                  in 1821.</note> is making for me, of the same price. One of these is a view of the Church of a Reduction with the contiguous
               buildings, – made up from an abominable plan in Peramas,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Josephus Emmanuel Peramas (1732–1793),
                     <title>De Vita et Moribus Sex Sacerdotum et Tredecim Variorum Paraguaycorum</title> (1791), no. 2209 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey’s library. This idea was not used in the printed version of <title>The Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> – but it
               looks well when reduced to Peramas, &amp; enlivened with figures. A Jesuit will be another for which here is a whole length print of
                  Vieyra<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio Vieira (1608–1697), the Brazilian-born Jesuit. The second print in <title>The
                     Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825) featured a Jesuit priest.</note> to give us the exact costume.</p><p rend="indent1"> My summer, for so it must be called by the courtesy of England, has been much interrupted, – but on the whole I have
               got thro a good deal of work, &amp; the winter (if nothing unforeseen should occur <del>to prevent</del>) will be still more
               productive.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have sent for Thevenots Coll. of Voyages<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean de Thévenot (1633–1667),
                     <title>Relation de Divers Voyages Curieux qui n’ont point este Publices, ou qui ont este traduites d’Hakluyt, de Purchas, et
                     Autres</title> (1663–1672), no. 2675 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> from a Catalogue – &amp; shall be glad if
               they are not already sold. – There is a voyage to Brazil by old Atkins the surgeon of the Weymouth which I have looking for these last
               ten years in vain.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">The naval surgeon John Atkins (bap. 1685, d. 1757; <title>DNB</title>). He
                  published accounts of his travels as <title>A Voyage to Guinea, Brasil and the West Indies</title> (1735). It contained little about
                  Brazil, and although it implied that Atkins had published another work on his voyage to Brazil, there was no earlier volume on this
                  subject.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has sent for my perusal a very interesting history of the Spanish
               Inquisition by Llorenti one of its Ex–Secretaries, to whom all its papers were committed after its suppression.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan Antonio Llorente (1756–1823), <title>Histoire Critique de l’Inquisition d’Espagne</title>
                  (1817–1818), no. 1738 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Llorente was Secretary-General to the Inquisition at Madrid
                  1789–1794, but supported the French-backed regime of 1808–1813 and was given control of the Inquisition’s archive. No English
                  translation appeared until 1826.</note> I hope it may be printed. It arrived only on Sunday so that as yet I have read only a few
               chapters. Among other curious extracts from the correspondence of Charles 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi><note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan Manuel (d. 1543), Ambassador to the Papacy 1520–1522 for Charles V (1500–1558; Holy Roman Emperor
                  1519–1556).</note> Ambassador at Rome, is one in which he advises the Emperor to frighten the Pope by showing some little favour
               towards one Martin Luther, of whom he says the Pope is very much afraid.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Histoire
                     Critique de l’Inquisition d’Espagne</title>, 4 vols (Paris, 1817–1818), I, pp. 398–399. Martin Luther (1483–1546) was the founder
                  of the Reformation in Germany. The Pope who was worried about Luther was Leo X (1475–1521; Pope 1513–1521).</note> The publication
               of this book can scarcely fail of doing good even in Spain, compiled as it is from such unquestionable documents, &amp; the author
               professing himself, with apparent sincerity, a Catholic.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco</ref> has been admitted into the English Church, &amp; is now residing at
                  <ref type="m" target="places.html#HollandHouse">Holland House</ref> as tutor to one of <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord H’s</ref> sons.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">White tutored Henry Edward Fox
                  (1802–1859; <title>DNB</title>), later 4th Baron Holland, son of Lord Holland in 1815–1817. White had signed the Church of England’s
                  Thirty-Nine Articles on 10 August 1814.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the boys – I hope <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> goes on well at school. – Here we are doing well, save only that I am kept within
               doors by a sprained ankle, – but a day or two more will set me free again</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p>A Serra de Cintra. poesia.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Ricardo Raimundo Nogueira (1746–1827), <title>A Serra de
                        Sintra</title> (1814).</note></p><p> Memorias para a vida da Beata Mafalda Rainha de Castella &amp;c. obra inedita de Fr. </p><p> Bernardo de Brito<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Fortunato de Sao Boaventura (1778–1844), <title>Memorias para a Vida da
                        Beata Mafalda, Rainha de Castella</title> (1814).</note></p><p> Evora Lastimosa &amp;c. Memoria Historica &amp;c – pelo P Jose Joaquim da Silva<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">José Joaquim
                  da Silva (dates unknown), <title>Évora Lastimosa pela Deplorável Catastrofe do Fatal Triduo de 29, 30 e 31 de Julho de
                        1808</title> (1809–1814).</note></p><p> Descripçaõ Topographica de Villa Nova de Gaya &amp;c. por Joam Antonio Monteiro e Azevedo.<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">João Antonio Monteiro Azevedo (dates unknown), <title>Descripção Topographica de Villa Nova de Gaya</title> (1808).</note></p><p> Obra Poetica de D. Joanna Margarida Mancia Ribeiro da Silva, em que descrive a sua vida<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">Joana
                     Margarida Mancia Ribeiro da Silva (dates unknown), <title>Obra Poetica em que Descreve a sua Vida</title> (1815).</note></p><p> O Oriente – Poema de Jose Agostinho de Macedo.<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">José Agostinho de Macedo (1761–1831),
                        <title>O Oriente</title> (1814), no. 3420 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p><p> Compilaçam das Ordens do Dia do Quartet General do Exercito Portuguez.<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Compilação das
                  Ordens do dia do Quartel General do Exército Portugues</title> (1809–14): a compilation of the daily orders of the Portuguese
                     army.</note></p><p> Santuario Mariano par P. F Agostinho de Santa Maria.<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors">Agostinho de Santa Maria (1642–1728),
                        <title>Santuário Mariano</title> (1707–1723), no. 3222 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>