<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2709</idno><idno type="nines">rce3980</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2709. Robert Southey to John Murray, 7 February
                  1816</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2709.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42551. ALS; 3p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2709" type="letter"><head>2709. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>,<date when="1816-02-07"> 7 February
                  1816</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London<lb/>
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: E/ 10 FE 10/ 1816<lb/> Watermark: J DICKINSON &amp; Co/ 1811<lb/> Endorsement: 1816 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 7/ Southey Rob<hi rend="sup">t</hi><lb/> MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42551. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
                  Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1816-02-07">7 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1816</date></dateline><salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> After maturely considering <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew Dalrymples</ref> letter I have to
               chuse between the apparent incivility of not acknowledging it, or the inconvenience of involving myself in a correspondence which could
               not be satisfactory to him &amp; would be very painful to myself.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In his first article on the
                  ‘Life of Wellington’, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 215–275, especially at 242–243, Southey had criticised
                  the conduct of Dalrymple when, arriving in Portugal as commanding officer, he had, at the Convention of Cintra, signed 30 August
                  1808, allowed a defeated French army free passage out of the country with its weapons and supplies intact. Dalrymple responded by
                  sending papers giving his version of events; see Robert Southey to John Murray, 31 January 1816, Letter 2706. Southey was unable to
                  avoid the correspondence that he here wished to escape; see Robert Southey to Hew Dalrymple, 6 March 1816, Letter 2732.</note> The
               former alternative is the least evil of the two, &amp; the incivility is considerably lessened by his having addressed me not
               personally, but as the author of the paper in the Q Review.</p><p rend="indent1"> I need not tell you how ill it would become me to let myself in the great work of this history<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> be influenced by personal considerations.
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew</ref> evidently feels at this time that the judgement of <del>the</del> {a}
               Court of Inquiry is not definitive, – &amp; that the voice of history is so.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dalrymple was one
                  of the generals responsible for signing, on 30 August 1808, the Convention of Cintra, whereby the French army commanded by
                  Jean-Andoche Junot (1771–1813) and defeated by Anglo-Portuguese forces under Wellington at Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed to
                  retreat intact, with its weapons, from Portugal. Wellington, who did not sign the Convention, had been superseded in command by
                  Dalrymple and by Sir Harry Burrard (1755–1813; <title>DNB</title>). These veteran generals, just arrived in Iberia, were content to
                  make peace. After a national outcry in Britain, a Court of Inquiry was appointed 14 November–27 December 1808, which failed to
                  discipline Burrard and Dalrymple. They were, however, never afterwards given active command.</note> His letter communicates nothing
               which can in the slightest degree alter my opinion, what indeed could he communicate which had not appeared upon the Inquiry? – Far be
               it from me to speak of him with asperity, – <del>what</del> the fault which he committed was an error of judgement; – but a generous
               error it was; proceeding less from a want of local knowledge than from a want of political wisdom, &amp; a total ignorance of the means
               by which alone the contest in which we were engaged could be brought to a happy termination. I will <del>speak of</del> say every thing
               what can be said in his behalf, to represent things as they appeared to him: I will speak of him where I can (one of the letters which
               he has transmitted will enable me to do it) with commendation, – never with disrespect. But in this work I take a higher moral ground
               &amp; a wider political scope than historians have usually done; – &amp; write as I must answer for it to posterity &amp; to my own
               soul.</p><p rend="indent1"> You have never proposed to me a richer subject than <ref type="m" target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  Aikins</ref> Annals. To review it would be to sketch the outline of my intended Age of George 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Aikin, <title>Annals of the Reign of King George III</title> (1816) was not reviewed by Southey in
                  the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. (The book was no. 20 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.) Nor did Southey author a
                  history of the age of George III (1738–1820; King of the United Kingdom 1760–1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Do not fear that Ali Bey will escape too lightly thro my hands.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                  reviewed ‘Ali Bey’, i.e. Domingo Badia y Leblich (1766–1818), <title>Travels of Ali Bey in Morocco, Tripoli, Cyprus, Egypt, Arabia,
                     Syria, and Turkey, Between the Years 1803 and 1807</title> (1816) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (July 1816),
                  299–345.</note> Could you borrow to compare with him, a duodecimo volume about threescore years old by an Englishman who being made
               a slave in Barbary, performed the journey to Mecca, got home at last &amp; published his adventure. He was a West Country man (of
               Exeter if I recollect rightly) but whether his name were Pitts or Pellew I cannot recollect, – there are travels by men of both names,
               &amp; I have read both, – but it is nearly twenty years ago.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was thinking of Joseph
                  Pitts (1663–1735?; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A True and Faithful Account of the Religion and Manners of the Mohammetans</title>
                  (1704). Pitts was originally from Exeter and travelled to Mecca in about 1685. The other work was Thomas Pellow (1704–?), <title>The
                     History of the Long Captivity and Adventures of Thomas Pellow in South Barbary; Giving an Account of His being taken by two
                     Sallee Rovers and carry’d a Slave to Mequinez at Eleven Years of Age</title> (1739). Southey referenced Pitts’s work in a note to
                  the second edition of <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>, 2 vols (London, 1809), I, pp. 42–43.</note> It would be curious to
               ascertain whether this unpretending Englishman has not seen as much as this strange Spaniard, who having got leave to act the Renegado
               seems disposed to make all the advantage he can of the character for himself, – if not for the advancement of geographical
               knowledge.</p><p rend="indent1"> Thank you for Sir J Malcolm.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Malcolm (1769–1833; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>The History of Persia, from the most Early Period to the Present Time: containing an Account of the Religion, Government,
                     Usages, and Character of the Inhabitants of that Kingdom</title> (1815), no. 1662 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library, was
                  reviewed in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 236–292, by Southey’s friend Reginald Heber.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent2">Believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent3">Yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>