<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3042</idno><idno type="nines">rce4313</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3042. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles
                  Bedford, 26 November 1817</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3042.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47.
                  ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from
                     the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
                  80–83.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3042" type="letter"><head>3042. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles
                  Bedford</ref>, <date when="1817-11-26">26 November 1817</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
                  Postmark: E/ 29 NO 29/ 1817<lb/> Endorsements: 26 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1817;
                  26 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1817<lb/> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47.
                  ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from
                     the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
                  80–83.</note></head><opener><salute> My dear G.</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It is so long since I have written to you that you will I dare say
               give me credit for having been very busy the while, &amp; so in truth I have been,
               tho not in the way <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murraymagne</ref> would wish,
               or that you perhaps expect; – for I have not been <del>xxxxxxxx</del> {at work for
               the next Q.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Quarterly
                  Review</title>.</note>}, nor have I yet attempted to write ex officio upon the
               dismal occasion which has put us all in mourning,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#WalesCharlottePrincess">Princess
                  Charlotte</ref> had died in childbirth, after 18 months of
                  marriage, on 6 November. On 27 November, the day following this letter, Southey
                  drafted ‘Lines Written Upon the Death of the Princess Charlotte’, but these were
                  not published until they appeared in <title>The Amulet, or Christian and Literary
                     Remembrancer </title>(London, 1829), pp. 91–92. By 15 December 1817 Southey had
                  completed a ‘Funeral Song for the Princess Charlotte’, to serve as the Poet
                  Laureate’s New Year’s Ode for 1818; but this too was left unpublished for ten
                  years, when it appeared in <title>Friendship’s Offering: A Literary Album and
                     Christmas and New Year’s Present, for 1828</title> (London, 1828), pp. 1–6.
               </note> – the only occasion perhaps in which a public mourning ever carried with it
               so real a sense of sorrow. As soon as you left us, I finished the paper upon Lope de
               Vega, of which <del>xx</del> merely the beginning was written before.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">This paper was published as a review of Lord
                  Holland, <title>Some Account of the Lives and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega
                     Carpio, and Guillen de Castro</title> (1817), <title>Quarterly Review</title>,
                  18 (October 1817), 1–46.</note> Then I set steadily to work upon the Brazil, &amp;
               have been sedulously employed upon it every morning from that time; with the full
               intention (unless any unforeseen evil should prevent) of doing something to it
               (however little,) every day, till it is compleated. I have corrected four sheets,
               &amp; hope to keep the press going without intermission: the better to effect this I
               rise as soon as it is light, &amp; transcribe before breakfast.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of Brazil
                  </title>(1810–1819).</note> In the evenings I have paid off a heavy score of
               epistolary debts; – &amp; with a truant disposition, as if I had nothing to consult
               but the inclination of the hour have taken a good serious spell at the Life of
               Wesley, – which bids very fair to be a singularly curious book.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise
                     and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I would very – very fain be excused from any threnodial service,
               farther than what {must} needs be prepared for the <del>xx</del> Mus.Doc.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Master of the King’s Music, who was required
                  to set the Poet Laureate’s annual New Year’s Ode to music and conduct its
                  performance at St James’s Palace, though this ritual had not taken place since
                  1810. Sir William Parsons had died on 19 July 1817 and been replaced by <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShieldWilliam">William Shield</ref>.</note> But I see, from one or two
               private letters, that is it <hi rend="ital">looked for</hi>, &amp; it is no use to
               grumble at a task which I must not shrink from. In thinking over the matter, which
               you may be sure I have been going (even in fact at the time when I would willingly
               have persuaded myself that it was {not} a matter of necessity to undertake the task)
               a notion laid strong hold upon me, of producing something in distant imitation of
                  Boethius.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Anicius Manlius Severinus
                  Boethius (c. 480–525), <title>De Consolatione Philosophiae</title>, a dialogue
                  between the author and the character of Lady Philosophy, consisting of both prose
                  and verse. It urged endurance of life’s misfortunes and the certainty of
                  death.</note> In which instead of his Philosophia I should introduce Sir Thomas
                  More,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Thomas More (1478–1535;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor 1529–1532 and author of
                     <title>Utopia</title> (1516). He was executed for treason because he refused to
                  accept the Reformation of the Church of England and its break with Papal
                  suzerainty.</note> &amp; pass<del>xx xxxx</del> from the ostensible occasion of
               the book by an easy transition to a view of the prospect before us, compared with the
               state of things at the Reformation.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s idea bore fruit as <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the
                     Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> An obvious objection
               to this is that I make use of an event which ought to be my subject, merely as an
               introduction to something else, – perhaps this may be handsomely obviated by
               frequently recurring to it, &amp; bringing it again prominently forward at the end.
               You will perhaps hardly comprehend my scheme unless I <del>explain</del> {open} it a
               little more fully. There would be a mixture of verse as in Boethius, but the
                  <del>xxxx</del> bulk of the composition in prose, &amp; in colloquy between Sir T
               More &amp; Meipsum:<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Me–myself’.</note>
               how he of all persons should <del>xxx</del> think of paying Meipsum a visit you must
               trust me to explain: but you will at once perceive that no fitter personage could be
               introduced, he {having} taken pretty much the same view of affairs in his age, as I
               do in mine. – The <hi rend="ital">tone</hi> would of course be funereal, relieved by
               such imaginative parts as the introduction of one from another world would produce.
               And the main object is to show that we are rapidly approaching a <hi rend="ital">crisis</hi> in society (if indeed we have not actually reached it,) as <hi rend="ital">critical</hi> as that which the restoration of letters &amp; the
               discovery of printing brought with them in the days of Sir Thomas More. The extent
               about as much as a long paper in the review, – a little volume from 150 to 200 pages.
               These digressions are not very convenient for one who has so many huge undertakings
               in hand, &amp; has to provide for <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murraymagne</ref> also – I hope you like his new title.</p><p rend="indent1"> Oh my books! my books! Pray ask Cornaghi if he has heard any thing
               from Discacciati about them: that if not I may get <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> to inquire <del>about them</del>.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The firm of printsellers and art dealers at Cockspur St,
                  Charing Cross, headed by Paul Colnaghi (1751–1833; <title>DNB</title>). It was
                  handling the passage through London of the consignment of books that Southey had
                  purchased in Milan and that had been dispatched by Discacciati (dates unknown),
                  Southey’s guide in the city.</note> And if the larger consignment from Brussels be
               not arrived, I must write about these <del>xxx</del> also. </p><p rend="indent1"> Your pencils shall be looked after. The <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Grand Dormouse</ref> returned on Monday from
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouses</ref>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> is gone to London on business. I have not heard from
               <del>xx xxxxxx</del> {<ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Sirius</ref>} –
               Heaven knows when, – he might as well be in his own star for any thing I know of him.
               – Pulcheria is in great favour, &amp; sends a purr to Narses, – her countryman.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Cats belonging to Southey and Bedford. Both
                  Pulcheria (c. 398–453; Empress 450–453) and Narses (c. 478–566/574), a leading
                  general, were central figures in the early Byzantine Empire.</note> – I have put
               on my leathern jerkin for the first time to day. – And yesterday I dined at the
                  island,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">With General Peachy, who owned
                  Derwent Island House.</note> which as I certainly shall not have another
               invitation these six months, may <del>xx xxx</del> perhaps, (&amp; how possibly!) be
               the last time I shall ever dine out. And the wind is blowing. On the fells it is
               snowing: And the torrents flowing. And the women are sewing. And the <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General</ref> is going. And the oats are still growing, (they
               have got them so slow in – ) – &amp; my nose wants blowing, so farewell M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bedford.</p><closer><signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1817-11-26">26 Nov. 1817.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>