<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3026</idno><idno type="nines">rce4297</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3026. Robert Southey to John Murray, 4 October
                  1817</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3026.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42551. ALS; 3p.  .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3026" type="letter"><head>3026. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1817-10-04">4 October
                  1817</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London <lb/>
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb/> Postmark: E/ 7 OC 7 /1817 <lb/> Watermark: R E &amp; S BATH 1814<lb/> Endorsement: 1817 Oct 4 Southey
                  R<lb/> MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42551. ALS; 3p. <lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1817-10-04">4 Oct. 1817</date></dateline><salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have been very idle, or more truly speaking, very much engrossed by a succession of visitors. However I shall send
               you an article upon Lope de Vega in two or three days, – which besides a good many translations, will from his own writings establish
               certain facts in his history that have escaped <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> &amp; all his
               other biographers.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (October 1817), 1–46, Southey reviewed
                  Lord Holland, <title>Some Account of the Lives and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio, and Guillen de Castro</title>
                  (1817).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The parcel with Hoares Wiltshire is arrived, – I shall select from this book all that is useful &amp; return it
               speedily, – &amp; then I will forthwith put together my numerous sepulchral notes in a paper upon the Catacombs.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Richard Colt Hoare (1758–1838; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Ancient History of North and South
                     Wiltshire</title> (1812–1819), which Southey had asked for in connection with his review article ‘Cemeteries and Catacombs of
                  Paris’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 359–398. </note></p><p rend="indent1"> For the next number we <hi rend="ital"><hi rend="ital">must</hi></hi> take up the Poor Report,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman and Southey’s views on the poor appeared in the articles ‘On the Poor Laws’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>,
                  18 (January 1818), 259–308, and ‘On the Means of Improving the People’,<title> Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 79–118.
                  The former was ostensibly a review of several texts, including <title>Reports of the Select Committee on the Poor Laws</title>
                  (1817–1818).</note> because it will be acted upon next Session: &amp; we may at the same time do some good &amp; obtain some credit
               by writing upon the subject in time, &amp; with that knowledge which – I think I have obtained in great part, &amp; have within reach
               where farther information may be required. Besides this I should really very much like to take up <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> book, &amp; fight <del>xxx</del> his battle &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> &amp; my own, in which if I do not thrash <ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> more severely than <ref type="m" target="people.html#CoplestonEdward">Copplestone</ref> did<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Edinburgh Review</title> had continued its hostilities to
                  Wordsworth, Southey and Coleridge, publishing an attack on the latter’s <title>Biographia Literaria</title> (1817), <title>Edinburgh
                     Review</title>, 28 (August 1817), 488–515. The essay’s author was Hazlitt. Southey now wished to review <title>Biographia
                     Literaria</title> for the <title>Quarterly</title>, and use his article to attack Jeffrey, the <title>Edinburgh</title>’s editor.
                  Southey’s proposed review, which he here compares to Edward Copleston’s <title>A Reply to the Calumnies of the Edinburgh Review Against
                     Oxford</title> (1810), did not materialise. </note> – may my right hand forget its cunning.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Psalms</title> 137: 5. </note> Trust me with this, – I have some choice powder &amp; shot made up in
               cartridges, ready to fire off. If when it is done it be thought too personal for the Review, – (which I am well aware is the best
               battery) – in that case I can <del>only at last</del> make it more so, &amp; discharge it in a pamphlett but I have little doubt of
               making it fit the Review, – &amp; sure I am that it will make a report.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall like to see Evelyns Book,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of <title>Memoirs,
                     Illustrative of the Life and Writings of John Evelyn</title> (1818) appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April
                  1818), 1–54.</note> – he is a most interesting writer.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#HolroydJohnBaker">Lord Sheffield</ref> has sent me more papers. The time which is not given to the
               QR. just now is bestowed upon the first chapter,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular
                     War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), I, pp. 3–62.</note> – &amp; I am too much set upon both at present to allow myself
               leisure for writing farther.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yrs faithfully</salute><signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> Let me have N<hi rend="sup">o</hi><hi rend="ital">32</hi> in your next parcel. That wretch <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Hazlitt</ref> suspects me
                  of having reviewed the Round Table.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Hazlitt’s <title>The Round Table, a Collection of Essays
                        on Literature, Men and Manners</title> (1817) was reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 17 (number 33, not 32)
                     (April 1817), 154–159. The identity of the reviewer is not certain.</note> Fool as well as scoundrel! When I deal with him (for
                     <hi rend="ital">he</hi> it is who has reviewed <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>) he shall
                  learn to know the sting of a scorpion from that of a gnat.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>