<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2954</idno><idno type="nines">rce4225</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2954. Robert Southey to Joseph
                  Cottle [fragment], [c. 24 March 1817] </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2954.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>MS untraced; text is taken from
                  Joseph Cottle, Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert
                     Southey (London, 1847). .  Previously  published: Joseph Cottle,
                     Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey
                  (London, 1847), pp. 234–235 [in part]. Dating note: Dating from Joseph Cottle
                  to Robert Southey, 27 March 1817, which records that he had ‘just received’ a
                  letter from Southey; see Lynda Pratt, ‘The “sad habits” of Samuel Taylor
                  Coleridge: Unpublished Letters from Joseph Cottle to Robert Southey, 1813–1817’,
                     Review of English Studies, n.s. 55 (2004), 88. Note on the
                  text: Cottle is notorious for his cavalier treatment of correspondence, and it is
                  possible that the postscript he published as part of this letter ([c. 24 March
                  1817]) did not belong to it, but was taken from another letter of Southey’s which
                  does not appear to have survived but dated from late March or early April 1817.
                  This is suggested by the postscript’s mention of Southey’s pamphlet A
                     Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P., which was not begun until 26 March
                  1817; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 26 March 1817, Letter 2957.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2954" type="letter"><head>2954. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph
                  Cottle</ref> [fragment], <date when="1817-03-24">[c. 24 March 1817] </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from
                  Joseph Cottle, <title>Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert
                     Southey</title> (London, 1847).<lb/> Previously published: Joseph Cottle,
                     <title>Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey</title>
                  (London, 1847), pp. 234–235 [in part].<lb/> Dating note: Dating from Joseph Cottle
                  to Robert Southey, 27 March 1817, which records that he had ‘just received’ a
                  letter from Southey; see Lynda Pratt, ‘The “sad habits” of Samuel Taylor
                  Coleridge: Unpublished Letters from Joseph Cottle to Robert Southey, 1813–1817’,
                     <title>Review of English Studies</title>, n.s. 55 (2004), 88.<lb/> Note on the
                  text: Cottle is notorious for his cavalier treatment of correspondence, and it is
                  possible that the postscript he published as part of this letter ([c. 24 March
                  1817]) did not belong to it, but was taken from another letter of Southey’s which
                  does not appear to have survived but dated from late March or early April 1817.
                  This is suggested by the postscript’s mention of Southey’s pamphlet <title>A
                     Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title>, which was not begun until 26 March
                  1817; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 26 March 1817, Letter 2957.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Cottle,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> You will have seen by the papers, that some villain, after an
               interval of three and twenty years, has published my old uncle, ‘Wat Tyler.’ I have
               failed in attempting to obtain an injunction, because a false oath has been taken,
               for the purpose of defeating me.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                  refers to the affair of his Jacobin drama <title>Wat Tyler</title>, which he had
                  written in 1794 and sent to James Ridgway (1755–1838) and Henry Symonds
                  (1741–1816), radical booksellers, for publication; see Robert Southey to Edith
                  Fricker, [c. 12 January 1795], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey.
                     Part One</title>, Letter 123. Ridgway and Symonds did not publish it and it
                  remained in manuscript until a pirated publication, designed to embarrass the now
                  anti-Jacobin Southey, appeared in 1817. Having taken advice from <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>, Southey
                  launched a suit in Chancery in order to gain an injunction suppressing the
                  publication, on the grounds that it breached his copyright. The case was heard on
                  18–19 March 1817 and, in Southey’s view, lost because of perjury in an affidavit
                  given to the court by William Winterbotham, who swore that Southey had,
                  when visiting Newgate prison, where Winterbotham, Ridgway and Symonds were all
                  confined, given the manuscript of <title>Wat Tyler</title> and the copyright to
                  Winterbotham and Daniel Isaac Eaton (1753–1814; <title>DNB</title>), to do with as
                  they liked. Southey referred to <title>Wat Tyler</title> as his ‘uncle’ because of
                  his family connections – he had three uncles with the surname ‘Tyler’.</note> * *
               * *</p><p rend="indent1"> I am glad to see, and you will be very glad to hear, that this
               business has called forth <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, and with the recollections of old times, brought back
               something like old feelings.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to
                  Samuel Taylor Coleridge, 21 March 1817 (Letter 2949): ‘I have no reason to regret
                  the apparition of my Uncle Wat, since with the recollection of old times, it has
                  brought back some of their feelings also’.</note> He wrote a very excellent paper
               on the subject in the ‘Courier,’<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge
                  wrote in defence of Southey in the <title>Courier</title> on 17, 18 and 27 March
                  1817 and 2 April 1817. However, he did not visit Greta Hall.</note> and I hope it
               will be the means of his rejoining us ere long; so good will come out evil, and the
               devil can do nothing but what he is permitted.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am well in health, and as little annoyed by this rascality as it
               becomes me to be. The only thing that has vexed me, is the manner in which my counsel
               is represented in talking about my being ashamed of the work as a wicked
                  performance!<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was aggrieved at
                  the case made by his lawyers, Sir Anthony Hart (c. 1754–1831; <title>DNB</title>)
                  and Sir Lancelot Shadwell (1779–1850; <title>DNB</title>), as reported in e.g.
                     <title>Morning Post</title>, 19 March 1817, when pleading for an injunction to
                  stop the publication of <title>Wat Tyler</title>: ‘it was of the utmost importance
                  that the dissemination of a work, professing such wicked and mischievous
                  sentiments, both as it regarded the public welfare, and the character of the
                  individual, who had long since disavowed the sentiments contained in it, should be
                  immediately stopped’.</note> Wicked! My poor ‘old uncle’ has nothing wicked about
               him. It was the work of a right-honest enthusiast, as you can bear witness; of one
               who was as upright in his youth as he has been in his manhood, and is now in the
               decline of his life; who, blessed be God, has little to be ashamed before man, of any
               of his thoughts, words, or actions, whatever cause he may have for saying to his
               Maker, ‘God be merciful to me a sinner.’<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Luke</title> 18: 13.</note> God bless you, my old and affectionate
               friend, </p><closer><signed rend="indent1">Robert Southey. </signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> I am writing a pamphlet, in the form of a letter, to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">Wm. Smith</ref>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title>
                     (1817).</note> Fear not, but that I shall make my own cause good, and set my
                  foot on my enemies. This has been a wicked transaction. It can do me no other harm
                  than the expense to which it has put me. </p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>