<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3089</idno><idno type="nines">rce4360</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3089. Robert Southey to Walter
                  Scott, 10 March 1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3089.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 3889.
                  ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life
                     and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV,
                  pp. 295–297.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3089" type="letter"><head>3089. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter
                  Scott</ref>, <date when="1818-03-10">10 March 1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Scott Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Abbotsford/ near/ Melrose<lb/> Stamped: [partial]
                  KESWICK<lb/> Endorsement: Southey<lb/> MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 3889.
                  ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life
                     and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV,
                  pp. 295–297.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1818-03-10"> 10 March. 1818</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear Scott</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your last letter reached me in London, when I was just setting out
               for the Continent.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In early May
                  1817.</note> Three months of continual movement, exertion &amp; excitement were of
               great use both to my health &amp; spirits. During that time I saw the outside of
               Paris, the best parts of Switzerland, crost the Alps twice, got as far as Milan,
               returned by way of the Black Forest &amp; Frankfort, &amp; so from Mentz to Cologne
               by the left bank of the Rhine, bringing back a store of recollections for the rest of
               my life. Few persons have ever had a stronger appetite for travelling than I have,
               tho I sit at home till I almost grow to my chair.</p><p rend="indent1"> Our home scenery was somewhat diminished by the comparison, yet less
               so than might have been expected, &amp; this impression soon wore off after my
               return. The poverty of our vales was more striking after the chesnuts on the Italian
               side of the Alps &amp; the magnificent walnuts of Switzerland. Switzerland is
               certainly the country in which an Englishman who should chuse to live abroad would
               find manners &amp; feelings the least unlike his own, – that is, in the Protestant
               cantons: but I did not go far enough South for the <del>xxx</del> blessings of a
               climate which would vie with that of Portugal.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am glad that the first tidings which informed me of your illness,
               told of your recovery also. There is an enjoyment of our absent friends, – even of
               those from whom we are far distant, – in talking &amp; thinking of them, which make a
               large part of the happiness of life. It is a great thing to be in the same place with
               a friend – it is something to be in the same planet. And whenever you are removed to
               a better, there are few men whose loss will be more widely felt in this, – for I know
               no one who had administered so much delight to so extensive a part of the public. – I
                  <del>if</del> {hope} your illness has left no weakness behind it. We stand in need
               sometimes of visitations which may lead us to look toward eternity, – &amp; in such
               cases the stroke is merciful when it falls upon the body. There is a joyousness too
               in the sense of returning health, a freshness of <del>xxxx</del> sensation such as
                  <del>xx</del> one might expect from a draught from the fountain of youth.</p><p rend="indent1"> In the course of the summer I shall make my appearance before you in
               the shape of <del>quarto</del> a third quarto, which concludes my long Brazilian
                  labours.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The third volume of Southey’s
                     <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> There will be much curious
               matter respecting the mines, the equestrian tribes, &amp; the Jesuits, – great part
               from manuscript materials, &amp; the whole altogether new to the British public. – I
               have full accounts of all that occurred <del>at</del> {in} Pernambuco, a deplorable
               story it is! The prime mover was a man with whose private history I was well
               acquainted, &amp; with whom indeed I was in habits of communication, tho not
                  directly.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Joam Ribeiro Pessoa de Melo
                  Montenegro (1766–1817), a priest who was a member of the provisional government
                  set up by a group of revolutionaries in Pernambuco, 8 March–18 May 1817. He
                  committed suicide in the town of Paulista after the defeat of the revolutionary
                  forces and the fall of Recife, the provincial capital.</note> I had sent him my
               first volume, – &amp; the second was on the way to him, when he brought this
               destruction upon himself. The Revolution was planned by a few men, far gone in
               American politics &amp; French philosophy: – &amp; the great landholders when it was
               begun joined in, more from fear than inclination. But there had been an attempt to
               establish a commonwealth in Pernambuco about a century ago,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Mascate War (or ‘War of the Peddlers’) in Pernambuco,
                  Brazil in 1710–1711, between landowners based around Olinda and merchants in
                  Recife (backed by the colonial government). The landowners’ leaders were the first
                  to call for Brazil to become an independent Republic.</note> in which their
               ancestors had been engaged, – so that their wishes lay that way. I have the history
               of that attempt, the mss was <del>xxx</del> copied from the original in 1810 by P.
               Joam Ribeiro, – who at that very time no doubt was meditating his more disastrous
               explosion, – &amp; from his transcript mine was made.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Guerra Civil ou Sedissoens de Pernambuco Exemplo Memoravel aos
                  vindouros’, no. 3840 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> On that
               occasion the Government behaved with remarkable lenity, &amp; did not put a single
               person to death. A bloody vengeance has been exacted now, &amp; in the worst manner,
               – the worst actors have escaped &amp; assisted in the punishment of others far less
               guilty than themselves, – &amp; the mob have been allowed to commit great outrages
               &amp; <del>xx</del> cruelties. At present they have a Governor<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Major-General Luis do Rego Barreto (1777–1840), Governor of
                  Pernambuco 1817–1821. He was a distinguished military commander in the Peninsular
                  War 1808–1813.</note> who acts humanely as well as firmly, &amp; are, of course,
               under military law. The Quarterly is not quite accurate in what it says of an
               Englishmans interference.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The review by
                  Reginald Heber of the second volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title>
                  (1810–1819) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (October 1817), 99–128: ‘in
                  Pernambuco (we speak from accurate information) it was only the interposition of
                  an Englishman resident in the country, which prevented the city, during the short
                  government of the liberals, from rivalling jacobin France in its scenes of
                  extravagance and blood’ (125).</note> That Englishman was my friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Henry Koster</ref>, what he did was this, – he prevented the leaders of
               the Revolution, when they found their cause desperate, from butchering all the
               Loyalists in prison, &amp; setting fire to the city, as they had resolved to do. [MS
               obscured] I have <del>x</del> a list of all who have suffered, or are still [MS torn]
               &amp; it is a melancholy thing to see it filled with family names which I have [MS
               torn] written for honour.</p><p rend="indent1"> About four months ago <ref type="m" target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">John Ballantyne</ref> wrote to ask me if he
               should dispose of my property in the Ed. An. Register to Constable<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had written the historical sections of the
                     <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808–1811</title> (1810–1813) and had
                  agreed to take up a 1/12th share in the concern. However, he had not been paid for
                  his final year’s work on the <title>Register</title> and feared the financial
                  difficulties of the Ballantynes had rendered his share in the venture worthless.
                  The Ballantynes were winding up their publishing business and Archibald Constable
                  (1774–1827; <title>DNB</title>), publisher of Scott and the <title>Edinburgh
                     Review</title>, had agreed to take over some of their concerns. What Scott did
                  not reveal to Southey was that he was himself deeply involved in the financial
                  affairs of both the Ballantynes and Constable.</note> upon the same terms as those
               of {the} other persons who had the same stake in it. – As I had given it up for a
               lost concern I was very glad to hear that I was to have about the same sum which the
               share had cost, in a bill from Constable at twelvemonths date: four months however
               have elapsed, &amp; I have heard nothing farther. Perhaps, if you have an
               opportunity, you will do me the kindness to ask how the matter stands.</p><p rend="indent1"> The neighbouring county is in an uproar already with the expected
                  election<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A general election was
                  imminent, though the House of Commons was not dissolved until 10 June 1818. It was
                  already clear, though, that there would be a contest in Westmorland, which was
                  dominated by the Lowther family, who were supporters of the government – the two
                  sitting MPs were the brothers Henry Lowther (1790–1867), MP for Westmorland
                  1812–1867 and William, Viscount Lowther (1787–1872), later 2nd Earl of Lonsdale
                  and MP for Cockermouth 1808–1813, MP for Westmorland 1813–1831 and 1832–1841. So
                  complete was the Lowthers’ dominance that the last contested election in
                  Westmorland was in 1774. However, in January 1818, a committee of Whigs and
                  smaller landowners had brought forward Henry Brougham to challenge the Lowthers –
                  Brougham’s family home was Brougham Hall near Penrith and he could plausibly be
                  presented as a local candidate.</note> – <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref>
               has succeeded in producing as much turbulence there as he could desire – &amp; if we
               may judge of what the play will be by what the rehearsal has been, <del>xxxx</del> it
               may prove a very serious tragedy before it is over. I am out of the sphere of this
               mischief. – We shall have mobs I think upon the Poor Law question <del>xxxx</del>
               which is as perilous in its nature as a Corn Bill<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Corn Law (1815), which excluded the import of corn until
                  domestic prices reached 80 shillings per quarter and, so raised bread prices, had
                  produced considerable popular protest.</note> &amp; yet must be taken in hand. I
               know not whether the next Q. R. will look the danger in the face &amp; say honestly
               that we must be prepared to meet it.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Rickman’s article on the poor, ‘On the Poor Laws’, appeared in
                     the<title> Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 259–308, published on 9
                  June 1818.</note> Preventive measures are very easy &amp; would be found
               effectual. – How grievously do we want some man of commanding spirit in the H. of
               Commons to do constantly what <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> only rouses
               himself to do now &amp; then. There is however good promise in the S. General<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Robert Gifford (1779–1826;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Solicitor-General 1817–1819, Attorney-General 1819–1824,
                  Chief Justice 1824, Master of the Rolls 1824–1826.</note>– to him I think we may
               look with hope &amp; to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Peel">Peel</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> I saw Humboldt<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander
                  von Humboldt (1769–1859), the traveller, scientist and, in his voluminous
                  writings, the leading authority on South America.</note> at Paris <del>xxxx</del>
               never did any man pourtray himself more perfectly in his writings than he has done!
               His excessive volubility, his fullness of information &amp; the rapidity with which
               he fled from every fact into some wide generalization <del>xxx</del> made you
                  <del>xxxxxxxxx</del> {more} acquainted with his intellectual character in half an
               hour than you would be with any other persons in half a year. Withal he appeared
               exceedingly good natured &amp; obliging. It was at Mackenzies<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Colin Alexander Mackenzie (?1778–1851), a wealthy Scot who was
                  employed on a number of delicate diplomatic missions and may well have been a
                  government spy. In 1815 he was appointed one of the Commissioners of Liquidation,
                  Arbitration and Deposit, who adjudicated on claims by British citizens for loss of
                  property against the French government. Southey dined with him on 17 May and 19
                  May 1817, meeting Humboldt on the latter occasion.</note> that I met him.</p><p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">Mrs Scott</ref> &amp; your
                  daughter<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte Sophia Scott
                  (1799–1837). She married John Gibson Lockhart in 1820.</note> – who is now, I
               expect, the flower of the Tweed.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Believe me my dear Scott</salute><salute rend="indent2"> ever affectionately yours</salute><signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>