<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3023</idno><idno type="nines">rce4294</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3023. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, [10 September 1817] </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3023.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery. ALS; 2p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3023" type="letter"><head>3023. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1817-09-10">[10 September 1817] </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: Probably written soon
                  after the last<lb/> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
                  Unpublished.<lb/> Dating note: Dating from content.</note></head><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> frank will cover a few hasty lines.
                  Marianne<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Anne Gonne (b. 1792),
                  sister of Louisa, Henry Herbert Southey’s wife, had married, in 1816, Thomas March
                  (1781–1859), a British merchant from a family prominent in the trade with
                  Portugal.</note> got Rattons book for me from her husband.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacques Ratton (1736–1820), a Portuguese businessman in exile
                  in Britain, who published his memoirs in London under the title <title>Recordações
                     de Jacome Ratton: Sobre Ocorrências do seu Tempo, de Maio de 1747 a Setembro de
                     1810</title> (1813). This volume was listed as no. 3442 in the sale catalogue
                  of Southey’s library, with a note as to its origin: ‘This book was printed only
                  for private distribution. <hi rend="ital">Robert Southey, from Mr. March, London,
                     15 Aug. 1817</hi>.’</note> I perfectly remember the face of the man, tho I
               never till now knew to whom it belonged. There is less in the book than there ought
               to be, – still there is something which will be of use.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Koster</ref> has sent me the
               transcript of a large packet from <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">her son</ref>
               containing the details of the Insurrection. The chiefs were about to set fire to the
               city, &amp; murder their prisoners, – <del>xxxx xxxxxxxxx</del> he seems to have been
               greatly instrumental in preventing this latter crime.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">An attempted revolution in the Brazilian province of Pernambuco
                  March–May 1817. Koster was based in the area and was a witness to the events in
                  the provincial capital, Recife.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I hear nothing of my books from Milan or Brussels this is because
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> is in Ireland, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> on his way here from Wales, – all information concerning
               them must come thro these channels.</p><p rend="indent1"> The French Anecdotes of Pombal in one volume which I picked up at
               Tournay, bear the false date of <hi rend="ital">Warsaw</hi>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Anecdotes du Ministère de Sébastien-Joseph Carvalho,
                     Comte d’Overas, Marquis de Pombal</title> (Warsaw, 1783), no. 46 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey’s library. Sebastião José de Carvalho e Melo, 1st Marquess of
                  Pombal (1699–1782), was effectively Prime Minister of Portugal 1750–1777. </note>
               There is much curious matter in them about Maranham, – but there is the gross
               absurdity of supposing that the assassination<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph I (1714–1777; King of Portugal 1750–1777). An alleged assassination
                  attempt on him in 1758 was used by Pombal to justify the suppression of his
                  opponents and the Jesuit order.</note> was a trick of the ministers, in which the
               King was either his dupe or his accomplice. A number of the Correio Brazil, which I
               received yesterday contains the Alvara of 1768 against the Puritanos, which the
               Editor says has never before been printed.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The London-based journal <title>Correio Braziliense</title>, 18 (May 1817),
                  473–481, printed the alvara, or declaration, issued on 5 October 1768 by Pombal
                  against Portuguese nobles labelled as ‘Puritans’ because they wished to preserve
                  the distinctions between descendants of Jewish converts and other
                  Portuguese.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I am at work upon the Mines, &amp; upon the effects produced by the
               introduction of <del>xx</del> horses &amp; <del>the xxxx</del> kine in S America, – a
               chapter upon the Equestrian tribes.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapters 36 and 38, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London,
                  1810–1819), III, pp. 246–298, 374–441.</note> This will be very curious. I was
               lucky enough to find at Paris Azaras book upon the quadrupeds of Paraguay,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Felix Manuel de Azara (1742–1821), Spanish
                  solider, engineer and naturalist. Southey’s copy of <title>Essais sur l’Histoire
                     Naturelle des Quadrupedes de la Province du Paraguay</title> (1801) was no. 89
                  in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> – which I had scent of before but
               knew not where to seek for it. </p><p rend="indent1"> You will be glad to hear that a new channel has been presented for
               obtaining books from Madrid. Kinder (to whom I acknowledge obligations in the last
               preface) has a house of business in that city &amp; thro him we can obtain whatever
               we want.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey refers to the merchant
                  Thomas Kinder (c. 1781–1846), who had witnessed at first-hand the events in Buenos
                  Aires in 1808–1810 that led to the independence of the states of the Rio de la
                  Plata. Kinder had lent Southey his journal and ‘a volume of Noticias del Paraguay,
                  and the prose Argentina, both in manuscript’, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3
                  vols (London, 1810–1819), II, p. [v].</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The Rickmans<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Susannah Rickman</ref> and
                  their children: Anne (b. 1808); William Charles (1812–1886); and Frances (dates
                  unknown).</note> have been here twelve days, &amp; they depart tomorrow.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">Love to my <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">Aunt</ref> &amp; the Orsini<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Hills’ children.</note></salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1817-09-10">Wednesday. </date><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>