<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2713</idno><idno type="nines">rce3984</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2713. Robert Southey to Wade Browne, 11 February
                  1816</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2713.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>British Library, Add MS 47891. AL; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2713" type="letter"><head>2713. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BrowneWade">Wade Browne</ref>, <date when="1616-02-11">11 February
                  1816</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To Wade Browne Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Ludlow<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb/> MS: British Library, Add MS 47891. AL; 4p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1816-02-11">11. Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1816</date></dateline><salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> During the month of November I expected to have seen you at Ludlow &amp; from day to day hoped I should be able to
               inform you on what day <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> myself &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> should set off from London in that direction. We were engaged to halt at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Wynnstay">Wynnstay</ref>, &amp; at Liverpool on the after part of our journey. But the state of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith’s</ref> health which seemed to grow worse instead of better in London made us
               very anxious to reach home, especially when winter was so close at hand; she herself seemed to pine for her native air, &amp; we were
               compelled to take the straightest road on that account, leaving all our friends unvisited. This was a great mortification.</p><p rend="indent1"> We had been a long journey. A proposition of my brother <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henrys</ref> who was going with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">his bride</ref> to Brussels, induced me to
               determine upon a visit to Waterloo:<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Site of the decisive battle which ended the Napoleonic Wars
                  on 18 June 1815.</note> &amp; the scheme ended in my taking the two Ediths with me, missing the family party which we intended to
               join, &amp; falling in with another company,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMr">Thomas</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMrs">Elizabeth Vardon</ref>, and <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Edward Nash</ref>.</note> strangers till that time, with whom we kept from our first meeting in
               the Ostend packet, till we separated at their house at Greenwich on our return. I think you have been in Flanders, – you will not
               wonder therefore if I was delighted with the towns, the country, &amp; the people. Of all <del>towns</del> cities which I have ever
               seen Bruges is the most striking, of all countries the Pays de Wals that in which industry has been most wisely directed &amp; most
               bountifully rewarded.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> This area comprises part of the modern provinces of East Flanders in
                  Belgium and Zeeland.</note> Our route after having seen the three fields of battle, (Waterloo, Les Quatre Bras, &amp; Ligny<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Les Quatre Bras, Belgium, was a strategic crossroads at which French and Allied armies fought on
                  16 June 1815; on the same day at nearby Ligny, Napoleon’s forces defeated the Prussian army.</note>) was to Namur, Huy, Liege, Spa
               &amp; Aix la Chapelle<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Present-day Aachen, Germany.</note>: at which last place we arrived under
               very distressing circumstances. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> had been seized with a bad sore throat
               the preceding night at Herve – a place where it <del>xx</del> was impossible to remain; when we reached Aix she was in a high fever. It
               was in fact an attack of scarlet fever. We were fortunate enough to find a physician who had been educated at Edinburgh<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gerhard Reumont (1765–1828), eminent Belgian doctor, who had studied at Edinburgh University in
                  1792–1793. Reumont visited Edward Jenner (1749–1823; <title>DNB</title>), the pioneer of vaccination against smallpox, in 1800 and
                  introduced Jenner’s discoveries to the Continent. He also enjoyed literary pursuits, and when Southey revisited Aix-la-Chapelle in
                  1817, he took with him, at Reumont’s request, a copy of Thomas Percy (1729–1811; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Reliques of Ancient
                     English Poetry</title> (1765).</note> – &amp; the disease is seldom formidable in that country; – but except in this instance we
               experienced every imaginable kind of inconvenience &amp; discomfort from the incivility &amp; brutality of the people at the Hotel.
               Happily the disorder was of no long continuance, &amp; we were only detained there from Wednesday till the Tuesday following.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s party were in Aix-la-Chapelle 10–17 October 1815.</note> The interval when our
               uneasiness abated was well employed – for I fell in at the Table d’hote with some Prussian officers of distinction, &amp; there on
               account of their wounds – one of whom was that Aid-de-Camp of Bluchers who was ridden over with him in the battle of the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> At Ligny, Gebhard Leberecht von Blücher (1742–1819), Field Marshal in
                  command of the Prussian army, was trapped under his horse and ridden over by cavalry. The officer whom Southey met was Ferdinand
                  Augustus Leopold Francis von Dresky (dates unknown), who commanded the 2nd Regiment of Silesian infantry at Ligny.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> From Aix we turned our faces homewards by way of Maestricht, Tongres, Tirlemont &amp; Louvain to Brussels. I then gave
               a second day to Waterloo: – we had <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">an artist</ref> in our company, &amp; went now chiefly
               for the sake of obtaining views of the more interesting part of the ground.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Engravings of seven
                  of Nash’s sketches were included in Southey’s <title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> We then went to
               Antwerp, Ghent, Courtray, Ypres, Bergue, Dunkirk &amp; Calais – &amp; were caught on our passage to Dover in the beginning of a storm,
               which did not end before some vessels were lost on the Goodwin sands. We were absent from England five weeks, &amp; were as much longer
               before we could leave London.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will probably guess at what has been my chief occupation since my return. In the course of a few weeks I hope to
               send you my ‘Pilgrimage to Waterloo’. The poem is nearly compleated, – I say nothing of the battle, that is I make no attempt at
               delineating it in verse, – it is enough to have done that in prose, – but I describe the ground minutely such as it was when we saw it,
               &amp; thus accompanied as it will be with views of all the most memorable points of the action will give a certain kind of interest
               &amp; value to the book, whatever it may prove in other respects.</p><p rend="indent1"> Never did the English character stand so high as at that time in that country. the soldiers were as much admired for
               their good conduct as for their courage, whereas the Prussians were universally execrated. This is the effect of the military spirit
               which old Frederick<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frederick II (1712–1786; King of Prussia 1740–1786).</note> infused into
               the nation. There seemed to be a very general sense of instability among the people, – a persuasion that things could not continue as
               they were, – a dissatisfaction at the arrangements which had been made, &amp; – especially in Liege, a sense of the injustice of
                  <del>xxxxxxxx</del> throwing them over to a foreign prince.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> At the Congress of Vienna
                  (1815), the United Kingdom of the Netherlands was created by joining together the Dutch Republic with the Austrian Netherlands and
                  the Bishopric of Liege. The sovereign was William I (1772–1843; King of the Netherlands 1815–1840), who was perceived as a foreign
                  prince by many of his new subjects from the Austrian Netherlands and Liege.</note> The prevailing wish appeard to be that things
               should be restored to their former state such as they were before the French Revolution. They dated all their evils from thence. I
               found it very generally believed that Buonapartes return from Elba<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 26 February 1815
                  Napoleon Bonaparte (1769–1821; Emperor of the French 1804–1814, 1815) escaped from imprisonment on the Isle of Elba, returning to
                  France to begin the ‘Hundred Days’ of rule that ended at Waterloo.</note> was the work of English, &amp; argued upon the absurdity
               of this notion without effect. The answer was – if it were not so – why did you not put him to death.</p><p rend="indent1"> Is Wade<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wade Browne (1796–1851), only son of Wade Browne and later a country
                  gentleman at Monkton Farleigh in Somerset. He was at this time a student of Trinity College, Cambridge (B.A. 1819 and M.A
                  1822).</note> at Cambridge? Have an eye to the fever there I entreat you. It reappeared in the autumn, – &amp; the medical men know
               not how to treat it.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> was very unwell in London. The effects of her illness hung upon her
               &amp; she was tormented with tooth ache during half the time of her stay, even after the guilty tooth was extracted. She recovered
               immediately on her return – the effect of her native air seemed to act like magic. Remember me most kindly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Browne</ref> &amp; your daughters<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  Wade Browne’s daughters from his first marriage: Lydia (c. 1789–1864); <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneElizabethdau">Elizabeth</ref>; and <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneSarah">Sarah</ref>: and Mary Browne (dates unknown), his only child
                  from his second marriage.</note> &amp; believe me my dear Sir</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">yrs most truly</salute> [remainder of MS missing]</closer></div></body></text></TEI>