<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2943</idno><idno type="nines">rce4214</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2943. Robert Southey to William
                  Smith, 17 March 1817</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2943.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Berg Collection, New York
                  Public Library. ALS; 3p.  .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2943" type="letter"><head>2943. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">William
                  Smith</ref>, <date when="1817-03-17">17 March 1817</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Berg Collection, New York
                  Public Library. ALS; 3p. <lb/> Unpublished.<lb/> Note on MS: The letter survives
                  as an early draft, which is reproduced here. Southey made a fair copy, which
                  appears not to have survived, and he sent this as an enclosure to Charles Watkin
                  Williams Wynn on 17 March, 1817, Letter 2944. Wynn’s absence from home meant there
                  was a delay in his receiving it. By the time he did so, the debate had moved on
                  and so Southey decided to incorporate this letter into his pamphlet <title>A
                     Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title> (1817).</note></head><p rend="center"> For the Courier.</p><p rend="center"> ———</p><p rend="center"> To William Smith Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P.</p><p rend="indent1"> Sir</p><p rend="indent1"> You have thought proper to attack me in the House of Commons in
               language which I shall not imitate, – however fitly it might be applied to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> William Smith.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Smith
                  had denounced Southey in the House of Commons on 14 March 1817 in the debate on
                  the Seditious Meetings Bill, condemning ‘the settled, determined malignity of a
                  renegado’ and comparing Southey’s arguments against radical views in the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 227, with those expressed
                  in <title>Wat Tyler</title> (1817), Act 2, lines 103–112.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> You call upon the Government to prosecute me for a work written in
               the year 1794, &amp; now first published, for motives which cannot be mistaken, by
               some person as little scrupulous as yourself concerning the means by which he may
               gratify the malignity of factious feeling.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1794 Southey had sent James Ridgway (1755–1838) and Henry Symonds
                  (1741–1816), radical booksellers, then in Newgate prison, a copy of his Jacobin
                  drama <title>Wat Tyler</title>; see Robert Southey to Edith Fricker, [c. 12
                  January 1795], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>,
                  Letter 123. Ridgway and Symonds did not publish it and it remained in manuscript
                  until a pirated publication, designed to embarrass the now anti-Jacobin Southey,
                  appeared in 1817. Having taken advice from <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>, Southey launched a suit in
                  Chancery so as to gain an injunction suppressing the publication. His case was not
                  heard until 18–19 March 1817.</note> And you bring it as a heinous charge against
               me that having entertained wild &amp; extravagant notions of liberty in my youth,
               three &amp; twenty years should have produced a change in the opinions of one whose
               life has been devoted to unremitting study, &amp; who may say <del>to</del> in the
               words of Bentley to you &amp; to such as you, that he has forgotten more than ever
               you learnt.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Bentley (1662–1742;
                     <title>DNB</title>), classical scholar and Master of Trinity College,
                  Cambridge. Richard Cumberland (1732–1811; <title>DNB</title>) had reported that
                  when a schoolmaster had promised to make Cumberland as learned as his grandfather,
                  Richard Bentley, the latter had exclaimed to the schoolmaster: ‘Pshaw, Arthur, how
                  can that be, when I have forgot more than thou ever knew’st?’, <title>Memoirs of
                     Richard Cumberland. Written by Himself</title>, 2 vols (London, 1807), II, p.
                  33. </note></p><p rend="indent1"> In my youth I fell into the political opinions which the French
               Revolution scattered over Europe. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> William Smith may possibly
               be acquainted with other persons who were republicans at that time, &amp; have long
               since ceased to be so with as little impeachment of their integrity as their
               judgement. From the metaphysics &amp; the atheism which were usually connected with
               those principles, I was at all times free: &amp; instead of connecting myself with
               clubs at home, I gave up the course of life for which I had been designed, &amp; the
               prospects of advancement in any professional line, which it will be no presumption
               for me now to say were within my reach,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey left Balliol College, Oxford without a degree in 1794 and declined to
                  become a clergyman as he could not subscribe to the Church of England’s
                  Thirty-Nine Articles.</note> – that I might retire into the wilds of America,
               &amp; there with a few persons as inexperienced &amp; as enthusiastic as myself, lay
               the foundations of a community upon what we believed to be the system of Christian
               equality. It matters not in what manner that purpose, happily for ourselves, was
                  <del>xxxx</del> frustrated. Erroneous as it was, God forbid that I should ever
               feel ashamed of such an error! And God be thanked that the intemperate &amp;
               misapplied expression of the opinions upon which I proceeded before I was twenty
               years of age, – is the worst offence with which I can be charged by <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Brougham</ref>,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey may be referring to Brougham’s speech on the Seditious
                  Meetings Bill in the House of Commons on 24 February 1817, when he contrasted the
                  unwillingness of the government to prosecute Southey’s early radical play
                     <title>Wat Tyler</title>, with its pursuit of radical writers.</note> sore as
               he is from many a well-merited chastisement, – by the gratuitous hostility of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith, &amp; by Envy, Hatred, Malice
               &amp; all Uncharitableness.</p><p rend="indent1"> You believe that I was sincere when, according to your own judgement
               (&amp; it is one of the very few subject on which I agree with it) {my opinions} were
               grossly erroneous; &amp; you do not believe that the course of years &amp; events may
               have corrected me where I was wrong, &amp; confirmed me in what was right. The events
               of the last five &amp; twenty years have been lost upon you, &amp; perhaps you judge
               of me by yourself. This Sir you may think a fair criterion, but I must protest
               against being measured by any such standard.</p><p rend="indent1"> The offence which I have committed is, that I did not transfer to the
               French Emperor<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte
                  (1769–1821; First Consul 1799–1804; Emperor of the French 1804–1814, 1815).</note>
               that interest which at one time I felt for the French Republic; – that I did feel
               that same interest for the Spaniards, &amp; to the best of my power proclaimed the
               opinion that perseverance against Bonaparte would be crowned with success, – standing
               upon firm ground, when you were stuck fast in the Slough of Despond.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">In John Bunyan (1628–1688; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>Pilgrim’s Progress</title> (1678–1684), a bog into which Christian sinks
                  under the weight of his sins and his guilt for them.</note> In this also I have
               offended, that while I have never ceased in my writings to point out the real evils
               of society, &amp; to press upon the public mind the necessity of bettering, in every
               way, the condition of the poor, I have lifted up my voice against the Apostles of
               Anarchy, &amp; my voice has been heard. There are those among us who imitate in their
               writings as far as they dare, the words of the French Revolutionists, &amp; if the
               opportunity were come would imitate them as faithfully in their deeds. I used to
               include M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> William Smith among those persons who tho’ they
               cooperated with these incendiaries, were nevertheless actuated by good intentions,
               &amp; entitled for their general character to respect. This opinion must now be
               qualified. The <del>xxxx xx</del> unwarrantable attack which in his parliamentary
               character he has made upon an individual, not present to vindicate himself &amp;
               reply to the foul slander as it deserved, entitles me to think as ill of his
               disposition as of his discretion</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">I am Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs <del>with every</del> with as little courtesy as you
                  deserve</salute><signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1817-03-17">17. March. 1817</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>