<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3125</idno><idno type="nines">rce4396</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3125. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 24 April
                  1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3125.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Keswick Museum and
                  Art Gallery, WC 166. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3125" type="letter"><head>3125. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1818-04-24">24 April
                  1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Herbert Hill/ Worting/ near Basingstoke/
                     Hampshire<title><lb/></title>Stamped: [partial] Keswick<lb/> Postmark: E/ 27 AP 27/ 1818<lb/> Seal: red wax, design illegible<lb/> MS: Keswick Museum and
                  Art Gallery, WC 166. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> I have sent off another portion of MS. to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, which will have
               plenty of time for a journey into Hampshire; for <ref type="m" target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> had a full fortnights work
               in his hands.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Manuscript drafts of the third volume of the <title>History of Brazil</title>
                  (1810–1819) sent to John Rickman in London and thence to Herbert Hill in Hampshire for comment, before being despatched for printing
                  by Pople.</note> He kept me a long while without a proofs, which is the reason why you have not seen my progress during that time.
               But I have not been idle, &amp; have got far ahead of him. I am now busy with the Diamonds,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 36 of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, pp. 246–298. Diamonds were discovered in
                  Minas Gerais in 1725.</note> &amp; have to day digested the matter from those two papers upon this subject in the Pinheiro
                  Collection,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly the 9 volumes of manuscript material described as ‘Papeis Varias
                  Politicos’ (1674), no. 3852 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> by help of which there will be no chasm in this part
               of the narration. My next business is the <del>Capitation</del> siege of N Colonia,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, pp. 286–298. The Portuguese colony of Nova Colonia (or
                  Sacramento) in modern Uruguay was besieged by Spain in 1735–1737.</note> – then the Capitation,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (1810–1819), III, pp. 270–274. The capitation was a special poll tax imposed
                  in 1735 in Minas Gerais on all free people (they also had to pay a sum for every slave they owned).</note> – Mato Grosso &amp; the
               voyage down the Madeira,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 37, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London,
                  1810–1819), III, pp. 299–373. In this chapter, Southey related the voyage in 1742 of Manoel Felix de Lima (dates unknown), a
                  Portuguese adventurer, together with several Brazilians, along the rivers Guapore and Madeira and to the mouth of the Amazon, pp.
                  310–344.</note> – this I abstracted while <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Koster</ref> was here, who helped me to
               decypher the spelling, &amp; to the meaning of some Brazilian words, which none but a Brazileiro could have explained. Then comes the
               affair of the seven Reductions<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">In fact this matter was left to Chapter 39, <title>History of
                     Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, pp. 442–504, which dealt with the Treaty of Madrid (1750), the ceding of seven
                  missions (or ‘Reductions’) by Spain and the Guarani War or ‘War of the Seven Reductions’ 1756–1757.</note> for which I am
               excellently well prepared.</p><p rend="indent1"> Lozanos History (which I have returned to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nott)<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">George
                  Frederick Nott (1767–1841; <title>DNB</title>), scholar, theologian and Prebendary of Winchester Cathedral 1810–1841, had lent
                  Southey Pedro Lozano (1697–1752), <title>Historia de la Compañia de Jesús en la Provincia del Paraguay</title> (1754–1755). Southey
                  thanked Nott for the loan of this book in <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, pp. vi–vii, noting that
                  Nott was unknown to him.</note> contains more historical matter about Chili than about Paraguay, &amp; only comes down to 1615 (I
               think) – so that to have compleated it down to his own time upon the same scale would have required about twenty more such thick &amp;
               full folios as the two volumes which he set forth. Something I gained from him for the chapter upon the equestrian tribes,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 38, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, pp. 374–441. References
                  to Pedro Lozano, <title>Historia de la Compañia de Jesús en la Provincia del Paraguay</title> (1754–1755) appeared on
                  pp. 174, 375, 388, 398, 402, 890.</note> &amp; a little bibliographic knowledge concerning the Paraguay writers.</p><p rend="indent1"> I believe the new funds interfere with my books, – the worthy Israelite thro whose hands they must pass is fully
               engaged with the three &amp; a halfs,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The consignment of books Southey had bought in Brussels
                  in 1817. Its transportation proved astonishingly complex and Southey had recruited the eminent banker Nathan Mayer Rothschild
                  (1777–1836; <title>DNB</title>), to help secure its safe arrival. The government’s new issue of 3½ per cent stock was not selling
                  well and was declining in value; among the major subscribers was Rothschild’s firm, which had reportedly invested £2 million; see
                  the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 20 April 1818.</note> – &amp; I suspect they are waiting his leisure in the Custom House, –
               for they were sent from Brussels about two months ago. Enquiry is making by what ship they went from Ostend, &amp; I am living in daily
               hopes.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Editor of the Correio Braziliense<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Hipólito José da Costa Pereira Furtado de
                  Mendonça (1774–1823), editor of the London-based liberal journal <title>Correio Braziliense</title> (1808–1822). Southey owned a
                  complete set, no. 3203 in the sale catalogue of his library. Mendonça did not write his proposed history of Brazil.</note> announces
               a History of Brazil by himself, &amp; advertises for materials; the Portugueze he says, may be assured that he will not vitiate them
               thro ignorance of the language as some English &amp; French writers have recently done, to whom some Portugueze have communicated
               valuable manuscripts which they would not entrust to their own countrymen. This fellow is a rogue. Neither he nor the
                  Investigador,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>O Investigador Portuguez em Inglaterra</title> (1811–1819), a
                  London-based conservative journal that opposed the <title>Correio Braziliense</title>. A complete set was no. 3409 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> have ever mentioned my work, not even in their list of new publications. <hi rend="ital">His</hi> motive is plainly that he means to appropriate as much of its matter as he can, without acknowledging the source.</p><p rend="indent1"> You asked me about Espriella:<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Longman had been re-advertising the third edition
                  of 1814 of Southey’s <title>Letters from England: By Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella</title> (1807). In the same notice they stated
                  ‘Also speedily will be published, TRAVELS in ENGLAND. By Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. In three vols. Duodecimo’, <title>Morning
                     Chronicle</title>, 25 March 1818. This was a fairly transparent device to boost interest in an edition that was selling
                  poorly.</note> – the advertisement is <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> own doing &amp; so far are the
               Travels from being in the press that not one chapter is written, – tho I have a great collection of materials. My hands must be cleared
               of much more important affairs before this can be taken up.</p><p rend="indent1"> A new volume of Chronicas Ineditas<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Collecçaõ de Livros Ineditos de
                     Historia Portugueza</title>, vols 4 and 5 (1816–1824), no. 3361 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Volume 4 did contain
                  ‘Chronica d’El Rey D. Fernando’ by Fernao Lopes (c. 1385– after 1459). The volumes were published by the Royal Academy of Sciences
                  (founded 1779). </note> is announced by the Academy. This will be a treasure, – tho I guess that it will chiefly, or wholly consist
               of the Chronica del R D Fernando, which was printed in the former volumes.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have sent Wesley<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of
                     Methodism</title> (1820).</note> to the press &amp; am now in daily expectation of the first proof, – an event which is always
               among the great pleasures of life.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will see me I think in November, – about that time it will suit me to work at <ref type="m" target="people.html#BunburySirHenryEdward">Sir H. Bunbury’s</ref> upon his papers,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Bunbury,
                  who had been Under-Secretary of State for War and the colonies 1809–1816, had made his papers available to Southey to aid him in
                  researching his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–32).</note> – &amp; it will safe both time &amp; money to take in
               London both going &amp; returning.</p><p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref>. I hope all the Orsini<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s nickname for the Hills’ children.</note> are going on well – <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My daughter Edith</ref> the other day found upon one of these mountains a copper spear head, –
               lying upon the surface of some crags, where it may have lain (as indeed it must) for centuries. Perfectly green as if covered with
               enamel (not corroded) – &amp; brittle in consequence, it is very well made &amp; appears to have been cast, – just one of my spans in
               length.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1818-04-24">24 April. 1818.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>