<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2912</idno><idno type="nines">rce4183</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2912. Robert Southey to Sir
                  George Beaumont, 1 February 1817</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2912.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>MS untraced; text is taken from
                  William Knight (ed.), Memorials of Coleorton, 2 vols (Edinburgh,
                  1887) .  Previously  published: William Knight (ed.), Memorials of
                     Coleorton: Being Letters from Coleridge, Wordsworth and his Sister, Southey,
                     and Sir Walter Scott to Sir George and Lady Beaumont of Coleorton,
                     Leicestershire, 1803 to 1834, 2 vols (London, 1887), II, pp.
                  179–183.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2912" type="letter"><head>2912. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir
                  George Beaumont</ref>, <date when="1817-02-01">1 February 1817</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from
                  William Knight (ed.), <title>Memorials of Coleorton</title>, 2 vols (Edinburgh,
                  1887)<lb/> Previously published: William Knight (ed.), <title>Memorials of
                     Coleorton: Being Letters from Coleridge, Wordsworth and his Sister, Southey,
                     and Sir Walter Scott to Sir George and Lady Beaumont of Coleorton,
                     Leicestershire, 1803 to 1834</title>, 2 vols (London, 1887), II, pp.
                  179–183.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1817-02-01">1 Feby. 1817.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Sir,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> We have usually a good many water-fowl offered for sale at this time
               of the year, but this winter we have had none, from which I conclude that the season
               has been as mild abroad as it is at home, and that the web-footed family, who direct
               their movements by the temperature, and not by the almanac, are waiting till the
               winter begins. I should very much enjoy this mild open weather if I had not some
               apprehensions for what is to come. Vegetation is fearfully premature in this country.
               The children<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Southey’s daughters
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>,
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and
                  their cousin <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara
                  Coleridge</ref>.</note> gathered a primrose and a <hi rend="ital">flos adonis</hi><note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">An
                  ornamental and medicinal plant, it has scarlet flowers with a darker base.</note>
               on Christmas Day; to-day they brought me in wall-flowers, and the polyanthuses have
               been in full bloom for some time. It looks ill to see things thus out of time. If the
               seasons continue out of order we may dread the failure of another harvest, and, in
               the present state of men’s minds, such an evil is indeed to be dreaded. But for one’s
               own personal feelings never was such a month of January. I was on Walla Crag a
               fortnight ago, and a day in September could not have been warmer. And for <hi rend="ital">effects</hi>, never have I witnessed finer than what have been almost
               daily displayed, from vast masses of soft swelling cloud, hovering about the whole
               range of mountains from Borrowdale to Grisdale, and the sun – who shouts to the god
               of painters as well as poets – moving among them, and producing all imaginable
               glories. A few days back there was the most striking effect I ever remember to have
               seen. The depth of Newlands was filled with an
               exceedingly dark cloud, in form like a truncated pyramid, and the sun appearing just
               upon the summit, shot its rays down on all sides, literally like streams of
               light.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> is painting
               with great perseverance, and, as far as I can judge, with great success. She tells me
               a great deal about difficulties, and of being provoked with what she has done, and
               with what she is doing, but she goes on as long as the light will permit. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss Hutchinson</ref> is with her at present, and has
               been employing herself very kindly as an amanuensis for me. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> is safely
               landed at Merton,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Merton College, Oxford,
                  where Hartley Coleridge was a student.</note> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref> returned this day
               to school.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The school in Ambleside run by
                  the Revd John Dawes.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The papers interest me very much at this time. I am a good deal
               surprised at <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">Marquis
                  Wellesley’s</ref> speech upon the Address.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Marquis Wellesley had spoken in the House of Lords on 29
                  January 1817 in the debate on the Prince Regent’s Address on the opening of
                  Parliament. He argued that ‘the great and original cause of all our evils was, the
                  magnitude of our expenditure’.</note> Of all cries, the cry for retrenchment is
               the most senseless. Of the many causes which have combined to produce the existing
               difficulties, the greatest is unquestionably a sudden and enormous diminution of
               expenditure, – Government spending from forty to fifty millions a year less than
               during the war. And as a remedy for this unavoidable evil they are advised to
               diminish the expenditure still further! Nor does any person seem to perceive that
               when so many hands are out of employ, every soldier that shall be disbanded must
               either want employ himself, or deprive some other person of it: so many as you
               disband so many will you cast, in some form or other, upon the public, <hi rend="ital">totidem numeris</hi>, if not <hi rend="ital">totidem
                  personis</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">‘the same number if not
                  the same people’.</note> Some will go to the parish, some to the highway, and not
               a few will be found in the mobs which are beginning to try their strength with the
               established authorities.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am glad to see the decided manner in which <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Mr. Canning</ref> spoke concerning
               Parliamentary Reform.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Canning had spoken
                  in defence of the government in the House of Commons on 29 January 1817, in the
                  debate on the Prince Regent’s Address on the opening of parliament. His speech
                  included a ringing denunciation of parliamentary reform: ‘I deny the assumption,
                  that the House of Commons, as it stands, is not, to all practical purposes, an
                  adequate representative of the people.’</note> Yet there are some things which I
               could wish we were well rid of, as Tillotson said of the damnatory clauses in the
               Athanasian Creed.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Tillotson
                  (1630–1694; <title>DNB</title>), Archbishop of Canterbury 1691–1694. In a letter
                  to Gilbert Burnet (1643–1715; <title>DNB</title>) of 23 October 1694 he condemned
                  the Athanasian creed, the statement of Christian orthodoxy drawn up c. AD 420 and
                  attributed to the Greek theologian St Athanasius (293–373). Assent to it remained,
                  however, the eighth of the Church’s Thirty-Nine Articles of Faith. Tillotson may
                  have particularly disliked verses 2 and 42 of the Creed that asserted all
                  non-believers would ‘perish eternally’ – Southey certainly disapproved of them, as
                  well as of the Creed’s relentless emphasis on the orthodox doctrine of the
                  Trinity.</note> The great sinecures are among these things: the saving to be
               effected by abolishing them is a mere nothing, not worthy to be mentioned, but they
               afford a fair topic for mischievous men, and therefore, as long as they continue,
               they do a great deal of harm. But if there were no other objection to removing them,
               the triumph which it would give these vagabonds, in whatever manner the thing were
               done, is a very weighty one. I well remember when the Talents<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The ‘Ministry of All the Talents’ 1806–1807, of which Lord
                  Grenville was Prime Minister.</note> came into power, thinking that <hi rend="ital">that</hi> was the time. An enormous increase of taxation was
               necessarily laid on. Had the Grenvilles then given up their sinecures (instead of
               passing an Act for enabling <ref type="m" target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord
               G.</ref> to hold two places, which his own subsequent
               conduct clearly proved ought not to have been united in one person), they would have
               acquired a popularity which even their blunders could scarcely have shaken.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">When Lord Grenville became Prime Minister in 1806
                  he, as usual, became First Lord of the Treasury. However, the law required him to
                  give up the lucrative sinecure of Auditor of the Receipt of the Exchequer (a post
                  he had held since 1794), as this role could not be held at the same time as the
                  First Lordship. Grenville’s solution was an Act of Parliament to allow him to hold
                  both offices together. This was felt to be particularly reprehensible because it
                  placed Grenville in the position of auditing his own Department’s accounts. The
                  Auditorship was merely part of the Grenville family’s group of sinecures, though.
                  One of Grenville’s brothers, George Grenville, 1st Marquess of Buckingham
                  (1753–1813; <title>DNB</title>) was Teller of the Exchequer (worth £23,000 in 1808
                  alone); while his other brother, Thomas Grenville (1755–1846; <title>DNB</title>),
                  was Chief Justice of Eyre, south of the Trent (worth £2,316 per annum).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My good friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> has a very deep sense of the kindness which he experienced at
                  Coleorton.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Beaumont’s estate in
                  Leicestershire.</note> We mean to pass six weeks together on the Continent in the
               months of May and June; so I shall hope to see you in April on my way through town.
               If <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Mr. Westall</ref> be with you, pray remember me
               to him. My ‘womankind’ as the Antiquary calls them,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref>, and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>. In Walter Scott’s <title>The Antiquary</title> (1816), the
                  eponymous central character refers to all the women in his household as his
                  ‘womankind’.</note> beg to be remembered to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMargaret">Lady
                  Beaumont</ref>; so would our neighbours if they knew I were writing.– </p><closer><salute rend="indent2">Believe me, Sir George, very truly and respectfully
                  yours,</salute><signed rend="indent3">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>