<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3061</idno><idno type="nines">rce4332</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3061. Robert Southey to Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn, 1 January 1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3061.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 4p. .  Previously 
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                     Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 292–294 [in
                  part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3061" type="letter"><head>3061. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>,<date when="1818-01-01"> 1 January 1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn
                     Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Llangedwin/ Oswestry <lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb/> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                     Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 292–294 [in
                  part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1818-01-01">1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>
                     1818.</date></dateline><salute> My dear Wynn</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Many happy returns of the new year to you &amp; yours! It is now
               thirty years since you &amp; I first met in Deans Yard,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A central feature of Westminster School, where Southey and Wynn
                  had first met in 1788.</note> – &amp; in the course of those years half the human
               race who were then living have gone under ground. How long either of us may keep
               above it, God knows, but while we do, there is little likelihood that any
               circumstances can break or loosen an attachment which has continued so long. Your
               path has been just what might have been predicted, straight, honourable, &amp; in
               full view, – only that one might have expected to have found you on the other side
               the house,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn was a leading figure in the
                  Grenvillite group that had coalesced around his uncle, <ref type="m" target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord Grenville</ref>, in 1803–1804. They had been in
                  opposition ever since they participated in the ‘Ministry of All the Talents’ in
                  1806–1807; but they fundamentally disagreed with the Whig opposition on a number
                  of points and were in many ways closer to the position held by the government,
                  e.g. on supporting the war with France in 1803–1815 and opposition to
                  parliamentary reform. The Grenvillites finally decided to separate from the Whigs
                  in July 1817 to form a ‘third party’ and joined the government in 1822.</note>
               &amp; in office;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn had briefly served as
                  Under-Secretary of State for the Home Department in 1806–1807, but on 2 June 1817
                  he had been defeated in the election for The Speaker of the House of Commons. He
                  was not to hold office again until 1822, when he became President of the Board of
                  Control.</note> – &amp; one day or other, (the sooner the better) I trust to see
               you there. What mine might have been without your helping hand,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn had paid Southey an annuity of £160 from
                  1797, until he secured a government pension of £200 per annum for Southey in 1807
                  (Southey was actually worse off under this arrangement as he had to pay fees and
                  taxes).</note> when I was among the bogs &amp; briers; I know not: – with that
               help it has been a very pleasant uphill road, with so many <del>odd</del> incidents
               by the way that the history of them would make no bad Pilgrims Progress, – especially
               as I am now at rest among the Delectable Mountains, &amp; have little more to do than
               to cross the river whenever my turn comes.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was fond of portraying life via allusions to John Bunyan (1628–1688;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Pilgrim’s Progress</title> (1678). The Delectable
                  Mountains were encountered by Christian and Hopeful after their escape from
                  Doubting Castle. There they were able to glimpse the Celestial City and were shown
                  some of the delights of Paradise. To finally reach the Celestial City, though,
                  they had to cross the River of Death.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> We are enjoying a beautiful winter here. No snow has yet fallen in
               the valley, &amp; it lies on the <del>xxx</del> fells not raggedly but in an even
               line, so that <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> &amp; Grisdale<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Grizedale Pike is a fell to the southwest of
                  Keswick, visible from Southey’s home, Greta Hall.</note> bear no distant
               resemblance to the Swiss mountains, &amp; imbibe tints at morning &amp; evening which
               may vie with any thing that ever was seen upon Mont-Blanc or the Jungfrau. Have you
               noticed the news from the North Pole? –<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Reports of events in the Arctic were widespread in British newspapers, e.g.
                     <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 22 November 1817, which coincides closely
                  with Southey’s information.</note> to me it is more interesting than any thing
               that has happened since the Battle of Waterloo,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The battle in which an allied force finally defeated the French army on 18
                  June 1815, so ending the wars of 1793–1815.</note> or seems likely to happen. The
               Greenlandmen got as far as 84 &amp; had then no ice in sight, – the coast of East
               Greenland which has been shut up for four or five hundred years was open. It is
               believed that some great convulsion of nature has broken up the ice about the pole, –
               the floating masses occasioned those unnatural cold winds from the S. &amp; S. W.
               which pinched us with cold in Burgundy &amp; Franch Comte at the end of May last.
               Most probably a volcano has broken out there, – for for the last two years there have
               been no fish upon the coast of Kamtschetka.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">British newspapers had recently carried a number of extracts from Hamburg
                  papers, e.g. <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 8 December 1817. One of the
                  extracts reported that in the Kamchatka peninsula ‘in the course of last winter an
                  incredible number of bears have left the woods, frequently entered the houses of
                  the Kamtschdales; in many places have attacked and devoured the inhabitants; nay
                  traces have even been found of their having killed and devoured each other; at the
                  end of the winter many bears were found who had perished of hunger. In several
                  settlements they have killed from two to three hundred bears, the oldest
                  Kamtschadales do not remember ever to have seen so many bears so savage and
                  blood-thirsty. The cause of this savageness and of their hunger is, that for these
                  two years past there has been an entire want of fish in the Kamschatka sea, and
                  fish, as is well known, are the chief food of the bears, which being usually so
                  abundant in those waters, they easily contrive to catch. A couple of shocks of an
                  earthquake have been lately felt in the Peninsula.’</note> What if we should
               accomplish the N West passage, this year, &amp; perhaps reach the Pole!<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Newspaper accounts (e.g. <title>Morning
                     Chronicle</title>, 22 November 1817) reported that the Royal Society was
                  pressing the government to mount an expedition to search for the North West
                  passage and offering fishermen a bounty to explore the area. Two Royal Navy
                  expeditions were made. In April 1818 one commanded by David Buchan (1780–1838;
                     <title>DNB</title>) and John Franklin (1786–1847; <title>DNB</title>) explored
                  the Arctic sea around Spitsbergen; another commanded by John Ross (1777–1856;
                     <title>DNB</title>) sought a North West passage around Baffin Island. Neither
                  was successful.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I am writing for the QR. upon the Poor Laws, or rather upon the means
               of improving the lower classes, – a practical paper, containing I think some hints
               which any clergyman, or other influential person in a parish may usefully
                  improve.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of the Report of
                  the House of Commons Select Committee to consider the Poor Laws (1817) in
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 259–308, was actually
                  mainly written by John Rickman.</note> It is not unlikely that I may gradually
               withdraw from the review, – that is to say as soon as I can live without it; – it
               takes up far too great a portion of my time: for altho no man can take to task-work
               with less reluctance, still from the very circumstance of its being task-work, –
               something which must be done, &amp; not which I desire at the time to do, it costs me
               twice or thrice the time of any other composition; – as much <del>perhaps</del> in
               the course of the year as it took <del>xx</del> to write Thalaba, or Kehama.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801)
                  and <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810). The fourth edition of the latter
                  was published in 1818.</note> This last poem is going to press for a fourth
               edition; – they sell slowly &amp; steadily, &amp; will keep moving onward when some
               of their greater contemporaries shall have fallen asleep by the way side, to wake no
               more.</p><p rend="indent1"> The life of Wesley is my favourite employment just now, &amp; a very
               curious book it will be; – looking at Methodism abroad as well as at home, &amp;
               comprehending our religious history for the last <del>fourscore</del> hundred
                  years.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Life of Wesley; and
                     the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820). </note> I am sure I shall
               treat this subject with moderation. ––I hope I come to it with a sober judgement, a
               mature mind, &amp; perfect freedom from all unjust prepossessions of any kind. <del>I
                  have nothing</del> There is no party which I am desirous of pleasing, none which I
               am fearful of offending, nor am I aware of any possible circumstance which might tend
               to bias me one way or other from the straight line of impartial truth. For the bigot
               I shall be far too philosophical, for the libertine far too pious, – the Archdeacon
                  Hooks<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">James Hook (c. 1772–1828;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Archdeacon of Huntington 1814–1818, Dean of Worcester
                  1825–1828 and noted Anglican polemicist. Southey had known him at school at
                  Westminster and regarded him with disdain.</note> &amp; other such Ultra-Churchmen
               will think me little better than a Methodist, &amp; the Methodists will wonder what I
               am, “Αγια ‘Αγιοις will be my
                  motto.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The proclamation at the
                  elevation of the host in the Mass: ‘holy things for holy people’.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My books from Milan have reached London, – something more than 100
               volumes. Ramusio is among them, &amp; the Gesta Dei.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Giovanni Battista Ramusio (1485–1557), <title>Navigationi et
                     Viaggi</title>, 3 vols (1556–1588), no. 2382 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                  library. Jacques Bongars (1554–1612), <title>Gesta Dei per Francos</title> (1611),
                  no. 1193 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> I have not yet heard
               of my Acta Sanctorum, – the arrival of which will <del>xx</del> form a grand day in
               my life.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had bought in Brussels
                  the massive compendium of hagiographies entitled <title>Acta Sanctorum</title>, 53
                  vols (1643–1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> Little [MS
               torn] as I find for poetry, &amp; seldom indeed as I think of it, there is yet a sort
               of reluctance in me wholly to give up any scheme of a poem on which I have ever
               thought with any degree of fondness; – &amp; because I had meditated a Jewish poem
               many years ago<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Common-Place
                     Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849–1850), IV, p. 11,
                  for Southey’s brief notes on ‘Jewish Stories’ that might be turned into epic
                  poetry; and pp. 2–3 for his ideas for a poem on Noah and the flood, outlined in
                  1800–1801. None of these projects came to fruition.</note> I bought at Milan the
               great Biblotheca Rabbinica of Bartolacci<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Giulio Bartolocci (1613–1687), <title>Bibliotheca Magna Rabbinica de
                     Scriptoribus et Scriptus Hebraicis</title> (1675–1694), no. 236 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> as a repository of materials. Could I have
               afforded to have written verses during those years when nobody bought them I verily
               believe I should have written more than any of my predecessors. </p><p rend="indent1"> As soon as the first canto of the Paraguay Tale is finished I will
               transcribe &amp; send it. It moves the slower because of the metre.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Tale of Paraguay</title>, in Spenserian
                  stanzas, was not finished and published until 1825.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>