<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3181</idno><idno type="nines">rce4452</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3181. Robert Southey to Caroline
               Bowles, 12 August 1818 </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3181.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3181" type="letter"><head>3181. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline
               Bowles</ref>,<date when="1818-08-12"> 12 August 1818 </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Bowles/ Buckland/
                  near Lymington/ Hampshire <lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb/> Postmark: E/ 15 AU 15/
                  1818 <lb/> Endorsements: To Miss Caroline Bowles/ Keswick 12 August 1818; 12 Aug
                  1818 <lb/> MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Unpublished.
               </note></head><p rend="indent1"> I was absent from home when your letter arrived, – &amp; much
               occupied after my return. – Now then for your poem,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The manuscript poem ‘Ellen Fitzarthur’ that Bowles had sent to
                  Southey, seeking advice on bringing it to publication. Southey sent it to Murray,
                  who did not publish it; Longmans did, in 1820.</note> – &amp; remember that
               criticism cannot be too minute, nor too rigid when it is in time to prevent what is
               faulty from being rendered permanent by the press.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is not well to rhyme upon the same vowel (if the sound be strongly
               marked) in succession, as you have done in the first &amp; second four lines: ‘climb’
               &amp; ‘<hi rend="ital">divine</hi>’, – <del><hi rend="ital">bare</hi></del> {‘says’}
               &amp; ‘gaze’.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Ellen Fitzarthur: a
                     Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (London, 1820), p. [v] changed these
                  rhymes to ‘sublime’ and ‘climb’, and ‘gaze’ and ‘rays’. Almost all the following
                  deletions and changes that Southey recommended were made in the published
                  poem.</note> Perhaps my ear may be the more sensible of this because I am
               accustomed to Spanish poetry in which the most popular metre requires no other
               similarity of sound than that the {two} final syllables of the alternate lines should
               contain the same <hi rend="ital">vowels</hi>.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The assonant rhyme scheme often used in medieval Spanish romances, as in
                  ‘Cantar de Mio Cid’, which Southey had translated in <title>Chronicle of the
                     Cid</title> (1808).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> ‘We’ll shroud in dark obscurity’. To shroud is one of those verbs
               which <del>xxxx xxxxxxxxxxx after them</del> will not admit the omission of the word
               to which they apply. You mean to say shroud ourselves, – there is another fault in
               the line obscurity must be dark, &amp; therefore the epithet is superfluous. This is
               a case in which two faults are better than one, because <del>both are</del> in
               getting rid of one you will amend the other.</p><p rend="indent1"> I would rather call them children than cherubs, – we take the
               resemblance from tombstones only, – this is a mere matter of individual taste, –
               cottage children are generally chubby <del>enough</del> for cherubs, but seldom clean
               enough.</p><p rend="indent1"> To scan a vision is an awkward expression – nor is it well to speak
               of <hi rend="ital">gazing</hi> on the forms of other days, which is confounding too
               much visible with ideal objects.</p><p rend="indent1"> Have you not made your father too old? Having been a pastor sixty
               years he must be at least 82, – but you do not mean Ellen to be over one or two &amp;
               twenty. – ‘The parent <hi rend="ital">dove</hi>’ seems an expression too obviously
               created by the rhyme. ‘<hi rend="ital">Clear</hi>’ is not a happy epithet for the
               tones of infancy. – It is not from weeds that a germ requires guarding, so much as
               from other things – all this however is very pretty &amp; with a sweet flow of tender
               female feeling. I <hi rend="ital">doubt</hi> whether in such circumstances the sort
               of illusion which you describe in looking at his grown daughter could arise, – man
               himself changes too much for it. – ‘And scattered times unresting feet, with
               blessings,’ – if I understand this rightly, it is an awkward passage. ‘Hope &amp;
               ‘spoke’ cannot be allowed as rhymes, tho I would always allow large license: moreover
               the word ought to be <hi rend="ital">spoken</hi>. So also ‘wove’ ought to
                  <del>be</del> be ‘woven’.</p><p rend="indent1"> You cannot say ‘the tide of the kettle’. Never force a word out of
               its appropriate meaning, unless there be a peculiar propriety in doing it: ‘Slumber
               seals his drowsy brain’ get rid of this if you can passages of this kind require an
               easiness of expression, – any thing forced or violent is out of place, &amp; here the
               strong metaphor is evidently produced for the sake of the rhyme. – ‘Wove’ is once
               more used instead of ‘woven’ in this canto. – All that follows, till the last four
               lines, is evidently fresh from the heart.</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Where relief &amp; rest</l><l rend="indent3"> And needful care might <hi rend="ital">wait</hi> him best – </l></lg><p> I am {not} sure that I read this word rightly, but if I do it is not
               well exprest. – And it would be better to say ‘whose lowly home to rest Now welcomed’
               &amp;c – than to make rest the welcomer. It is one of the faults of modern poetry
               that it uses figurative language too lavishly, &amp; thus lessens its effect when it
               is required.</p><p rend="indent1"> The lapse of time is marked with right poetical feeling. But the
               primrose bank &amp; the Orchard cannot <hi rend="ital">pass away</hi>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Ellen Fitzarthur: a Metrical Tale, in Five
                     Cantos</title> (London, 1820), p. 29, made it clear that it was the ‘primrose
                  blossom’ and ‘sheeted bloom of orchard gray’ that actually ‘passed away’.</note>
               It is to such improprieties as these that I wish particularly to draw your attention;
               – most persons are insensible to them &amp; yet they make one great part of the
               difference between writing well or ill. – I doubt whether ‘<hi rend="ital">hoary
                  hair</hi>’ will not strike the reader as being improper, because we always speak
               of grey hair<hi rend="ital">s</hi>. The line which presently follows about the
               sparrow is a bad one, &amp; appears worse because it brings to mind the beautiful
               expression in the Gospel.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Matthew</title> 10: 28–31, ‘Are not two sparrows sold for a
                  farthing? and one of them shall not fall on the ground without your Father. But
                  the very hairs of your head are all numbered. Fear ye not therefore, ye are of
                  more value than many sparrows’.</note> Confidence &amp; Providence are not rhymes
               the sound being the same in both words.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Ellen Fitzarthur: a Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (London,
                  1820), p. 31, changed the rhyme to ‘pious sense’ and ‘confidence’.</note> – A sigh
               does not make the lips quiver. – ‘Can mortal designate his own’: – call would be a
               better word here being the more obvious one. – ‘The heart that trusts in man must
               bleed – And leans’, &amp;c: – it is not the <hi rend="ital">heart</hi> that
                  leans.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Ellen Fitzarthur: a
                     Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (London, 1820), p. 38, retained: ‘The
                  heart that trusts in man must bleed,/ And leans upon a broken reed.’</note> –
                  Roo<hi rend="ital">f</hi>, trut<hi rend="ital">h</hi>: not allowable as rhymes. A
               Garlands votive <hi rend="ital">twine</hi>, – alter this &amp; the whole passage is
                  <del>xx</del> very pleasing, – only in the beginning of the Canto Ellens youth
               should not be called gay as well as buoyant, – there was an end of all its gaiety.
               ‘Disappointed misery’ is an odd combination of words – for misery is never
               disappointed. – ‘Spa<hi rend="ital">r</hi>k’ will not do with ‘hea<hi rend="ital">r</hi>t’, &amp; in the next couplet the metaphor is changed, which it ought not
               to be. – Womans heart may be the seat of love, but you would not call it its clime,
               if the verse had not betrayed you into it. This is the danger which you have to guard
               against when you write in rhyme, – it continually tempts the writer to forced
               constructions &amp; a violent use of words out of their proper place. ‘All forgot’ –
               should be ‘forgotten’. – The conclusion of this Canto serves the metaphor so far,
               that at first I thought she had thrown herself into the water. The fault may be as
               likely in the reader as in the writer.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have thus gone thro three cantos. &amp; as there is not room to
               conclude the poem upon this sheet, the others must be reserved for another letter
               which shall follow in a few days. You will find this dull enough, – but do not
               consider it disheartening, – for if I had not thought that {the} virtues
                  <del>xx</del> {greatly} preponderated I should never have bestowed a moments
               attention upon the faults – nor would I point them out for any other purpose than
               that they might be corrected in time.</p><p rend="indent1"> Farewell. In the course of a few days you shall have the remainder of
               these unconnected remarks. Be of good heart, – &amp; <del>do not</del> whatever may
               be the fate of this poem do not be discouraged from planning &amp; executing
               others.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">Yrs faithfully</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1818-08-12">12 Aug. 1818.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>