<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3182</idno><idno type="nines">rce4453</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3182. Robert Southey to John
                  Rickman, 14 August 1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3182.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Huntington Library, RS 350. ALS; 2p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3182" type="letter"><head>3182. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                  Rickman</ref>, <date when="1818-08-14">14 August 1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Stephens Court/ New Palace Yard/
                  Westminster<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: FREE/ 17 AU 17/ 1818<lb/>
                  MS: Huntington Library, RS 350. ALS; 2p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute> My dear R.</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Put upon the direction of the inclosed <del>xxxx</del> honours of the
               Alphabet as the said <ref type="m" target="people.html#DouglasHoward">Sir Howard</ref><note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">General Sir Howard Douglas was an artillery
                  officer and engineering expert who had been employed in 1812 on missions to
                  organise resistance to the French occupation in the north of Spain. At the time of
                  this letter he was Inspector-General of the Royal Military College, Sandhurst. The
                  ‘alphabet’ of letters after his name included CB (Companion of the Order of the
                  Bath) and FRS (Fellow of the Royal Society). He had offered to send Southey
                  material to help with his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>
                  (1823–1832).</note> is entitled to, – I have no means here of discovered which
               they are. It is a letter concerning the Peninsular War. He offers me communications
               on the application of some M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Townsend of Sandhurst,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">George Townsend (1788–1857; <title>DNB</title>),
                  author and clergyman. Professor at the Royal Military College, Sandhurst and
                  Curate of Farnborough 1816–1822, Chaplain to the Bishop of Durham 1822–1825,
                  Prebend of Durham Cathedral 1825–1857.</note> – whom to the best of my knowledge I
               never heard of before.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall soon send up more Brazil, – an interesting portion, a river
               voyage from the very centre of the continent by the Guapiri &amp; Madeira to Para, –
               from the original narrative in the Adventurers own hand writing.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey discusses the voyage down this river in
                  his <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, 349–359,
                  drawn from ‘Voyage up the Madeira in 1749, with a MS. Map’, no. 3849 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – I am reading Clarendon,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A new edition, printed by Pople, of Edward Hyde,
                  1st Earl of Clarendon (1609–1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the
                     Rebellion and Civil Wars in England </title>(1816).</note> a book which ought
               to be more read. – Are the Americans seeking to provoke another war?<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The United Kingdom and United States were
                  attempting to negotiate a settlement of outstanding disputes, which finally led to
                  the Convention, signed on 20 October 1818, dealing mainly with the Oregon
                  Territory.</note> &amp; are we to take <del>x</del> no cognizance of the murder of
               these Englishmen?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a reference to
                  the execution on 29 April 1818 of Alexander Arbuthnot (1748–1818) and Richard
                  Ambrister (1797–1818), two British citizens, for aiding the Creek and Seminole
                  against United States forces in Spanish Florida. The men were condemned by a
                  military tribunal, and on grounds of very dubious legality (to say the least),
                  provoking protests from the British and Spanish governments.</note> – I cannot
               think that Government will hold together. In the contest between the two principles
               here the good will prevail at last, – <del>&amp;</del> perhaps at <hi rend="ital">first</hi>, – there, it will require a severer process to bring about that
               wholesome degree of inequality which is necessary for the well being of society: when
               it is formed by mere wealth it is odious &amp; useless.</p><p rend="indent1"> Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                  R.</ref></p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1818-08-14"> 14 Aug. 1818.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>