<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3216</idno><idno type="nines">rce4487</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3216. Robert Southey to John Murray, 4 December
                  1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3216.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42551. ALS; 4p.
                   .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3216" type="letter"><head>3216. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>,<date when="1818-12-04"> 4 December
                  1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London <lb/>
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb/> Postmark: E/ 7 DE 7/ 1818 <lb/> Seal: black wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb/> Watermark: R E
                  &amp; S BATH 1814<lb/> Endorsements: 1818 Dec 4 Southey, R; Murray 9/5<lb/> MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42551. ALS; 4p.
                  <lb/> Unpublished. </note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1818-12-04"> 4 Dec. 1818.</date></dateline><salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> You will see by the paper which I have just dispatched<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s article on the
                  ‘Inquiry into the Copyright Act’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (January 1819), 196–213.</note> that I have given your friend
                  M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Baber<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s article, ‘Inquiry into the Copyright Act’ (209). Here
                  Southey severely criticised Henry Hervey Baber (1775–1869; <title>DNB</title>), Keeper of Printed Books at the British Museum
                  1812–1837, for serving a writ on Murray because his firm had been dilatory in sending to the British Museum copies of four books it
                  had published, as the Copyright Act (1814) required.</note> a gentle touch, &amp; dealt with Professor Christian according to his
                  deserts.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">One of the works reviewed by Southey in his article, ‘Inquiry into the Copyright
                  Act’, was Edward Christian (1758–1823; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Vindication of the Right of the Universities of the United
                     Kingdom to a Copy of Every New Publication</title> (1818). Christian was Downing Professor of the Laws of England at the
                  University of Cambridge 1800–1823 and vigorously defended the right of eleven designated public and university libraries to receive
                  free copies of all publications. Southey profoundly disagreed and represented this procedure as a tax on the publishing
                  industry.</note> I thought of inserting something respecting those fellows who are the disgrace &amp; nuisance of the bookselling
               business, the fellows who deal in abridgements, &amp; when they cannot steal the works of an esteemed author, steal his name, &amp;
               wound his reputation in that way, your action about <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> would have been a case in
                  point.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The legal case Lord Byron v. James Johnston (dates unknown) in 1816; in which Murray
                  acted on Byron’s behalf to gain an injunction preventing the publication of a work that was to appear under Byron’s name, but which
                  Byron had not written.</note> Miss Edgeworth &amp; D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moore (Zeluco Moore) have been used in the same manner
                  <del>but</del> {&amp;} there was no redress in their case.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Maria Edgeworth (1768–1849;
                     <title>DNB</title>), and John Moore (1729–1802; <title>DNB</title>), author of <title>Zeluco: Various Views of Human Nature,
                     Taken from Life and Manners, Foreign and Domestic</title> (1789). </note> But I left this matter untouched rather than extend the
               article farther.</p><p rend="indent1"> I wrote to you about a translation of Dobrizhoffer.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The account of the Jesuit
                  missions in Paraguay by Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717–1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae
                     Natione</title> (1784), no. 843 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. </note> I will tell you (in confidence) what induced
               me to propose it. You probably are not unacquainted with the manner in which <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> has left his sons to shift for themselves, &amp; find their way in the world as they can. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">The younger</ref> is now acting as private tutor to some little boys &amp; will continue in
               that capacity a year longer.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Derwent Coleridge was living with the Hopwood family,
                  well-connected Lancashire landowners, at Summerhill, near Ulverston 1817–1819. Robert Gregge Hopwood (1773–1854) had married in 1805
                  Cecilia Elizabeth Byng (1770–1854), daughter of John Byng, 5th Viscount Torrington (1743–1813). Derwent Coleridge was tutor to the
                  Hopwoods’ sons: Edward (1807–1891); Frank (1810–1890); and Hervey (1811–1881). He entered St John’s College, Cambridge, in October
                  1820.</note> He has a strong mathematical turn, &amp; a strong desire (in consequence) to try his fortune at Cambridge. Some help we
               have in view for him, &amp; he is most laudably desirous of helping himself. Now this work of Dobrizhoffers is so good a book &amp; so
               entertaining that I think there is little risque in publishing it, tho it be three octavos of about 500 pages. I have spoken of it in
               my Brazil as the best book which has ever been written respecting savage life.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>History of
                     Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, p. 398, described Dobrizhoffer’s work as ‘of all books relating to savage life
                  the most curious, and in every respect the most interesting’.</note> My “Tale of Paraguay” is taken from this book, &amp; will
               certainly attract attention to it in a considerable degree.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>A Tale of
                     Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> And I would review it so that the reviewal should appear close upon the publication.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray did publish a translation of Dobrizhoffer’s book, but by <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref>, not Derwent, Coleridge, <title>An Account of the Abipones, an
                     Equestrian People of Paraguay</title> (1822). It was reviewed by Southey, as he promised, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 26
                  (January 1822), 277–323.</note> – In the course of twelvemonths <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent
                  Coleridge</ref> could accomplish the translation, – &amp; if you either paid him so much for the task, or allowed him a share of the
               eventual profits, <del>it would enable him</del> the first arrangement would enable him to look on to College with certainty, – the
               second with reasonable hope, – &amp; he might thus meritoriously &amp; honourably put himself in that way of fortune for which he is
               calculated, &amp; on which his heart is fixed. – You will consider the proposal as a bookseller, – the explanation is made
               confidentially to a friend.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your affidavit &amp; some other papers upon the subject<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was returning
                  papers Murray had sent him to compose his article, ‘Inquiry into the Copyright Act’, including Murray’s testimony to the House of
                  Commons Select Committee on the Copyright Act (1818).</note> are inclosed with the article to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gifford</ref>. The first part of the Catacombs<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s ‘Cemeteries and Catacombs of Paris’ appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 359–398.
                  However, he did not stop regularly contributing to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> will be dispatched in two or three
               days, – I laid it aside for the Copyright question. After this paper you will do without me for two or three numbers. I shall be
               employed more to my own advantage &amp; to yours.</p><p rend="indent1"> When next you send to me, – there is a stray parcel lying in Albermarle Street, which lost the last chance of
               conveyance.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">Believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1">It was said some time ago in the Times (the most rascally of all newspapers) that <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Hazlitt </ref><del>xxx</del> had instituted an action against Blackwoods Magazine. I do not believe it. He would not run the risk of having me
                  subpœnaed upon the trial.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Hazlitt, resenting a series of personal attacks on his appearance,
                     character and conduct in <title>Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</title> that culminated in ‘Hazlitt Cross Questioned’, 3 (August
                     1818), 550–552, did sue for libel; the magazine settled with him out of court. The case was referred to in <title>The
                        Times</title>, 21 September 1818, which stated ‘Mr. Hazlitt has directed a prosecution to be commenced against the publishers
                     of <title>Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</title>, for an alleged libel upon him in the last number of that work. It is a book
                     filled with private slander.’ Southey felt Hazlitt would fear that Southey might be called to give witness to Hazlitt’s conduct
                     and would relate Hazlitt’s behaviour in Keswick in October 1803, when he fled the town after an incident with a woman in a local
                     inn.</note></p><p rend="indent1">You will tell me when you send the proof, if the statement of your <del>affair</del> treatment by Baber is given as
                  you would wish it.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>