<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3049</idno><idno type="nines">rce4320</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3049. Robert Southey to William Wilberforce, 10 December 1817</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3049.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>.  Previously  published: R.
                  I. Wilberforce and S. Wilberforce, The Correspondence of William
                     Wilberforce, 2 vols (London, 1840), II, pp. 387–389; R. I. Wilberforce
                  and S. Wilberforce, The Life of William Wilberforce, 5 vols
                  (London, 1838), IV, p. 373 [in part; misdated 11 December 1817].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3049" type="letter"><head>3049. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">William Wilberforce</ref>, <date when="1817-12-10">10 December 1817</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: Pte M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ recommending/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Henry Koster <lb/> MS:
                  Berg Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: R.
                  I. Wilberforce and S. Wilberforce, <title>The Correspondence of William
                     Wilberforce</title>, 2 vols (London, 1840), II, pp. 387–389; R. I. Wilberforce
                  and S. Wilberforce, <title>The Life of William Wilberforce</title>, 5 vols
                  (London, 1838), IV, p. 373 [in part; misdated 11 December 1817].</note></head><opener><salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have just received a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Kosters</ref> sister,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Koster had seven sisters: Harriet (b. 1780);
                  Charlotte (b. 1783); Juliana Elizabeth (1788–1790); Maria Susanna (d. 1790);
                  Lucretia (1795–1822); Emma (1797–1817); and Elizabeth (1799–1875).</note>
               informing me that the Consulship at Maranham is vacant, the person who held the
                  office<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Hesketh (1789–1868),
                  Consul in Maranhao 1812–1832, Consul at Rio de Janeiro 1832–1852. He retained his
                  post, despite his reported behaviour.</note> being obliged to leave that place in
               consequence of an intrigue with the Governors daughter,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A daughter of Paulo Jose da Silva Gama, Baron de Bage
                  (1748–1826), Governor of Maranhao 1811–1819.</note> – of course it is impossible
               that he should ever return there.</p><p rend="indent1"> A very erroneous notion has got abroad that I who dwell at the foot
               of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>, who associate more with
               the dead than <del>xxx</del> with the living, &amp; who have set my heart &amp; hopes
               upon the next world – not upon this, – am very much engaged in political affairs:
               &amp; possess in consequence some political influence. This draws upon me a great
               deal of abuse to which I am properly indifferent; tho it induces likewise occasional
               applications from which I would willingly be spared.</p><p rend="indent1"> In writing to you upon this occasion I mean merely to <del>xxx</del>
               say that if this Consulship in Maranham, or any similar situation in Brazil at any
               future time, could be obtained for <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Henry Koster</ref>, the interest of the British merchant, &amp; the honour of the
               British nation would be in safe, upright &amp; conscientious keeping. But I am
               perfectly aware that the claims upon you must be numerous, &amp; the applications
               with which you are troubled, ten times more so. And I am also aware that your
               parliamentary interest, when you might chuse to exert it, is probably by no means
               commensurate with the weight which your opinion carries to the public, – this being,
               I believe, far greater than that of any other individual. </p><p rend="indent1"> I have looked with some anxiety for the letter of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pitts<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">William Pitt (1759–1806;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minster 1783–1801 and 1804–1806. Pitt had presided
                  over the declaration of war on Revolutionary France in 1793 and favoured Catholic
                  Emancipation.</note> with which you promised to favour me. It is not I think from
               any clinging prejudice that I am unable to regard M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pitt as a
               great statesman. His conduct of the war appears to me to have been miserable, &amp;
               his domestic policy perilously erroneous in some momentous points – more especially
               in the Catholic question. I do however full justice to his intrepidity, his talents,
               &amp; his English feeling, – in which last &amp; most essential quality for a British
               minister <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  Fox</ref> was lamentably wanting. – But I am better qualified to
               deliver an opinion upon Ignatius Loyola<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Ignatius of Loyola (1491–1556), founder of the Jesuit order.</note> or George
                  Fox,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">George Fox (1624–1691;
                     <title>DNB</title>), founder of the Religious Society of Friends (the
                  Quakers).</note> than upon either of these great leaders.</p><p rend="indent1"> Perhaps you may have heard that I am writing (in truant hours &amp;
               yet with great diligence) a life of Wesley.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of
                     Methodism</title> (1820).</note> It will be upon such a scale as to comprize a
               view of our religious history during the last fourscore years. I think it will not be
               read without interest &amp; I hope not without utility sooner or later. I remember
               Wesley well, he laid his hands upon me when I was about six years old, &amp; blest
               me. It was a chance meeting: – I was going <del>xx</del> up the stairs of a lodging
               house at <del>xxx</del> Bath when he came out of one of the rooms, &amp; was struck
               with my appearance.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">farewell my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> &amp; believe me faithfully &amp; most respectfully</salute><salute rend="indent3"> yrs</salute><signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1817-12-10">10 Dec. 1817.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>