<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3041</idno><idno type="nines">rce4312</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3041. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 24 November
                  1817</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3041.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3041" type="letter"><head>3041. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1817-11-24">24 November
                  1817</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb/> Postmarks: 10 o’Clock/ NO 27/ 1817 FN<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; E/ 27 NO 27/ 1817<lb/> Location: Keswick Museum and Art
                  Gallery, WC 162. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> We shall best be able to ascertain what Laws are wanting by making a list of what are here–</p><table rows="6" cols="3" width="740"><row><cell width="100"/><cell width="320">Ordenaoçens d’El Rei DAffonso 5.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Ordenaçoens do Senhor Rey D.
                           Alfonso V</title> (1786), no. 3269 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></cell><cell width="320">Parte 1<hi rend="sup">a</hi> da Legislaçam Antiga.</cell></row><row><cell width="100"/><cell width="320">––––– –––––– Manoel.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Ordenaçoens do Senhor Rey D. Manuel</title>
                        (1797), no. 3270 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></cell><cell width="320">––– D<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.–</cell></row><row><cell width="100"/><cell width="320">Leis Extravagantes. – Sebastian<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Leis Extravagantes Collegidas e
                           Relatadas pelo Licenciado Duarte Nunez do Lião</title> (1796), no. 3268 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                     library.</note></cell><cell width="320">–– D<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. </cell></row><row><cell width="100"/><cell width="320">Ordenaçoens Publicadas em 1603.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Ordenaçoēs e Leis do Reino de
                           Portugal, Publicadas em 1603</title> (1786), no. 3271 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></cell><cell width="320">Parte 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. da Legislaçam Moderna.</cell></row><row><cell width="100"/><cell width="320">Collecçam dos Assentos<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Collecçao Chronologica dos Assentos das Casas
                           da Supplicação e do Civil</title> (1786), no. 3267 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></cell><cell width="320"> ––––––– D<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</cell></row><row><cell width="100"/><cell width="320">Repertorio das Ordenaçoens e Leis.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Repertório das Ordenaçoēs e Leis
                           do Reino de Portugal</title> (1795), no. 3272 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></cell><cell width="320"> D<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</cell></row></table><p> It is the Collection which this Index in four volumes<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to the last-named of these
                  books, <title>Repertório das Ordenaçoēs e Leis do Reino de Portugal</title> (1795), no. 3272 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                  library.</note> refers to that seems wanting, – I find it referred to in one of the MS. volumes respecting the Mines pretty
               frequently, &amp; suppose it to be a compilation – or Code in use, under the title of Ordenaçoens e Leis do Reino de Portugal.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly this was the <title>Ordenaçoēs e Leis do Reino de Portugal, 1603</title> (1786), no. 3271
                  in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> For neither the Index nor the references in the MS. correspond with either of
               these which I possess.</p><p rend="indent1"> When you write to Lisbon, write also for the Historia Sebastica of Fr. Manoel dos Santos,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Manuel dos Santos (1672–1760), <title>Historia Sebastica, Contém a Vida do Augusto Principe o Senhor d. Sebastiaõ,
                     Rey de Portugal, e os Successos Memoraveis do Reyno, e Conquistas no seu Tempo</title> (1735).</note> – &amp; the Vida do
               Capateiro Santo, Simaõ Gomes, by Manoel da Veiga,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Manuel Veiga (1566–1647), <title>Tratado da
                     Vida, Virtudes &amp; Doutrina Admirável de Simão Gomez, Português, vulgarmente chamado o Çapateiro Santo</title> (1625). This
                  publication was an account of a prophet who predicted the return of Sebastian I (1554–1578; King of Portugal 1557–1578) and the
                  restoration of Portuguese independence from Spain – an agenda that served the interests of the Braganza family who gained the
                  Portuguese throne in 1640.</note> – a work cobbled up by the Sebastianizing, or rather Braganzan Jesuits. – Seabras Deducçaõ
                  Chronologica<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Jose de Seabra da Sylva (1732–1818), <title>Deducção Chronologica, e
                     Analytica</title> (1767), no. 2599 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. This was a strongly anti-Jesuit work that was
                  reluctant to recognize any contribution by the Society of Jesus to Portuguese life, including the restoration of Portuguese
                  independence in 1640.</note> leads in this part precisely to the very opposite deduction to what he would fain draw.</p><p rend="indent1"> Diogo de Sousa is the author <del>who</del> in the Feniz;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Diogo de Sousa
                  (16th–17th centuries), <title>Jornada ás cortes do Parnaso de Diogo Camacho</title>, a satirical journey to Parnassus probably
                  written 1614–1621. It was first published in <title>A Fenix Renascida</title> (Lisbon, 1716–1728). Southey possessed a 1746 edition of
                  this work, no. 3647 in the sale catalogue of his library. Southey had asked Hill to identify the author in his letter to him of 6
                  October 1817 (Letter 3027). He wished to quote from the poem in his review of Lord Holland, <title>Some Account of the Lives and
                     Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio, and Guillen de Castro</title> (1817),<title> Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (October 1817),
                  1–46 (at 32–33).</note> – I <del>xxxxxx</del> found a mark of mine made seventeen years ago against a passage in one of D Francisco
               Manoels Dialogues,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Francisco Manuel de Mello (1608–1666), <title>Apologos Dialogaes
                  </title>(written c. 1655–1665; published 1721).</note> which ascertained this fact, – &amp; luckily I met with it in time. </p><p rend="indent1"> I have good reason to hope that Dobrizhoffer<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717–1791),
                     <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae Natione</title> (1784), no. 843 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey’s library. </note> will be left for me ere long at the <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctors</ref>.
               It is travelling somewhere between <del>Xxx</del> Vienna, &amp; Leipsic, or Leipsic &amp; Paris at this time, having been purchased for
               me at Vienna by <ref type="m" target="people.html#KenyonJohn">Kenyons</ref> brother,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward
                  Kenyon (d. 1856), who lived in Vienna. Like his brother, John Kenyon, he was noted for giving away much of his wealth.</note> –
               Kenyon is at Paris &amp; will consign it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>. This is a great piece
               of attention on his part, – especially as he makes me a present of the book. I had gutted the book well,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had made extensive transcriptions from a copy that Scott had borrowed from the Advocates Library, Edinburgh
                  in early 1809.</note> but shall be very glad to have it <del>hand</del> at hand before the chapter upon the equestrian tribes is
               sent to the press.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 38, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819),
                  III, pp. 374–441.</note> I am going on steadily with Brazil, &amp; if I keep my health, shall do more in the next six months, than I
               have ever before accomplished in the same span of time. To day I have been working upon the MS. which <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Koster</ref> brought me,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Guerra Civil ou Sedissoens de
                  Pernambuco Exemplo Memoravel aos vindouros’, no. 3840 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. This was an account of the Mascate
                  War (or ‘War of the Peddlers’) in Pernambuco, Brazil in 1710–1711, between landowners based around Olinda and merchants in Recife
                  (backed by the colonial government). The landowners’ leaders were the first to call for Brazil to become an independent
                  Republic.</note> &amp; which he transcribed from poor P. Joam Ribeiro’s transcript of the original: – it is a history of the
               insurrection at Pernambuco in 1710, Ribeiro little thought when he copied it, that he was to be the prominent personage in the next
               rebellion himself.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Joam Ribeiro Pessoa de Melo Montenegro (1766–1817), a priest who was a
                  member of the provisional government set up by a group of revolutionaries in Pernambuco, 8 March–18 May 1817. He committed suicide
                  in the town of Paulista after the defeat of the revolutionary forces and the fall of Recife, the provincial capital.</note> The MS
               is very curious because R. Pitta<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Sebastião da Rocha Pitta (1660–1738), <title>Historia da
                     America Portugueza</title> (1730), no. 3624 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> takes the side of the insurgents,
               &amp; conceals the fact that they endeavoured to establish a republic “after the manner of Holland or Venice.”</p><p rend="indent1"> You will wonder perhaps that I have given no geographical account of the M Geraes<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Minas Geraes, one of the provinces of Brazil, described in <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London,
                  1810–1819), III, pp. 819–833.</note> – but it is reserved till the time when that Captaincy was separated from S Paulo. –<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">The captaincy (or region) of Minas Geraes was separated from São Paulo in 1720.</note> I have no
               account of Goyaz, nor do I know when it was made a Captaincy.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Goiás (formerly, Goyaz) became a
                  captaincy in 1744; described in <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, pp. 833–838.</note> There is an
               account of M. Grosso in the Patriota<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>O Patriota, Jornal Litterario, Politico, Mercantil
                     &amp;c do Rio de Janeiro</title> (1813–1814), no. 3641 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. In <title>History of
                     Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III, pp. v-vi, Southey thanked John May for procuring the third volume of <title>O
                     Patriota</title> for him, ‘when it was not to be obtained at Lisbon’. A long geographical description of the captaincy of Mato
                  Grosso featured in the issues for July, August, November and December 1813 and January and February 1814. </note> – I am writing to
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">J May</ref> to procure me the remaining numbers of the Journal (which is now defunct)
               from the Rio.</p><p rend="indent1"> I wish I were a better Patrono for my intended namesake the Baron.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert
                  Hill’s final child, born on 10 November 1817, was christened Robert Southey Hill. He became a doctor and a botanist.</note> The name
               however has done pretty well in the world with me, &amp; I hope it will do better with him, who is not likely to have so uphill a path,
               nor so many rubs in it.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> sets out for London to day. <del>I do not know of his departure
                  xxx xxxx I would xxx</del> I do not know if you have become acquainted with your neighbour <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">his brother</ref>. The <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctor</ref> no doubt will see him, &amp; will hear from him perhaps that in truant hours (&amp; with a very truant-like appetite
               for the employment) I am getting on with a life of John Wesley, which bids fair to be a work of substantial interest.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> It includes
                  Whitfields<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">George Whitefield (1714–1770; <title>DNB</title>), evangelical preacher. His life
                  was dealt with in <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820), I, pp. 136–154,
                  362–388.</note> life, much incidental biography, – an account of Moravianism, &amp; a compleat history of Methodism. I do not yet
               know whether two such volumes as those of Nelson will contain it, – but rather think it will extend to a third.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813) was published in two volumes; as was the <title>Life of
                     Wesley</title>.</note> My poems have stood still since my return: – one of them there is which I want courage to pursue,<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a reference to Southey’s poem, ‘Consolation’, prompted by the death of his son, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, on 17 April 1816. Sections were published after his death as
                  ‘Fragmentary Thoughts Occasioned by his Son’s Death’ in <title>Oliver Newman: A New-England Tale (Unfinished): With Other Poetical
                     Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp. 93–95, and ‘Additional Fragment, Occasioned by the Death of his Son’, <title>Poetical Works
                     of Robert Southey. Complete in One Volume</title> (London, 1850), p. 815.</note> – not desire. Were this done my wish would be
               never to write another verse, – Solve senescentem.<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">From Quintus Horatius Flaccus (65–8
                  BC), <title>Epistles</title>, Book 1, Epistle 1, lines 8–9; ‘Put your aged, broken horse out to pasture’.</note> My great desire is
               to get into the press with the history of Portugal, that so much labour may not be lost, &amp; that I may compleat what it is scarcely
               possible any other person <del>will</del> {would} ever take the pains of performing.<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                  never published his ‘History of Portugal’.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the young ones. Remember me also to
               Miss Bigg.<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">Alethea Bigg (1777–1847), Herbert Hill’s sister-in-law; Southey had met her in
                  Switzerland on his continental tour in 1817.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1817-11-24">24 Nov. 1817.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>