<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3096</idno><idno type="nines">rce4367</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3096. Robert Southey to John Rickman, 17 March
                  1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3096.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Huntington Library, RS 335. ALS; 3p.
                  .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
                  179–181.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3096" type="letter"><head>3096. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1818-03-17">17 March
                  1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: RS/ 17 March 1818 <lb/> MS: Huntington Library, RS 335. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
                  Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
                  179–181.</note></head><opener><salute> My dear R.</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> As soon as your Returns arrived last night I fell to work upon them, &amp; dispatched that portion forthwith; the
               second part having been pruned of what was extraneous, &amp; received its addenda, is now on the table before me, packed &amp;
               directed, wanting only its seal, &amp; will be at the Admiralty (the channel thro which it reaches <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>) some few minutes before you receive this.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman had returned drafts of his and Southey’s joint article ‘On the Poor Laws’ (published in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18
                  (January 1818), 259–308) which Southey was now sending to press via Bedford.</note> There is a note to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">G.C.B.</ref> under the same inclosure, properly worded, &amp; in all likelihood on
               Monday or Tuesday he will transmit the proofs to you.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am finishing the paper which was laid aside to make room for this.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s
                  article ‘On the Means of Improving the People’ appeared in<title> Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 79–118.</note> It
               relates to the means of improving the lower class, calling for vigilance in the magistrates &amp; parish officers with respect to ale
               houses, – &amp; speaking a good word in recommendation of the stocks.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">‘On the Means of Improving
                  the People’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 82–84, called for a reduction in the number of ale houses; Southey
                  also lamented that the stocks were no longer used (82), suggesting they might be a suitable punishment for public gambling on
                  Sundays (101).</note> Upon the subject of education there is no choice in this stage of society: – it is a ground which if you do
               not occupy the enemy will; – if you do not sow wheat, he will sow tares: – Scotland was, a hundred &amp; fifty years ago what Ireland
               is at present, &amp; education has made the difference. You can no longer have contented, unoffending &amp; submissive ignorance; – let
               us therefore take the people in childhood &amp; teach them what to believe.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Education was the
                  main focus of ‘On the Means of Improving the People’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818); Southey declared ‘Give us an
                  educated population … taught to fear God and honour the king, to know their duty toward their fellow-creatures and their Creator …’
                  (97).</note> I proceed to the prisons, to enforce your doctrine there, &amp; expose the folly &amp; mischief of suffering known
               criminals to escape punishment by the quirks quibbles &amp; informalities which Lawyers hold sacred.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">‘On the Means of Improving the People’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 113–116, dealt with prison
                  reform; 116–117 condemned legal loopholes that allowed criminals to escape justice.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> This I shall follow by a third paper upon the middle class, to point out where the real overplus of population exists,
               &amp; the great change which has been effected in the constitution of society by this redundance of educated &amp; half-educated
                  persons.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey made this point in ‘British Monachism’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 22
                  (July 1819), 59–102 (at 91), but did not make it the subject of an article.</note> Here again I shall preach upon the necessary of
               colonization, – which is as necessary to the security of the state, as bleeding to an apoplectic subject: &amp; then, passing to the
               condition of women, I shall look at your old papers upon that subject, which I think we have now the means of bringing forward to
                  advantage.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘British Monachism’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 22 (July 1819), 59–102 (at
                  90–102).</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref><note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. the <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title> outsold the<title> Edinburgh Review</title>.</note> at this time outsells the Edinburgh, &amp; it is a great thing
               to write for readers who are disposed to assent to every thing you say.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is well that you have got thro the measles, – an evil which we have to encounter, – <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> is the only one who has had this disorder: I look to it with some apprehension,
               having lost a <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEliza">sister</ref> in it.</p><p rend="indent1"> If <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> fails it will be for want of money.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A general election was imminent, though the House of Commons was not dissolved until 10 June 1818. It
                  was already clear, though, that there would be a contest in Westmorland, which was dominated by the Lowther family, who were
                  supporters of the government – the two sitting MPs were the brothers Henry Lowther (1790–1867), MP for Westmorland 1812–1867 and
                  William, Viscount Lowther (1787–1872), later 2nd Earl of Lonsdale and MP for Cockermouth 1808–1813, MP for Westmorland 1813–1831 and
                  1832–1841. However, in January 1818, a committee of Whigs and smaller landowners had brought forward Henry Brougham to challenge the
                  Lowthers – Brougham’s family home was Brougham Hall near Penrith and he could plausibly be presented as a local candidate.</note> He
               has none himself, – &amp; Curwen has none, <del>then</del> John Christian being kept always poor by the innumerable bastards whom he
               has to support, – this is actually the case.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Christian Curwen (1756–1828;
                     <title>DNB</title>), MP for Carlisle 1786–1790, 1791–1812, 1816–1820, and MP for Cumberland 1820–1828. Rumours of his
                  extra-marital affairs were commonplace in the Lake District, but the real cause of his financial difficulties were increasing costs
                  and declining profits in his collieries. His liabilities at his death exceeded £100,000.</note> Lord Thanet<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Sackville Tufton, 9th Earl of Thanet (1769–1825; <title>DNB</title>), the largest landowner in Westmorland to support
                  the Whigs, and Hereditary High Sheriff of Westmorland 1786–1825.</note> comes down with 4000 £, &amp; this I am told is all upon
               which <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">B.</ref> can reckon, – so that it is doubted whether he can come to a poll.
               Yet some of his agents talk largely, &amp; his mob at Kendal have shown their readiness to go to any lengths. They had very nearly
               murdered one of the most respectable gentlemen of the county.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1818 the Westmorland
                  constituency was contested for the first time since 1774, when the chosen candidates of Lord Lonsdale were opposed by Henry
                  Brougham. The whole campaign had been marked by disorder. According to <title>The Times</title>, 17 February 1818, Lonsdale and
                  other gentleman of his party were, at the hustings in Kendal on 11 February, ‘much bespattered’ by missiles hurled by a drunken mob.
                  On 21 February, John Fleming (c. 1769–1835) of Rayrigg Hall, Rector of Bootle 1814–1835, was injured in the election
                  violence.</note> You are right about the taint in the family, – it is from this that <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">B.</ref> acts, from impulse, passion, &amp; the total absence of any principle, for I <hi rend="ital">know</hi>, that even his friends never supposed him to have any, but looked upon him as ready for the best bidder. This
               indeed is the clue to the E–Review politics.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The politics of the <title>Edinburgh
                     Review</title> (1802–1929), the main Whig quarterly journal.</note> They set out ‘open to all parties”, coquetting with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Addington,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757–1844;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1801–1804, Home Secretary 1812–1822.</note> &amp; Anti Catholick (if I mistake not.) They
               thought {afterwards} that the Gregres<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s term for the Whig supporters of William Wyndham
                  Grenville, 1st Lord Grenville and Charles Grey, 2nd Earl Grey (1764–1845; <title>DNB</title>).</note> were the stronger side, &amp;
               therefore took a decided part with them</p><p rend="indent1"> The style Hansardic is truly characteristic<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. of the letter that Luke
                  Hansard (1752–1828; <title>DNB</title>) had sent in March 1818, concerning <ref type="m" target="people.html#LovellRobertJr">Robert
                     Lovell</ref>, whom Rickman had sought to place in his printing office. For the letter, written in Hansard’s extraordinary style,
                  see Orlo Williams, <title>Lamb’s Friend the Census-Taker. Life and Letters of John Rickman</title> (Boston and New York, 1912), p.
                  205: ‘Mr. Hansard has perused and reperused with much pleasure Mr. Southey’s classical and biographic sketch of Robert Lovell; a
                  sketch equally honourable to the gentleman by whom it is drawn, as it is creditable to the gentleman who is the subject of it. So
                  far as can at present be observed of Robert Lovell’s progress in the printing-office, Mr. Southey’s interesting trait is not
                  overdrawn; and if the young man perseveres in the variety of trying scenes ever attendant upon a parliamentary business late and
                  early, chiefly early hours, some cramfull to overflowing, then standing still (but yet in awaiting) and then to another overflowing
                  of diversities, still waiting and giving instant attention Mr. Hansard will then have fair opportunities even though Lovell be but a
                  young man and a new hand but just come into camp Mr. Hansard will have fair opportunities, which he shall gladly seek for and as
                  gladly embrace, of coming up to Mr. Southey’s and Mr. Rickman’s kind and solicitous wishes.’ For Lovell’s reluctance to take the
                  job, see Southey to John Rickman, 14 March 1818, Letter 3091.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> should use that scourge of his more frequently.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a reference to Canning’s speech on 11 March 1818, defending the Indemnity Bill, which prevented
                  prosecution of government officials for their actions under the suspension of habeas corpus in 1817–1818.</note> To be sure it was a
               tremendous dressing. You seem also to have a good man in the Solicitor General.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Robert
                  Gifford (1779–1826; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Eye 1817–1824, Solicitor-General 1817–1819, Attorney-General 1819–1824, Lord Chief
                  Justice 1824, Master of the Rolls 1824–1826.</note> He however ought to go on with prosecutions, till he checks the press, or makes
               the necessity of new laws for that purpose palpable to the common sense of the country.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1818-03-17">17 March 1818.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>