<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2527</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3798</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                    25.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2527" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2527" type="letter">
        <head>2527. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1814-12-24">24 December 1814</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9. Stafford Row/ Buckingham Gate/ London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 27 DE 27/
                        1814<lb />Endorsement: 24. Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1814<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                    25<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1814-12-24">24. Dec. 1814.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Six months ago you asked me a question respecting my Income Tax.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1814
                        Southey had become increasingly anxious about his tax status and had consulted Bedford, who worked in the Exchequer; see
                        Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 21 April 1814, Letter 2406. Bedford&#8217;s response had clearly not allayed his
                        concerns.</note> I have chewed the cud upon that question ever since. <del>The pr</del> When a man once gets into his own
                    Court of Conscience he is sure to be cast there. The process in my mind has been &#8211; I wish I had paid it. I wish I could pay it. I
                    ought to pay it. I must pay it. I will pay it. You have it here in brief, but the process was long &amp; not very easy. Especially
                    with the staring question How the Devil is it to be paid?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My income was fairly given in originally, &#8211; for my authorship concerns for many years left me more &amp; more a
                    debtor to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, &#8211; to whom I am debtor at this moment between 2 &amp; 300 &#163;. I was
                    living upon credit till the Register began,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had worked for Ballantyne&#8217;s
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> from 1810&#8211;1813. He was paid &#163;400 p.a. for his labours.</note> &amp; am living
                    upon credit now. For the Register most certainly the tax was clearly due, &#8211; but to the best of my recollection I have never
                        <del>been</del> received a schedule since it began. For after having returned first my annuity<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The annuity of &#163;160 which Southey had received from Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, until this was exchanged for
                        a government pension in 1807.</note> &amp; then my pension, this return seems to have been thought permanent as well as
                    satisfactory, &amp; no papers are ever sent to me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Deducting my losses in the Register I hold myself accountable for the tax upon 1200 &#163;. 1300 &#163; <del>xx</del>
                    &lt;more&gt; will more than cover all my other <del>x</del> emoluments. I owe Government therefore 250 &#163;. &#8211; There is but one means
                    of paying this. I must engage again in the heavy task of a Register which <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>
                        offers;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to John Murray, 12 December 1814 (Letter 2515), for Murray&#8217;s
                        suggestion that he might take over the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> and invite Southey to write for the
                        publication again. Nothing came of this plan.</note> &amp; set apart 100 &#163; out of each volume for this purpose. You must find
                        <del>means</del> &lt;the way&gt; of paying it for me, &amp; no person but you must know the transaction, if it can be
                    conducted with this secrecy. Three instalments will pay it, &amp; that in the course of two years &amp; a half. &#8211; there is a
                    difficulty also in beginning to pay regularly: &amp; I must avail myself of the commencement of this new concern to do it, if I
                    can tell how. As for the removal of the tax<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The income tax was not abolished until
                        1816.</note> it is manifestly a thing not to be looked for, &#8211; not possible in the state of our finances; &amp; I hardly think
                    it can even be lessened. Altered it most certainly ought to be, for it is cruelly disproportionate.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tho you hear of the matter now for the first time, it has been long &amp; often in my mind, since your question,
                    &amp; I am well satisfied with having come to this determination. I have written to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, without saying a word about terms; &#8211; in my letter to him I rather advise that the work should take a new title
                    &amp; <del>new</del> begin from the peace;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to John Murray, 23 December 1814
                        (Letter 2526), which suggested the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> might be re-named the <title>Annual
                            History</title>, and begin from the Treaty of Paris, 30 May 1814.</note> &#8211; but in spite of the additional labour
                        <del>I</del> my secret wishes are that he may chuse to continue the former work; &#8211; for were I to carry on the series <del>from
                        an</del> for any number of years, it would be a body of contemporary history such as no person has ever yet produced. Perhaps
                    too, &amp; this has at the moment occurred to me, a continuance of the work might make my luckless share in it turn out a good
                    venture after all.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been persuaded by the <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">John</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James Ballantyne</ref> to
                        invest &#163;209 in return for a share of the profits of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>. This had not proved a wise
                        investment.</note> If <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> is in earnest, as doubtless he is, no time ought to be
                    lost. It will take some time to get down the necessary books, &#8211; but when they are once here I will be in the press within three
                    weeks, &amp; then run for it: &#8211; for run in the <del>sho</del> harness I shall till I founder upon the road. However I am in high
                    condition, never more able &amp; never more willing.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>