<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2542</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3813</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum
                        and Art Gallery.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                        Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 394&#8211;396 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2542" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2542" type="letter">
        <head>2542. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1815-01-14">14 January
                        1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/
                        Surry<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmarks: [partial] 10 o&#8217;Clock / JA 17 / 1815; E/ 17 JA 17/ 1814<lb />MS: Keswick Museum
                        and Art Gallery<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                        Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 394&#8211;396 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1815-01-14">14 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1815. </date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will have a third portion of Brazil<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. a portion of the MS of
                            <title>The History of Brazil</title>. Southey was working on the final two volumes, which appeared in 1817 and 1819
                        respectively.</note> in a day or two, &#8211; it is only wanting an occasion for franking it to town. In the fourth portion (which
                    also is transcribed) you will find a full solution of Francisco de Sousas meaning.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Francisco de Sousa Coutinho (1597&#8211;1660), Portuguese Ambassador to the Netherlands 1643&#8211;1650. He was charged with negotiating a
                        settlement to the Dutch-Portuguese war, but delayed talks in 1646 until Portuguese troops could take Recife in Pernambuco. A
                        Treaty was not signed until 1654.</note> He had some blank signatures of the King,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        John IV (1604&#8211;1656; King of Portugal 1640&#8211;1656).</note> &#8211; &amp; for the sake of gaining time <del>by</del> (the game he was to
                    play) he filled up one of these with instructions to cede every thing to the Dutch, &#8211; thus delayed those succours to Recife which
                    had they arrived in time would have crushed the insurrection. Ericeyra<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luis de Meneses,
                        3rd Conde de Ericeira (1632&#8211;1690), <title>Historia de Portugal Restaurado</title> (1679&#8211;1698), no. 3587 in the sale catalogue
                        of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> tells the whole story, &#8211; it is the most impudent instance of diplomatic falsehood upon record.
                    Fr: de Sousa is the &#8216;perfect Embassador&#8217; of the Portugueze, &amp; there must be a work of his in existence which would throw great
                    light on the history of his times. D Francisco Manuel<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dom Francisco Manuel de Mello (1608
                        &#8211; 1666), Portuguese writer and soldier.</note> mentions it, &amp; calls it <hi rend="ital">o famozo livro, antes perfeyto que
                        acabado, das memorias historicas e politicas dos annos das suas Embayycidas &#8211; que sa&#333; quase dezoyto</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;The famous book, by a good and talented writer, of historical and political memoirs about the
                        years of his ambassadorial duties, which were nearly eighteen&#8217;.</note> He was brother to Fr Luiz de Sousa the Dominican
                        Historian.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luis de Sousa (1555&#8211;1632), Portuguese Dominican friar and
                    historian.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> From Ericeyra, Vieyra<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio Vieira (1608&#8211;1697), Portuguese Jesuit and
                        writer.</note> &amp; the Pinheiro Collection<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly the 9 volumes of manuscript
                        material described as &#8216;Papeis Varias Politicos&#8217; (1674), no 3852 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> (as I call
                    your nine MSS volumes from the Dezembarqador for whom they seem <del>first</del> to have been transcribed) I <del>have a</del>
                    make out the whole history of the negociations with Holland. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The pieces of old Wither are printed by Sir Egerton Brydges at his private press, &#8211; they make a very small part of
                    his works. Sir Egerton is in like manner printing many of our early writers, but I have not subscribed to them from an
                    apprehension <del>of</del> that the price may be more than they are really worth, &amp; that it is not very prudent for a man in
                    my circumstances who must necessarily purchase so many books because he wants to have them at hand, to buy anything of which one
                    perusal would suffice for his purpose.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Brydges had established a private press at Lee
                        Priory, Ickham, near Canterbury, in 1813. It closed in 1823. The Lee Priory Press issued rare works, in particular poetry, by
                        British authors from the Renaissance onwards. These included two editions of George Wither (1588&#8211;1667; <title>DNB</title>);
                            <title>Shepherd&#8217;s Hunting</title> (1815) and <title>Select Lyrical Poems</title> (1815). Brydges also wrote the preface to
                        new editions of Wither&#8217;s <title>Fidelia: A Love Epistle</title> and <title>The Hymnes and Songs of the Church</title>
                        published by Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme and Brown in 1815. Southey acquired a copy of the latter, no. 3038 in the sale
                        catalogue of his library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do you know any thing of <del>the history of</del> Joam Fernandes Vieira<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Joao Fernandes Vieira (c. 1613&#8211;1681). He played a key role in defeating the Dutch in Pernambuco in the 1640s and 1650s. After
                        serving as Captain-General of Angola, 1658&#8211;1661, he was Superintendant of Fortifications in North East Brazil,
                        1661&#8211;1681.</note> after the recovery of Pernambuco &#8211; Raphael de Jesus promises a second part of his history, tho of what it
                    was to consist I cannot divine.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rafael de Jesus (1614&#8211;1693) chronicled Vieira&#8217;s exploits
                        in <title>Castrioto Lusitano</title> (1679).</note> I believe he was made governor of Angola, which looks very much like a
                    banishment &amp; of the worst kind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will see in the last Quarterly a story which you told me at Lisbon brought in to correct Forbes&#8217;s account of
                    the same thing.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Forbes (1749&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Oriental
                            Memoirs</title> (1813), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (October 1814), 180&#8211;227. Southey had
                        corrected a story told by Forbes about an English Jesuit who had been imprisoned in Lisbon; see <title>Oriental
                            Memoirs</title>, 4 vols (London, 1813), II, pp. 538&#8211;30, and <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (October 1814),
                        211&#8211;212.</note> He is manifestly wrong, for it is absurd to suppose that an Englishman could stand begging at a prison grate
                    in Lisbon till somebody happened to pass who knew him. The former part of the story which you did not know is very curious. &#8211; It
                    is a cruel thing to see how <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> mutilates &amp; emasculates my reviews, &amp;
                    still worse to see what he fosters upon me. Not contented with cutting out all that was most striking &amp; demonstrative in my
                    remarks upon Popes Homer, he puts in a sentence to introduce those remarks, praising the translation in <del>such</del> a manner
                    which gives the <del>xxxx</del> lie to all that follows.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey objected to Gifford&#8217;s
                        insertion of a sentence (&#8216;Of Pope&#8217;s Homer we are, as Englishmen, proud to acknowledge the great and general merits&#8217;) at the
                        start of his generally critical discussion of Alexander Pope&#8217;s (1688&#8211;1744; <title>DNB</title>) translation of Homer. The
                        offending interpolation appeared in Southey&#8217;s review of Alexander Chalmers (1759&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works
                            of the English Poets, from Chaucer to Cowper</title> (1810), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (October 1814), 60&#8211;90
                        (85). See also Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 14 January 1815, Letter 2541.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Loureiros account of Cochin China is in existence, &amp; Langsdorff in his travels quotes a passage from the MS.
                    which he had perused.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joao de Loureiro (1717&#8211;1791), Portuguese Jesuit missionary who
                        lived in Vietnam for thirty years. He was best-known as a botanist and author of <title>Flora Cochinchinensis</title> (1790),
                        no. 1644 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Loureiro&#8217;s work in manuscript was referred to in Georg Heinrich
                        Langsdorff (1774&#8211;1852), <title>Bemerkungen auf einer Reise um die Welt in den Jahren 1803 bis 1807</title>, 2 vols (Frankfurt,
                        1812), I, p. 121, no. 1417 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Langsdorff stated he had seen this work whilst he was
                        in Lisbon between 1797 and 1802. His book was reviewed by John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>) in <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 9 (July 1813), 433&#8211;443. Southey&#8217;s hope that Loureiro&#8217;s manuscript would be published imminently was
                        disappointed.</note> This Langsdorff you must have seen at Lisbon, tho I did not. His book is very amusing, tho Barrow has
                    given so poor an account of it in the Quarterly. Loureiros work will most likely be published by the Academy, &#8211; if I did not think
                    this I would request <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> to get a transcript of it. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref> has just sent me an epitaph for Nelson, requesting that I will allow it to
                    occupy the vacant fly leaf at the end of the Life.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frere had sent an epitaph to be
                        annexed to a future edition of Southey&#8217;s<title> Life of Nelson</title>. It was not attached to the third edition of 1825; see
                        Southey to John Hookham Frere, 16 January 1815, Letter 2545.</note> It is like every thing which <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref> does, very good. Both he &amp; <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> were meant for something better than politicians.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Roderick<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> is selling neither better nor worse than I expected. The first
                    edition will be gone as soon as the second<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of <title>Roderick</title>
                        was published in 1815.</note> can be ready: but it is an edition of 500 only, &amp; compared with fashionable poems its sale
                    is just in an inverse proportion to its merit. I have at last begun my New England story, in irregular rhyme, the only measure
                    which will allow of that inequality of manner &amp; tone that the subject requires.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s posthumously published, and unfinished, &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;.</note> You shall see it as it proceeds.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I received yesterday a huge pile of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpoles papers, of much more value than the former
                    consignment; tho I have merely as yet seen their titles. There seems to be an abstract of the diplomatic correspondence for half a
                    century before his time.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Walpole (1736&#8211;1810), Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                        Plenipotentiary to Portugal, 1771&#8211;1800. Southey had been asked to write his life, but did not accomplish this task; see
                        Southey to John May, 15 January 1815.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A certain M Miot published Memoirs of the Egyptian Expedition in 1804. He has now published a second edition with
                    certain additions qui n&#8217;out pu paroitre sous le Gouvernement precedent, &#8211; one of these additions is a circumstantial detail of the
                    massacre at Jaffa <del>of</del> &lt;to&gt; which he was an eyewitness.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacques Fran&#231;ois
                        Miot (1779&#8211;1858), <title>M&#233;moires pour servir &#224; l&#8217;Histoire des Exp&#233;ditions en Egypte et en Syrie</title> (Paris, 1814). This
                        included Miot&#8217;s first-hand account of the rape and murder by French troops of the population of Jaffa after the city fell on 3
                        March 1799 (pp. 140&#8211;148), which he was not able to reveal under the previous government.</note> The poisoning story which he
                    exclaimed against in his former edition, he accredits in this, but without positively averring it.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The story that when Bonaparte retreated from Jaffa on 27 May 1799, he ordered that French troops who had been
                        struck down by the plague be poisoned; Miot, <title>M&#233;moires pour servir &#224; l&#8217;Histoire des Exp&#233;ditions en Egypte et en
                            Syrie</title> (Paris, 1814), p. 206.</note> I shall review this book.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 1&#8211;55.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; to the ursine nobility.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Hills&#8217; sons, <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref>, <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Herbert</ref> and <ref target="people.html#HillErrol">Erroll</ref>.</note> I shall
                    see them sometime in spring I hope.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>