<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2554</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3825</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 396&#8211;399.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2554" type="letter">
        <head>2554. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1815-02-12">12 February
                        1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey. R. N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helens/ Auckland <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 396&#8211;399.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1815-02-12">12 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1815</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is a long while since I have heard from you, &#8211; &amp; things go on in so even a course here where my life passes
                    between down stairs to my meals &amp; up stairs to my books or desk, &#8211; that this is verily all I have to say. To fill up the sheet
                    I must beat about the bush &amp; follow whatever happens to start.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did I tell how a Monsieur A. J. de Mierre, Interpr&#232;te Traductions asserviente des langues etrangeres pres la Cour
                    de Casation, has written a letter directed A Monsieur Monsieur Robert Southey Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>, Poete Laureat, auteur du
                    Poeme intitul&#233; Roderick the Last of the Goths, a Londres,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Maker of translations from
                        foreign languages in the service of the Court of Appeal&#8217;.</note> &amp; how this said epistle by some strange stupidity at the
                    General Post Office travelled about London in the postmans pocket till it became as filthy as that pocket itself; &amp; how M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey <del>the paper-hanger in</del> N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 28 Bedford Place (who&#8217;s he? the paper hanger
                    lived in Bedford Street) &#8211; refused it, &#8211; &amp; so at last some person had wit enough to carry it to Longmans? &#8211; M. Le Mierre
                    having heard many of my compatriots speak with the greatest eulogies of my works &amp; particularly of Roderick, is desirous of
                    passing it into his language, &#8211; his last translation having been the Castle of Indolence.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Auguste-Jacques Le Mierre d&#8217;Argy (1762&#8211;1815), <title>Le Ch&#226;teau de l&#8217;Indolence, Po&#232;me en Deux Chants, suivi de Deux autres
                            Po&#232;mes, Traduit, Avec le Texte en Regard</title> (1814), a translation of James Thomson (1700&#8211;1748; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Castle of Indolence</title> (1748). Although Mierre did not live to translate <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814), two French versions were published: <title>Roderic, dernier roi des Goths. Po&#232;me, traduit de
                            l&#8217;anglais de Robert Southey, Esq., po&#232;te laur&#233;at, par M. le Chevalier ***</title> (1821) and <title>Roderick, le dernier
                            des Goths, po&#235;me</title>, 3 vols, in <title>Oeuvres po&#233;tiques de Robert Southey, traduites de l&#8217;anglais par M. B. de
                            S.</title> (1820). See also Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 16 January 1815, Letter 2544.</note> But seeing the poem
                    advertised in the Times<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note>
          <del>newspaper,</del> he continues, J&#8217;avoue que le prix auquel il est port&#233; est un peu au dessus de mes facultes; et pourtant je
                    me voudrois pas perdre l&#8217;occasion de faire connoitre un bon livre &#224; ma nation. Auriez-vous la boute, Monsieur, si vous avez un
                    exemplaire <hi rend="ital">defectueux</hi> de votre poeme, pourvu qu&#8217;il fut <hi rend="ital">bien complet</hi> (good!) de
                        <del>xx</del> me l&#8217;envoyer a Paris. Je m&#8217;occuperois sur le champ de le traduire, apres quoi, je vous renverrai religieusement
                    votre exemplaire. Je mettrai &#224; cette traduction tout le soin dont je suis susceptible, et je me plais &#224; croire qu&#8217;elle me fera
                    honneur. Un libraire de cette ville se charge de l&#8217;impression. S&#8217;il y avoit quelques-uns de vos autres ouvrages que vous
                    voulussiez faire connoitre en France par la voie de le traduction &#8211; je vous le demanderai &#233;galement.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;I confess that the price at which it is offered is a little beyond my means; and yet I would not wish to miss
                        the opportunity of bringing a good book to the attention of my countrymen. Would you have the kindness, Monsieur, if you have
                        a <hi rend="ital">faulty</hi> copy of your poem, provided it was <hi rend="ital">fully complete</hi> (good!) to send it to me
                        in Paris. I would immediately get busy translating it, after which I would faithfully return your copy. To this translation I
                        would apply all the care I am capable of, and I like to think it would do me honour. A bookseller in this town will take care
                        of the printing. If there were any of your other works which you would like made known in France by means of translation &#8211; I
                        would ask for it in the same way.&#8217;</note> And then he ends with a flourish about the Republick of Letters.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wrote a civil answer to this poor hungry fellow, who would set about translating a <del>book</del> poem that he
                    has never seen: telling him in the first place that when the second edition was published I would send him a copy<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> appeared in 1815.</note>
                    which I desired he would not think of returning, but adding withal, that he probably did not know the extent or nature of the
                    work, which I was very sure was no way <del>calculated</del> adapted to the taste of a French public. I reminded him with a
                    reference to his Castle of Indolence, how much the character of every poem must be affected by the metre in which it is written,
                    &amp; the impossibility of giving any thing like a resemblance of an English blank verse poem in French rhyme, &#8211; &amp; therefore
                    counselled him, if he persisted in his purpose after seeing the book, to render it into prose. And so God send Roderick a good
                    deliverance! &#8211; I added that of all my works the one which might be Frenchified with the best chance of success was Kehama;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> the measure being of so novel a kind that it would justify an attempt at a
                    like experiment in translating it.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s reply does not appear to have
                        survived.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I give you joy of the <del>xxxx</del> death of the Income Tax:<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Government had made an announcement in the House of Commons on 9 February 1815 that income tax would be abolished. In fact,
                        the renewed war with France in 1815 meant the war-time income tax was not finally ended until 1816.</note> it is a great evil
                    got rid of, tho I certainly think in all sober reason that it would have been much better to have continued it for another year,
                    so as to have let government wind up the account of the war with as much ease as possible. <del>This was not done</del> You
                    doubtless see why Government has not been able to do this: &#8211; <hi rend="ital">not</hi> because the tax fell with a crushing weight
                    of injustice upon the annuitant, &amp; those persons who like you &amp; I live upon little, &#8211; but because it falls <del>xxx</del>
          <hi rend="ital"> justly</hi> as well as <hi rend="ital">heavily</hi> upon the rich landed proprietors, who cannot be got at so
                    justly in any other manner. <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref> for instance must pay not less than
                    10,000 &#163; a year income tax: no other direct tax can take from him a tenth part of that sum.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have worked hard at reviewing lately, &#8211; to make both ends meet. &#8211; My last operation was upon Lewis &amp; Clarkes
                        travels<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meriweather Lewis (1774&#8211;1809) and William Clark (1770&#8211;1838), <title>Travels to
                            the Source of the Missouri River, and Across the American Continent to the Pacific Ocean</title> (1814), reviewed by
                        Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (January 1815), 317&#8211;368.</note> &#8211; my next will be upon a Life of <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Ld Wellington</ref>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed
                        George Elliott (dates unknown), <title>The Life of the Most Noble Arthur Duke of Wellington, from the Period of his first
                            Achievements in India, down to his Invasion of France, and the Peace of Paris in 1814</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 215&#8211;275. He went on to review a further series of books relating to Wellington in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (July 1815), 448&#8211;526.</note> &#8211; Just now I am taking a treat at my great history.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &#8211; Meantime the <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Printer</ref> goes on with Brazil,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The History of Brazil</title>; volume 2 was published in 1817 and volume 3 in 1819.</note> &amp; the new edition of my
                    poems is half printed.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815).</note> I place at the end of the second volume the fiery ode against Buonaparte, &amp; that
                    which I <del>xxxxx</del> wrote for <ref target="people.html#ParsonsJohn">the fiddler</ref> in December, &#8211; but which was too good
                    to be fiddled; &#8211; so I sent them a second which was fit to be bum-fiddled.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Ode, Written
                        During the Negociations with Buonaparte in January, 1814&#8217;, <title>Minor Poems</title>, 3 vols (London, 1815), II, pp. 217&#8211;224.
                        &#8216;Ode, Written in December 1814&#8217;, <title>Minor Poems</title>, 3 vols (London, 1815), II, pp. 227&#8211;238. The latter was retitled
                        &#8216;Ode, Written During the War with America, 1814&#8217; in <title>The Poetical Works of Robert Southey</title>, 10 vols (London,
                        1837&#8211;1838), III, pp. 221&#8211;228. Southey had also provided a more anodyne, official version; see Robert and Edith Southey to
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 31 December 1814, Letter 2534.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> &amp; the young ones. The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Moon</ref> has begun to learn German, &amp; has for his own amusement written the life of
                    William the Conquerer.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> William I (1027/8&#8211;1087; <title>DNB</title>; King of England
                        1066&#8211;1087).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>