<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2639</idno><idno type="nines">rce3910</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42551
                    .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2639" type="letter"><head>2639. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref> [fragment], <date when="1815-07-23">23 July
                        1815</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Watermark: [partial] J D[MS cut]KINSON &amp; Co/
                        1811<lb/>Endorsement: 23 July 1815/ R. Southey Esq <lb/>MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42551<lb/>
                    Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1815-07-23">23 July 1815.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I thought to have begun the great article with an account of the French Memoirs written to prove that <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> is no General, – but the tone will not harmonize; &amp;
                    as the book is a masterpiece of its kind it may have a few pages to itself, which I shall most likely send off tomorrow.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Eustache-Auguste Carel (1788–1836), <title>Précis Historique de la Guerre d’Espagne et de
                            Portugal, de 1808 à 1814</title> (1815). It was incorporated into Southey’s article on books relating to Wellington and
                        the Waterloo campaign in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (July 1815), 448–526.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The turn which affairs have taken in Paris is very curious, &amp; gives me the best of all topics for winding up
                    with, – the necessity of weakening [MS missing] the state in which Louis 14<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis XIV
                        (1638–1715; King of France 1643–1715).</note> found her. [MS missing] oks – I shall be glad of Mig [MS missing] <hi rend="ital">or</hi> is a book <del>xx</del> or pamphlett of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bowdle<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Thomas Bowdler (1754–1825; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Observations on Emigration to France</title>
                        (1815).</note>[MS missing] French Memoirs of the Revolution by Prudhomme, a bookseller, who was once one of the most ferocious
                    of the Jacobines.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The bookseller and journalist Louis-Marie Prudhomme (1752–1830). An
                        opponent of Bonaparte’s, Prudhomme welcomed the Bourbon restoration. The book is possibly his <title>L’Histoire Générale et
                            Impartiale des Erreurs, des Fautes et des Crimes commis pendant la Révolution Française</title> (1797); Southey’s copy was
                        no. 2300 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I sent off a parcel some time ago in which among other things the number of the Military Chronicle were returned,
                    because I have the whole series.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Royal Military Chronicle, or, The British Officer’s Monthly Register, Chronicle, and Military Mentor</title>
                        (1811–1817).</note> The Military <title>Panorama</title> from Jany. 1814 was what I wanted – if that work be continued.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Military Panorama</title> (1812–1817), nos. 1847–1848 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> Some of
                    the other books were duplicates, – &amp; I inclosed the duplicate 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> vol. of Chardin to be exchanged for the
                        6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John Chardin (1643–1713; <title>DNB</title>), Protestant
                        French jeweller and traveller who settled in England and published <title>Voyages en Perse et autres lieux de l’Orient</title>
                        (1711). Southey had been sent by Murray the ten-volume edition published in Paris in 1811 (no. 573 in the sale catalogue of
                        his library); see Southey to John Murray [c. 30 December 1811] (Letter 2009) and 1 July 1815 (Letter 2628).</note> – this will
                    be indispensible in reviewing Sir J Malcolms <del>books</del> history,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John Malcolm
                        (1769–1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of Persia</title> (1815); no. 1661 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                        library. The review of Malcolm in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 236–292, was by <ref target="people.html#HeberReginald">Reginald Heber</ref>, not Southey.</note> – for which I shall be well prepared.</p><p rend="indent1"> I collect materials for the great article from many quarters, &amp; expect much from <del>xxxxx</del> the best
                        sources.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The ‘great article’ was presumably Southey’s forthcoming article on
                        Wellington and Waterloo in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (July 1815), 448–526.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> You have sent me the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. of the Museum Criticum, – but not the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> &amp; 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Museum Criticism; or Cambridge Classical Researches</title> (1813); no. 2015 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                        library.</note> – By the bye connected as you are with the Universities it might be worth your while to think of
                        <del>xxx</del> making a <del>complete</del> collection of the Latin poems of British authors, in a neat form, &lt;publishd&gt;
                    volume by volume, – the more compleat the better.</p></div></body></text></TEI>