<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2327</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3598</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        47891.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2327" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2327" type="letter">
        <head>2327. Robert Southey to [<ref target="people.html#BrowneWade">Wade
                        Browne</ref>], <date when="1813-11-11">11 November 1813</date>
                    [fragment]</head><p>MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47891<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>London.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-11-11">Nov. 11. 1813</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Still you see I am in this city, &amp; you will I am sure,
                    forgive me, if after so long &amp; for the most part, compulsory an absence, I
                    travel home by the straightest road &amp; the quickest conveyance, instead of
                    extending the time as I originally hoped to do by a series of visits thro
                    Shropshire &amp; Wales to Liverpool. &#8211; I am as homesick as a Swiss<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The idea of homesickness (nostalgia) as a
                        peculiarly Swiss illness was explored by Johannes Hofer (1669&#8211;1752) in his
                            <title>Dissertatio medica de nostalgia, oder Heimehe</title> (1688),
                        which tried to develop a scientific theory to explain the symptoms suffered
                        by Swiss mercenaries serving abroad.</note> (or a school boy) &amp; long
                    equally for regular employment &amp; for rest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Today I am to make my appearance at the Levee.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s official presentation at Court as
                        Poet Laureate.</note> Of my appointment to the Laureatship you will seen
                    some truth mixed with much falsehood in the newspapers. The real statement is
                    this. On my arrival I found most unexpectedly that upon Pyes<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s predecessor as Poet Laureate the
                        poet-politician Henry James Pye (1745&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>). He died on
                        11 August 1813.</note> death <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Croker</ref> had asked the succession for me, &amp;
                    the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> had
                    granted it saying, he understood I had written well in defence of the Spanish
                    cause. Meantime <ref target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lords Liverpool</ref>
                    &amp; <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Hertford</ref> (the latter of whom
                    has the situation in his gift) consulted together &amp; agreeing that <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> was the most proper person,
                    wrote &amp; offered it to him. The Prince when he learnt this was angry, &amp;
                    said he had given it to me &amp; I should have it; <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> very properly then said that he was
                    a friend of <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> as well as of
                    mine, &#8211; that we also were friends &#8211; &amp; that it would be equally unpleasant to
                    all three if the matter were not suffered to rest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> who knew nothing of all this
                    declined the appointment, thinking that the two professional situations which he
                    enjoyed to the amount of 1500 a year rendered it unfit for him to accept one of
                    the very offices which seem to have intended for men of letters
                        exclusively.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Scott to
                        Hertford, 4 September 1813, H. C. Grierson (ed.), <title>The Letters of
                            Walter Scott, 1787&#8211;1832</title>, 12, vols (London, 1932&#8211;1937), III, pp.
                        342&#8211;343. Scott held two legal offices: he was Sheriff-Depute of Selkirkshire
                        (since 1799); and Principal Clerk of the Court of Session (since 1806).
                        These posts gave him a combined salary of &#163;1600 p.a.</note> He urged that it
                    should be offered to me, &amp; wrote to me in the handsomest terms, I hardly
                    know how to express my sense of the manner in which this was done.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Scott&#8217;s letter of 1 September [1813],
                        telling Southey that he had declined the Poet Laureateship and instead
                        recommended him to Croker. He also cautioned &#8216;I am uncertain if you will
                        like it, for the laurel has certainly been tarnished by some of its wearers,
                        and as at present managed, its duties are inconvenient and somewhat liable
                        to ridicule&#8217;, H. C. Grierson (ed.), <title>The Letters of Walter Scott,
                            1787&#8211;1832</title>, 12, vols (London, 1932&#8211;1937), III, pp. 335&#8211;336.
                        Southey replied to Scott on 5 November 1813, Letter 2323.</note> This result
                    had seemed to me so far probable, that I had thought seriously how it would
                    become me to act. So I wrote to <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>
                    saying that the time was past when I could write verses upon demand upon any
                    subject &#8211; but that if I were permitted upon great public occasions to write, or
                    to be silent, as the spirit might move, in that case the office would become a
                    mark of honourable distinction which I should gladly accept. Of course it was
                    not for me to propose terms to the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref>, &amp; I left it to him to <del>determine</del>
                    discover how this sort of arrangement could be made.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey to John Wilson Croker, [4 September 1813],
                        Letter 2298.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The salary was originally 100 marks. It was raised for B
                        Jonson<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> One of Southey&#8217;s
                        predecessors; Ben Jonson (1572&#8211;1637; <title>DNB</title>), Poet Laureate
                        1616&#8211;1637.</note> to 100&#163; &amp; a tierce of Spanish Canary Wine. The wine
                    has been wickedly commuted for &#163;26 &#8211; &amp; the various deductions reduce the
                    whole to &#163;90. There was nothing to tempt me in such a salary, but in thinking
                    over the matter it occurred that there was a way in which it might be made of
                    great &amp; permanent advantage. Accordingly by adding about 12&#163; annually I have
                    ensured my life for 3000&#163;, &amp; thus converted it into this substantial legacy
                    for my family. And this thought will make me even write the odes with good will
                    if they should be called for.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At all events I purpose preparing a lyric poem upon the present
                    state of public affairs, as soon as I reach home, &#8211; so that something for the
                    Court Fiddlers may be ready if called for. And my intention is to publish it
                    with an Epistle to the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince
                        Regent</ref> in blank verse saying something about the office, &#8211; about those
                    who have held if, about myself, &amp; finally of the manner in which it becomes
                    him to be addressed &amp; me to address him.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s first official poem was the controversial
                        &#8216;Carmen Triumphale, a New Year&#8217;s Ode for 1814&#8217;. It was not accompanied by an
                        epistle to the Prince Regent.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>