<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2607</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3878</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Berg Collection, New York Public Library.  Previously  published: John
                        Holland and James Everett, Memoirs of the Life and Writings of James Montgomery, 7 vols (London, 1854&#8211;1856), III, pp. 66&#8211;68 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2607" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2607" type="letter">
        <head>2607. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">James Montgomery</ref>, <date when="1815-05-29">29 May 1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> James Montgomery/ Sheffield<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library<lb />Previously published: John
                        Holland and James Everett, <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of James Montgomery</title>, 7 vols (London, 1854&#8211;1856), III, pp. 66&#8211;68 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1815-05-29">29 May. 1815</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Montgomery</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The first thing I have to say relates to <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>. I put into his hands your review of the Excursion &amp; he
                    desired me to tell you how much he was gratified by it, &#8211; by the full &amp; liberal praise which it awarded him, &#8211; by the ability &amp; discrimination which were shown, but above
                    all by the spirit which it breathed, which is so unlike the prevailing tone of criticism.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Montgomery&#8217;s review of <title>The
                            Excursion</title> (1814), in <title>Eclectic Review</title>, 3 (January 1815), 13&#8211;39. This celebrated, amongst other things, Wordsworth&#8217;s unparalleled ability to afford
                        readers &#8216;such familiar and complete access&#8217; to the &#8216;human heart&#8217; (22) and described the poem as a work that &#8216;<hi rend="ital">will</hi> live&#8217; (39). It did, however, express
                        reservations about the poem&#8217;s lack of religious sentiment: &#8216;The love of Nature is the purest, the most sublime, and the sweetest emotion of the mind &#8230; yet the love of Nature
                            <hi rend="ital">alone</hi> cannot ascend from earth to heaven&#8217; (19).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Secondly, &#8211; but first in importance, &#8211; now that the fine season is arrived, will you fulfil in summer the purpose which was frustrated in autumn, &amp; come to visit
                    me? Neither you nor I need be reminded of the uncertainty of life, &#8211; <del>xxxxx</del> we are now neither of us young men, &amp; if we suffer year after year to pass by, we may
                    perhaps never know each other in the body: <del>xxxxx</del> I want to have the outward &amp; visible Montgomery in my minds eye, the form &amp; outline &amp; tangible image of my
                    friend. Come! &amp; come speedily. There is a coach from Leeds to Kendal, but whether daily or only thrice a week, I do not know; you can easily learn this at Sheffield. From
                    Kendal here, there is one every weeks-day in the morning, which will bring you here by twelve o&#8217;clock. Write, &#8211; &amp; fix the time for coming: <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, who is now in London, will probably be home in about a fortnight, &amp; both he &amp; <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> (with whom you will be much interested) are very desirous of seeing you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I think your objection to the warlike part of Rodericks character is not well founded; &#8211; it would be so if I had designed &lt;him&gt; as a model of Christian
                    perfection, &amp; yet tho wars are most unquestionably forbidden by the Gospel, there are wars of that description in which it is allowable to take part, &#8211; unless we suppose that
                    even self-defence is unlawful, which is an absurdity.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Montgomery had read parts of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814)
                        prior to its publication. He had also reviewed it for the <title>Eclectic Review</title>, 3 (April 1815), 352&#8211;368; and expressed particular concern about Roderick&#8217;s invocation
                        of God to justify his killing of others: &#8216;the vengeance pursued by him [Roderick], is vengeance against infidels, traitors and usurpers. Be it so; but still let the patriot
                        fight, and the avenger slay, in any name, except in the name of Him, whose &#8220;kingdom is not of this world&#8221;&#8217; (361).</note> But without entering into that question, Roderick acts
                    under <del>xx</del> what was then the universal, &amp; is still the general belief that he was doing his duty in making war against the cruel enemies of his country with all his
                    heart, &amp; with all his soul &amp; with all his strength. &#8211; If I proceed with Oliver Newman<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Oliver Newman</title>, set in New
                        England in 1675&#8211;1676, with an eponymous Quaker as a hero. It was unfinished at the time of Southey&#8217;s death and was published posthumously.</note> of which I have as yet only
                    written the first short canto, I shall pursue the Quaker principle as far as it can be carried, without violating an <del>xxxxxxxxx xxxxx</del> instinct, &amp; after leading Oliver
                    thro many trials of patience place him in a situation wherein it becomes his clear duty to cut a man down with a tomahawk. You exhort me to take an English story, &amp; I would
                    fain do so, if our history offered one to my satisfaction: but I have often &amp; often revolved it in my mind without success. At present I am wholly occupied in prose, &#8211; my
                    concluding volume of the history of Brazil is in the press,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Two further volumes of <title>The History of Brazil</title> appeared, in 1817
                        and 1819, respectively.</note> &amp; it will not be long before that of the Peninsular war<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular
                            War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> be in the printers hands also. I have work before me of this kind to an extent which you will be surprized to see; &amp; shall not be out of
                    the printers hands for several years, &#8211; if I live so long.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The apprehensions under which you last wrote are fully confirmed, &amp; Europe is once more involved in war by the ambition of a single individual, whom I verily
                    believe to have accumulated a heavier load of guilt upon his soul than any human being ever did before him.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Napoleon Bonaparte
                        (1769&#8211;1821), who had left his exile in Elba on 26 February 1815 and re-assumed his role as Emperor of France.</note> I could almost <del>believe</del> persuade myself that this
                    is permitted in order to draw upon him &amp; his atrocious army &amp; that guilty city of Paris the punishment due to their crimes. The game which he is now playing proves his
                    weakness, which he must feel very severely before he could court the Jacobines &amp; affect to talk <del>xxx</del> &lt;of&gt; liberty.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        During the &#8216;Hundred Days&#8217; Napoleon gave France a Constitution, with a Chamber of Peers, elected Chamber of Representatives and a guarantee of freedom of the Press. This &#8216;Acte
                        Additionel&#8217; to the original Bonapartist regime was approved by a plebiscite. He also definitely and finally abolished the French slave trade.</note> I am sorry to see the
                    Jacobines act with him, &#8211; for I would fain have believed that with all their dreadful errors, they set out with a noble principle: but they are now proving that their only impulse
                    at present is a feeling of personal hatred toward the Bourbons, which Lewis 18<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis XVIII (1755&#8211;1824; King of France 1814&#8211;1824), head of
                        the French House of Bourbon.</note> is far from deserving. I look to the war with anxiety, but not with fear: on our part it is so just, so called for by every proper feeling
                    &amp; sound principle, that nothing can oppose it except that vile infatuation which has made a few persons cling to Buonaparte thro all his crimes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thought you would be pleased with the party whom I directed to you in the autumn. Lady Olivia Sparrow<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lady Olivia
                        Sparrow (c. 1778&#8211;1863), daughter of the Irish peer Arthur Acheson, 1st Earl of Gosford (c. 1745&#8211;1807). She married Robert Sparrow (1773&#8211;1805) on 14 March 1797. The marriage
                        produced three children. A religious woman, Lady Olivia was also interested in the education and welfare of the poor. In the 1830s she established schools and encouraged
                        mission work on her estates, helped by Ridley Herschell (1807&#8211;1864; <title>DNB</title>).</note> is not related to Lord Calthorpe.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        George Gough-Calthorpe, 3rd Baron Calthorpe (1787&#8211;1851).</note> She is the widow of a man who tyrannized over me at school, <del>xxx</del> &lt;where&gt; I was unlucky enough to
                    sleep in the room with him.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sparrow had been a fellow pupil of Southey&#8217;s at Westminster School. His &#8216;ungovernable passions&#8217; led him to
                        pour water in Southey&#8217;s ear, try to frighten him by pretending to be a ghost, and attempt to hang him out of a window by the leg. Sparrow joined the army, rose the the rank of
                        Brigadier General and died on active service.</note> He was not without some noble seeds in his nature, but of ungovernable passions, which he had never been taught to regulate
                    or controul. I have understood that she was not happy with him, &#8211; indeed it was impossible that she should be, &#8211; it was mating the falcon with the dove. I was a good deal affected
                    when in dining with her I first discovered who she was, &amp; saw <del>that</del> the boy whom she then introduced to me as her son,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Robert Acheson Bernard St John Sparrow (c. 1800&#8211;1818).</note> &#8211; just at the age that his father was when I had seen him last, twenty-five years ago. In point of person the
                    father was one of the finest youths I ever beheld, &#8211; tho with a wildness about the eye that bespoke his unruly mind too plainly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The sale of Roderick has exceeded my expectations, a third edition is going to press, the first was 500 copies, the second 1500.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> A second edition of <title>Roderick</title> had been published in 1815, a third appeared in 1816.</note> I have seen no review of it, but can perceive more
                    faults thant the most malicious critic will point out; &amp; I have a happy indifference to criticism &#8211; which proceeds I suppose as much from temperament as philosophy. &#8211; Write
                    &amp; tell me when you will come. Remember me to Mr Gilbert<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Congregational minister Joseph Gilbert (1779&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>).
                        In 1814 he was classical tutor at Rotherham College and pastor of the Nether Chapel, Sheffield. A friend of Montgomery&#8217;s, Gilbert had married the poet Ann Taylor (1782&#8211;1866;
                            <title>DNB</title>) on 24 December 1813.</note> when you see him, &#8211; I should rejoice to see him again.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>