<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1949</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3220</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.80.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1949" type="letter">
        <head>1949. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1811-09-05">5
                        September 1811</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/
                        Durham<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.80<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1811-09-05">Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 5. 1811.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> At length we are returned after a long &amp; weary circuit, during the greater part of which our movements from
                    place to place were so frequent, that except intelligence from home at stated intervals, I never received a single letter. We
                    heard of you at Liverpool from the Dysons,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Thomas Fournice Dyson (1767&#8211;1843) of
                        Everton. He had formerly lived in Lisbon and moved in the same circles there as Southey in 1800&#8211;1801. His wife, Anne Baldwin
                        Sealy (c. 1780&#8211;1857), was the sister of Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s first wife, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary-Harriet</ref>.</note> &#8211; &amp; now shall look to hear <hi rend="ital">from</hi> you without delay, &amp; to see you
                    as soon as you can come to us. I expected to have found a letter from <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> saying
                    when he would be here, tomorrow I shall write to enquire about his plans (today there is no London post) &#8211; perhaps you had better
                    arrange your plans so as to take him back to Durham with you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My journey to London had the good effect of at least expediting <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref>
                        business.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Tom Southey&#8217;s promotion; see also Southey to Herbert Hill, 12 May 1811,
                        1921, and Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 4 August [1811], Letter 1943.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> wrote me a very handsome note when it was done, &amp; it is much to his
                    credit that he should have thus interfered to oblige me, after the manner in which I had spoken <del>of</del> upon the D. of Yorks
                        business,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1809, Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827;
                            <title>DNB</title>), had been forced to resign as commander-in-chief of the British army in the wake of allegations that he
                        had profited from office trafficking. After a lengthy investigation, the charges were found to be unproven. It had, however,
                        become apparent that his former mistress Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) had received money from
                        individuals keen for her to use her influence with the Duke, and that the Duke himself had known of her actions. For Southey&#8217;s
                        account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 109&#8211;301.</note> &amp; the Walcheren Expedition,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Walcheren Campaign, an unsuccessful British expedition to the Netherlands in 1809. The
                        plan had been to open another front in the war against Napoleon. Although there was little actual fighting, the British forces
                        were severely depleted by a sickness quickly dubbed the &#8216;Walcheren Fever&#8217;. For Southey&#8217;s account, <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 660&#8211;692.</note> &#8211; for the sheets of the Register were at the Admiralty before the
                    whole was printed. Unquestionably common sense ought to teach a minister that he may be assisted more efficaciously by
                        <del>the</del> a man who does not fear to condemn parts of his conduct, than by one who defends him thro thick &amp; thin, but
                    this is a kind of sense which is very improperly named, for no kind is so uncommon.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I went to Taunton, leaving <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> at Bristol. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">My Aunt</ref> was well &amp; in good spirits, convinced that there had been some foul play
                    about the wills, &amp; determined to spare no trouble in finding it out. She has recovered tenements to the amount of about 400 &#163;.
                    purchased after the dormant surrenders were made, &amp; therefore devolving to her as heir at law by the custom of Taunton
                        Dean.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;custom&#8217; of Taunton Deane was the local Manor&#8217;s custom of copyhold tenure.
                        Mary Southey felt this allowed her to inherit some of her brother, Thomas Southey&#8217;s, copyhold property, especially property
                        that was separate from the land and buildings he held in trust (under a &#8216;dormant surrender&#8217;).</note> There seems also a chance
                    that I may have a lawsuit for the recovery of ten acres recovered under Cannon Southeys<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Cannon Southey (d. 1768), was a distant cousin of Southey&#8217;s. His exceptionally complex will, especially concerning his estates
                        at Fitzhead, was a constant source of litigation. Thomas Southey had been a trustee of some of this property.</note> will,
                    &amp; sold by <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> T. Southey</ref>, he it is supposed having no
                    power to sell them. This poor man had the punishment before his descent &#8211;of perceiving the rascality of his servants, when it was
                    too late for him to alter his will. They would literally have let him die for want of necessaries in his bed, if <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt</ref> had not been in the house, &#8211; &amp; he declared that if he lived to get up again
                    he would make strange alterations. His man Tom<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom, a servant of Thomas Southey (dates and
                        surname unknown).</note> has never gone to bed sober since, it is a race between his constitution &amp; his finances, &amp; if
                    he do not drink himself to death, he will live to be a beggar &#8211; so completely is this wretched fellow ruined by having his fortune
                    made. Old Oliver<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Simon Oliver (1732&#8211;1814), a Bristol linen merchant and an old
                        acquaintance of Thomas Southey, who was also in this line of business. His son, William Oliver (1775&#8211;1830) of Hope Corner,
                        Taunton, was probably a major beneficiary of Thomas Southey&#8217;s will.</note> it seems has for years been maligning <del>x</del>
                    us, in the view of obtaining <del>t</del> what he has got for his own family. The old <del>xxxxxxxx</del> scoundrel now affects to
                    wonder at the will, but he says nobody could expect he would leave his property to a set of nephews who were always insulting him.
                    This charge he has frequently &amp; publicly made in Bristol, &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> is
                    now authorised to meet it with a declaration that the charge is absolutely false, &amp; that <del>he himself has</del>
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> T.Ss</ref> belief of it was produced by Oliver himself, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt</ref> having <hi rend="ital">heard</hi> him abuse us. I know not why I have written
                    so much upon a subject of which I have thought so little.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Write &amp; tell me how you are, &amp; what are your present plans. It would give me great pleasure to hear you had
                    resolved upon remaining at Durham, &#8211; By this time you are in some degree recovered from the shock which you have sustained, &amp;
                    are more able to consider calmly the hazard of exchanging a certainty for a precarious adventure.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;shock&#8217; was the death of Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s first wife, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary-Harriet</ref>. He was thinking of moving his doctor&#8217;s practice from Durham to London.</note> My own views may not be
                    entirely disinterested, for it is a considerable comfort to me to have you settled in the North, within a days journey; but I
                    think that however this may influence my wishes, it has no effect upon my judgement.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel</ref> is here, &amp; will be rejoiced to see you in these
                    parts, tho I dare say the first sight of you upon the island will throw him into such a fit of tears, as <del>he</del> came upon
                    yesterday when we were for the first time at his table.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> This was Peachy&#8217;s first visit to
                        Keswick since the death of his first wife, <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma</ref>.</note> It was a very painful visit
                    to all parties.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The children are all well, &#8211; I hope you will soon come &amp; make acquaintance with the three whom you have never
                    seen. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>