<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2277</idno><idno type="nines">rce3548</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2277" type="letter"><head>2277. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1813-06-30">30 June
                        1813</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/
                        Llantony/ Abergavenny<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 26<lb/>Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 36–37
                        [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1813-06-30">June 30. 1813</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your comedy<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor had sent Southey the manuscript of ‘The Charitable
                        Dowager’, a comedy. It was never published or performed.</note> came to hand a fortnight ago. My house then was &amp; long
                    had been in a dismal &amp; comfortless state. <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">A brother</ref> of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">my wife’s</ref> came here at Christmas, intending to stay only a few weeks; – he brought a
                    liver-complaint with him, a blood vessel gave way in the lungs soon after his arrival, &amp; he died on Thursday last, having long
                    been more like a skeleton than I could have supposed it possible for any thing living to be.</p><p rend="indent1"> What you tell me of Bethams conduct equally grieves &amp; surprizes me.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Charles Betham (b. 1779), brother of Mary Matilda. Southey had been responsible for introducing Betham and Landor, see his
                        letter to Mary Matilda Betham, 30 October 1811, Letter 1974. Charles had rented one of Landor’s largest farms at Llanthony. 
                        Betham and Landor were soon in dispute over the rent and the use of the land. The final straw was when Betham’s brother, Frederick (b. 1789/1790), dug up trees Landor had
                        planted. Landor denounced Frederick in a handbill that he personally posted up in Monmouth during the assizes. Betham sued for
                        libel, Landor lost and had to pay £100 in damages. For Betham’s version of events, see Ernest Betham, <title>A House of
                            Letters</title> (London, 1905), pp. 262–277.</note> Of him personally I know very little; but <ref target="people.html#BethamMatilda">his sister</ref> is a woman of talents &amp; great goodness, – &amp; in spite of every
                    disadvantage of person &amp; manner, a favourite with all who know her; – I thought him a of a good stock, &amp; doubted not that
                    he was a man of honour as well as honesty, – otherwise I should never in evil hour have directed him to the vale of Ewias. Nothing
                    can be worse than what you say of him, nor does it appear possible that any representation on his part can alter the plain facts,
                    which are as bad as possible. – He sent me a vulgar fellow from Aberga’ny last summer, which gave me a bad opinion of his taste in
                        companions.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The Charitable Dowager I suppose is drawn from life, – at least it has all the appearance of a portrait. As a drama
                    there is a want of incident, &amp; of probability in that upon which the catastrophe depends; but the dialogue abounds with those
                    felicities which flash from you in prose &amp; verse, more than from any other writer. I <del>x</del> remember nothing which at
                    all resembles them, except in Jeremy Taylor;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Church of Ireland bishop and religious
                        writer Jeremy Taylor (bap. 1613, d. 1667; <title>DNB</title>).</note> he has things as perfect &amp; as touching in their
                    kind, but the kind is different; there is the same beauty, the same exquisite fitness, – not the point &amp; poignancy which you
                    display in the Comedy &amp; in the Commentary,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor’s <title>Commentary on Memoirs of Mr
                            Fox</title>, which was ostensibly a response to John Bernard Trotter’s (1775–1818; <title>DNB</title>) laudatory account
                        of his erstwhile employer Charles James Fox. Although the <title>Commentary</title> was
                        printed, Murray eventually suppressed its publication, refusing to issue a book that attacked the Tory government and was
                        dedicated to James Madison (1751–1836), President of the United States 1809–1817, with whom Britain was about to go to
                        war.</note> – nor the condensation &amp; strength which characterise Gebir &amp; Count Julian.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor’s epic <title>Gebir</title> (1798) and his tragedy <title>Count Julian</title> (1812).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I did not fail to notice the neighbourly compliment which you bestow upon the town of Abergavenny.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The town nearest to Landor’s Llanthony estate. Landor’s disputes with his neighbours had given
                        him a hatred of most things Welsh.</note> – Even out of Wales however something good may come, – besides Welsh flannel, &amp;
                    lambs-wool stockings. I am reading a great book from Brecknock, – for from Brecknock of all places under the sun, the fullest
                    Mahommedan history which has yet appeared in any European language, has come forth.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        orientalist and army officer David Price (1762–1835; <title>DNB</title>), a native of Breconshire and later deputy lieutenant
                        of the county. His <title>Chronological Retrospect, or, Memoirs of the Principal Events of Mohammedan History</title> was
                        published in three volumes between 1811–1821. Southey’s copy was no. 2350 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> Without
                    being a good historian Major Price is a very useful one; he amuses me very much, &amp; his volumes are full of facts which you
                    cannot forget, tho the Mahommedan Propria quæ maribus<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘names which are deemed
                        appropriate’. Southey clearly had difficulty with Arabic proper names.</note> render it impossible ever to remember any thing
                    more than the great outlines. – A <del>x</del> dramatist in want of tragic subjects never need look beyond these two quarto
                    volumes.</p><p rend="indent1"> In about three weeks I go to London, at an ill-timed season – but unavoidably. I give up the Edinburgh Register
                    with this fourth volume,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813) was the last issue to contain contributions from Southey.</note>
                    having got into bad hands with it, &amp; therefore in a fair way of being defrauded. Except in the direct loss which I am likely
                    to sustain there is little to regret in this, – for if I cannot employ myself to more advantage, I shall at least in fortune be
                    perfectly master of my own time.</p><p rend="indent1"> What Jupiter means to do with us, he himself best knows, for as he seems to have stultified all parties at home,
                    &amp; all powers abroad there is no longer the old criterion of his intentions to help us <del>t</del> in our foresight. I think
                    this campaign will lead to a peace, – <del>tho</del> such a peace <del>be xxxx may probably</del> &lt;will&gt; be worse than a
                    continuance of the war if it leaves Buonaparte alive; but the causes of the armistice<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        There was a brief armistice between France and the forces of the Sixth Coalition 4 June-13 August 1813, to allow both sides to
                        re-group their forces.</note> are as yet a mystery to me, &amp; if hostilities should be renewed which on the whole seems more
                    probable than that they should be termin[MS torn]. I still hope to see his destruction. The peace which would then come would be
                    lasting, &amp; during a long interval of exhaustion &amp; rest perhaps the world will grow wiser, &amp; learn a few practical
                    lessons from experience. The worst prospect is at home, – <del>&amp;</del> our naval superiority shaken, – the foundations of
                    every establishment undermined, &amp; the dragons teeth sown all around us. – I suspected that the Americans<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Britain and the United States were at war 1812–1814. The United States had only six frigates, but
                        they were heavily armed with 44 or 38 guns and won some notable victories against British ships, beginning with the USS <hi rend="ital">Constitution</hi>’s defeat of HMS <hi rend="ital">Guerriere</hi> on 19 August 1812.</note> must have made some
                    improvements in gunnery, &amp; it was a relief to my heart when I learnt that this was actually the case. They stuff their wadding
                    with bullets, – which accounts for the carnage on board our ships, – &amp; they make their cartridges of very thin sheet lead, so
                    that it is not necessary to spunge the guns, – thus they give nearly two to one, almost doubling their force.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> I fear I shall not see you this year. Remember me to <ref target="people.html#LandorJulia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Landor</ref> – God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>