<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2124</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3395</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British
                        Library, Add MS 47888 .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 283&#8211;287 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2124" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2124" type="letter">
        <head>2124. Robert Southey to Edith Southey, <date when="1812-07-18">18 July 1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland./ Single<lb />Stamped: AUCKLAND<lb />MS: British
                        Library, Add MS 47888 <lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 283&#8211;287 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>St. Helens Auckland.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-07-18">July 18. 1812</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Edith</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> We had a delightful walk after leaving <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> as far as Lyulphs Tower,
                    where we parted with <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">S. Reid</ref>, &amp; then went on to Pooley Bridge, had a comfortable
                    cup of tea &amp; reached Penrith about eight o&#8217;clock. Called on A. Harrison<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anthony
                        Harrison (dates unknown), a Penrith attorney, whose <title>Poetical Recreations</title> (1806) had some success.</note> found
                    he was at Carlisle, but that we were expected to supper, excused ourselves on the necessity of eating at the inn, supped there
                    upon trout &amp; roast fowl, drank some most admirable cyder &amp; a new manufactory of a nature between soda water &amp;
                    ginger-beer, &amp; called pop because pop goes the cork when it is drawn, &amp; pop you would go off too if you drank too much of
                    it. Wednesday we left Penrith at five o clock bound for the house of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Salkeld of Ranbeck near Kirkland,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Salkeld (1763&#8211;1819), who owned and farmed the Ranbeck estate.</note> from whom we were
                    to receive directions for <del>xxx</del> our march over Crossfell &amp; trusting to find a place to breakfast at upon the way. The
                    road was now new to us. Past thro a newly inclosed country covered with fine corn. in Penrith parish there are this year 400 acres
                    of wheat more then were ever sown there before. 4 miles to Eden-hall, the seat of the Musgraves;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The owner at this time was Sir Philip Musgrave, 8th Baronet (1794&#8211;1827).</note> &#8211; a fine old mansion, deserted
                    by the family, but inhabited by servants. crost the Eden about three quarters of a mile <del>below</del> &lt;farther&gt; by a fine
                    bridge, &#8211; a beautiful stream <del>winding</del> flowing under a wooded bank by <del>a</del> fine meadows on the other side.
                    Langwathby the next village &#8211; then <del>xxxxx</del> crossing a great common <del>before xx</del> we came to Skirwith a village
                    pleasantly bowered in trees, seven miles from Penrith. here we learnt was the only public house which we should find, &#8211; &amp; a
                    miserable one it was, where all we could get was a basin of milk &amp; a piece of dry bread, served us by a girl whose
                        <del>xxxx</del> hands went out of the washing-<del>xxx</del> tub into the milk vessel. This breakfast cost us three pence a
                    piece. about nine we reached M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Salkelds, at the foot of Cross fell he provd to be a brother of Colonel
                        S.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lieutenant-Colonel Salkeld (1761&#8211;1820) of Holme Hill, formerly Quarter Master
                        General of the Bengal Army.</note> &amp; a very good natured man, but living quite <del>like a man who</del> as his fathers
                    had done before him. Tho only nine o clock nothing was said of breakfast, we had beer set before us, hung beef, &amp; an uneatable
                    cold gooseberry pie. The beef &amp; beer however stood us in good stead, as you will possibly perceive.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How far to Middleton Tees-dale over the fells? About ten mile, he said, &amp; he would go with us to the top of the
                    mountain which was three miles. Accordingly he guided us up a very easy ascent to the highest point of Crossfell &#8211; where a heap of
                    stones with a plank placed upright at the top of them had been raised <del>xxx</del> by Colonel Mudge<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Mudge (1762&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), superintendent of the Ordnance Survey. He had been responsible
                        for developing the Ordnance board&#8217;s trigonometric and topographical surveys.</note> when he took the height of the mountain
                    <del>x xxxxxxxxx &lt;xxxxxx&gt; it with the xxx</del> which it seems is now ascertained to be inferior to <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>, &#8211; as indeed
                    it evidently appears to be. About two years a remarkable accident occurred here. Three men from Alstone Moor were crossing the
                    mountain, &amp; were on the descent walking over a mass of frozen snow <del>which</del> when as they were near the edge of the
                    snow it slid from beneath &lt;them&gt; the under part being dissolvd. Two of the men attempted to run, but were of course
                    overtaken by the <del>xxx</del> current of <del>xxx</del> water &amp; half dissolved snow. The third, as he afterwards said,
                    thought it best to face the enemy, he <del>xxxxx xx</del> turned round when he felt his feet failing him, sprung up, &amp; threw
                    himself with his face on the crust of snow &amp; fixed his hands into it. In this manner he was floated down about two hundred
                    yards, with tremendous rapidity, faster he said than ever mail coach went, but he reached the bottom with no other injury than a
                    few scratches from the masses of hard snow &amp; found his way to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Salkelds which was the nearest house.
                    Salkeld immediately mustering all the men about his house set out with his sheep dog in quest of the other two. The dog who had
                    been accustomed to search for sheep under the snow soon found their bodies, &#8211; they had been drowned &amp; crushed at once,
                        <del>xxx</del> so that their death must have been instantaneous, &#8211; &amp; they were dashd against the stones as the incumbent
                    torrent <del>xxx</del> swept them away.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A very little below the summit is the head of the Tyne, you hear water flowing under the stones &lt;beneath you&gt;
                    for several yards before you reach the place where it is visible, the spring which appears is but a small stream, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> could step over it, the water intensely cold. Close beside are the remains of some
                    stone tables where the Duke of Norfolk<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wealthy aristocrat and landowner, whose property
                        included estates in North and North West England; at this time the title was held by the Whig politician Charles Howard, 11th
                        Duke of Norfolk (1746&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>). The anecdote, though, may refer to his father, Charles Howard, 10th Duke of
                        Norfolk (1720&#8211;1786; <title>DNB</title>), who was well-known for his heavy drinking.</note> &amp; a party of Cumberland
                    gentlemen used annually to dine. The <del>xx</del> meeting was at length given up because they used to get drunk &amp; break their
                    bones in riding down the mountain, no person was so glad of its discontinuance as Salkeld&#8217;s father,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Salkeld (d. 1809), who owned land at Ranbeck, Kirkland and Penrith.</note> &#8211; who used to have
                        <del>xx</del> to nurse the drunkards in <del>xx</del> his house <del>xx xxxxx xxxx</del> while they were under the surgeon&#8217;s
                    hands. At one of the last meetings a quarrel arose between two of the party, &#8211; one of whom in his cups ordered the fidlers to play
                    Over the water to Charley,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The toast given by Jacobites to the Stuart pretender to the
                        British throne, Charles Edward, &#8216;Bonnie Prince Charlie&#8217; (1720&#8211;1788; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; &amp; a battle took place
                    upon this Jacobite provocation, some forty years after Jacobitism was at an end every where else.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Within a mile of the Tyne head, &amp; on the same summit is the head of the Tees, so small a spring that just below
                    its rise I spanned it. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> S. told me to follow this, &amp; it would bring us to the Weal, the Cauldron Snout
                    &amp; the High Force. We had from seven to ten miles he said, to Middleton &amp; the day was before us for it was not twelve when
                    he left us. From thence till eight at night we were on our feet, &amp; except one mine at which we enquired <del>xxx</del> &amp; a
                    party of three miners afterwards saw nothing <del>xxx</del> which bore any marks of humanity or cultivation till 7 in the evening
                    when we came to the first house about three miles below Cauldron Snout. Luckily about <del>xxxxx</del> a mile &amp; half farther
                    we came to a public house at Moor-Ridge near the Falls where we got one bed, &#8211; heartily glad to get there, after the most
                    fatiguing days work (except one days water-work at Cambridge)<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> When Southey rowed from
                        Cambridge to Ely and back in one day, Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, [c. 3 June 1793], <title>The Collected Letters of
                            Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 50.</note> that I ever went thro. We were fifteen hours on foot with only half an
                    hours rest, &#8211; a most bad breakfast &amp; no dinner.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Next morning saw the Force &amp; Wynch bridge &#8211; which I have no time to speak of farther than to say that they well
                    repaid us for our march.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> met us. We got here
                    in good time &amp; good spirits but <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> found a letter telling him of his
                    wretched brothers death.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Danvers (d. 1812), a bankrupt former apothecary.</note>
                    Desirable as such an event was it has affected him, as it naturally would a good deal, he thinks it best not to say anything of it
                    while he is here. We supt at the Taylors<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The home at St Helen Auckland of George Taylor
                        (1772&#8211;1851), a Durham farmer with classical interests and occasional contributor to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. He
                        was the father of Southey&#8217;s friend Sir Henry Taylor (1800&#8211;1886; <term>DNB</term>).</note> yesterday. I should have written
                    yesterday but the letters <del>xxx</del> must set off at ten in the morning, so an early epistle this morning will arrive as soon
                    as if it had been pennd yesterday afternoon. We go to Durham today, return tomorrow or Monday, &amp; start Tuesday. Tom I believe
                    will walk back with me. Harry we shall see in the autumn when he leaves Durham. Yesterday he received a letter from <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, telling him that Sealey<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard
                        Sealy (d. 1821), a merchant at Lisbon and father of Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s first wife.</note> will assist him to try his
                    fortune in London, where he cannot fail of making it.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you. Love from all here, &amp; a kiss to the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Queen</ref>
                        &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref>.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>