<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1871</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3142</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                        c. 24.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 302&#8211;305 [in part]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1871" type="letter">
        <head>1871. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1811-02-16">16 February 1811</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                        c. 24<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 302&#8211;305 [in part]. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1811-02-16">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 16. 1811.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If I had not heard of you from <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> at the beginning of the month
                    I should have been very uneasy about you. Thank you for your letter, &amp; for your serviceable interpolation of the review,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bedford&#8217;s interpolations in Walter Scott&#8217;s review of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>
                        (1810), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5 (February 1811), 40&#8211;61 (esp. 55&#8211;56). See also Southey to Grosvenor Charles Beford,
                        1 January 1811, Letter 1848.</note> which is just what it should be, &#8211; that is to say, <del>x</del> just what I would wish it,
                    only I wish you would <del>expunge the</del> not call me the most sublime poet of the age,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The offending phrase did not appear in the published version, which, instead, paid &#8216;our highest tribute of praise &#8230; to Southey
                        as a poet and a man&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5 (February 1811), 55.</note> &#8211; because in this point both <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> are at
                    least my equals. You will not suspect me of any mock-modesty in this. On the whole I shall have done greater things than either, &#8211;
                    but not because I possess greater powers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My <del>xxx</del> abode under <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> will have been more unfavourable to
                    my first years annals<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Southey&#8217;s work for the historical section of the
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810).</note> than to any other, because I had fewer <del>xxxx</del>
                    channels of information opened, &amp; because &lt;of&gt; home politics I was very ignorant, never liking them well enough to feel
                    any interest beyond that of an election feeling. Now that it becomes my business to be better informed I have spared no pains to
                    become so, &#8211; &amp; the probability is that I learn as much political news to my purpose by letter as I should do by &lt;that&gt;
                    intercourse <del>x</del> which would be compatible with my way of life. &#8211; Of three points I have now <del>persuaded</del>
                    &lt;convinced&gt; myself, &#8211; that the great desideratum in our own government is a Premier instead of a Cabinet, &#8211; <del>&amp;</del>
                    that a regular opposition is an absurdity which could not exist any where but in an island without destroying the government, &#8211;
                    &amp; that parliamentary reform is the shortest road to anarchy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am sincerely obliged to <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> for his desire to serve me, &amp;
                    sincerely glad that I stand in need of no services. Not that I am by any means above being served, or feel any ways uncomfortable
                    under an obligation. On the contrary I should &lt;hold&gt; myself in the highest degree obliged to any person who would promote
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> for my sake, &#8211; but for this we must wait till the First Lord is in power.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a reference to Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville (1742&#8211;1811; DNB), First Lord of
                        the Admiralty 1804&#8211;1805.</note> For myself I am in a fair way of wanting nothing, &amp; if great men will but give me their
                    praise, they may keep their promises for others; &#8211; their praise would prove actual pudding, &#8211; let them only make it the fashion to
                    buy my books, &amp; in seven years time I will purchase a house &amp; ground enough for the use of a dairy, within a days journey
                    of London. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> had 2000 guineas for the Lady of the Lake.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>The Lady of the
                            Lake</title> (1810). It sold over 20,000 copies in the year of its publication.</note> &#8211; If <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> would but compare Buonaparte to Kehama in the H of Commons, &#8211; I might get half as
                    much by my next poem.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am reviewing Pasleys book,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Charles William Pasley (1780&#8211;1861;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Essay on the Military Policy and Institutions of the British Empire</title> (1810). Southey&#8217;s
                        article was deemed by <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> to be &#8216;perfectly incorrect and dangerous&#8217;. The
                        version published in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5 (May 1811), 403&#8211;457, was, therefore, much altered by <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, in consultation with Gifford and <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>; see <ref type="l" target="/reference/qr/index/10.html">Jonathan Cutmore, <title>The Quarterly Review Archive</title>
            </ref>.</note> &#8211; the most important political work that ever appeared in any
                    country. The minister who shall first become a believer in that book, &amp; act upon its <del>unanswe</del> unanswerable
                    principles will obtain a higher reputation than ever statesman did before him. My review will be conciliatory towards the
                    husbanding politicians<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Those politicians who wished to conserve Britain&#8217;s resources and
                        not commit money and men to the war in Spain.</note> &#8211; that is &#8211; it will endeavour to make them ashamed without <del>feeling
                        irritated</del> &lt;making them angry&gt;. The blistering plaister for Whitbread <del>&amp; Co</del> goes all into the
                    Register, which is designed to be a perpetual blister for that Devil&#8217;s Advocate.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        radical MP Samuel Whitbread (1764&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>). For an example of Southey&#8217;s comments: &#8216;Mr Whitbread rose, as
                        usual, to play the part of advocate for Buonaparte, and to revile the allies of England&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register,
                            for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 303.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We start in May for the South. My work at present stands thus 256 pages of the Register printed, about four sheets
                    more in readiness, leaving yet another full sheet before the Parl. Proc. of the year are compleated, &#8211; including however the D of
                    York&#8217;s business<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1809, Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827;
                            <title>DNB</title>), had been forced to resign as commander-in-chief of the British army in the wake of allegations that he
                        had profited from office trafficking. After a lengthy investigation, the charges were found to be unproven. It had, however,
                        become apparent that his former mistress Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) had received money from
                        individuals keen for her to use her influence with the Duke, and that the Duke himself had known of her actions. For Southey&#8217;s
                        account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 109&#8211;301.</note> which has swoln it to this unmerciful
                        length.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> was concerned enough about the length of the historical section to
                        insist that Southey explained himself to the readers in a prefatory note; see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), [v]&#8211;vi.</note> Flushing<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The siege and capture of
                        Flushing by British troops, part of the ill-fated Walcheren campaign of 1809. For Southey&#8217;s account, <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 660&#8211;692.</note> is done, &amp; 65 pages of Spain, &#8211; there remains to write the
                    Austrian war,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> See chapters 24&#8211;27 of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 575&#8211;659, dealing with the defeat of Austria by France in 1809.</note> the American &amp; Baltic
                        affairs<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Chapters 15 and 16 of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>,
                        2.1 (1811), 405&#8211;469.</note> &amp; &lt;the change of ministry cum Duello&gt;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Spencer Perceval</ref> had become Prime Minister on 4 October 1809. The duel, on 21
                        September 1809, was between the feuding Cabinet members <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> and Robert Stewart,
                        Viscount Castlereagh (1769&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>); Canning was wounded in the thigh, his opponent lost a button from his
                        coat; see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 788&#8211;792.</note> about as much more of Spain,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey underestimated: events in Spain and Portugal occupied the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 470&#8211;574 and 633&#8211;786.</note> &#8211; so that April will begin before all this can be
                    compleated. There is little Appendix for the year &#8211; <del>my pa</del> &amp; this makes room for my own overgrown Annals which I
                    think will exceed the bulk of the former by nearly one third; in remuneration for <del>which</del> &lt;this&gt; I have &#8211; my labour
                    for my pains. However it is well paid. <ref target="people.html#AbellaManuel">Abella</ref> supplies me well with Spanish papers, &#8211;
                    something he has got me concerning Zaragoza<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish city of Zaragoza had been
                        besieged in 1808 and 1809. It fell to the French after an outbreak of disease. For Southey&#8217;s account of the second siege
                        see, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 508&#8211;527.</note> from D Pedro Maria Rio,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Maria Ric y Monserrat, Baron de Valdeolivos (1776&#8211;1831), Spanish aristocrat and politician.</note> now Deputy for Aragon in the Cortes, I
                    have found him excellently useful. He writes to me in &#8211; issimos &#8211; of esteem &amp; I <del>am in return</del> outstep a little the
                    usual pace of English compliments in return, &amp; am his friend &amp; servant in superlatives &#8211; With a good conscience believe
                    me, for I really like him, &amp; am very sensible of his services. Of course I have sent him my best works, &amp; no doubt my name
                    will soon be in high odour in the Isle of Leon. It was a mortification to me to hear he was about to return, before I could
                        <del>xx</del> see him in London. We have <hi rend="ital">dispeeded</hi> ourselves of each other in the most cordial terms,
                    &amp; are to continue frequent correspondents.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have again taken to Pelayo,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> What became <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814).</note> after a long interval, &amp; the third section is nearly finished &#8211; it will bring me into
                    busier scenes &amp; the story will begin to open. I am afraid that having thus begun <hi rend="ital">ab ovo</hi>
          <note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;from the beginning&#8217;.</note> I must change the title <del>&amp; call</del> of the poem &amp; call
                    it Spain Restored, &#8211; for Pelayo cannot appear till <del>xx</del> I have got on a thousand lines. If I cared about <del>xxxx
                        xx</del> rules this would be a fault, but the structure must depend upon the materials, &amp; I have not too much of Roderick
                    in the beginning, considering the part he has to play in the end. &#8211; I have conceived of another poem, &#8211; upon that Philips War<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> King Philip&#8217;s War, or Metacom&#8217;s Rebellion, 1675&#8211;1676. An armed conflict between English
                        colonists and the native American inhabitants of New England. Southey&#8217;s poem was &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;, left incomplete at his
                        death.</note> which you may see <del>struck</del> in the review of Holmes&#8217;s American Annals<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Abiel Holmes (1763&#8211;1837), <title>American Annals; or, a Chronological History of America, from its Discovery
                            in 1492 to 1806</title> (1808). For Southey&#8217;s appraisal see <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (November 1809),
                        319&#8211;337.</note> impressed me some time ago. I have a strong conception of grand possibilities in this story, &#8211; &amp; you will
                    be amused to hear that the hero is to be a Quaker. There was one person you know Grosvenor who could make an epic poem with such a
                    hero, &#8211; nay with a Jack-pudding for the hero, or what <del>was</del> &lt;is&gt; more wonderful still &#8211; himself, &#8211; but tho I am not
                    the Butler,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey and Bedford had a long-standing private joke about &#8216;the Butler&#8217;, a
                        mythological hero of extraordinary powers.</note> I think I can succeed in the attempt.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you paid <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> for shoeing me, &amp; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">his Honour</ref> for the Books?<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 14 December 1810, Letter 1839.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>Xxxxxx</del> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">your father &amp; mother</ref>, &#8211; the former I hope is
                    well recovered from his illness. &#8211; Sarsaparella for your worshipful self, is I think one of the medicines which had better <hi rend="ital">not</hi> be forgotten &#8211; for without knowing what it is good for I have some faith in it as <del>xxx</del> being
                    adopted from savage herbary; &#8211; a good school of medicine. &#8211; The Capture of the Isle of France<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French territory of &#206;le de France had been captured by British troops in December 1810. It was renamed
                        Mauritius (the name by which it had been known until 1715).</note> is a good thing &#8211; <del>but</del> We must now look to the
                    Persian Gulph &amp; the Red Sea, &#8211; &amp; take especial care to keep the French out of those important points, &#8211; important as to
                    the means they afford of annoying us in their hands, &#8211; or of spreading civilization in ours. Next year I purpose to give a whole
                    chapter to the French <del>xxxxx</del> intrigues with Persia<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> In fact the French embassy
                        to Persia only received a passing mention in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.1 (1812), 300, though
                        Southey did insist on the importance of defeating French plans in the Indian Ocean as &#8216;our possession of Mauritius may be as
                        beneficial to East Africa, as the British conquests in Asia have been to the people of Hindostan&#8217;.</note> &amp; their views in
                    that quarter: I have neither time nor room for it in the present volume. Farewell send me all the news you know, &amp; continue to
                    tell me you are mending &#8211; which is the best news <del>of all</del> you can send.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I most heartily rejoice that the Outs are Outs still.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Regency Act of
                        1811 did not produce a change of ministry.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> Not a line from <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> yet. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">his wife</ref> are at Durham &#8211; He
                        waits for her delivery, which is expected late in March, &amp; then goes to sea. Our household is in good order once more<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> Not a &#8230; more: Written at top of fol 1r.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>