<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2189</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3460</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 309&#8211;311 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2189" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2189" type="letter">
        <head>2189. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1812-12-10">10 December
                        1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey. R. N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helens/ Auckland <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 309&#8211;311 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-12-10">Dec. 10. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been expecting your report upon Andrewes,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had possibly
                        suggested that his brother should consult James Pettit Andrews (c. 1737&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of Great
                            Britain connected with the Chronology of Europe</title> (1794), no. 166 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This
                    was an example of the kind of chronological history that Tom Southey might undertake in his work on the West
                        Indies.</note> &#8211; which however there was no reason for awaiting, inasmuch as what you have to consult it for is not to see
                    whether you can do what I have proposed, but how you are to do it. I cannot send you all the books in my possession which
                    appertain to the subject, because I have to write upon the state of Hayti as soon as I can find leisure for it, either for the
                    Quarterly or the Register.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 192&#8211;196.</note> &#8211; however one of the main advantages of your
                    work is that you can go on with any part of it at any time, one as well as another, according as you may have materials at hand. I
                    will send off a <del>xxx</del> parcel by the next carrier containing books enough to employ you for some time. <del>Xxx</del>
                    there will be Peter Martire&#8217;s Decades &#8211; the old translation.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pietro Martire d&#8217;Anghiera
                        (1457&#8211;1526). His <title>De Orbe Novo</title> (1511&#8211;1530) provides important early accounts of the exploration and
                        colonisation of Central and South America. In this letter, Southey references the English translation by Richard Eden (c.
                        1520&#8211;1576; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Decades of the Newe Worlde or West India: Conteyning the Navigations and Conquestes
                            of the Spanyards</title> (1555); Southey owned an edition of 1612, no. 1862 in the sale catalogue of his library. (Southey
                        also owned a Latin edition of 1574, no. 1811 in the sale catalogue of his library.)</note> This is the very earliest account
                    of the discoveries, &#8211; being as you will perceive written as the news of the discoveries reachd the Court of Castille. Munoz&#8217;s
                    history &#8211; (all that has been published &lt;of it&gt; I believe), &#8211; <del>which</del> where you will find a more methodized &amp;
                    critical account.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Juan Bautista Mu&#241;oz (1745&#8211;1799) was commissioned to write an official
                        account of Spanish involvement in the New World. Part of his researches appeared as <title>Historia del Nuevo-Mundo</title>
                        (1793), the rest were unpublished at his death. Southey owned an English translation of 1797, no. 1263 in the sale catalogue
                        of his library.</note> Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> John Smiths History, containing our first attempt at settling in any of these
                        islands.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Smith (1562/1563&#8211;1616; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Generall Historie
                            of Virginia, New-England and the Summer Isles</title> (1624), no. 2645 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
                    Charlevoix&#8217;s history of S Domingo<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pierre Francois Xavier de Charlevoix (1682&#8211;1761),
                            <title>Histoire de l&#8217;Isle Espagnole, ou de Saint Dominque</title> (1730). Southey owned an edition of 1733, no. 574 no.
                        1263 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> the two first vols of which you will do well to read <del>after</del>
                    &lt;with&gt; the Spanish accounts, &amp; the two latter are of main importance to your subject. One or two others I shall also
                    find: &amp; perhaps I may as well delay the parcel a few days till I can make any extracts from Labats&#8217; Voyages,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean-Baptiste Labat (1663&#8211;1738), <title>Nouveau Voyage aux Iles de l&#8217;Amerique</title> (1722), no.
                        1582 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; send them also, &#8211; for this will be one of your best
                    authorities.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There should be an introductory chapter upon the original inhabitants of these Islands. Do you open <del>xxx</del>
                    a book for this subject, &amp; collect in it whatever materials you meet with; &#8211; in a summary manner, with <del>xxx</del>
                    reference to the authority in every case that they may be referred to when the account comes to be drawn up. I will do the same
                    &amp; collect for you the materials <del>xxx</del> to be found in my Spanish authors. There must be another chapter concerning the
                    Slave Trade &amp; the Negroes. Keep a book for this also. I will revise these chapters for you, or arrange them when they are
                    wanted &#8211; And I will give you a final chapter, casting a philosophic eye back over what has happened in these Islands, &amp;
                    forward to what may be expected there.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The subject is much richer than you may perhaps imagine. You will find the undertaking easy when you are fairly got
                    into it, &amp; every day will interest you in it more &amp; more. You will have a good deal to do with the Buccaneers &amp; the
                    Pirates.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Keep a book, as I do, of Bio- &amp; biblio-graphy. That is all particulars relating to the lives of the authors
                    whom you consult, &amp; their works: so that you <del>xx</del> may give in the appendix a biographical account of them, &amp; a
                    critical account of their works. All historians ought to do this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Should we get you a ship you may carry on your work aboard. For the last fifty years, many of your materials must
                    be gleaned from the Naval Chronicle.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Naval Chronicle</title> was an annual
                        account of naval affairs. It had first appeared in 1759 and re-started in 1799.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must hasten for this nights post. How anxious this intelligence from Russia make me for every newspaper! Gods
                    vengeance seems to be falling upon this pestilent Tyrant at last: for allowing for much exaggeration (tho Kutusoffs letters<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Accounts of events in Russia from General Mikhail Kutuzov (1745&#8211;1813) appeared for instance
                        in the <title>London Gazette</title>, 8 December 1812.</note> have nothing of the braggart about them, &amp; seem to me in
                    every respect better than those of any of his contemporary generals) still it is unquestionable that the French are in actual
                    flight under the most dreadful circumstances: &amp; nine tenths of the army will probably be destroyed before they can reach any
                    secure winter quarters. Well done the Russians &amp; the Cossacks! What a delight will it be for Sir Robert Wilson if he should be
                    in at the death!<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The army officer Sir Robert Wilson (1777&#8211;1849; <title>DNB</title>). He
                        had travelled to Russia earlier in 1812 and was a first-hand witness of the campaign against the French invaders.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Keep the volume of the Hist. of Constantinople<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a volume of the
                        eight-volume <title>Histoire de Constantinople depuis la R&#232;gne de l&#8217;Ancien Justin jusqu&#8217;a la fin de l&#8217;Empire</title> (1672),
                        translated into French by Louis Cousin (1627&#8211;1707); Southey&#8217;s copy was no. 666 in the sale catalogue of his library. Henry
                        Herbert Southey had conducted research on the Crusades in 1811.</note> till there be an opportunity of sending it &#8211; the other
                    volumes are here: this was leant <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> for the Crusades. You will do well to
                    read it. &#8211; Probably you will be able to find some of the necessary books in the Durham Libraries. I do not know if there be any
                    thing in Purchas<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Volumes by Samuel Purchas (c. 1577&#8211;1626; <title>DNB</title>), probably
                        <title>Hakluytus Posthumus, or Purchas his Pilgrime</title> (1625) or <title>Purchas his Pilgrimes</title> (1624&#8211;1625).</note> to your purpose, but most probably there
                    will be. Good old Mr Viner<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Samuel Viner (c. 1740&#8211;1815), a minor canon of Durham
                        Cathedral.</note> will help you to this book: &amp; perhaps Hakluyt<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Hakluyt
                        (1552?-1616; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Principal Navigations, Voiages, Traffiques and Discoveries of the English
                            Nation</title> (1598&#8211;1600), no. 1212 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> may be in the same library, &#8211; in
                    my next I will tell you what Hakluyt has.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am in the tenth books of Roderick,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> having got on 2500 lines in the poem, this I hope will be half
                    of it, I wish I were getting on faster with your copy &#8211; however now that the franking season is returned I shall take a spell at
                    it sometimes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref>, &amp; my nieces<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom and Sarah&#8217;s daughters <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretdauTomandSarah">Margaret</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHannah">Mary Hannah Southey</ref>.</note> &#8211; I believe you have never been told that as
                    Bertha is Queen Henry the Eighth so Kate is Queen Katharine, &#8211; but not Katharine Parr,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Katherine Parr (1512&#8211;1548; <title>DNB</title>), the sixth and last wife of Henry VIII (1491&#8211;1547; King of England 1509&#8211;1547;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; for my Katharine is above par.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> has just lost a child to the measles. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthThomas">poor little Tom</ref> this is the second in one year.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Wordsworth died on 1 December 1812. His sister <ref target="people.html#WordsworthCatherine">Catherine</ref> had died of convulsions on 4 June 1812.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>