<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2537</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3808</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Morgan Library, MA 38.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2537" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2537" type="letter">
        <head>2537. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">James Burney</ref> [<date when="1814-12-31">c. written between
                        late December 1814 and early 1815</date>]</head><p>Address: For/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Burney<lb />Endorsement: R. Southey<lb />MS: Morgan Library, MA 38<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note: This letter
                        contains the &#8216;notices&#8217; about the &#8216;Buccaneers&#8217; compiled by Southey for Burney&#8217;s use; see Southey to John Rickman, 4 November
                        [1814], Letter 2496. A letter to John Rickman of 16 December 1814 (Letter 2518), records that Southey had been thwarted in his
                        plan to put together the &#8216;memoranda&#8217; for Burney &#8216;this evening&#8217; by the unexpected demand for a Laureate ode. The &#8216;notices&#8217; were
                        probably compiled and sent shortly after this, giving a date of between c. late 1814 and early 1815.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a thick 12ms volume, containing more than a modern quarto, of geographical &amp; statistical accounts of the
                    Spanish progression in S America &lt;of the whole viceroyalty of Peru&gt;, which were printed during a succession of years at the
                    end of the Lima Almanack.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Descripcion de las Provincias Pertenecientes al Arzobispado de Lima</title> (n.d.), no. 3645 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library. This compilation had been sent to Southey by Murray; see Southey to John Rickman, 1 August 1810, Letter
                        1797.</note>
          <del>x below the latest xxxx xxx xxxx</del>. In the volume I <del>collect</del> find these scanty facts respecting the
                    Buccaneers</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The town of Ca&#241;ete has not recovered from what it suffered in the earthquake of 1687, &amp; from its saccage by a
                    pirate. It had been very flourishing before </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The town of Pisco was una poblacion muy Buena<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. well-populated.</note>
                    before it was sacked by English pirates in 1685. &amp; injured &amp; partly inundated in the earthquake of 1687<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pisco was almost destroyed in a tsunami triggered by the 1687 earthquake.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Hu&#224;u<del>t</del>&lt;r&gt;a<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Huaral in central Peru.</note> (as well
                    as I can read an ill-printed word) &#8211; a town sacked in 1686 by the pirate Eduardo David.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The English pirate Edward Davis (fl. 1682&#8211;1693; <title>DNB</title>). In 1685&#8211;1687 he carried out a series of raids on coastal
                        settlements in western South America.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Santa Maria de la Parrilla, a town en otro tiempo muy poblado<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;at this time
                        well-populated&#8217;.</note> destroyed by English Pirates 1685. The inhabitants then removed two miles from the sea upon the river.
                    Where they suffered from an inundation in 1761</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Santiago de Miraflores de Sana. sacked Match 4. 1686 by the Pirates who afterwards sacked Casma &#8211; Santa (Maria de
                    la Parrilla) &#8211; Huaura, Pisco, &amp; Huayaquil <hi rend="ital">lo que la atraso mucho</hi>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        &#8216;The which fact delayed it considerably.&#8217;</note> But a heavy rain of many days continuance &amp; an inundation of the river destroyed it entirely March 15.
                    1720. In consequence of this Lambayeque became the capital of the province, &amp; is now (i-e some fifty years ago) one of the
                    most populous &amp; flourishing places upon the whole coast containing 7000 inhabitants, the whole province having only 2000
                    more</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Payta, a <hi rend="ital">pueblo</hi>, or village, sacked &amp; burnt by Anson. 24 Nov. 1741.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British naval officer and politician George Anson, Baron Anson (1697&#8211;1762;
                        <title>DNB</title>) led the sacking of the coastal city of Paita, 13&#8211;15 November 1741.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <hi rend="sup">x</hi> Concerning the loss of the Wager<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Wager</hi>, a
                        28-gun ship, was wrecked off the coast of south Chile on 14 May 1741. A group of the survivors mutinied, abandoned the ship&#8217;s
                        captain David Cheap (d. 1752) and his supporters, and headed back to England. Some of them survived the journey. Cheap and his
                        followers also made it home, arriving two years after the mutineers. A court martial resulted.</note> in 1741 the writer says
                    &#8211; All this coast as far as the Cabo de Pilares same North &amp; South. And it is not accurate that which Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                    Cheap affirms that the cause of his being lost was the error of the charts which lay down the coast in the direction North &amp;
                    South, whereas they ought to have laid it North East &amp; S. E. For this point has been newly confirmed, &amp; thus what he
                    asserts <del>are</del> is rather <del>for</del> an excuse for his own error, that a truth which ought to be followed. </p>
        <p rend="center"> _____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At the end of El Mara&#241;on y Amazonas by P. Manuel Rodriguez 1684<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manuel
                        Rodriguez (1633&#8211;1701), <title>El Mara&#241;on y Amazonas</title> (1684); a history of expeditions along the river, making use of
                        first-hand accounts. Southey&#8217;s copy was no. 3627 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> is an Indice Chronologico
                    Pernano y del V Rey no de Granada. in which there are these notes</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 1591 fourteen of Cavendish&#8217;s<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Cavendish (bap. 1560, d. 1592;
                            <title>DNB</title>), leader of an expedition to Brazil.</note> men taken, of whom 12 were hanged &amp; the other two kept
                    prisoners</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 1594 Richard Aquines an Englishman entered by the Straits &amp; was taken in battle by D Beltran Castro de la
                        Cueva.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Beltran de Castro y de la Cueva (fl. 1590s), a well-connected Spanish
                        nobleman, related to the Dukes of Albuquerque.</note> This must be Hawkins<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard
                        Hawkins (c. 1560&#8211;1622; <title>DNB</title>), English seaman, whose ship, the <hi rend="ital">Dainty</hi>, was captured by the
                        Spanish in 1594 after raiding the western seaboard of Spanish South America. He was not released until 1602.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 1595 An English pirate called Guateral infested the coast of Tierra Firma. Speaking of Drakes death he says his
                    mother brought him forth on board ship at sea, &amp; it was remarkable enough (fue harto) that he should have died ashore.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Francis Drake (1540&#8211;1596; <title>DNB</title>). He was born at Crowndale, near
                        Tavistock, Devon, and died on board ship at Porto Bello. &#8216;Guateral&#8217; here presumably refers to Drake, who was raiding Tierra
                        Firma, or Panama, in 1595.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 1616 A pirate called William Fzeten<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a reference to the Dutch
                        expedition led by Jacques Le Maire (1585&#8211;1616) and Willem Schouten (d. 1625), which rounded Cape Horn in January 1616 and
                        sailed up the coast of Chile before crossing the Pacific.</note> (so printed from some manifest error of the press, &amp; God
                    knows for what) enterd the S Sea &amp; explored the coasts without making any robberies or attempting any, for he seemd only to
                    come exploring</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 1618. There entered the city of S Thom&#233; de la Guayne an English Pirate called Gualteri Reali, who killed some
                    people there, &amp; plundered all that he could find<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Walter Raleigh&#8217;s (c. 1554&#8211;1618;
                            <title>DNB</title>) ill-fated expedition to South America. The capture of Sao Tome on the Orinoco, against government
                        instructions, led to Raleigh&#8217;s execution.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> x 1624 A number of English landed at Guayaquil,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> This attack was actually
                        by a Dutch fleet, led by Jacques L&#8217;Hermite (or le Clercq) (c. 1582&#8211;1624), which had been given the task of raiding Spanish
                        ships and establishing a Dutch colony on the west coast of South America.</note> &amp; were repulsed in that port, it being
                    garrisoned by troops who had been sent there from Quito, &amp; who obtained a victory muy applaudia<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;much applauded&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> x 1640. This year the Armada de Barloventi<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. the Fleet of the Windward
                        Islands in the Caribbean.</note> was established, muy deseada contra los Cosarios,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        &#8216;greatly desired to fight the pirates&#8217;.</note> for the security of commerce &amp; navigation of the Isles de Barloventi y de
                    Tierra Firma.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 1670 Morgans<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The privateer and colonial governor Sir Henry Morgan (c.
                        1635&#8211;1688; <title>DNB</title>), who captured and sacked Panama City in December 1670.</note> capture of Panama. Much private
                    property was saved. &#8220;forces came from Lima &amp; from Quito to dislodge him, but he was gone, &amp; so the cost &amp; the trouble
                    were thrown away.&#8221;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The same year an English pirate in a frigate of 40 guns entered the S Sea &amp; landed in the port of Valdivia<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> A Royal Navy expedition, led by Sir John Narborough (bap. 1640&#8211;1688; <title>DNB</title>),
                        Captain of HMS <hi rend="ital">Sweepstakes</hi>, to establish trading links with South America. At Valdivia he was compelled
                        to leave four of his crew behind as hostages, an action for which he was much-criticised.</note> &amp; D Carlos Enriquez
                        Clerck<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Narborough&#8217;s secretary, Charles Henry Clerk (d. 1682).</note> who was taken
                    &amp; sent to Lima</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 1680 The Pirates who had entered by Darien,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> A reference to the raiding
                        expedition led by Bartholomew Sharpe (fl. 1650s-1690s; <title>DNB</title>) to Panama and the western coast of South America in
                        1680&#8211;1682.</note> being only 150 men in a ship which they took on the coast of Panama did great damage along the coast of
                    Peru. they took a bark &amp; its crew which went out from Gravesend, they sacked Coquimba &amp; other small places &amp; caused a
                    great expence in a fleet which went out from Callao to sack them without having the <del>fortune</del> luck to chasten them, or
                    &lt;even&gt; see them, according to the account of those who <del>were</del> went in their search</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> x 1682. Clerk (above mentioned) executed at Lima (strangled) he had been sent by the English of Jamaica to spy the
                    whole coast of Peru</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 1683. 18 May Vera Cruz<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> The city of Vera Cruz in Mexico was sacked on the
                        night of 17&#8211;18 May 1683 by a combined force led by the Dutch pirates Laurens de Graaf, alias Laurencillo, (c. 1653&#8211;1704) and
                        Nikolaas van Hoorn (c. 1635&#8211;1683).</note> sacked by 800 Pirates under Lorencello a native of Celanda (Zeeland?) married in the
                    Canaries</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>