<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2267</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3538</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Don.
                        d. 3.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.) Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 34&#8211;36 [in part]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2267" type="letter">
        <head>2267. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1813-06-06">6
                        June 1813</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ Queen Anne
                        Street/ Cavendish Square/ London.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK / 298<lb />Postmark: D/ 9 JU 9/ 1813<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don.
                        d. 3<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.) <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 34&#8211;36 [in part]. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-06-06">June 6. 1813</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> That you will see me ere long is as certain, according to all appearances, as any thing can be in this uncertain
                    world, &#8211; I have been idling a week at <ref target="places.html#LowBrathay">Old Brathay</ref>, &#8211; the change was needful, &amp; the
                    idleness also, tho I could have wished it had been at a more convenient season. I shall start for the south as soon as my hands
                    are clear, &#8211; this is unluckily the <del>seaso</del> time of year for interruptions, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> comes to me tomorrow, &#8211; the <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhora </ref>
          <del> has</del> &lt;hourly expects&gt; a merry old Uncle <del>hour</del> who has been to Edinburgh to unmarry his daughter,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> One of Mary Barker&#8217;s maternal uncles, Sir Jeremiah Homfray (1759&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>)
                        had been to Edinburgh to help secure the divorce of his daughter, Marianne (d. 1819), from Thomas Montford Newte (dates
                        unknown). Under Scottish law, the Commissary Court could grant divorces on the grounds of adultery or desertion.</note> &amp;
                    I must lay my account with some days of dissipation, so that I think <del>it</del> my appearance in town will more likely be in
                    the second week of July than in the first.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You were right in supposing that the sprawler upon the red sofa <del>was</del> &lt;is&gt; your niece <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">
            <hi rend="ital">K</hi>ath<hi rend="ital">a</hi>rine</ref>, &#8211; who had also the honour of being
                    the original child in the eagles nest, &#8211; <del>for</del> that huge picture was begun &amp; half finished in this house, &#8211; wherof a
                    good story when we meet. I do not know whether the likeness in the great picture has been altered, &#8211; it was one of the happiest I
                    ever saw, &#8211; &amp; the other (which is to come when the Exhibition is over) was copied from it.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The history and portrait painter George Dawe (1781&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>) had been in residence at Greta
                        Hall in late autumn 1812 whilst he worked on the 9 foot by 8 foot canvas &#8216;Mother Rescuing her Child from an Eagle&#8217;s Nest&#8217;. His
                        visit was not without controversy. In particular, his love of fresh air and open windows upset some of the household. Dawe&#8217;s picture was
                        based on William Hayley&#8217;s (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;The Eagle&#8217;, first published in <title>Designs to a Series of
                            Ballads</title> (1802). At the same time he painted a small portrait of Katharine Southey.</note> Have you seen the best
                    portrait which has ever been taken of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kates</ref> father, &#8211; by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Downman<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Downman (1750&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>) had painted two portraits of
                        Southey in 1812. One was commissioned by Murray, the second by Southey himself. In addition, Downman painted a portrait of
                        Edith to sit alongside that of her husband; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 7 October 1812, Letter 2154.</note> &#8211; in <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> possession. I have its fellow here which satisfies every body.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was glad to see your presentation, as indicative that you were in road to preferment.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Herbert Southey had been presented at Court.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But there are two <del>thin special</del> things which may be considered as the special cause of this letter. first
                    a particular <del>des</del> request of <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Ch. Lloyds</ref>, often &amp; solicitously repeated,
                    that I would mention to you, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Boddington<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Samuel
                        Boddington (1766&#8211;1843), West India merchant, scholar, friend of Richard Sharp and Samuel Rogers, and Whig MP for Tralee in
                        1807.</note> seems hurt at your non appearance at the party to which you promised to come, &#8211; no <del>xxxx</del> apology for
                    the said non appearance or rather explanation of it having reached <del>xx</del> him. &#8211; My answer to <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> was that I supposed you had written a note which had been lost on the way.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Secondly &#8211; do you want to make your fortune in the philosophical world? &#8211; If so &#8211; you may thank Owen Lloyd<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Owen Lloyd (1803&#8211;1841), third son of Charles and Sophia Lloyd, later curate of
                        Langdale.</note> for the happiest opportunity that was ever put into an Aspirants hands. &#8211; You must have heard the vulgar
                    notion that a horse hair, plucked out by the root &amp; put in water, becomes alive in a few days. The boys at <ref target="places.html#LowBrathay">Brathay</ref> repeatedly told <ref target="people.html#PembertonSophia">their mother</ref> it
                    was true &#8211; that they had tried it themselves, &amp; seen it tried. Her reply was &#8211; show it me &amp; I will believe it. &#8211; While we
                    were there last week in came Owen with two of these creations in a bottle. <del>xxx </del>
          <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam"> Wordsworth</ref> was there, &#8211; &amp; to our utter &amp; unutterable astonishment did
                    the boys to convince us that these long thin black worms were their own manufactory by the old receipt, lay hold of them by the
                    middle while they writhed like eels, &amp; stripping their nails down on each side, actually lay bare the horse-hair in the
                    middle, which seemd to serve as the back-bone of those <del>xxx</del> creatures, &#8211; or the substratum of the living matter which
                    had collected round it. <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; I should both have supposed that it was
                    a collection of animalcul&#230; round the hair (which however would be only changing the nature of the miracle) if we could any way
                    have accounted for the motion upon this theory, &#8211; but the motion was that of a snake. We could perceive no head, &#8211; but something
                    very like the root of the hair. And for want of glasses could distinguish no parts. The creature or whatever else you may please
                    to call it is black or dark brown, &amp; about the girth of a fiddle string. As soon as you have read this <del>x</del> draw upon
                    your horses tail &amp; mane for half a dozen hairs, be sure they have roots to them, bottle them separately in water, &amp; when
                    <del>you have</del> they are alive &amp; kicking, call in <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref>, &amp; make the fact known to the philosophical world. &#8211; Never
                    in my life was I so astonished as at seeing what even in the act of seeing I could scarcely believe, &#8211; &amp; now almost doubt. &#8211;
                    If you verify the experiment, as Owen &amp; all his brothers will swear must be the case, &#8211; <del>the</del> you will be able to
                    throw some light upon the origin of your friend the tape worm, &amp; <del>all</del> his diabolical family.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> No doubt you will laugh, &amp; disbelieve this, &amp; half suspect that I am jesting. But indeed I have only told
                    you the fact <del>x</del> as it occurred; &#8211; &amp; you will at once see its whole importance in physiology, &#8211; &amp; the use which
                    you &amp; <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> may derive from it, coming forth with a series of experiments, &amp;
                    with such deductions as your grey-hound sight, &amp; his beagle scent will <del>enable you to</del> soon start &amp; pursue. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And if the <hi rend="ital">horses</hi> hair succeeds Sir Domine, &#8211; by parallel reasoning you know try one of your
                    own.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have left myself <del>no room</del> little room to speak of my own concerns. With this fourth volume I give up
                    the Register,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813) was the last issue to which Southey contributed.</note> &#8211; &amp;
                    therewith two thirds of my income; &#8211; there is however a better bird in the bush &#8211; than that which I let loose from my hand. I
                    shall recast <del>my</del> the peninsular-matter in those volumes, &amp; bring forth, under all possible advantages of authority a
                    regular history of the affair of the peninsular from the commencement of those troubles.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> will
                    apply to <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> to <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M. Wellesley</ref>, &#8211; to whom also I have access thro his son in
                    law <ref target="people.html#Hatherton">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Littleton</ref>, <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir
                        Edwards</ref> heir. &#8211; Two quartos will comprize it, if our part in it should not continue longer than the close of next year;
                    &#8211; probably it will terminate in this, &#8211; for France cannot &lt;long&gt; sustain the cost of such victories as Buonaparte is now
                        gaining.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> France had fought the forces of the Sixth Coalition at Lutzen on 2 May 1813
                        and Bautzen 20&#8211;21 May 1813. Both battles could be construed as tactical victories for France, but France could not sustain the
                        scale of casualties inflicted in these contests.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Love to my Aunt<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Either <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">Catherine Hill</ref> or <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">Mary Southey</ref>.</note>
          </salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>