<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2269</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3540</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2269" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2269" type="letter">
        <head>2269. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1813-06-15">15 June
                        1813</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Bristol<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: 1813/ June 15<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address> June 15 1813</dateline>
          <salute>My dear Charles</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#Frickerfamily">Eliza</ref> arrived last week a few <del>xxxxx</del> hours before <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; I returned from <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref>, where
                    we had been passing a week. I went there for the sake of being idle, &#8211; the weather was uninterruptedly fine, &amp; we were as you
                    may suppose always on the move. I have been perfectly well since I wrote to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref>, bating
                    only a little annoyance from my summer cold, which however has been very much alleviated, &amp; often suspended by small doses of
                    James&#8217;s&#8217; powder<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A popular patent medicine, invented by Robert James (c. 1703&#8211;1776;
                            <title>DNB</title>), used to combat fevers and as a pick-me-up.</note> at night. Both my stomach attacks<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 3 January 1813 (Letter 2196) and 21 May 1813 (Letter
                        2260).</note> I verily believe were <del>pr</del> occasioned by eating crude roots: &#8211; if there be any diminution of strength
                        <del>in the stomach</del> or derangement in the stomach itself, it is not owing to want of exercise, for I have taken more
                    during this &lt;last&gt; winter than in any former one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George</ref> is very near his end. He is now so weak that he can do
                    nothing whatever for himself &amp; is carried up &amp; down stairs. The use of one side is nearly gone, &#8211; every day, &#8211; every hour
                    &#8211; his release may be looked for, yet he does not appear to have the slightest apprehension of his real state, &amp; talks of
                    buying new things &amp;c &#8211; as if all that ailed him were a temporary indisposition. He suffers little except occasionally in his
                    breathing: &#8211; the quantity of laudanum which he takes keeping him probably in <del>a</del> constantly <del>xxxx xx xxxxxxx</del>
                    under its influence. You never saw a more ghastly object than he is, &#8211; a mere skeleton, dosing in his chair. I wish the last scene
                    of the tragedy were over. He has been perfectly patient from the beginning, never uttering a complaint, &amp; always saying he is
                    better, &#8211; or comfortable, &#8211; or easy &#8211; &amp;c &#8211;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Fricker died on 24 June 1813; see
                        Southey to Charles Danvers, 28 June 1813, Letter 2274.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will have seen by my letter to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> that I break off my connection
                    with the Register<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813) was the last issue to which Southey contributed.</note> with this
                    volume. What loss I shall sustain is as yet uncertain, &#8211; that I am in very bad hands is but too <del>certain</del> plain: however
                    I shall make the best of it, &amp; suffer nothing of this kind to disquiet me. Henceforward my time will be more at my own free
                    disposal, &amp; I hope it will not be less productive. I mean to recast those parts of the Register which relate to the Peninsula,
                    &amp; write a regular history of the Spanish &amp; Portugueze war: &#8211; this is settled with the booksellers; <del>the</del> the
                    terms remain for consideration, but on this head there is not likely to be any difference or demur.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Published in three volumes between 1823&#8211;1832 as the <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>.</note> I
                    shall have the best documents which are attainable in this country, &amp; have excellent channels open both in Portugal &amp;
                    Spain. <del>xxxxxx</del>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is in this part of the world: he came to me last week &amp; went this morning to
                        <ref target="places.html#LowBrathay">Old Brathay</ref>. <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> has been
                        <del>xx</del> better of late than I ever expected to see him, &#8211; &amp; if he can be induced to take opium regularly without
                    scruple, in such quantities as his own feelings dictate, if seems as if he might <del>xxxx xxx</del> subdue the diseased
                    irritability to which he is subject. He lives almost wholly upon milk, seldom or never taking animal food.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A few days ago I received a long letter from <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">S. Reid</ref> in answer to that
                    which I wrote him in December last.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Robert Southey to Samuel Reid, 5 December 1812,
                        Letter 2187.</note> His letter is a very interesting one, &amp; leads me to conclude that he is more likely to remain where he
                    is, &amp; settle himself by marriage, than to go abroad upon schemes of which he begins to see the wildness &amp;
                    impracticability. I shall write to him again, <del>with</del> as soon as I have leisure.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have learnt by mere accident from <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George</ref> that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lunell<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Peter Lunell (1758&#8211;1840), prominent Bristol merchant,
                        antiquarian and anti-slavery activist, with premises in Brunswick Square.</note> has possibly a copy to spare of a book for
                    which I sent to America without success: &#8211; it is <del>an xxx</del> a history of Three of King Charles&#8217;s Judges who took refuge
                    there, &amp; written (if I recollect rightly) by President Stiles.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ezra Stiles
                        (1727&#8211;1795), <title>History of the Three Judges of King Charles I</title> (1794). Southey obtained a copy, no. 2552 in the
                        sale catalogue of his library. Stiles was President of Yale College, 1778&#8211;1795.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George</ref> says that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> L. had several copies: pray try if you can
                    obtain one for me. It is of main importance to me, because my next poem is founded upon this very history, my hero Oliver
                        Goff<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The hero of Southey&#8217;s posthumously published, and unfinished, &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;,
                        published in <title>Oliver Newman: a New-England Tale, Unfinished; with Other Poetical Remains</title> (1845).</note> being an
                    imaginary son of one of these Judges. If <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Mr L.</ref> has not a duplicate copy left which he
                    can spare me, he will perhaps have the goodness to lend me his own whenever there may be an opportunity of conveying it. &#8211; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ariel<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Either D. Ariel (d. 1817) or his son Miles Ariel (c.
                        1792&#8211;1840), Bristol residents, Nonconformists and merchants.</note> called here while we were at <ref target="places.html#LowBrathay">Brathay</ref>. I heard of him from M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Smith of Coniston<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Juliet Smith (fl. 1770s-1830s), mother of the scholar and translator, Elizabeth Smith (1776&#8211;1806;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; he has been purchasing an estate somewhere near Kendal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the course of next month, if nothing unforeseen prevent I shall be in London. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref> has <del>been</del> had a respite from her intestinal tormentors ever
                    since <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Kings</ref> letter arrived: &#8211; that letter however has been effectual in relieving me;
                    &amp; as soon as they <del>xxxxxx</del> renew their operations I shall commence a campaign against them according to his
                    directions. &#8211; We have no electrical machine, otherwise I would certainly try the experiment which he proposes &#8211; it is exceedingly
                    promising.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> They have invited me to deliver a course of Lectures upon Poetry at the Royal Institution,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The Royal Institution, London, founded in 1799.</note>&#8211; &amp; as you may
                    suppose I have declined.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>