<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2587</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3858</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 28603.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2587" type="letter">
        <head>2587. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1815-04-13">13 April
                        1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To / Major-General Peachy/ 9 Pulteney Street/
                        Bath.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 28603<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1815-04-13">13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April. 1815</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> This morning on my usual walk to Friars Crag, old Daniel Crosthwaite<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In
                        Keswick directories of this period, M. and D. Crosthwaite are described as &#8216;mercers, drapers and grocers&#8217; and D. Crosthwaite
                        as &#8216;bookseller&#8217;. The Crosthwaites are possibly related to Peter Crosthwaite (1735&#8211;1808), a retired naval commander, publisher
                        of maps and inventor of the aeolian harp. In the 1780s he established the first museum in Keswick. Its treasures included a
                        set of musical stones, a stuffed albatross and a pig with no legs. By 1811 the Museum was run by his son Daniel (c.
                        1776&#8211;1847), a portrait painter.</note> the Grocero-Bookseller accosted me to say that the Bishop of Gloucesters book was out
                    of print.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Isaac Huntingford (1748&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Gloucester.
                        In 1813 he published <title>A Protestant Letter Addressed to Lord Somers</title> opposing Catholic Emancipation.</note> In
                    reply to my first inquiries concerning it he had said that it was not published, &#8211; &amp; his second order to his London
                    correspondent produces the intelligence that the whole edition is sold. This blundering deprives me of the satisfaction of seeing
                    my own opinions upon an important subject confirmed by one whose abilities &amp; authority are of great weight: but it is not a
                    subject upon which I stand in need of farther knowledge, as there are very few upon which I have formed so decided a judgement. I
                    should however have perused the Bishops work with great interest. Have you seen Herbert Marsh&#8217;s Comparative View of the
                    differences between the Churches of England &amp; of Rome?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Herbert Marsh (1757&#8211;1839;
                            <title>DNB</title>), cleric and biblical critic. His <title>Comparative View of the Churches of England and Rome</title>
                        (1814) became a standard work of anti-Catholic apologetics.</note> It is becoming yearly of more importance that these
                    differences should be generally understood. The Jesuits have established themselves within fifteen miles of Dublin in the County
                    of Kildare, where they have given &#163;18,000 for a house &amp; about 140 acres of land &#8211; They have opened a College there, where they
                    have about 40 pupils, children of farmers &#8216;who keep their gigs.&#8221; The age of admission is from 7 to 14, &amp; no vacations are
                    allowed, that nothing may disturb the operation of their system upon the growing mind. Their friends boast that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Kenney the President of this College has more money at command than any Bishop in the Kingdom.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Jesuit Peter James Kenney (1779&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>) founded Clongowes Wood College, County Kildare,
                        in 1814. It became the leading boarding school for Irish middle class Catholics.</note> Government knows all this, &amp;
                    contented itself with making some fruitless questions at the commencement of the transaction. &lt;But&gt; Were you or I to
                    discover a <del>viper</del> brood of vipers in our gardens, I think we should &lt;not&gt; defer operations against them, till some
                    of the family had been bitten.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The last newspapers have disheartened me very much. There is clearly a party in the Cabinet who are in the cold fit
                    of the ague, &amp; are disposed to temporize, &amp; vacillate &amp; negociate, at a moment when <del>we oug</del> they ought to
                    speak in thunder, &amp; write their manifestoes in blood. Meantime<del>s</del> the old admirers of the Usurper Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Whitbread<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. the Whigs as followers of Samuel Whitbread (1764&#8211;1815;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; Co, are staunch in his cause, &amp; the <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Grenvilles</ref> who know that war is not only just &amp; necessary, but that it is inevitable, &amp; ought not to be avoided
                    even if it could, instead of coming manfully forward with an avowal of this to strengthen &amp; stimulate the Government, are
                    activated only by that cursed spirit of party which it is to be feared may ultimately prove as fatal to England as it did to
                        Carthage.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The main rival to ancient Rome, destroyed in 146 BC.</note> The blunders of
                    last year ought to be regarded not as matters for criminating the Ministry, but as lessons for the future: as <del>decisive
                        proof</del> demonstrating that there can be no peace for Europe while Buonaparte lives, &amp; while the army which he has
                    formed after his own heart is suffered to exist. War must be made upon him as an Usurper &amp; upon them as rebels. I do not mean
                    to say that they are to be put to death when taken prisoners, &#8211; but that they should be sent to Siberia, never to return.
                    Notwithstanding the cowardly language of Ministers, I think we must have immediate war &amp; this is &lt;felt&gt; by all persons
                    with whom I have any intercourse <del>distinctly felt</del>: If it be prompt &amp; vigorous it <del>x</del> may be soon
                    terminated: but in <del>regarding</del> &lt;reference to&gt; that moral order of things which may be distinctly traced throughout
                    the course of history, I should regard any <del>xx</del> sufferings which might be inflicted upon France, &amp; any
                        <del>catastrophe</del> calamity with which Paris might be visited, as judicial dispensations, <hi rend="ital">almost</hi> to
                    be expected.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I announced last year a series of Inscriptions recording the acts of <del>xxxxx</del> the British Army in the
                        Peninsula;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In early 1814, Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Inscriptions Triumphal and Sepulchral, recording
                        the acts of the British army in the Peninsula&#8217; had been advertised as &#8216;nearly ready for publication&#8217; (e.g. in <title>European
                            Magazine</title>, 65 (January 1814), 77). Only 18 of the projected 30 poems were completed and they were not collected
                        together until they were published in <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), III, pp. 122&#8211;156.</note> &#8211;
                    the plan was formed because I thought it <del>incumbent upon me</del> became me to seek all worthy occasions for writing upon
                        <del>public affairs</del> &lt;national topics&gt;, as much as to shun the common-places of court-poetry. But I postponed it
                    during the peace, because when the French Marshals had been taken into favour, there might have &lt;been&gt; some impropriety in
                    applying to them those epithets which they deserved, when I was <del>compelled</del> was writing <hi rend="ital">quasi ex
                        officio</hi>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. semi-officially.</note> tho not actually so. In my history I felt
                    no such restraint.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s writings in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>
                        1810&#8211;1813.</note> Now however I have resumed the task, &#8211; <del>No</del> &amp; shall publish as soon as possible. The plan
                    includes an inscription for every battle <del>&amp; capture of</del> &amp;c, &amp; epitaphs for all the distinguished officers who
                    fell.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In looking for what good may arise out of this new state of things, I think we may promise ourselves the pleasure
                    of seeing you next summer <del>xx</del> at the Island. Our best remembrances to <ref target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>. <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> past a day with us last week on
                    his way Southward. I am fixed to my desk, &amp; shall hardly travel before the Autumn &#8211; Believe me my dear Sir</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>