<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2248</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3519</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        30927.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2248" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2248" type="letter">
        <head>2248. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1813-04-17">17 April
                        1813</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey. R. N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helens/ Auckland <lb />Stamped: [partial] KESWICK<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        30927<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-04-17">April 17. 1813.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not go to London till a more convenient season, &#8211; <del>xxx x</del> &amp; you must come &amp; have some boating
                    &amp; some mountaineering. Next week being Easter week, the boys<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent
                            Coleridge</ref>.</note> are here from school. As soon as they are gone <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>
                    &amp; I remove into the room which they occupy, while our own undergoes the operations of painting &amp; papering. This will
                    disorganize the house for a second week, &amp; the third will be required to get all things to rights again. &#8211; After that come as
                    soon as you please, &#8211; that is any time after the seventh of May. &#8211; You will wonder how one room should make any difference to us
                    at this time of year; &#8211; but we have one unhappily occupied by poor <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George Fricker</ref>.
                    He came down in January thinking to enjoy himself; a blood vessel broke in his lungs after he had been here three or four weeks; &#8211;
                    from this he seemed to be well recovering. &#8211; but &lt;more decided&gt; consumptive symptoms came on, the disease is making a most
                    rapid progress, &amp; I believe he is very far gone.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Robert Southey to Henry Herbert
                        Southey, 3 February 1813, Letter 2218.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your Nelson<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A copy of the <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813). A second
                        edition appeared in 1814.</note> &amp; your Quarterlies<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Copies of the <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>.</note> will probably find their way to you next week. My 105&#163; copyright is gone to the three per cents,
                    &amp; <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> promises another hundred when he prints a second edition, this is very
                    fair on his part, considering all circumstances: for you know he offered me the hundred to enlarge the reviewal into a volume
                    which might be sold for a dollar.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Five shillings.</note> Any labour beyond this was work
                    of supererogation on my part. He &amp; his printer<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Moyes (d. 1839), of Greville St,
                        Hatton Garden, London.</note> must share the blame between them for not printing close enough, &amp; I suppose the edition is
                    larger than it would have been if two volumes had been intended. However if it sells well, so as to prove a lucrative speculation
                    to him, I dare say he will make me a third payment, for tho I <del>xxx</del> had no claim to the promised second hundred,
                    certainly had I written these volumes &amp; offered them for sale I would not have sold them for 2 nor even for 300&#163;. &#8211; There
                    however they are; &#8211; you have made me glad that I have written them; &#8211; &amp; they are already worth <del>xxxx</del> five pounds per
                    annum to me &amp; my heirs for ever. I am not a little pleased that the errors were so few &amp; of such little import. &#8211; It must
                    have been another Brierly who led the fleet, &#8211; &amp; I have a notion that I blundered by <del>xxx</del> saying of the Bellona,
                    taking it for granted it was your Master.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had stated that the Bryerly who had led
                        the British fleet through the treacherous shallows at the Battle of Copenhagen in 1801 was &#8216;the master of the Bellona&#8217;, see
                            <title>The Life of Nelson</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813), II, p. 120. Tom Southey had presumably informed his brother that
                        this man was another Bryerly, and not Alexander Bryerly (dates unknown), Master of Tom&#8217;s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Bellona</hi>.</note> But the books are gone back so that I cannot now ascertain this. Certain however it is that all the
                    documents before &lt;me&gt; gave this name.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is rather unlucky that this life cannot be reviewed in the Quarterly<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> It
                        could not be reviewed in the <title>Quarterly</title> because it was published by the journal&#8217;s publisher John Murray.</note>
                    where a reviewal could be of such service, &#8211; &amp; that &lt;it&gt; is pretty sure of being abused in the Naval Chronicle,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Naval Chronicle</title> was a twice yearly publication, first issued in 1759 and
                        re-founded in 1799.</note> which was originally set on foot by Stanier Clarke.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> James
                        Stanier Clarke (1765?-1834; <title>DNB</title>). His 1809 life of Nelson had been one of a number of biographies noticed by
                        Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218&#8211;262. Southey&#8217;s own <title>Life</title> was an expansion of
                        this article. His dislike of Clarke was compounded when the latter was appointed Historiographer Royal, a post Southey
                        had campaigned for.</note> However I think it will make its way for in spite of all obstacles my reputation seems to ride as
                    buoyant as a pettrel upon the waves. I see myself called &#8220;o celebre Southey&#8221;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;The famous
                        Southey&#8217;; in <title>Investigador Portuguez em Inglaterra</title>, 2 (1811), 416. The journal was no. 3409 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> in the Investigador Portuguez, &#8211; &amp; in the Espa&#241;ol I read of my own &#8220;extraordinaire
                        <del>x</del> universal lectura&#8221;, &#8211; &amp; of my &#8216;incomparable laborisidad&#8217;.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>El Espa&#241;ol</title>, 6 (1813), 45, referring to Southey&#8217;s &#8216;extraordinary and wide-ranging reading&#8217; and &#8216;incomparable
                        industry&#8217;. A set of this newspaper was no. 3214 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This latter virtue is likely to have ample scope. <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has proposd to
                    me to undertake a View of the World,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Later retitled the &#8216;Cosmographia&#8217;, nothing came of
                        this scheme; see Southey to John Murray, 31 March 1813, Letter 2238.</note> &#8211; I fancy the account of Iceland<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of Sir George Steuart Mackenzie (1780&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels
                            in the Island of Iceland, in the Summer of the Year 1810</title> (1811) and Sir William Jackson Hooker (1785&#8211;1865;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of a Tour in Iceland, in the Summer of 1809</title> (1811), <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 7 (March 1812), 48&#8211;92.</note>
          <del>suggested</del> led him to think of this. The terms are yet to be settled, but he allows ample room, &#8211; three or four quartos
                    &amp; talks of numerous engravings. I like the scheme &#8211; because it is so much in the course of my <del>xx</del> previous reading,
                    that I have a great &lt;disposable&gt; capital of <del>material knowledge at my disposal</del> the requisite knowledge, &amp; I
                    know precisely what is to be done. Where to look for materials, &amp; how to use them. Should the scheme be brought to bear as
                    most likely it will, I shall strive to produce such a view of the world in its present state as <del>xxxxx may be referred
                        to</del> will remain a standard work, which will increase in value &amp; in esteem the older it grows. &#8211; There is not a part
                    of the globe from Spitzbergen to Sandwich land<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hawaii.</note> about which I have not read
                    something; not a stage of society concerning which I have not at some time or other, <del>x xxxx xxx</del> had occasion to
                    reflect, &amp; scarcely a form of superstition <del>with</del> &lt;of&gt; the causes &amp; consequences of which I have not some
                    knowledge. To systematize all this &amp; making use of other mens knowledge as an architect does of the stones which are hewn from
                        <del>his building</del> the quarry, to give to the whole the character of my own <del>xxxxx</del> mind &amp; thus
                    individualize &amp; appropriate it, would be a worthy work.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Pray thank M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Castle<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom&#8217;s father-in-law, Samuel
                        Castle (d. 1815), a Durham solicitor.</note> for his letter. I am quite of his opinion about the thundering Methodist parson
                    &amp; should be very glad if such a one were to make his appearance here. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> is better, &amp; has translated several of Alfieri&#8217;s plays.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Italian dramatist Vittorio Alfieri (1749&#8211;1803). Lloyd&#8217;s translation of <title>The Tragedies
                            of Vittorio Alfieri</title> was published in 1815. It was reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 14
                        (January 1816), 333&#8211;368.</note> This I recommended him to do last year, &amp; he is likely to compleat the whole of them.
                        <del>Which</del> &lt;The translation&gt; will be an acquisition to our literature, &amp; will do him credit. <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> is made Stamp Distributor for Westmoreland: &#8211; the appointment is
                    supposed to be from 4 to 600&#163; a year. He owes it to <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref>. He is about to
                    remove into that delightful house of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Norths at Ryedale, &#8211; you remember it &#8211; <ref target="places.html#RydalMount">Ryedale Mount</ref>.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rydal Mount had been owned by
                        Ford North of Liverpool (1765&#8211;1842), between 1803 and 1812, when he sold the house and moved to Ambleside. By 1813 it was
                        owned by Lady Diana Le Fleming (1748&#8211;1816), who lived in the adjacent house, Rydal Hall. Wordsworth moved into the house in
                        May 1813 and remained there until his death.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Perhaps I may go back with you for a week or ten days, to be introduced to my new nieces.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom&#8217;s daughters, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretdauTomandSarah">Margaret</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHannah">Mary-Hannah</ref>.</note> In that case you &amp; I will renew our acquaintance at
                        Rokeby.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Yorkshire estate of John Bacon Sawrey Morritt (1771&#8211;1843;
                            <title>DNB</title>), traveller and classical scholar.</note> We might take the coach to <del>xxxx</del> Brough &amp; walk
                    from thence <del>xxx</del> to Teesdale, calling upon M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hutchinsons<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Possibly Wordsworth&#8217;s brother-in-law, John Hutchinson (1768&#8211;1831), of Stockton-on-Tees.</note> on the way.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth&#8217;s</ref> prophecy about the Germans is accomplishing. &#8220;She of the Danube &amp; the Northern Sea&#8221;<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wordsworth&#8217;s sonnet &#8216;A Prophecy&#8217; (1807), line 7. The War of the Sixth Coalition was underway
                        against France in Germany.</note> is rising in her strength &#8211; &amp; the overthrow of this intolerable tyranny seems according
                    to all human probabilities, to be at hand.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Our love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> &#8211; God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent6"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>