<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1799</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3070</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                        University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos, The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                            1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 121&#8211;122; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 289&#8211;290 [misdated 5 August 1810]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1799" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1799" type="letter">
        <head>1799. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1810-08-09">9 August 1810</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/13 AU 13/1810; [partial]10o&#8217;C<lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 149 1810/ Robert Southey/
                        Keswick 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> August/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.<lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                        University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos, <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                            1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 121&#8211;122; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 289&#8211;290 [misdated 5 August 1810]. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1810-08-09">
              <del>Jul</del> Aug. 9. 1810.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Inclosed is a draft for 100 &#163;. &#8211; the first payment I have ever been able to make towards discharging a debt of
                    which I have never felt the weight, &amp; shall never cease to feel the obligation.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> May
                        had loaned Southey money to pay for Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s education.</note> If it please God to continue to me the blessings
                    of life &amp; health, there is a fair prospect of my discharging the whole at no very distant period, &#8211; certainly I shall be able
                    to remit a <del>sim</del> similar draft by the end of the next winter. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The cause of my long silence has been that for more than two months I have been expecting the publication of the
                    Ed. An. Register, &#8211; that being the <del>circumstance</del> &lt;event&gt; which &lt;would&gt; authorize<del>d</del> me to draw on
                    the publisher. The whole of the first volume is mine (that is except the Prospectus<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), v&#8211;xii.</note> &#8211; ) &amp; when you see the quantity &amp;
                    recollect the labour of weaving such disjointed materials as newspapers &amp; parliamentary papers into a connected narrative, you
                    will not think that 400 &#163; has been an overpayment. It is however good payment, &amp; comes to me like <del>flood tide to a</del>
                    spring-tide to a vessel <del>agroun</del> which has grounded. Henceforward I hope &amp; expect there will be no farther necessity
                    for my drawing upon <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in advance, &#8211; that my publications in his hands will
                    clear me in his books, &amp; in the course of a few years produce some returns which however trifling at first will assuredly
                    increase, &amp; may not improbably enable me at last to provide an independence for my children, if not for my self.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Whatever you may think of my part in the Register in other respects you will, I am sure, be well pleased with the
                    perfect freedom which inspires it. It will offend many persons, &amp; will please no party, but my own heart is satisfied, &amp;
                    that feeling would always be to me a sufficient reward. And even if it should injure me in a political point of view (as it
                    probably may) by cutting off the prospect of obtaining any thing from Government beyond the pitiful pension which <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord Grenville</ref> gave more truly to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>
                    than to me, &#8211; still I believe that even <del>upon</del> the balance of <del>world</del> selfish prudence, tho M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Worldly Wiseman<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> A character in John Bunyan (1628&#8211;1688; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Pilgrim&#8217;s Progress</title> (1678&#8211;1684). He attempts to entice Christian away from his journey.</note> himself
                    were to adjust the scales, would prove in my favour. For I confidently expect that this work will materially increase my
                    reputation among the booksellers, &#8211; &amp; indeed as long as I continue to be engaged in it, I shall &lt;need&gt; no other means of
                    support.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the second part of the volume you will see me abundantly praised &amp; very respectfully censured.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.2 (1810), 421&#8211;423. Southey would have been mortified to learn that the
                        author of this criticism was Walter Scott.</note> I know not who the critic is nor can I guess. He is very showy &amp;
                    sufficiently shallow. It is scarcely possible for any criticism to display less discernment. &#8211; As for my contempt of the received
                    rules of poetry, I hold the same rules which Shakespere, Spenser &amp; Milton held before me, &amp; desire to be judged by those
                        rules.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.2 (1810), 422, had noted Southey&#8217;s &#8216;resolute contempt of the ordinary
                        and received rules of poetry, and a departure from all their precepts, too shocking to all our pre-conceived opinions and
                        expectations.&#8217;</note> nor have I ever proceeded upon any principle of taste which is not to be found in all the great masters
                    of the art, of every age &amp; country wherein the art has been understood. When the critic specifies parts of my writings to
                    justify his praise, he overlooks every thing which displays either a knowledge of human nature, or a power of affecting the
                    passions, &amp; merely looks for a specimen of <del>rich</del> &lt;able&gt; versification, &#8211; specimen of which he might have found
                    by pricking with a pin for them. &#8211; Shallow however as all this is the praise will have its weight.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Edith was safely delivered of a <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">daughter</ref> this day week, &amp; is doing
                    as well as could be wished. &#8211; You have probably heard that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is married. <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">His wife</ref> is a very interesting &amp; excellent woman &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are only two trifling articles of mine in the last Quarterly, the Tongataboo Journal,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>An Authentic Narrative of Four Years&#8217; Residence at Tongataboo</title> (1810), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (May
                        1810), 440&#8211;455.</note> &amp; <ref target="people.html#GrahameJames">Grahames</ref> Georgics.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Grahame, <title>British Georgics</title> (1809), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (May 1810),
                        456&#8211;461.</note> In the next you will see a summary of the Obs. Portuguez<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Observador Portuguez</title> (1809), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (August 1810), 1&#8211;24; no. 3556 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; for which I am ashamed to think that I have never before thanked you.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>