<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2246</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3517</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National
                        Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2246" type="letter">
        <head>2246. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, [c. <date when="1813-04-13">13 April 1813</date>]<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.P./ Duke Street/ Westminster<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: [partial] 13 13/ 1813<lb />MS: National
                        Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note: dated from internal evidence; letter to Wynn, 25 April 1813,
                        seems to continue discussion about copyright law.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thank you for your hint about &#8216;Which buy&#8217;. &#8211; In the Omniana I saw no more unfitness in making a note upon one of
                    my own books than upon any other; &#8211; &amp; the lie of the Critical about J of Arc was originally <del>xxx</del> pointed out in the
                    Athenaeum &#8211; when you told me of it, otherwise I <del>should</del> &lt;might&gt; never have known that such a thing had been
                        said.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> An entry on Richard Hole (bap. 1743, d. 1803; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Arthur, or the Northern Enchantment</title> (1789), in <title>Omniana, or Horae Otiosiores</title>, 2 vols (London,
                        1812), I, pp. 83&#8211;85. Southey took the opportunity to rebut the assertion in the <title>Critical Review</title>, 10 (March 1807),
                            305, that Hole&#8217;s poem had only failed because of the number of other epics published at the same time. These included his
                            own <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796). Southey pointed out that his poem was published seven years after Hole&#8217;s
                            <title>Arthur</title>. Southey had already made this point in a letter to the <title>Athenaeum</title>, 13 (1 January
                            1808), 1&#8211;2; see <title>Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Three</title>, Letter 1408.</note> &#8211; If my reviewals were ever considered in writing them as things of which the author was to be
                    unknown then I should most probably feel that there would be something like a deceit in referring to <del>xxxx</del> myself, but
                    the fact is that I never write with the feeling of an anonymous writer, &amp; refer from one book to another, just as in writing
                    the History of Portugal<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s unfinished prose magnum opus.</note> I might do to the
                    History of Brazil,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> &#8211; or to the Cid.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> &#8211; However this is meant rather to explain than to justify, &amp; I
                    certainly will not again do what might expose me to censure, when there is no adequate <del>motive</del> or reasonable motive for
                    incurring &amp; braving it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will receive Nelson<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Nelson</title> (1813). A second edition appeared in 1814.</note> in about <del>xxxxx</del> a week or ten
                    days. I have received 105&#163; for it, &amp; if a second edition be published am to have as much more. Mirabile dictu<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Wonderful to relate&#8217;.</note>
          <del> this money xxxx</del> I have sent to put this money in the funds. Give me joy at thus beginning to make a provision for my
                    family, &#8211; late &amp; little as the beginning is.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The claim of the eleven copies is little <del>less</del> better than downright robbery.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The 11 copies of all new publications that existing copyright law required to be delivered to public and
                        university libraries. Southey shared the concerns of publishers and fellow authors that this was being enforced too
                        rigorously, especially after two court cases in 1812 put the responsibility to deliver the copies onto publishers. In
                        particular, he objected to libraries claiming their copies of second and subsequent editions of a work. His review of Isaac
                        D&#8217;Israeli (1766&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Calamities of Authors; Including some Inquiries Respecting their Moral and
                            Literary Characters</title> (1812), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (September 1812), 93&#8211;114, attacked the existing
                        copyright law that &#8216;an author may retain or dispose of the property of his works for a term of eight and twenty years, after
                        which it becomes common property&#8217; (111). Southey&#8217;s argument for reform was followed by the proposal that the government
                        establish an academy to provide employment for literary men and benefit individual and national interests (113&#8211;114). See also
                        Robert Southey to John Rickman, 22 January 1813, Letter 2210.</note> Government might as well claim so many trees out of every
                    plantation for the navy, &#8211; or so many pair of shoes for the army out of every shoemakers shop. This however is a light evil
                    compared to the laws of copyright. Do you know that if a bookseller publishes a work upon the agreement that he takes the risk
                    &amp; shares the profit, &#8211; this by their custom gives them half the copyright! &#8211; No author ever dreamt of this; &#8211; but so it is, in
                    pure ignorance, which I have literally been <del>making</del> sacrificing present convenience for the sake of preserving my
                    copyrights. I have in this manner given half away of every book which I have hitherto published! &#8211;<ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke"> Kirke White&#8217;s</ref> Remains<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White</title> (1807).</note> are in the same predicament, &amp; in this case <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville</ref> I believe is determined to try whether the law affords him no redress. The
                    claim is so impudent that the booksellers do not like to avow it till they are compelled, &#8211; &amp; of this there was a curious
                    instance in the case of the Remains. &#8211; I know not what the Authors can do, &#8211; but if you say something in their favour, it may one
                    day prove of use.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn participated in a parliamentary debate on copyright on 11 March
                        1813, describing the number of copies of books required by copyright libraries as a &#8216;tax&#8217; upon authors. A government committee
                        to enquire into existing copyright law was established in March 1813. Its findings led to legislation in 1814. This extended
                        copyright to an unconditional 28 years or the life of the author if longer. This was applied to new publications and those
                        already published by living authors. Posthumous works were also given a copyright period of 28 years. But publishers were
                        still required to deliver 11 copies of all new publications to public and university libraries.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>