<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2323</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3594</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National
                        Library of Scotland, MS 3884.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849-1850), IV, pp. 46-49.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2323" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2323" type="letter">
        <head>2323. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter
                    Scott</ref>, <date when="1813-11-05">5 November 1813</date>
          </head><p>Watermark: crown with fleur de
                        lys<lb />Endorsement: the New Laureate/ 5 November 1813<lb />MS: National
                        Library of Scotland, MS 3884<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849-1850), IV, pp. 46-49.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>London.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-11-05">Nov. 5. 1813</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Scott</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you have not guessed at the reason why your letter has lain
                    ten weeks unanswered, you must have thought me a very thankless &amp; graceless
                    fellow, &amp; very undeserving of such a letter. I waited from day to day that I
                    might tell you all was compleated, &amp; my patience was nearly exhausted in the
                    process. Let me tell you the whole history in due order, before I express my
                    feelings toward you upon the occasion. Upon receiving yours<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s letter of 1 September [1813],
                        telling Southey that he had declined the Poet Laureateship and instead
                        recommended him to Croker. He also cautioned &#8216;I am uncertain if you will
                        like it, for the laurel has certainly been tarnished by some of its wearers,
                        and as at present managed, its duties are inconvenient and somewhat liable
                        to ridicule&#8217;, H. C. Grierson (ed.), <title>The Letters of Walter Scott,
                            1787&#8211;1832</title>, 12, vols (London, 1932&#8211;1937), III, pp.
                        335&#8211;336.</note> I wrote to <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>
                    saying that the time was past when I could write verses upon demand, but that if
                    it were understood that instead of the old formalities I might be at liberty to
                    write upon great public events, or to be silent, as the spirit moved, in that
                    case the office would become a mark of honourable distinction &amp; I should be
                    proud of accepting it.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Robert
                        Southey to John Wilson Croker, [4 September 1813], Letter 2298.</note> How
                    this was to be managed he best knew: for of course, it was not for me to propose
                    terms to the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref>.
                    &#8211; When next I saw him he told me that after the appointment was compleated, he
                    or some other person in the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Princes</ref> confidence would suggest to him the fitness of making this
                    reform in an office, which requires some reform to rescue it from the contempt
                    into which it had fallen. &#8211; I thought all was settled, &amp; expected every day
                    to receive some official communication, but week after week past on. My head
                    quarters at this time were at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> going one day into town to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brothers</ref>, I found that Lord W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Gordon<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lord William Gordon (1744&#8211;1823), son of Cosmo George
                        Gordon, 3rd Duke of Gordon (1720&#8211;1752). He owned the Waterend estate on the
                        west side of Derwentwater and was married to Frances Ingram-Shepherd
                        (1761&#8211;1841), sister of Isabella Anne Ingram-Shepherd (1760&#8211;1834), second
                        wife of the Marquis of Hertford, the Lord Chamberlain.</note> with whom I
                    had left a card on my first arrival, had called three times on me in as many
                    days, &amp; had that morning requested that <del>if</del> I would call on him at
                    eleven, twelve, one or two o clock. I went accordingly never dreaming of what
                    the business could be, &amp; wondering at it. He told me that the <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Marquis of Hertford</ref> was his
                    brother-in-law, &amp; had written to him as being my neighbour in the country, &#8211;
                    placing in fact the appointment at his (Lord W<hi rend="sup">ms</hi>) disposal,
                    &#8211; wherefore he wished to see me to know if I wished to have it. The meaning of
                    all this was easily seen, I was very willing to thank one person more, &amp;
                    especially a good natured man to whom I am indebted for many neighbourly
                    civilities, he assured me that I should now soon hear from the Chamberlains
                    Office &amp; I departed accordingly in full expectation that two or three days
                    more would settle the affair. But neither days nor weeks brought any farther
                    intelligence, &amp; if plenty of employments &amp; avocations had not <del>very
                        much</del> filled up my mind as &lt;well as&gt; my time, I should perhaps
                    have taken dudgeon, &amp; returned to my family &amp; pursuits from which I had
                    so long been absent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At length after sundry ineffectual attempts owing sometimes to
                    his absence, &amp; once or twice to public business, I saw <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> once more, &amp; he discovered for
                    me that the delay originated in <del>xxx</del> a desire of <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Lord Hertford</ref> that <ref target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lord Liverpool</ref> should write to him,
                    &amp; ask the office for me. This calling-in the Prime Minister about the
                    disposal of an office the net emoluments of which are about 90 &#163; a year,
                    reminded me of the old proverb about shearing pigs.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;&#8220;Great cry and little
                    wool,&#8221; said the fool, when he sheared a pig.&#8217;</note>
          <ref target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lord Liverpool</ref> however was informed
                    of this by <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, the letter was
                    written, &amp; in the course of another week <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Lord Hertford</ref> wrote to <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> that he would give orders for
                    making out the appointment; &#8211; a letter soon followed to say that the order was
                    given, &amp; that I might be sworn in whenever I pleased. &#8211; My pleasure however
                    was the last thing to be consulted, after due enquiry on my part &amp; some
                    additional delays I received a note to say that if I would attend at the
                    Chamberlains Office, at one o&#8217;clock on Thursday Nov. 4 a gentleman usher<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hale Young Wortham (1747&#8211;1820), First
                        Gentleman Usher and Daily Waiter on His Majesty.</note> would be there to
                    administer the oath. Now it so happened that I was engaged to go to Woburn<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The seat of John Russell, 6th Duke of
                        Bedford (1766&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), the patron of Herbert Hill&#8217;s living
                        at Streatham.</note> on the <del>xx</del> Tuesday, meaning to return on
                    Thursday to dinner, or remain a day longer as I might feel disposed. Down I went
                    to the office &amp; solicited a change in the day, &#8211; but this was in vain, &#8211; the
                    gentleman-usher had been spoken to, &amp; a Poet Laureat is <del>an animal</del>
                    a creature of a lower description I obtained however two hours <del>xx</del>
                    grace, &#8211; &amp; &lt;yesterday&gt; by rising by candle-light &amp; hurrying the
                    post boys, reached the office to the minute. I swore to be a faithful servant to
                    the King, to reveal all treasons which might come to my knowledge, to discharge
                    the duties of my office &amp; to obey the <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Lord Chamberlain</ref> in all matters of the Kings service, &amp;
                    in his stead the Vice Chamberlain,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Francis Charles Seymour-Conway (1777&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>), who, as heir
                        to the Marquessate of Hertford, held the courtesy title Lord Yarmouth. He
                        was a close friend of the Prince Regent, who appointed him to the post of
                        vice-chamberlain in 1812.</note> &#8211; God is henceforth to help me as I observe
                    all this. Having taken this upon my soul I was thereby inducted into all the
                    rights privileges &amp; benefits which Henry James Pye<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poet-politician Henry James Pye (1745&#8211;1813;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Poet Laureate 1790&#8211;1813.</note>
          <del>xxx xx xxxxxxx xxxxxx xx</del> did enjoy, or ought to have enjoyed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The original salary of the office was 100 marks; it was raised
                    for Ben Jonson<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ben Jonson (1572&#8211;1637;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Poet Laureate 1616&#8211;1637.</note> to 100 pounds &amp;
                    a tierce of Spanish Canary Wine, now wickedly commuted for 26 &#163;, which said sum,
                    unlike the Canary is subject to income tax, land tax &amp; heaven knows what
                    taxes beside. The whole net income is little more or less than 90 &#163;. It comes to
                    me as a God-send &amp; I have vested it in a life-policy, &#8211; <del>adding
                        xxxx</del> by making it up 102 &#163; it covers an insurance for &#163;3000 upon my
                    own life. <del>You</del> I have never felt any painful anxiety as to providing
                    for my family, &#8211; my mind is too buoyant, my animal spirits too good <del>&amp; I
                        may add</del> for this care ever to <del>xx</del> have affected my
                    happiness, &#8211; &amp; I may add that <del>my</del> a not-unbecoming trust in
                    providence has ever supported my confidence in myself. But it is with the
                    deepest feeling of thankfulness that I have <del>xx</del> secured this legacy
                    for <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">my wife</ref> &amp;
                    children, &#8211; &amp; it is to you that I am primarily &amp; chiefly indebted for
                    this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To the manner of your letter I am quite unable to reply.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott had assured Southey, &#8216;you are
                        my better in poetry&#8217;; see Walter Scott to Robert Southey, 19 October 1813,
                        H. C. Grierson (ed.), <title>The Letters of Walter Scott, 1787&#8211;1832</title>,
                        12, vols (London, 1932&#8211;1937), III, pp. 364&#8211;366.</note> We shall both be
                    remembered hereafter, &amp; ill <del>xxxx</del> betide him who shall institute a
                    comparison between us. There has been no race; &#8211; we have <del>both</del> got to
                    the top of the hill by different paths, &amp; meet there not as rivals but as
                    friends, each rejoicing in the success of the other.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wait for the Levee,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        In order to be presented at Court.</note> &amp; hope to find a place in the
                    mail for Penrith on the evening after it, &#8211; for I <del>am</del> have the Swiss
                    malady, &amp; am home-sick.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The idea
                        of homesickness (nostalgia) as a peculiarly Swiss illness was explored by
                        Johannes Hofer (1669&#8211;1752) in his <title>Dissertatio medica de nostalgia,
                            oder Heimehe</title> (1688), which tried to develop a scientific theory
                        to explain the symptoms suffered by Swiss mercenaries serving abroad.</note>
                    Remember me to <ref target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Scott</ref> &amp; your daughter<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charlotte Sophia Scott (1799&#8211;1837).</note>
                    &amp; believe me my dear Scott</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> most truly &amp; affectionately yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>