<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1806</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3077</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence
                            of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 291&#8211;293 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1806" type="letter">
        <head>1806. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, <date when="1810-09-17">17 September
                        1810</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Scott Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Achiestiel/
                        Selkirk<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Southey/ 17 Sept<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1810<lb />MS:
                        Nationa Library of Scotland, MS 3879<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence
                            of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 291&#8211;293 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1810-09-17">Sept. 17. 1810</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Scott</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the Courier of the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> (which has this evening reached us) is an article pretending to
                    exhibit imitations from your poems &amp; signed S.T.C.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Courier</title> (15 September 1810) had published an article entitled &#8216;Some Imitations of Scott&#8217;. This compared
                        extracts from <title>The Lay of the Last Minstrel</title> and <title>Marmion</title> with ones from Dryden, Baillie, Home,
                        Ossian, Pope, Spenser, and Southey (<title>Madoc</title>) in an attempt to prove that Scott had been &#8216;more particularly &#8230;
                        guilty of imitation&#8217;.</note> At the first sight of this I was certain that <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">S.T. Coleridge</ref> had nothing to do with it, &amp; upon putting the paper into his hands, his astonishment was equal to
                    mine. What may be &lt;the&gt; motive of this dirty trick Heaven knows, &#8211; I can only conjecture that the fellow who has practised
                    it, designs in some other paper or magazine to build up a charge of jealousy &amp; envy in Coleridge, &#8211; founded upon his own
                    forgery. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> declares he will write to the Courier, disavowing the
                    signature, &#8211; I know he means to do it, but his actions so little correspond to his intentions that I fear he will delay doing it,
                    &#8211; very probably till it is too late.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> On this occasion, he did not delay. A declaration,
                        supplied by Coleridge, that the &#8216;S.T.C.&#8217; who had signed the piece on Scott was not the same person as &#8216;Mr. S. T. Coleridge&#8217;
                        appeared in the <title>Courier</title> on 20 September 1810.</note> Therefore I lose no time in assuring you that he knows
                    nothing of this petty &amp; paltry attack, &#8211; which I have no doubt from whatever quarter it may have come, originates more in
                    malice towards him than towards you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was not without hopes of seeing you in this land of <del>la</del> Lakes on your way from the Yorkshire
                        Greta,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott had been visiting John Bacon Sawrey Morritt (1771&#8211;1843;
                            <title>DNB</title>) at Rokeby Park in Co. Durham.</note> but happening to see <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> about a fortnight ago he told me you were settled at <ref target="places.html#Ashestiel">Ashiestiel</ref> for the rest of the autumn. I say happening to
                    see him, because his visit was to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, not to me, &amp; he told <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> that he had not called immediately on me, as he did not know what my
                    feelings perhaps might be towards him, &amp;c &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have probably seen my labours in the Register,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810).</note> &#8211; upon almost all points of present politics I believe there
                    is little difference of opinion between us, &amp; every where I think you will give me credit for fair dealing as well as plain
                    dealing. At present I am working very hard upon the second volume,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title> (1810).</note> &#8211; it is an employment which interests me very much, &amp; I
                    complain of nothing but the want sometimes of sufficient documents respecting the Spanish war. Particularly I regret the want of
                    detailed accounts of the second siege of Zaragoza<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish city of Zaragoza was twice
                        besieged by the French in 1808&#8211;1809. The death toll was over 54,000 before it finally fell on 20 February 1809.</note> &amp;
                    the siege of Gerona,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The city of Gerona had fallen to the French on 11 December 1809 after
                        a siege of nearly seven months. Southey finally did obtain a copy of Juan Andres Nieto Samaniego (fl. 1810), <title>Memorial
                            Historica de los Sucesos mas Notables de Armas y Estado de la Salud Publica Durante el Ultimo Sitio de la Plaza de
                            Gerona</title> (1810).</note> &#8211; that I might be enabled to present a full record of those glorious <del>xxxxxx</del>
                    &lt;events&gt;. I suppose you know the whole secret history of the Register, otherwise I would tell you how liberally the <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn ">Ballantynes</ref> have behaved to me. They will probably find their account in having
                    engaged a man who writes with such perfect freedom; &#8211; for tho parts of the work may &amp; <del>xxx</del> indeed will, offend all
                    parties in turn, still there is a decided character of impartiality about it <del>xxxxxxxxxx</del> which will prove the surest
                    recommendation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Kehama<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> has travelled so slowly thro the press, that instead of appearing at the end
                    of one season, it will be ready about the beginning of the next. I expect every body to admire my new fashion of printing (tho
                    unfortunately the printers did not fall into it for the first three or four sheets) &#8211; &#8211; if any thing else is admired, &#8211; ponamus
                        lucro.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;We need the money&#8217;.</note> My unknown Critic in the Register will think that I
                    am going against wind &amp; tide with a vengeance, instead of sailing, according to his advice, <del>xx</del> with the
                        stream.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey refers to an article in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1808</title>, 1.2 (1810), 422: &#8216;We cannot stop to enquire whether Mr Southey may not, in many instances, be able to make a
                        rational and reasonable apology for neglecting the prescriptive rules of art. It is sufficient to our present purpose, that no
                        author, however undoubted his genius, can hope to stem the public opinion by swimming directly contrary to its
                        current&#8217;.</note> But if he or any body else should imagine that I purposely set myself in opposition to public opinion, they
                    are very much mistaken. I do not think enough about public opinion for this to be possible. In planning &amp; executing a poem no
                    other thought ever occurs to me than that of making it as good as I can. When <del>they are</del> &lt;it is&gt; finished, &#8211; the
                    ostrich does not commit her eggs with more confidence to the sand &amp; the sun, &amp; to [MS torn] nature, than I &#8216;cast it upon
                    the waters&#8217; &#8211; sure if it be good that it will &#8220;be found after many days.&#8221;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> A paraphrase of
                            <title>Ecclesiastes</title> 11: 1.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It gratified me much to hear that you had been interested with my first volume of Brazil.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810).</note> The second<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Published in 1817.</note> will contain more stimulating matter, &#8211; but it is from the history of
                        Portugal<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey never finished his planned &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> that I
                    think you will derive most amusement, &#8211; so full will it be of high chivalrous matter, &amp; beautiful costume. Pelayo<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early incarnation of what became <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                        (1814).</note> comes on slow &amp; sure, thoroughly to my own mind as far as it has advanced.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Things look well in the Peninsula. I have never in the worst times abated one jot of <del>my</del> hope respecting
                    the Spaniards &amp; my friends the Portugueze, &amp; do now firmly believe that if we carried on the war with vigour &amp; with
                    sufficient personality against Buonaparte, it would inevitably end in is overthrow &#8211; God bless you &#8211;remember me to <ref target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">Mrs Scott</ref> &amp; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> believe me very truly yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>