<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1797</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3068</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 149.  Previously 
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        537&#8211;538.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1797" type="letter">
        <head>1797. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1810-08-01">1 August
                        1810</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: Fr./ RS./ 1 Aug<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1810<lb /> MS: Huntington Library, RS 149<lb />Previously
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        537&#8211;538.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1810-08-01">Aug 1. 1810.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The thought of how long it is since I have written to you lies like a sin upon my conscience. It is six weeks since
                    you sent me the Portugueze book from <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Observador Portuguez</title> (1809), reviewed in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (August 1810), 1&#8211;24, and no. 3556
                        in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; the Tantararas have dispersed since that time, &amp; as I know not where
                    this may find you, I shall inclose it as usual in the franking season, &amp; trust it to <del>find</del> &lt;make&gt; its way by
                    help of the Grand Parleur.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;The Great Speaker&#8217;, i.e. Rickman&#8217;s employer, <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbot</ref>, The Speaker 1802&#8211;1817.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Shall we see you this season in Cumberland? there are yet three months of it to come, &amp; for a man who cannot
                    visit the Lakes in May, September is the best month he can chuse. I was sorry to hear of your loss,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Rickmans&#8217; daughter Martha died in 1810.</note> of which <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickmans</ref> note conveyed to me the first intimation. Is there any hope of our seeing <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref> here? &#8211; it would be a very great gratification both to
                        <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; myself &#8211; &amp; I would even bargain for letting you go on to look
                    after your roads &amp; bridges,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rickman was Secretary to the Commission on the Caledonian
                        Canal and Highland roads and bridges 1803&#8211;1819.</note> provided you would convoy her thus far on the way, &amp; return hither
                    after your survey was accomplished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am in daily &#8211; hourly &#8211; expectation of son or <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">daughter</ref>, &#8211; &amp; have
                    been so for this week past. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref> is here, sent by his
                    physicians to breathe mountain air, &amp; doing credit to this judgement. He is very much better since he has been here, &amp; I
                    have good hope that he may receive permanent &amp; effectual benefit. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> who has been quartered here since the beginning of May, talks of a journey to London! God help him! &#8211; He has
                    been in better health than usual, &amp; excellent spirits, &#8211; reading very hard, &amp; to no purpose, &#8211; for nothing comes of it,
                    except an accumulation of knowledge equal to that of any man living &amp; a body of sound philosophy superior to what any man
                    either of this or any former age has possessed, &#8211; all which will perish with him. I do not know any other motive that he has for
                    going to London, than that he becomes daily more &amp; more uneasy at having done nothing for so long, &amp; therefore flies away
                    to avoid the sight of persons, who he knows must be grieved by his misconduct, tho they refrain from all remonstrances.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been somewhat indolent myself for the last six weeks, partly because of my wicked annual cold, &#8211; &amp;
                    partly from sheer idleness, liking the mountains or the lake better than the desk. No day has past without me doing something, &#8211;
                    but it has not been regular steady work. However I feel my appetite for it returning, &amp; am usually the better for such seasons
                    of fallowing when they occur. <del>In</del> My second volume<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second volume of
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title>, published in 1817.</note> has advanced some way. I cannot tell what French voyages
                    there are which have escaped me, according to the <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Capitaneus</ref>, unless there be any
                    matter in Thevets Collection, which that scoundrel did not insert in his France Antarctique.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andr&#233; Thevet (1502&#8211;1590), whose <title>Les Singularitez de la France Antarctique</title> (1557) purported to
                        be a first-hand account of a French expedition to Brazil. The &#8216;Collection&#8217; could be his <title>Cosmographie
                            Universelle</title> (1575). Southey owned editions of both works, nos 2852 and 2677 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note> The only books which I am conscious of having wanted were two Portugueze works. <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> the Quarterly Bookseller has borrowed for me a very curious volume, composed of
                    pieces cut out from a series of Almanacks printed at Lima from the year 1760 to about 12 years later.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Descripcion de las Provincias Pertenecientes al Arzobispado di Lima&#8217;; no. 3645 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library, inscribed in his hand: &#8216;This book of which perhaps a duplicate is nowhere to be found, was given me by Mr
                        Murray; it contains the fullest account which has yet been published on the old Vice-royalty of Peru, province by province.
                        The information was obtained from the respective Corregidores, and printed for many successive years in the Lima Almanack,
                        from whence some curioso cut out the whole collection, and formed them into this <hi rend="ital">most valuable
                        volume</hi>&#8217;.</note> They contain<del>ed</del> descriptions of most of the Spanish provinces in South America, with more
                    information concerning their then state than I have ever seen elsewhere, &#8211; infinitely more than could be gleaned from the Mercurio
                        Peruano.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Mercurio Peruano</title> (1790&#8211;1795), the first newspaper published in Peru.</note> I have not yet got thro half the
                    volume, &amp; my gleanings from it are very copious &amp; highly <del>xxxxxxx</del> valuable. A friend<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Ridout (1788&#8211;1871), later Lecturer and Vicar of Newland, Gloucestershire. He was the son of John Gibbs
                        Ridout (1758&#8211;1823), London apothecary, who had provided Coleridge with medical advice.</note> of <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Pooles</ref>, who went to Spain with
                    Jacob, the M. P.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Jacob (1761/2&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Rye 1808&#8211;1812.
                        He made a 6-month visit to Spain in 1809&#8211;1810 and published <title>Travels in the South of Spain</title> the following
                        year.</note> bought a few books for me there, &amp; has also offered me his own journal &amp; all the information which he
                    possesses, &#8211; from the opportunities which he enjoyed this is likely to be considerable. It will be of use to me in my history of
                    1809 for the Register &#8211; which I have just begun.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> was here last week. I put to him the home question, whether he did not
                    think the Edinburgh Review had held very base &amp; mischievous language respecting Spain, &#8211; &amp; he answered <hi rend="ital">yes</hi>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My advertisement for books<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), I, p. vi.</note> has procured me one vol. of Jesuit letters<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had advertised for &#8216;volumes of the Jesuits&#8217; Annual Letters or Relations&#8217;; see
                            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), I, p. vi. The volume procured by Wynn is
                        unidentified.</note> bought by <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> for me, &amp; the Valeroso Lucideno<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manuel Calado (1584&#8211;1654), <title>Valeroso Lucideno e o Triunfo da Liberdade</title>
                        (1648), a first-hand account of Brazil during the period of Dutch rule.</note> to be lent by Stuart, our Envoy at Lisbon.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Stuart, Baron Stuart de Rothesay (1779&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), envoy at Lisbon
                        1810&#8211;1814.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> sends a list to Paris for me. <del>xx</del> I long to show you your old inmates
                    in their present resting place, &#8211; my library is one of the gayest you ever saw.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref>
          </salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>