<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2561</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3832</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        25.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2561" type="letter">
        <head>2561. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1815-03-01">1 March 1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        25<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1815-03-01">1. March 1815</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Roderick, a Bishop of Toledo finished his history in 1243 &amp; he says that the tomb at Viseu had been discovered
                        <hi rend="ital">lately</hi> &#8211; modernis temporibus &#8211; <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. &#8216;recently&#8217;. Southey is
                        referring to Rodrigo Jimenez de Rada (c. 1170&#8211;1247; Archbishop of Toledo 1209&#8211;1247), <title>De Rebus Hispaniae</title> (1243).
                        He used this Latin quotation in his note to <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 25, line 587.
                        Grosvenor Bedford had been commissioned, at Southey&#8217;s suggestion, to review <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                        (1814) for the <title>Quarterly</title>. His article eventually appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815),
                        83&#8211;113. However, it contained, as this letter demonstrates, many emendations and suggestions by Southey himself.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The change <del>xx</del> &lt;in&gt; the Vision tells badly when reduced to a mere caput mortuum,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Literally a &#8216;dead head&#8217;, i.e. something useless.</note> perhaps you had better quote the passage
                    at length from &#8216;Thus he cried &#8211; to in moonlight &amp; in silence; &#8211; it will occupy little more than a page in the review &amp; you
                    may allow yourself three or four such lengths with a safe conscience.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bedford finally
                        decided to quote <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 3, lines 194&#8211;259, at 92&#8211;93 of his
                    review.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="center"> ___</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Siverian has no suspicion of Roderick. The voice disturbed him <del>because he xxxx</del> but with no definite
                    recollection; &#8211; &amp; what he was afraid of in revealing in secret hope was that it might be treated as an utter impossibility, &#8211;
                        <del>that he might &amp; his</del> &amp; the consolation which he desired from it destroyed. In the last book he exclaims
                    Blind that I am I knew not till now.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 25, line 332, &#8216;Blind that I was to know him not till now!&#8217;.</note>
                    &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The objections to the 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Book may very well. I reply to them only quoad<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;with respect to&#8217;.</note> yourself. They may as well-stand as any other objections, &amp; better
                    than <del>all</del> some which might happen to be better founded.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here I think the Pussiygonial part of my reply may end</p>
        <p rend="center"> ___</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I received <ref target="people.html#RobertsBarreCharles">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Robertss</ref> book<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Grosvenor Bedford&#8217;s <title>Letters and Miscellaneous Papers &#8230; With a Memoir of His Life</title>
                        (1814) of his cousin Barr&#233; Charles Roberts, who had died in 1810 aged 21. It was reviewed by Southey in the <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 12 (January 1815), 509&#8211;519. Mr Roberts had sent Southey a copy bound in red morocco leather and with gilt
                        leaves; no. 2371 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> a few days <del>only</del> ago only &#8211; since I wrote to
                    you. &#8211; Doubtless I ought <del>x</del>to thank him for it, &amp; I will tell you in your ear why this has not been done. First
                    because of the sin which besets me of procrastinating that which I do not immediately feel <del>that</del> the power of doing as
                    it ought to be done; &amp; secondly because of a lurking desire &amp; hope that I might be able to gratify him &amp; myself by
                    some verses to <ref target="people.html#RobertsBarreCharles">his sons</ref> memory in the form of an Inscription for a tablet at
                        Oseney.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Osney Abbey, a ruined house of Augustinian canons, now in a suburb of Oxford.
                        Roberts had collected material for a &#8216;Note on Oseney Abbey&#8217;, <title>Letters and Miscellaneous Papers</title>, pp.
                        127&#8211;139.</note> This, as you know, is a form of composition of which I am very fond. If I succeed you will soon hear of this,
                    &#8211; do not mention it lest I should <del>xxxx</del> fail.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey eventually succeeded, but
                        the poem was not published until it appeared as &#8216;Written in an unpublished Volume of Letters, and Miscellaneous Papers &#8230; With
                        a Memoir of His Life (London, 1814), by Barr&#233; Charles Roberts&#8217;, <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838),
                        III, pp. 157&#8211;159, where it is mis-dated &#8216;<hi rend="ital">Keswick</hi>, 1814&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If the Quarterly should be delayed beyond another fortnight can you send me thirty pounds by that time, &#8211; &amp;
                    receive for it what will be coming to me for the article on Lewis &amp; Clarke?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Meriweather Lewis (1774&#8211;1809) and William Clark (1770&#8211;1838), <title>Travels to the Source of the Missouri River, and Across
                            the American Continent to the Pacific Ocean</title> (1814), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12
                        (January 1815), 317&#8211;368.</note> I endorsed a bill to that amount which has been protested &amp; I <del>x</del> have been
                    obliged to take it up. The drawer is a Commander in the navy &#8211; a relation of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref>,
                    &#8211; who wintered <del>here</del> &lt;in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>&gt;, &amp; who has nothing worse about him
                    than a leaden lining to his skull; so that I have no apprehension of losing the money; but a very great one that I may not be able
                    to find him out as soon as is expedient; or that being found out he may not be able to reimburse me &lt;directly&gt;, finding him
                    upon such terms with his agents:<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Captain Thomas Perkins (1778&#8211;1815), a cousin of Edith&#8217;s.
                        Southey did lose the money; see Southey to Thomas Southey, 16 March 1815, Letter 2573. However, as Perkins died at Dover on 3
                        April 1815, he may have been prevented from repaying Southey because of ill-health, rather than as part of a fraud.</note> By
                    good fortune there arrived some money just at that time to place <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> at
                    Oxford, &#8211; &amp; from him I borrow for the immediate exigency, &#8211; but he must set off in three weeks or sooner; &amp; I had fully
                    expected that the Review would be out before that time, if your letter had not shown me that it will certainly be delayed
                        <del>later</del> till a later day.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I can say nothing of my future movements. If this ear of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">the childs</ref>
                    should heal, &amp; I should easily be taught to expect <del>that</del> this, seeing that it gives her no annoyance, I should
                    probably not travel Southward till I could be sure of going on to my intended French expedition; &#8211; &amp; if I had not almost as
                    habitual a reliance upon the Bank of Faith as Breeches Huntingdon himself,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The preacher
                        and religious writer William Huntington (1745&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), whose <title>God the Guardian of the Poor and the
                            Bank of Faith</title> (1785&#8211;1802), describes how Providence assisted his early preaching career by supplying him with
                        food, clothing and all else he needed, including (pp. 70&#8211;72) a pair of leather breeches. Southey later condemned Huntington&#8217;s
                        account as unparalleled &#8216;in the whole bibliotheca of knavery and fanaticism&#8217; (<title>Quarterly Review</title>, 24 (January
                        1821), 482).</note> the thought of such an expedition would never have entered into my head. But <del>xxxxx in all money</del>
                    &lt;in&gt; matters <del>I have</del> of expenditure I am conscious of that sort of improvidence which is common to gamblers,
                    journeymen manufacturers, &amp; men of precarious income, &#8211; <del>or might</del> whose proverb is Spend &amp; God will send. It is
                    tempered in me by all my personal habits, &#8211; but when books come in my way, or any thing which is to gratify an intellectual
                    appetite, then am I a spendthrift. If my journey were extended to Spain, I could make it pay for itself. Two months in the
                    peninsula would suffice, &#8211; three would amply do. But this I fear would exceed your tether, &amp; I will not go without a
                    companion</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your Butler is a good Butler.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;The Butler&#8217; was a comical epic hero
                        invented by Southey and Grosvenor Charles Bedford.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should have sent this packet yesterday, but <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> made his
                    appearance here on Monday, &amp; left me this morning. His White Doe<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wordsworth&#8217;s
                            <title>The White Doe of Rylstone</title> (1815).</note> is in the press.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>