<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2383</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3654</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47891.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 343&#8211;346.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2383" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2383" type="letter">
        <head>2383. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">John King</ref>, <date when="1814-02-27">27 February 1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John King Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Mall/ Clifton/
                        Bristol<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47891<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 343&#8211;346.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-02-27">Feb. 27. 1814.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear King</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You once asked me for a passage in Herrera,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish chronicler Antonio
                        de Herrera y Tordesillas (1559&#8211;1625). King&#8217;s letter has not survived, so it is not possible to identify the passage he
                        requested.</note> which is not to be found in that author. at least I did not find it there when I read the whole work
                    carefully thro. If however I remember rightly, I sent you <del>xxxx xxx xxxxx xxxxxx</del> an extract to the same purport from the
                    letters of Amerigo Vespucci:<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Amerigo Vespucci (1454&#8211;1512), explorer who made three or four
                        voyages to the east coast of South America at the start of the sixteenth century.</note> &amp; this morning I have found the
                    matter more fully stated &amp; confirmed by much better authority. The Portugueze &lt;Academy&gt; have just published (for the
                    first time) some observations upon the natural history of Brazil by Anchieta:<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jos&#233; de
                        Anchieta (1534&#8211;1597), Jesuit missionary, whose interests extended to natural history. The &#8216;notes&#8217; on Anchieta&#8217;s
                            <title>Epistola Quamplurimarum Rerum Naturalium</title> (1560) were produced by Diogo de Toledo Lara Ordo&#241;ez (fl.
                        1780s&#8211;1810s) in <title>Collec&#231;&#227;o de Noticias para a Hist&#243;ria e Geografia das Na&#231;&#245;es Ultramarinas</title> (1812&#8211;1813). For
                        Southey&#8217;s copy, see no. 3273 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &amp; the nineteenth section is as follows.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Est alius vermiculus Scolopendrae fere similis, pilis totus obsitus, deformis visu, cujus varia sunt genera; colore
                    se differunt, et nomine; eadem forma omnibus.<hi rend="sup">x</hi>
          <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <hi rend="sup">x</hi> Larv&#230; sunt Papilionum, species omnes, quarum pili inferunt dolorem, nomen obtinent Brasilicum Tataurana
                        id est <hi rend="ital">tanquam ignis urens</hi>. [Southey&#8217;s note, from <title>Collec&#231;a&#245; de Noticias para a Historia e
                            Geografia das Na&#231;&#245;es Ultramarinas que vivem nos Dominios Portuguezes</title>, 2 vols (Lisbon, 1812&#8211;1813), I, no. III, p.
                        172; it translates &#8216;The larva are of butterflies, all species, whose hairs bring pain. They are called Tataurana Brasilicum,
                        that is like the burning of fire&#8217;.]</note> Horum alii si corpus tangant, magnum inferunt dolorem, qui multis horis perseverat;
                    aliorum vero (qui oblongi sunt et nigri rubro capite) pili venenosi sunt, et ad libidinem incendunt: quos solent Indi genitalibus
                    imponere, qu&#230; in vehementem excitantur libidinis ardorem, intument et post triduum computrescunt; unde s&#230;pe fit, ut pr&#230;putium
                    multifariam perforetur, aliquando etiam ipsa virilia corruptionem contrapant insanabilem, nec se solum ea morbi f&#339;ditate
                    deturpant, sed et ipsas etiam f&#339;minas, quibus se immiscuerint, conspurcant et inficiunt.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Collec&#231;a&#245; de Noticias para a Historia e Geografia das Na&#231;&#245;es Ultramarinas que vivem nos Dominios Portuguezes</title>, 2
                        vols (Lisbon, 1812&#8211;1813), I, no. III, p. 147: &#8216;There is another larva of the centipede which is almost the same, totally
                        covered with hairs, horrible in appearance, of various types: they differ in colour and name but they all have the same form.
                        Some of them, if they touch their bodies, give you great pain which lasts for a number of hours; but the hairs of others
                        (which are rectangular and black with a red head) are poisonous and arouse lust. These the Indians are accustomed to place on
                        their genitals, which are then aroused to great heights of lust, they grow and after three days they rot away completely; so
                        that it often happens that as the foreskin is perforated in many places, sometimes also their sexual organs suffer incurable
                        disease, so that not only do they disfigure themselves with the deformity of illness but they also infect and sexually defile
                        the women with whom they consort&#8217;.</note> &#8225;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8225; Si verum est h&#230;c ulcera
                        insanabilia fieri et contagiosa, Lue quoque venerea &#230;grotus laborare conjectari potest? [Southey&#8217;s note, from <title>Collec&#231;a&#245;
                            de Noticias para a Historia e Geografia das Na&#231;&#245;es Ultramarinas que vivem nos Dominios Portuguezes</title>, 2 vols
                        (Lisbon, 1812&#8211;1813), I, no. III, p. 172; it translates &#8216;If it is true that these ulcers are incurable and contagious, is it
                        possible to infer that the affliction works like a veneral disease?&#8217;]</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The notes are by Diogo de Toledo Lara Ordo&#241;ez, a correspondent of the Academy who communicated the original paper
                    from Brazil.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are one or two other things in this little treatise which (as I am writing) may be worth mentioning. Anchieta
                    says that a person who has once recovered from the bite of a dangerous serpent is in <del>xxx</del> &lt;no&gt; danger, &amp;
                    suffers much less pain if bitten a second time.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Cole&#231;&#227;o de Noticias para a Hist&#243;ria e Geografia das Na&#231;&#245;es Ultramarinas</title> 2 vols (Lisbon, 1812), I, no. III, p. 144.</note> This
                    seems to corroborate what Thunberg says, &#8211; which you will find in the Omniana. Vol. 2<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> &#8211; p. 261&#8211;2.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey and Coleridge, <title>Omniana, or Horae Otiosiores</title>, 2 vols (London, 1812), II,
                        pp. 261&#8211;262; citing the Swedish botanist, physician and disciple of Linnaeus, Carl Peter Thunberg (1743&#8211;1828), <title>Travels
                            in Europe, Africa, and Asia, 1770&#8211;79</title>, 4 vols (London, 1795), II, p. 163, no. 2812 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Thunberg related that natives of South Africa made themselves immune to poison by encouraging venomous reptiles and insects to bite them with gradually increasing severity.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> His commentator affirms that in one part of Brazil the inhabitants <del>were</del> &lt;are&gt; fully convinced
                        <del>that</del> they had &lt;a&gt; certain cure for the bite of a serpent, &#8211; if <del>th</del> it could be applied . As soon as
                    the patient <del>was</del> &lt;is&gt; bitten, another person, having his mouth half full of tobacco, <del>was</del> &lt;is&gt; to
                    suck the wound with great force, spitting repeatedly during the operation: this <del>was</del> to be continued for a considerable
                    time &#8211; &amp; then the tobacco to be laid upon the orifice.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Cole&#231;&#227;o de Noticias para a Hist&#243;ria e Geografia das Na&#231;&#245;es Ultramarinas</title> 2 vols (Lisbon, 1812), I, no. III, p. 130.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The same commentator says that the reason why Parrots so very rarely procreate in captivity (for the fact is
                    equally rare in all climates) is that it is their habit to couple while in the act of flying.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Cole&#231;&#227;o de Noticias para a Hist&#243;ria e Geografia das Na&#231;&#245;es Ultramarinas</title> 2 vols (Lisbon, 1812), I, no. III, p. 175.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I send you these facts with a safe conscience, as neither dog, cat, frog nor any other unhappy subjects of
                    experimental philosophy can possibly be the worse for them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <hi rend="sup">x</hi> Some of the hairy caterpillars in England are said to sting the hand if they are touched, like nettles. I
                    have handled all sorts that ever came in my way &amp; never found this to be the case: &amp; my skin is neither hardenend by
                    labour, nor inirritable by nature. But it may very possibly be unsusceptible of their particular irritation, just as some
                    constitutions are not liable to certain diseases &#8211; Why negroes suffer so dreadfully from the small pox is I believe accounted for.
                    &#8211; but has it ever been discovered why they &lt;are&gt; entirely free from the yellow fever?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you &amp; I were neighbours once more (which I sincerely <del>wh</del> wish we were) you would often be amused
                    at my physical speculations; &#8211; <del>X</del> here, like all my other speculations, they &#8216;waste their sweetness on the desert
                        air&#8217;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Gray (1716&#8211;1771; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;Elegy Written in a Country
                        Churchyard&#8217; (1751), stanza 14, line 4.</note> &#8211; <del>except when</del> &lt;unless&gt; in some idle <hi rend="ital">Omnianaish</hi> hour I commit them to <del>paper</del> &lt;writing&gt;!; <del>x</del> then they find their way into a little
                    desk appropriated for the reception of <del>xxxxx</del> stray papers: &amp; there they contract sweetness from a bottle of Ottar
                    of Rose, which my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> bought of a Jew at Tetuan, &amp; which serves no other
                    purpose than to <del>sweeten</del> perfume them for the printer. With him at least my <del>xxxxxxxx</del> works are in good
                    odour.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the course of the summer I shall have something to send you. Roderick<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> is in the press &#8211; &amp; I have corrected nine sheets; every
                    proof spurring me on towards the completion of it. Without this spur it would probably remain much longer unfinished; &#8211; for
                    occupations multiply upon me, &amp; I have none of that feeling which makes a young poet impatient to appear before the world
                    &amp; receive the reward of his labours. You will be pleased with this poem: it is deep tragedy throughout, but that kind of
                    tragedy which elevates the mind instead of destroying it. I am thinking already what to beg[MS torn] next, &#8211; for tho my motions in
                    poetry are <del>slow</del> now become slow as a tortoise, nevertheless I should not be happy <del>xx</del> unless some long one
                    [MS torn] in hand. I hesitate between four. 1. a New-England historical subject with an ideal Quaker hero by name Oliver Goffe,
                    son of one of K Charles judges, &amp; godson of Oliver Cromwell: &#8211; a rhymed poem, pitched in Spensers key, but with dramatic &amp;
                    lyric parts.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;, left incomplete at his death. In Southey&#8217;s poem, Newman was
                        the godson of Oliver Cromwell (1599&#8211;1658; <title>DNB</title>) and the son of William Goffe (d. 1679?; <title>DNB</title>),
                        Puritan, regicide and major general, who fled to New England in 1660 after he was excluded from the Act of Indemnity after the
                        Restoration.</note> 2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi> Robin Hood: to which the chief objection is that I should be accused of imitating
                        <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scotts</ref> manner &#8211; tho the story was planned, &amp; one or two detached sketches
                    written, before <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> was heard of.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        eventually collaborated with Caroline Bowles on a romance on the legendary outlaw. It was left unfinished at his death, and a
                        fragment published posthumously in 1847.</note> 3 a Persia romance founded upon the Zendavesta,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The sacred text of Zoroastrianism. Neither this nor the Runic poem were written.</note> &amp; 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> a Runic romance, &#8211; but this last has the least chance, as I should chuse to read the Sagas first, &amp; have a
                    language to learn.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Let me say a word or two to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> before I conclude. From the
                        list<del>s</del> of books which he has sent me I shall be glad to have Knox&#8217;s history of the reformation in Scotland.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> An unknown edition of the religious reformer John Knox&#8217;s (c. 1514&#8211;1572;
                        <title>DNB</title>) <title>History of the Reformation in Scotland</title> (1559&#8211;1566).</note> And about the money, whatever
                    balance may be in his hands, <ref target="people.html#Frickerfamily">Eliza</ref> will have a use for, when she removes to Wells,
                    which she will do in May. I thought I was in his debt for some books from <ref target="people.html#Gutch">Gutch</ref> &amp; a few
                    other commissions, <del>&amp; xxxxx that the xxxx xxxxx xxxx from George &amp; information about that xxxxxx xxxxx xxxx &amp; had
                        not xxxxxx perhaps I had not got other items</del>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our winter has been rigorous, but less uncomfortable than yours, for we have had less snow. We have had
                        <del>xx</del> ailments of late, which seem now to be passing away. I wish you could see my live stock. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> is my Long daughter, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> is my Slim daughter, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Katharine</ref> is my Round Daughter, &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> is my Square daughter, &amp; as for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> I add (&amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> repeat it after &lt;me&gt; with no small triumph) &#8211; he is no daughter at all. If
                    Buonaparte be killed (&amp; I pray to God that the war may continue till he is) I shall probably some years hence take them to the
                    continent &amp; domesticate there for some years, &#8211; as the easiest &amp; cheapest mode of education.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>