<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2270</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3541</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Wilberforce d. 15.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2270" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2270" type="letter">
        <head>2270. Robert Southey to [<ref target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">William Wilberforce</ref>], <date when="1813-06-19">19
                        June 1813</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: Southey Mr Pu/ Albuquerque&#8217;s popu/ larity &amp;
                        why<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Wilberforce d. 15<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-06-19">June 19. 1813.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter of May 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> lay at the booksellers till it could be inclosed in a parcel, &amp; has
                    only this day reached me.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Wilberforce&#8217;s letter, which had asked for information on
                        &#8216;Albuquerque&#8217;s being thanked by the widows of Hindostan, for saving them from the flames&#8217; and for &#8216;any other facts or
                        suggestions&#8217; to assist in the Christianisation of Hindus, Robert Isaac Wilberforce and Samuel Wilberforce (eds), <title>The
                            Correspondence of William Wilberforce</title>, 2 vols (London, 1840), II, pp. 264&#8211;265.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The fact<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;The fact&#8217;, as reported in Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Periodical Accounts of the
                        Baptist Missionary Society&#8217;, &#8216;that Alboquerque was blest by the women because he prohibited this custom [suti]&#8217;,
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 190.</note> respecting Alboquerque<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alfonso d&#8217; Alboquerque (1453&#8211;1515), Portuguese nobleman and officer. The governor of Portuguese India
                        1509&#8211;1515, he was responsible for the conquest of Goa and Malacca and the establishment of Portuguese imperial power in the
                        Indian ocean.</note> is related by his son Bras d&#8217;Alboquerque<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Br&#225;s d&#8217;Alboquerque
                        (1500&#8211;1580) published a collection of his father&#8217;s papers under the title <title>Commentarios</title> in 1576</note>. in his
                    Commentaries. Part 2. Chap<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 20. P 116 of the last edition (1774).<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Commentarios</title>, 4 vols (Lisbon, 1774), II, pp. 116&#8211;117. Southey&#8217;s copy was no. 3165 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note> After stating that it was the custom to make a widow burn herself, or in case of her refusal, condemn her to
                    prostitute herself for the advantage of the pagoda of which she was a parishioner, as he calls it, he adds &#8220;e como Afonso
                    Dalboquerque tomou o Reyno de Goa, na&#245; consentio que dali por diante se queimasse mais nenhuma mulher; e posto que mudar costume
                    seja parelha de morte, todavia ellas folgaram com a vida, e diziam grandes bens delle, por lhes mandar que se na&#245; queimassem.&#8221; &#8211;
                    when Af. D&#8217;Alboquerque took the kingdom of Goa he would not permit that any woman from thenceforward should burn herself; and
                    altho to change their customs is equal to death, nevertheless they rejoiced in life, &amp; said great good of <del>it</del> him,
                    because he commanded that they should not burn themselves.&#8221; This is as nearly as may be a literal translation. I may add in proof
                    of the veneration in which this great man was held by the natives, that long after his death when a Moor or Hindoo had received
                        <del>xxx</del> wrong, &amp; could obtain no redress from the Governor the aggrieved person would go to Goa, to Alboquerques
                    tomb &amp; make an offering of oil for the lamp which burned before it, &amp; call upon him for justice.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Having been for many years employed upon the history of Portugal,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                        uncompleted &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> its conquests &amp; colonies, the knowledge which I had thus gained of the history
                    of Hindostan enabled &lt;me&gt; to see that there was as much ignorance as irreligion in the arguments of the opponents of the
                    Missionaries. When Joam de Barros<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joao de Barros (1496&#8211;1570), Portuguese historian and
                        author of <title>Decadas da Asia</title> (1552&#8211;1615). Southey possessed an edition of 1778&#8211;1788, number 3180 in the Sale
                        Catalogue of his Library.</note> &lt;wrote&gt; (a man who for the extent of his researches is worthy to be ranked with
                        Herodotus<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Herodotus (c. 484&#8211;425 BC), Greek author of <title>The Histories</title> and
                        honoured as the &#8216;first historian&#8217;.</note>) a fourth part of the population of Malabar consisted of native Moors; &amp; the
                    reason which he assigns for their rapid increase, is, that they had obtained privileges from the King &amp; put themselves upon a
                    level with the high casts, &#8211; &#8220;for which cause many of the natives <del>became xxxxxx</del> &lt;embraced their faith.&gt;&#8220; He says
                    in another place that the natives esteemed it a great honour when the Moors took their daughters to wife.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> An unidentified reference from Joam de Barros (1496&#8211;1570), <title>Decadas da Asia</title>, 24 vols (Lisbon, 1778&#8211;1788).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Without dreaming that the British empire in Asia can be permanent I earnestly wish, for the sake of Asia, that it
                    may be preserved as long as possible &amp; that it may leave as much &lt;as&gt; possible behind it; &#8211; that our faith, &amp;
                    language, &amp; social institutions may survive us, it is our duty to use every allowable means for weaning the natives from their
                    own false-religion, because that system <del>xxxxxx</del> is equally injurious to their morals &amp; their temporal happiness, &#8211;
                    it oppresses <del>with</del> them with burthensome &amp; bloody ceremonies, making one portion of the community wicked &amp; the
                    other miserable. <del>Xx xxxxxxxxx xx xxxx xxxxx which xxxx xxxx xxxxxxxxx xxxxx religion xxxx</del> I express myself here in
                    terms which no man can contradict, let his opinions concerning Christianity be what they may; &#8211; for in fact all arguments against
                    attempting to spread the Gospel have their root in unbelief, or in indifference. It is our interest, because every native
                    Christian has a common interest with the British Government, &amp; <del>xx</del> becomes a faithful subject to it, <del>&amp; xxxx
                        xx</del> Native Churches therefore are the strongest forts which we can erect.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <del>foundation</del> &lt;work&gt; has been <del>laid</del> &lt;begun&gt; at Serampore. Carey is our Xavier,
                    &amp; his work will last longer than that of <del>this</del> &lt;the&gt; great Jesuit, because it is built upon a surer
                        foundation.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Carey (1761&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), orientalist and
                        missionary. A co-founder with his fellow Baptists Joshua Marshman (1768&#8211;1837) and William Ward (1769&#8211;1823), of the mission at
                        Serampore and later of Serampore College (1818). Southey&#8217;s comparison is with St Francis Xavier (1506&#8211;1552), the Jesuit
                        missionary.</note> But tho without Missionaries Government could do nothing, I fear that our Missionaries without Government
                    cannot do much; for while the English in India pay no regard to their own religion, the natives will necessarily despise it. A
                    Church Establishment is the first thing needful, &#8211; schools the second in which we should take as much pains for <del>teaching
                        xxxxxxx</del> &lt;communicating&gt; our own language &#8211; as are (most properly) bestowed in acquiring those of the country.
                    Lastly the converts, wherever it is possible, should be employed both by the State &amp; by individuals, in preference to other
                    persons. It matters little in a political view for what motives the father may be baptized; &#8211; tho it be for the grossest
                    self-interest, your work is done if you get his children to school &amp; to church.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Hasty as this letter is I must not conclude without saying how much it gratifies me to know that <ref target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Mr Wilberforce</ref> has been pleased with any thing which I may have written. &#8211;
                    Hitherto I have had much to learn, &#8211; much also to unlearn, <del>&amp; xxxx greatly xxxxx xxx deficit as a man xxxx can</del> &amp;
                    at this moment my deficiencies appear far greater to me than they can possibly do to my worst enemies, &#8211; for they can only compare
                    me with themselves, while I measure the thing I am by the standard of that which I ought to be. Should it please God to continue
                    to me the blessings &amp; faculties which I now enjoy, I have great plans to execute, &amp; good hope that I shall leave behind me
                    works which may be useful to posterity, &amp; worthy of remembrance. But the work is <del>xxxxxx</del> long &amp; the day is
                    shortening before me. I have a deep &amp; ever-present sense of the uncertainty &lt;of&gt; life, &amp; that feeling becomes almost
                    painful when I consider what there is yet for me to do.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is my pride to reckon among my friends, two of the greatest benefactors of the human race, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Bell</ref>. Henceforth I shall count <del>it</del> among the honours which have fallen to my lot that <del>I may</del> of
                    addressing <ref target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wilberforce</ref>, &amp; subscribing myself </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> with the greatest esteem &amp; respect</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> his faithful servant</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>