<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2192</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3463</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                  1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                  only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                  redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                        Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                  that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                  additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                  all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927. Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
               (London, 1856), II, pp. 311&#8211;314.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript
               Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
               Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University
               Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
               Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University; the John Rylands Library,
               Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
               Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public
               Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
               Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne;
               the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the English Department of
               Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2192" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey&#8217;s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2192" type="letter">
        <head>2192. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1812-12-24">24 December
                  1812</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey. R. N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helens/
                  Auckland <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927. ALS; 4p.<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter
                  (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 311&#8211;314.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-12-24">Dec. 24. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I think R.B.s name was Robert Burton, &#8211; he is however a very well known personage among our Bibliographers, &#8211; a Grub
               Street compiler who about 1680 used to make little close printed volumes for country readers, at one shilling each, with vile wooden
               cuts, &#8211; some of which books are now just reprinted in guinea quartos with fac-similes of these disfigurements as they may
                  <del>xxx</del> fitly be called.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Robert Burton&#8217; and &#8216;R.B&#8217; were pseudonyms used by the
                  bookseller and writer Nathaniel Crouch (c. 1640&#8211;1725?; <title>DNB</title>). They were chosen in reference to Robert Burton
                  (1577&#8211;1640; <title>DNB</title>), author of the <title>Anatomy of Melancholy</title> (1620), which incorporated hundreds of
                  translations from Latin and Greek sources, thus making classical knowledge more widely available to the less privileged classes.
                  Crouch was equally keen to democratise learning, producing simplified versions of more learned works and histories and publishing
                  these cheaply, thus ensuring a wide circulation.</note> The book which I have quoted could not help having some curious things in
               it, from its subject, &amp; is in fact often quoted without any farther suspicion of its fidelity than attaches to all works written in
               an age of physical credulity.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had quoted an anecdote from &#8216;R.B.&#8217;s&#8217; <title>Admirable
                     Curiosities</title> (1718), in <title>Omniana, or Horae Otiosiores</title>, 2 vols (London, 1812), I, pp. 193&#8211;194. This described
                  how a &#8216;Upon Midsummer Even, 1626, a codfish was brought to the market in Cambridge&#8217;, when it was cut open it was found to contain
                  several treatises by the evangelical theologian and martyr John Frith (1503&#8211;1533; <title>DNB</title>).</note> He is I believe just
               as good authority for the price of a ram, as a magazine or newspaper would be, &amp; the fact is certainly a curious one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorGeorge">Mr Taylor</ref> for his notes. &#8211; My Omniania are likely to be
               enriched in this way. I know the vulgar error of flesh-worms in the face, but never heard it of the hands, nor ever saw any thing in
               the hands which could be mistaken for them, &amp; this was what puzzled me.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had
                  included a substantial section on worms in <title>Omniana, or Horae Otiosiores</title>, 2 vols (London, 1812), I, pp. 245&#8211;248.
                  Taylor had presumably sent some information to supplement this. A second edition of <title>Omniana</title> was not published.</note>
               Thank him also for the portrait. I believe Henry Mores Poems were never printed with his works. He was a most very-odd fellow. The
               rarest believer in all ghosts goblins &amp; vampires! but I have not done full justice to him as a poet, strange &amp; sometimes
               unreadably uncouth as he is, there are lines &amp; passages of the highest feeling &amp; most exquisite beauty <del>in his</del>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The philosopher, poet and theologian, Henry More (1614&#8211;1687; <title>DNB</title>). Southey
                  possessed a copy of his <title>Philosophicall Poems</title> (1647), no. 1998 in the sale catalogue of his library. An account of
                  More&#8217;s &#8216;Platonick Song of the Soul&#8217; appeared in <title>Omniana, or Horae Otiosiores</title>, 2 vols (London, 1812), II, pp. 155&#8211;177.
                  Taylor had sent Southey a copy of a portrait of More.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All day I have &lt;been&gt; working to get into action at Copenhagen,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. to
                  write the account of the battle of Copenhagen, 2 April 1801, for the <title>Life of Nelson</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813). For the
                  build up to the battle, the engagement and its aftermath, see Ibid., II, pp. 95&#8211;153.</note> &amp; I would give one of my ears for
               your help. Brierleys Chart<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A chart made by Alexander Bryerly (dates unknown), Master of HMS <hi rend="ital">Bellona</hi> at Copenhagen, see <title>The Life of Nelson</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813), II, p. 117.</note> stands
               me in good stead; &amp; I have ransacked all my books to get the scene well before my eyes. Do send me as soon as you possibly
               &lt;can&gt; a letter of recollections upon this subject, things worthy of note before the battle, in &amp; after it &amp;c &#8211; How came
               your guns in the Bellona to be in such a state?<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom had served in HMS <hi rend="ital">Bellona</hi> at Copenhagen. Seventy-five of his fellow crew had been killed when their elderly cannon burst, see <title>The Life
                     of Nelson</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813), II, p. 126.</note> Did you not tell me that the spires at Copenhagen have a sort of
               spiral staircase outside? or something of the kind. &#8211; Tell me also the particulars about the man who shot Nelson<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Frenchman who shot Horatio Nelson, 1st Viscount Nelson (1758&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>) during the
                  battle of Trafalgar. For Southey&#8217;s account of Nelson&#8217;s fatal wound see<title>, The Life of Nelson</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813),
                  II, pp. 257&#8211;258.</note> &amp; whom Collingwood<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Southey&#8217;s account the French sniper was in
                  turn shot dead by two midshipmen in HMS <hi rend="ital">Victory</hi>, Francis Edward Collingwood (1785&#8211;1836) and John Pollard (d.
                  1868). See <title>The Life of Nelson</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813), II, pp. 264&#8211;265.</note> &amp; somebody else whose name I cannot
               remember shot at the same time. &#8211; Nelson&#8217;s are all good battles, for relation, which is not often the case with battles. For that of
               Copenhagen there is luckily <ref type="m" target="people.html#FeldborgAndreas">a Dane&#8217;s</ref> account to help me, written in English;
               it supplies me with a few fine circumstances not to be found elsewhere.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andreas Andersen
                  Feldborg, <title>A Tour in Zealand, the Year 1802; with an Historical Sketch of the Battle of Copenhagen</title> (1805).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will write to &#8220;Sister Anne&#8221;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Sister Anne&#8217; was presumably an acquaintance who
                  had converted to Catholicism. She might have been one of Tom Southey&#8217;s sisters-in-law.</note> as soon as I can satisfy myself what
               to say. Where I called in upon such a case to any person of sound reasoning faculties, accustomed to habits of investigation &amp;
               willing to enter into a full discussion of the subject I should expect to be succesful. But with many persons, &amp; especially with
               women, falling into a new religion is not unlike falling in love. Something strikes their fancy &amp; it is in vain to think to reason
               them out of it: they see things in parts &amp; cannot be made to comprehend the whole of a subject. Sis A must not look for any good
               from my interference. I could be of use to her in such a case, for the very reason which will prevent her from &lt;ever&gt; being under
               a like delusion. Her sister will show my letter to her Catholic friends, &amp; the family Priest will then come with his sophisms,
                  <del>which to</del> the regular moves by which these practioners at the game give scholars mate to the <del>xxx</del> unlearned
               &amp; unwary. A conversion of this kind is certainly a great family evil; the convert <del>xx</del> being persuaded that she shall lose
               sight of all her relations in the next world, gets weaned from them in this, &amp; they indeed on their part are bound in prudence to
               get as little as possible <del>within</del> in the way of an intellectual malady which is contagious. No child of mine should ever
               visit a Catholic family. You may go to Heaven that way certainly, &#8211; but there is no more reason for doing it, than there would be for
               going to London in a dung cart, when there are so many easier, cleanlier &amp; surer conveyances. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is in the Appendix to the first vol. of Clarkes Travels Suvarrof&#8217;s (Suwarrow) instructions to his soldiers, a
               most characteristic &amp; extraordinary composition.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Suvarof&#8217;s Catechism&#8217;, in Edward Daniel
                  Clarke (1769&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in Various Countries of Europe, Asia and Africa</title>, 6 vols (London,
                  1810&#8211;1816), I, 701&#8211;710, no. 601 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Alexander Vasilyevich Suwarrow (1729&#8211;1800) was a Russian
                  general, famed for his leadership and military skills.</note> Just now it is peculiarly interesting, for you may be sure it will
               long continue to be manual of the Russian army. &#8211; We may look for a good military history of this war from Sir R. Wilson, who I hope to
               Heaven will be in at the death.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The army officer Sir Robert Wilson (1777&#8211;1849;
                     <title>DNB</title>). He had travelled to Russia earlier in 1812 and was a first-hand witness of the campaign against the French
                  invaders.</note> The destruction of Moscow<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Moscow was destroyed by fire 14&#8211;18 September
                  1812, just as French troops entered the city.</note> with all its consequences is one of the grandest events that have ever taken
               place: great sacrifices have heretofore been made by communities as well as individuals, but never any with such great effects; the
               wisdom, &#8211; the <del>xxx</del> worldly wisdom &#8211; of this act, was equal to its heroism, &amp; its effect is the certain deliverance of
               Russia, &#8211; the probable deliverance of Europe.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The march of Augereaus corps<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The troops protecting the French retreat,
                  commanded by Marshal Charles Pierre Francois Augereau, 1st Duc de Castiglione (1757&#8211;1816).</note> shows <del>xx</del> clearly that
               Buonaparte intends to quarter himself about Kalonga &amp; Toola in the fertile provinces, &amp; Kutousoff<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Marshal Mikhail Kutusov (1745&#8211;1813), the commander of Russian forces fighting the French.</note> seems to have
               divined all his plans. This man has shown himself a great general, &amp; as for Platoff,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  Matvei Ivanovitch Platov (1757&#8211;1818), Ataman (Commander) of the Don Cossacks. He became a Count of the Russian Empire as a reward
                  for harrying the French forces on their retreat from Moscow in late 1812.</note> I hope to see his head as common upon sign-posts as
               ever Prince Eugene has been or the Marquis of Granbys.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Eugene of Savoy (1663&#8211;1736), one
                  of the allied generals in the War of the Spanish Succession (1701&#8211;1713) and John Manners, Marquis of Granby (1721&#8211;1770;
                     <title>DNB</title>), British soldier in the Seven Years&#8217; War (1756&#8211;1763). Both were popular figures on British inn signs. In
                  Granby&#8217;s case, this owed much to the assistance he gave disabled non-commissioned officers to establish themselves as
                  innkeepers.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Roderick<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> is in a good way, <del>&amp; when</del> &lt;as&gt; the mornings begin
               to lengthen I shall get rapidly on with the latter half.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>