<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2471</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3742</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales,
                        MS 4812D.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 372&#8211;374 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2471" type="letter">
        <head>2471. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin
                    Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1814-08-19">19 August 1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [readdressed in another hand] To/ C W
                        Williams Wynn Esqr M.P./ <del>Llangedwin</del>/ <del>Oswestry</del>
                        &lt;Acton&gt;<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Library of Wales,
                        MS 4812D<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 372&#8211;374 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-08-19">19 August. 1814.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know there prevails an unlucky opinion in the world
                    respecting Wales, that it never produced a man of genius; as if nature having
                    bestowed great care in bringing the mutton of the principality to perfection,
                    left the men thereof in a very unfinished state. I have more than once been
                    driven to a nonplus in opposing this wicked opinion, not having been able to
                    produce any greater men than Sir Henry Morgan the Buccaneer,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The privateer and colonial governor Sir
                        Henry Morgan (c. 1635&#8211;1688; <title>DNB</title>), son of Robert Morgan of
                        Llanryhmny, Glamorgan.</note> &amp; his namesake the great heresiarch
                        Pelagius.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The theologian Pelagius
                        (fl. c. 390&#8211;418; <title>DNB</title>), whose teachings on free will and
                        original sin were condemned as heretical. He was reputed to have been of
                        British origin. It was also claimed that his name was a Hellenization of the
                        common Welsh name &#8216;Morgan&#8217;.</note> &#8211; your friends the Catholicks however
                    hold that miracles have not ceased in Wales, &amp; S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        Winifred<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> St Winefride (7th
                        century), Welsh princess and saint, who is commemorated in a pilgrimage site
                        at Holywell, Flintshire.</note> is at this time in full odour. But if a man
                    of genius should peradventure be found there, look you M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                    Charles Williams, <del>I shall have xxxxx who do xxxx xxx xxxxx S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Winifred</del> &lt;<del>peradventure</del> it may be a miracle,
                    I dare not deny that;&gt; but as a good Protestant &amp; a staunch No Popery Man
                    I defy D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Milner<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        John Milner (1752&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), leading English Catholic and
                        Vicar-Apostolic of the Midlands region 1803&#8211;1826. He was the author of
                            <title>Authentic Documents relative to the miraculous cure of Winifred
                            White, of Wolverhampton, at St Winifred&#8217;s Well, alias Holywell, in
                            Flintshire, on the 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June 1805</title>
                        (1806).</note> to prove that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Winifred has any thing
                    to do with it. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As you may well suppose I receive plenty of letters from poets
                    aspirant, &#8211; more especially since my promotion to a dignity, which they seem to
                    regard as curates do the archiepiscopal see of Canterbury. This evening however
                    I have had a letter which is very <del>x</del> remarkable for its good sense,
                    &amp; &lt;- more remarkable still, -&gt; this letter is from <ref target="people.html#EvansGreeton">a Welsh herdsman in the Vale of
                        Clwyd</ref>. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> He tells me that his father died when he was seven years of age,
                    leaving him nothing to depend upon but a knowledge of reading writing &amp; the
                    principles of <del>arithmetic</del> &lt;grammar&gt;, which must needs have been
                    little enough. That for nine years &amp; a half he has tended the herds of a
                    farmer between Ruthin &amp; Denbigh. That thro the indulgence of a neighbouring
                    gentleman (whom he has not named) he possesses many advantages, &amp; he
                    requests permission to send me specimens of his compositions in prose &amp;
                    verse that I may advise him whether to submit them to public notice or let them
                    rest in oblivion. The most remarkable part of the letter is that he <del>says he
                        is</del> seems to be perfectly contented. He says that his situation is
                    comfortable, that he has no wish to change it, &amp; that his highest ambition
                    is the acquaintance of learned men. Whether he will prove poet or not remains to
                    be seen, &#8211; but he is certainly an extraordinary man, &amp; seems to possess that
                    wisdom which is more rare &amp; far more valuable than any brilliancy of
                    talents.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>I have</del> He sent his letter by an acquaintance to Manchester &amp;
                    requested an answer thro the same channel, but I am apprehensive from
                        <del>xx</del> the date &amp; the time allotted for his friends stay there
                    that that answer<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to
                        Greeton Evans, 19 August 1814, Letter 2470.</note> may arrive too late,
                    &amp; lie in the Manchester Post Office. So I write a second reply,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Greeton Evans, 20 August
                        1814, Letter 2472.</note> in the hope that you may direct it so as to find
                    him. And I have told him to direct his specimens under cover to you, giving him
                    a proper caution as to the weight. <ref target="people.html#EvansGreeton">Greeton Evans</ref> is his name, &amp; he dates from Llynn Aledd &lt;(which
                    is between Ruthin &amp; Denbigh, he says &#8211; you perhaps will know to which post
                    town it had better be addrest.)&gt; &#8211; Would it not have surprized you to
                        <del>find have</del> found a herdsman reading Madoc<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s Welsh-American epic <title>Madoc</title>
                        (1805).</note> in the vale of Clwyd? &#8211; I send my letter unsealed, that you
                    may see in what manner I have answered him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Should his writings possess any merit of their own, his lot may
                    be bettered by them, without changing it. And whatever their merit may be there
                    is something so happy in the mans state of mind that whenever I set foot in
                    Wales again I will find him out. If he proves to be a Welsh <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldRobert">Bloomfield</ref> I bespeak you
                    for his patron. His letter is so well &#8211; I might say so beautifully written that
                    it is the admiration of every person to whom I have as yet shown it. If he
                    writes under cover to you, open the <del>letter</del> inclosure &amp; judge for
                    yourself. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a letter from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> in which he expresses a wish for what has always
                    seemed to me the wisest thing which could be done for him considering his habits
                    &amp; character, &#8211; that an engagement could be procured for him at a respectable
                    theatre.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am about to send off the preface &amp;c of Roderick<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814).</note> to the <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">printer</ref>,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to James Ballantyne, [c.
                        23] August 1814, Letter 2475.</note> another fortnight will compleat the
                    printing. Where shall your copy be sent? &amp; did you receive the Laureates
                    last Odes?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Congratulatory
                            Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness The Prince Regent, His Imperial Majesty
                            The Emperor of Russia, and His Majesty the King of Prussia</title>
                        (1814).</note>
          <del>Xx xxxx xx xx xx</del> Remember that if you do not receive every thing of
                    mine as soon as it appears, <del>xxxx xxx xxx</del> negligence or oversight in
                    the publishers is very possible, &#8211; but there will never be any neglect on my
                    part. How is the eye?</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>