<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2677</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3948</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        30927.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2677" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2677" type="letter">
        <head>2677. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1815-12-07">7 December
                        1815</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey. R. N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helens/ Auckland<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        30927<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1815-12-07">7 Dec. 1815.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here I am at length once more by my own fireside, thank God. I had left <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> when your letter arrived there, &amp; as I was ever on the move between Richmond,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Home of John May.</note>
          <ref target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q Anne Street</ref> &amp; Champion Hill<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Home of the
                        Gonne family.</note> it was some days before it caught me. Let me know how <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref>
                    is, &amp; what will be done with this poor family. This event makes me feel how important it is that every man who has the means
                    of doing it should insure his life, &#8211; how easily might M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Castle in this way have secured a provision for
                        them!<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Castle (d. 1815), Durham solicitor and Tom Southey&#8217;s father-in-law.
                        Southey had taken out an insurance policy on his own life shortly after being appointed Poet Laureate in 1813; see Southey to
                        [John Wilson Croker], 21 October 1813, Letter 2315.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our stay in &amp; about London was much discomforted by the frequent ailments &amp; illness of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>; &amp; on her account we were compelled to give up all our promised
                    visits on the way homeward, &amp; take the straightest road, halting only for half a day at Nottingham. Here however we are: she
                    bore the journey better than <del>xx</del> I had expected, &amp; the return to home habits &amp; mountain air seems <del>xx</del>
                    immediately to have restored her. I find my table covered with letters, &amp; have a world of business to get thro. My first task
                    must be to produce a poem, which is planned much to my liking upon the battle of Belle-Alliance. You may be sure there will be no
                    battle in the poem. Why I call it Belle-Alliance &amp; not Waterloo you shall know when I have more leisure, &#8211; thereby hangs a
                    tale which will not a little surprize you.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816). Southey&#8217;s desire to name it the &#8216;Belle Alliance&#8217; was due to
                        his belief that it was more suited to verse (Southey to John Rickman, [c. 5 July 1815], Letter 2633), and that &#8216;the name of Waterloo was given to the battle by the Duke of Wellington in a spirit of the lowest &amp; vilest jealousy&#8217;
                        (Southey to Thomas Southey, 17 December 1815, Letter 2684).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The young ones are all in high health. We brought back store of play things for them &amp; you never saw a happier
                    household. I have purchased books pretty largely, &#8211; to the amount of about 300 volumes, &#8211; among which are the Acta Sanctorum 52
                        folios,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had purchased a copy of the <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> during his
                        time in Belgium; see Southey to John May, 6 October 1815, Letter 2660. However, this turned out to be a 6 volume edition of
                        1783&#8211;1794, no. 152 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, rather than a complete edition.</note> but of these I have not
                    yet received any account. &#8211; Roderick<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>. First published in 1814.</note> is doing well, &amp; going now to press for a
                    fourth edition. The Morte Arthur so many years ago announced for publication in my name is fallen into my hands at last.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had long hoped to produce an edition of Sir Thomas Malory (1415/18&#8211;1471;
                            <term>DNB</term>), <title>Le Morte d&#8217;Arthur</title> (1485) and even entered into an agreement with Longman. His proposed
                        edition was advertised in 1808; see, for example, <title>The Literary Panorama</title>, 3 (1808), col. 757, and Southey to
                        John Rickman, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Three</title>, [3 January 1808], Letter 1410. At one point,
                        he had ceded the project to Walter Scott; see Southey to Richard Heber, 9 April 1811, Letter 1900.</note> John Louis Goldsmith
                    who undertook it for <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has run away with another man&#8217;s wife, leaving his
                        own;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Louis Goldsmid (1789&#8211;1835). Goldsmid had left his wife, Louisa Boscawan
                        (1782&#8211;1862), whom he had married in 1809. Goldsmid&#8217;s library was sold at auction on 11&#8211;15 December 1815, perhaps indicating
                        financial woes; see <title>A Catalogue of the Curious and Valuable Library of John Louis Goldsmid Esq. Containing a Most Rare
                            Assemblage of Romances of Chivalry, Both Printed and Manuscript, Scarce Old Novels, and Facetiae, and Curious Books in
                            Various Departments of Literature</title> (1815). This included numerous examples of Arthuriana.</note> &#8211; the subscription
                    was full,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Longman had advertised and published a subscriptions list to Goldsmid&#8217;s edition
                        of the <title>Morte d&#8217;Arthur</title>, complete with &#8216;an INTRODUCTION and NOTES, tending to elucidate the HISTORY and
                        BIBLIOGRAPHY of the Work; as well as the FICTIONS OF THE ROUND TABLE CHIVALRY in general&#8217;, in a flyer at the back of
                            <title>Biblitheca Anglo-Poetica; or, A Descriptive Catalogue of a Rare and Rich Collection of Early English Poetry: In the
                            Possession of Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, and Brown</title> (1815). Southey was listed amongst the subscribers.</note> &#8211;
                    &amp; I shall be well paid for writing an introduction, &#8211; much to the advantage of the book.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>The Birth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur</title> was published in 1817.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I saw few strangers in town, &#8211; never so few on any former visit; &#8211; for I confined myself as much as possible to my
                    friends. The last day of my residence there I dined in company with Mina, &#8211; this was an important introduction which I
                        sought.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Either Francisco Javier de Mina (1789&#8211;1817), guerrilla leader in Navarre
                        1808&#8211;1810; or his uncle, General Espoz de Mina (1781&#8211;1836). Both had fled Spain after a failed rising in Pamplona on 25&#8211;26
                        September 1814.</note> I liked him much, &#8211; he will give me a sketch of his Life. But the principles &amp; language of the
                    Spanish refugees are the best justification of Ferdinand.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833; King
                        of Spain 1808, 1813&#8211;1833). In 1814 he had abolished the liberal Constitution of 1812, arrested the leading liberals and
                        restored the Inquisition.</note> They are, as I supposed them to be, thorough Jacobines &amp; thorough Atheists. They complain
                    of being treated with cruelty, &amp; declare that if they get the upper hand they will put all their enemies to death. This is
                    easily accounted for: &#8211; it is the natural effect of such a government &amp; such a religion; &#8211; but were I a Spaniard I should
                    rather hold with Ferdinand than with such reformers. My history<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History
                            of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> of course will offend all parties by fairly exposing the faults of all,
                    &amp; extenuating them by showing how the errors on one side produce those on the other. &#8211; I have seen <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref>; he is a man perfectly capable of appreciating the service which I shall do
                    him; &amp; I doubt not that he considers it as the <del>mor</del> happiest circumstance which could have befallen him, that I
                    should write the history of transactions in which he has been so deeply involved. He gave me much information, which in almost
                    every point confirmed the judgement that I had previously formed.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frere had been Minister
                        Plenipotentiary to the Central Junta in 1808&#8211;1809 and advised Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>) to advance on
                        Madrid, or, if necessary, to retreat through Galicia rather than Portugal&#8211; advice that led to the disastrous retreat to
                        Corunna. Southey had defended Frere in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 86&#8211;108.</note> I shall
                    have all the documents with which he can furnish me. Indeed I believe no history was ever undertaken with such advantages of this
                    kind. It will go to press as soon as the Brazil is finished, &#8211; &amp; of this 320 pages are printed.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The final two volumes of <title>The History of Brazil</title> appeared in 1817 and 1819
                    respectively.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is a hasty letter &#8211; My poem<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> will be in six-lined stanzas I think of taking the first 11
                    stanzas of the Proem for the intended Marriage, &amp; continuing them for the introduction.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1814 Southey, as Poet Laureate, had started a poem celebrating the forthcoming marriage of the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince Regent&#8217;s</ref> only child Charlotte Augusta (1796&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>)
                        to the Hereditary Prince of Orange, William (1792&#8211;1849; King of the Netherlands 1840&#8211;1849). The poem had not been published
                        because the royal engagement was broken off in June 1814. Southey did not use the first 11 stanzas in <title>The Poet&#8217;s
                            Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title>, instead he reworked the 1814 poem into <title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen
                            Nuptiale</title> (1816) to celebrate Charlotte&#8217;s marriage to Leopold of Saxe-Coburg (1790&#8211;1865;
                        <title>DNB</title>).</note> The strain will be in a high moral tone. I shall give notes from my journal<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The journal Southey had kept during his recent travels; published as <title>Journal of a Tour in
                            the Netherlands in the Autumn of 1815</title> (1902).</note> &amp; some prints, for which <ref target="people.html#NashEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nash</ref> an artist in our company made the sketches.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Engravings of eight of Edward Nash&#8217;s sketches were included in <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to
                            Waterloo</title> (1816).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Give our love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> &amp; let me hear how you are going on. Love also to
                        the young ones.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom and Sarah Southey&#8217;s children.</note>
          </salute>
          <salute rend="indent4"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> In the way of business, let me know the <hi rend="ital">weight</hi> of the cheese for the mice eat half by the
                        way, &amp; I am at war with the carrier to recover damages.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>