<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2223</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3494</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                    47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2223" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2223" type="letter">
        <head>2223. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1813-02-22">22 February
                        1813</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Bristol<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: 1813/ Feb 22<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS
                    47890<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-02-22">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 22. 1813</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The draft is safely arrived.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> About the time that your letter from Easton Grey arrived &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">G. Fricker</ref>
                    broke a blood vessel, &#8211; a thing so bad in itself could never have occurred under more favourable circumstances.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 3 February 1813, Letter 2218.</note> We were just about to
                    set out for Lodore, &#8211; &amp; think what a situation we should have been in had it happened there or on the way. The h&#230;morrhage was
                    not very great, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmondson</ref> found it necessary to bleed him that day &amp; again the
                    next. At present he has pretty well recovered his lost strength &amp; is not in worse state than <del>before</del> he was before
                    it happened. He had been using no kind of exertion. A very slight cough preceded the h&#230;morrhage, <del>xx</del> &lt;but&gt; was not
                    the cause of it, being apparently occasioned by the effusion of blood into the lungs. I never saw any man behave better than he
                    did; &#8211; but what a frightful thing it is for any one to witness who is not accustomed to such sights.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>Xx</del> If you should hear of any situation which may suit him let us know &#8211; This <del>xx</del> is of course all that can be
                    done. He looks either to London or Bristol &amp; says that he would rather be out of employment looking for a situation in the
                    latter place than in the former. Perhaps it may be possible to find temporary employ for him in London by &amp; by, while he looks
                    about for something more permanent. But (between ourselves <del>x</del> for I do not say this to his sisters<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note>) this is looking on I fear something
                        <del>xxxxxx</del> too far. Some internal disease he has &#8211; whether of liver of where else Heaven knows, &#8211; &amp; there seems to
                    me fresh reason to apprehend that he is consumptive also. At any rate he will remain here three or four months &#8211; till he has
                    enjoyed the country a little in a fairer season, &#8211; &amp; this he may very well do, for the danger &lt;does&gt; not <del>not</del>
                    appear to be close at hand, &amp; I think he has no suspicion of it, <del>xxx</del> he seems to have all the feelings, but none of
                    the fears of a valetudinarian.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am glad to hear so well of <ref target="people.html#JardineDavid">David</ref>. If his income
                    were twice what it is, or if the Socinians did not like all the dissenters, starve their own <del>xxxxxxx</del> I should wish to
                    hear that he followed his fathers way of life. But a ministers stipend would add little to his means, &amp; tho it is very
                    possible that he might marry a woman with some fortune, this is not to be calculated upon. It is as easy to get a wife with money
                    as without it &#8211; but as more women are fortuneless than otherwise, the probability always is that a man who consults only his heart
                    will not enrich himself by marriage. In law or physic he may start with the great advantage of having enough to support him
                    respectably till he gets into practice, the law has the most &amp; the highest prizes, &amp; what is of more importance will leave
                    him most leisure.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will receive Nelson<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> in about a month, &#8211; there are five or six sheets still to be printed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am as much pleased with the manner in which Granville Sharp<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The author
                        and abolitionist Granville Sharp (1735&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), who in 1813 became the first chairman of the Protestant
                        Union, a body formed to oppose Catholic emancipation. His <title>Address, Resolutions and Questions to the English Roman
                            Catholics</title> (1813) was based on a speech he gave to a meeting of the Union on 22 January 1813.</note> has come
                    forward upon the Catholic question, as you were with Lansdowne in Wiltshire.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry
                        Petty-Fitzmaurice, 3rd Marquis of Lansdowne (1780&#8211;1863; <title>DNB</title>), Chancellor of the Exchequer 1806&#8211;1807, Home
                        Secretary 1827&#8211;1828, Lord President of the Council, 1830&#8211;1834, 1835&#8211;1841, 1846&#8211;1852, had been a prominent speaker at a meeting
                        in favour of Catholic Emancipation. The proceedings were printed as <title>Wiltshire Meeting on the Roman Catholic Claims;
                            held at Devizes, Jan. 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 1813</title> (1813).</note> The advocates for that question must maintain
                    one of two positions, either that no opinions can properly disqualify a man in this country for legislative power; &#8211; or if he
                    shrink from that palpable absurdity &#8211; that the opinion of the Catholics are not <del>xxxx xxx xxx</del> disqualifying ones. The
                    latter position is refuted by Granville Sharp.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What <del>xxx</del> a mischievous &amp; foolish thing is this letter of the Princess of <del>xxx</del> Wales!<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Caroline of Brunswick-Wolfenb&#252;ttel (1768&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>) the estranged wife of
                        the Prince Regent. On 14 January 1813 she had written to her husband protesting about the restrictions placed on her access to
                        their daughter, Princess Charlotte Augusta (1796&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>). In early March a second letter on the same subject
                        was sent to the Speaker of the House of Commons. As it was unsigned its authorship was initially questioned, though it was
                        later attributed to Caroline. After debate, parliament agreed that it was the Regent&#8217;s right as a father and ruler to be in
                        charge of his daughter&#8217;s education; see <title>Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine</title>, 83 (April 1813), 361, 363&#8211;364, 373&#8211;376.</note>
                    From the letter itself because of its extreme rashness, &#8211; its savour of a lawyers profession &amp; a practised pen, &#8211; its extreme
                    mischievousness, &amp; <del>the</del> &lt;its&gt; impudent hypocrisy, (if that can be called hypocrisy which <del>xxxx
                        bareface</del> lies with a bare face, knowing that you know it to be a liar &#8211; from all this circumstance I suspected <ref target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> to be the author, before I saw it asserted that he was so in the
                        newspapers.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Brougham, had been Caroline&#8217;s legal adviser since 1812 and had, indeed,
                        written her letter.</note> It <del>has an</del> &lt;bears&gt; every mark of him, &#8211; for he is as remarkable for want of
                    prudence, as for the want of other more effectual virtues.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I start for the south, if nothing unforeseen should prevent, as soon as the Register<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813).</note> is done, which may be by the end of April. But I shall
                        <del>xxx</del> &lt;hardly&gt; see Bristol, unless summoned to Taunton. I wish we could expect you this summer. The young ones
                    often ask when you will come again &#8211; even <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> has not forgotten you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tell <ref target="people.html#KingMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> King</ref> that we see a great deal of <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLord">Lord Sunderlins</ref> family &amp; like them so well that we shall much regret their loss,
                    whenever they leave us. Lord &amp; <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLady">Lady S.</ref> are now in London, leaving <ref target="people.html#MaloneCatherine">Miss C. Malone</ref> alone with her suffering sister.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henrietta Malone (c. 1745&#8211;1824).</note> But <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLady">Lady S.</ref> has a sister
                    of her own<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> dying of dropsy whom she is gone to see for the last
                    time. There is a mournful prospect before this family: <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLord">Lord S.</ref> is in that state of
                    age &amp; debility that the first influenza will carry him off. The eldest sister <del>xx xxx</del> an incurable cripple
                        <del>xx</del> in constant pain; &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLady">Lady S.</ref> &amp; the other sister both advanced
                    in life, looking for the death of these persons (never did I see a family more affectionately attached to each other) &#8211; &amp;
                    having none to supply their loss. &#8211; The <del>xxx</del> misfortune of all the branches of a family being childless was never more
                        <del>xxxxxxxxx</del> evinced.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>