<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1986</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3257</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4868 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 346&#8211;349.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1986" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1986" type="letter">
        <head>1986. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1811-11-20">20 November
                        1811</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Norwich<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 10
                        Dec<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4868 <lb />Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 346&#8211;349.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1811-11-20">Nov. 20. 1811.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Whichever of us may have last written to the other, there is a long chasm in our never-very-frequent
                    correspondence, for which, I, for one, take my full share of shame, &amp; hereby offer atonement. &#8211; Your last letter told me that
                    you had not received Kehama;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810); Taylor to Southey, 2 February 1811, J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 343&#8211;346 (344).</note>
                    since that time I trust that it has reached you, because by my account with the publishers it appears to have been sent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Among the new acquaintance whom I made in London was <ref target="people.html#ButlerCharles">Butler</ref> the
                    Catholick whom you know. A man of singularly gentle mind &amp; manners, but neither in intellect nor in knowledge answerable to
                        <del>the</del> his reputation, nor to the opinion which I had been led to form of him. Upon some parts of the history of his
                    own church, on which I expected to acquire information from him, I was disappointed to discover how much less he knew than I did
                    myself. I dined with him, enjoyed his claret, coveted some of his books, &amp; came away believing him to be a thoroughly amiable
                    man, &amp; apparently a very happy one. &#8211; He gave me his life of Fenelon,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Butler&#8217;s
                            <title>Life of Fenelon: Archbishop of Cambray</title> (1810). This was a biography of Francois de Salignac de la
                        Mothe-Fenelon (1651&#8211;1715), a French Archbishop and theologian who had defended Quietism &#8211; the doctrine that the soul can be
                        absorbed in the divine by withdrawing from worldly interests and passively contemplating God. Quietism had been definitively
                        condemned as heretical by the bull <title>Coelestis Pastor</title> of 1687, hence Butler&#8217;s nervousness about expressing his
                        views on the matter.</note> &amp; the note upon Quietism which he has smuggled into private circulation. What must his opinion
                    be of his own church when he could feel it necessary, or at least prudent, <del>t</del> not to appear publicly as the author of
                        <del>such</del> any thing so harmless! He also made me read his uncle Alban Butler&#8217;s account of the Stigmata of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Francis;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alban Butler (1709&#8211;1773; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Lives
                            of the Fathers, Martyrs and other Saints</title> (1759), section on &#8216;St Francis of Assisium&#8217;, 4 October, told how in 1224
                        stigmata appeared on the saint&#8217;s body: &#8216;the marks of the nails began to appear in his hands and feet, resembling those he had
                        seen in the vision of the man crucified. His hands and feet seemed bored through in the middle with four wounds, and these
                        holes appeared to be pierced with nails of hard flesh; the heads were round and black, and were seen in the palms of his
                        hands, and in his feet on the upper part of the instep. The points were long, and appeared beyond the skin on the other side,
                        and were turned back as if clenched with a hammer. There was also in his right side a red wound, like one made by the piercing
                        of a lance; out of which there often issued blood, so as to stain the saint&#8217;s tunic and drawers &#8230; there miraculous wounds were
                        seen by several during the two years which he survived &#8230; and by great multitudes after his death; and the proofs of the fact
                        are incontestable&#8217;.</note> &#8211; a point upon which any Catholick may be crucified in argument. His favourite dream is of a
                    reunion of the Church. Two things I conceive must precede this measure, &#8211; S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pierres perpetual <del>xxxx
                        perpetual</del> peace,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> An idea for establishing peace over a defined area (ideally the
                        whole world) propagated by the French writer and radical Charles-Ir&#233;n&#233;e Castel, Abb&#233; de Saint-Pierre (1658&#8211;1743).</note> &#8211;
                    &amp; a universal language.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The much touted, and equally much ridiculed, idea for a
                        language spoken by all.</note> The perpetual peace I do not believe to be unattainable, &#8211; the others hardly seem desirable
                    &amp; may fairly be <del>xxx</del> supposed impossible. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your life of Fransham<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Memoir of the Life of the late John Fransham, the
                        Norwich Polytheist&#8217;, <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 31 (May 1811), 342&#8211;348. Fransham (bap. 1730, d. 1810;
                        <title>DNB</title>) was a scholar and teacher with a reputation for eccentricity. Southey, who had a marked taste for the
                        eccentric, undoubtedly enjoyed the anecdotes about Fransham&#8217;s unusual dress, taste in food, conduct and beliefs. The latter
                        included a fear of being buried alive: &#8216;he repeatedly desired, that his body should be laid before a fire, that wine should be
                        offered to his lip, and that the arm of a woman clasped about his neck, before he was given up as irrecoverable&#8217; (348).</note>
                    amused &amp; interested me much, &#8211; yet in most points I held with your opponent.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Taylor&#8217;s
                        portrayal of Fransham&#8217;s views on religion had been critiqued by &#8216;Christianus&#8217; in &#8216;Remarks on the Biographer of Fransham&#8217;s
                        Assertions respecting the Advantages of Infidelity&#8217;, <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 31 (July 1811), 518&#8211;519: &#8216;Had he
                        impartially examined the New Testament &#8230; he could not have considered Christianity and cruelty as synonimous terms&#8217; (519).
                        Taylor&#8217;s reply, &#8216;Biographer of Fransham, in reply to Christianus&#8217;, <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 32 (September 1811),
                        117&#8211;119, set out his principles for &#8216;biographic writing&#8217;: &#8216;By whatever opinions a given individual was influenced, from the
                        point of view which those opinions indicate, his conduct should be surveyed. The biographer ought to climb upon the same
                        standing, and to take the same regard of men and things and thoughts, which the departed spirit took&#8217; (117). Christianus
                        replied in <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 32 (December 1811), 452&#8211;453, pushing home his point that Taylor&#8217;s &#8216;Life&#8217; was &#8216;an
                        attack upon Christianity&#8217; (452) and refuting his charge of &#8216;the want of moral courage in Christians&#8217; (453).</note> Nor do I by
                    any means assent to those principles of biography which you lay down in your defence. My way as a biographer is to account for the
                    actions of men by their own principles, &amp; represent them as the persons represented themselves to themselves, &#8211; but in judging
                    them to stand aloof, &amp; measure the action by my own rule of right.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you have seen my Register for 1809 you will have seen that the <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdettites</ref> have cured me of all wish for Parliamentary Reform, at least for any reform of their making, or after their
                        fashion.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 282&#8211;294. This described would-be reformers as anti-patriotic
                        for distracting government attention from the pressing need at hand &#8216;to abate the power of France&#8217; and argued for would-be
                        reformers to bring forward &#8216;practicable plans&#8217; which the ministry could cooperate with: &#8216;the poor laws and the penal laws
                        require revision, and means are still desired to prevent the necessity of pressing for the navy&#8217; (293).</note> I am thinking
                    of an Essay in the Quarterly upon the means of bettering the condition of Society, which will be a set off of the Reformers
                        <del>x</del> versus the Refor<hi rend="ital">mists</hi>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first of a series of
                        Southeyan articles on the poor appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356. It was republished
                        in an expanded, retitled form as &#8216;On the State of the Poor, the Principle of Mr. Malthus&#8217; Essay on Population, and the
                        Manufacturing System&#8217; in Southey&#8217;s <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title>, 2 vols (London, 1832), I, pp. 75&#8211;155.</note> In
                    the last number I had an article upon the New System of Education, from which all the stings were drawn before it went to the
                    Press. I am enlarging it for seperate publication, with an epistle dedicatory to <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">the
                        Editor</ref> of the Edinburgh Review.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s defence of <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">Andrew Bell&#8217;s</ref> educational system over <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Joseph Lancaster&#8217;s</ref>, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (August 1811), 264&#8211;304. This formed the basis of his
                            <title>The Origin, Nature, and Object, of the New System of Education</title> (1812). The latter was not dedicated to
                        Jeffrey, though it contained many swipes at him and Brougham.</note> It will convict that Review of gross &amp; wilful
                    falsehood. <ref target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> it seems is the man whom the Lord hath thus delivered into
                    my hands, &amp; the Devil shall not deliver him out of them.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>The Origin,
                            Nature and Object, of the New System of Education</title> (London, 1812), pp. 153&#8211;180 castigated the article &#8216;The
                        Education of the Poor&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 17 (November 1810), 58&#8211;88, for its condemnation of Andrew Bell as a
                        plagiarist and an Anglican bigot. The author of the article was Brougham, though he was not named by Southey.</note> It will
                    be a heavier blow to the Review than that which they have received from <ref target="people.html#CoplestonEdward">Copplestone</ref>,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Copleston had engaged in a prolonged public debate with
                        the <title>Edinburgh</title>. His <title>A Reply to the Calumnies of the Edinburgh Review against Oxford</title> (Oxford,
                        1810), reacted to an attack on &#8216;classical learning as currently taught in England&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 15
                        (October 1809), 40&#8211;53. Copleston noted in response that no one would &#8216;apply to the Edinburgh Review for information about the
                        Classics&#8217; (<title>Reply</title>, p. 118). For the reviewers&#8217; reaction see <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 16 (April 1810),
                        158&#8211;187. Copleston followed up with <title>A Second Reply to the Edinburgh Review</title> (1810) and <title>A Third Reply to
                            the Edinburgh Review</title> (1811).</note> inasmuch as this goes directly to the moral or rather immoral principle upon
                    which it is conducted, &#8211; the principle of lying point-blank whenever it serves their purpose. &#8211; I have drawn up an abstract of the
                    New System, as clearly &amp; compendiously as possible, showing also what elementary works are wanting to adapt its practice to
                    classical schools, the principle applying equally to all schools, &#8211; this I have sent to Cadiz, to <ref target="people.html#AbellaManuel">my good correspondent there</ref>, who applied to me upon the subject, the Cortes being
                    about to take<del>s</del> measures for providing national instruction for the future.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> has been with me, he made a shorter stay than I wished, &amp; could he have
                    staid longer his time would not have been unprofitably spent. <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> is one of those
                    men whom I liked at first sight, &#8211; &amp; the more I know him the higher he stands in my opinion. You probably know that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>, being naturally enough disposed to remove from Durham, means to try his
                    fortune in London, at the west end of the town. I rather dissuaded him from it, but think he will be succesful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was fortunate enough to get my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> promoted at last. It was
                    done by <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Percevals</ref> interference, &#8211; &amp; in the course of the business I was led to
                    an acquaintance with <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, a man of pleasant manners, lively talents, &amp;
                    remarkable quickness. The manner in which <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> speaks of the Battle of Talavera,
                    in his reviewal of <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scotts</ref> Vision, is a good specimen of the honesty of <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrays</ref> criticism.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>Vision
                            of Don Roderick</title> (1811), appraised in <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 18 (August 1811), 379&#8211;392. This highlighted
                        a &#8216;decidedly vulgar&#8217; passage in the <title>Vision</title>, adding that &#8216;if Mr Scott had never written any thing better, his
                        poetical reputation would not at this moment have stood much higher than that of the author of the Battles of Talavera&#8217; (388).
                        The &#8216;author&#8217; was Croker, whose <title>The Battles of Talavera</title>, first published in 1809 had gone into nine editions by
                        1812. Southey was also undoubtedly stung by Jeffrey&#8217;s attack, in the same review (390&#8211;391 n.*) on &#8216;an ingenious person, who
                        compiles what he calls the History of Europe for the Edinburgh Annual Register &#8230; The misfortune is, that his annual volume is
                        rather too long to be conveniently read through within the year&#8217;. Southey was the &#8216;ingenious person&#8217; in question.</note> &#8211; And
                    this reminds me of my own poem Pelayo,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early incarnation of <title>Roderick, the Last
                            of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> &#8211; from which, if there were room, I would send you a passage which forms a most
                    curious parallel with a part of <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scotts</ref>. <del>forms a most curious parallel with a part
                        of Scotts</del>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the course of the winter I shall have some volumes of Omniana<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Omniana, or Horae Otiosiores</title> (1812).</note> to send you.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>