<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2288</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3559</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2288" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2288" type="letter">
        <head>2288. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1813-08-09">9 August
                        1813</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey. R. N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Helens/ Auckland<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is a long time since you have heard from me, &#8211; a little uncertainty about my own movements has been one cause,
                    ever-calling employments another, to which you may add interruptions &amp; Lakers, &amp; lastly that like the author of the long
                    Psyche I too <del>am</del> &lt;have&gt; sometimes to make slow way thro the lake of my own laziness.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Beaumont (1615&#8211;1699; <title>DNB</title>), whose religious epic <title>Psyche, or, Love&#8217;s
                            Mystery</title>, first published in 1648 and in an expanded version in 1651, runs to 30,000 verses. The quotation is from
                            <title>Psyche</title>, Canto 24, stanza 9, line 6. An edition of 1702 was no. 242 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library.</note> &#8211; I am going to London, most probably tomorrow week will be the day of my departure. I could go sooner if the
                    coach days suited us both perhaps, &#8211; but an inflammation in the lid of the eye, which <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#WilsonMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Wilson</ref> have had is come to me tho at present in a very mild form, &amp; under the most favourable termination, (that is
                    to say if it goes off without closing the eye &amp; bursting) it will be four or five days before I ought to inflame my system by
                    the jolting of a journey. It is a mere trifle at present, in no degree affecting the sight, &#8211; nor am I sensible of it, only if I
                    life lift the lid.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of my employments Roderick<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> is that most interests you, &#8211; &amp; me too just at this moment.
                    I have been ever since the beginning of January gravelled in the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> book, but the way opened before me on
                    Friday evening, &amp; I began the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> this morning. As soon as I return it will certainly go to press, &amp;
                    I expect to make some progress in at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> &amp; I are at issue &amp; I withhold from him the conclusion of the
                        volume<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813).</note> till the dispute is settled. All that is certain at present
                    is that he is a knave, &amp; wants to trick me not only of the 209 &#163; paid for my 12/th share, but of some 200 &#163; more
                        <del>upon</del> on the pretext of loss upon that share. &#8211; he himself having originally promised to repurchase the share at the
                    original price whenever I might chuse to give it up, &amp; to give me at the publication of each volume, his bill for my profits
                    at 12 months date. The fraud is gross &amp; palpable. I am about to lay the case before <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">W
                        Scott</ref> &amp; request him to interfere. Exposure in that quarter is what <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> will not like.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> offers me 1000 guineas for the history.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s proposed <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note>
          <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> will be my adviser whether to accept this offer. It has a good sound, &amp; if
                    I could live the while without forestalling it, I should probably be contented with it. The work will occupy 18 months, reckoning
                    from the beginning of next year. &#8211; I bring out Roderick in the spring, &amp; Brazil<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        second part of the <title>History of Brazil</title> was published in 1817, and the concluding volume in 1819.</note> in the
                    coming winter &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wrote to Burdon<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Burdon (1764&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), writer on
                        politics and literature.</note> for Estradas<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alvaro Florez Estrada (1765&#8211;1853),
                        Spanish economist, lawyer and liberal. He was a prominent member of the Cadiz Cortes.</note> address, &amp; have had no answer
                    &#8211; of course he is not at Hexham. &#8211; I am to meet Von Hesse the Hambro patriot<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jonas Ludwig
                        von Hess (1756&#8211;1823), who organised the defence of Hamburg against French and Danish forces in 1813.</note> in London, where
                        <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> has fallen in with him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has the exordium to the history, which he will annex to the advertisement<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The advertisement for Southey&#8217;s projected <title>History of the Peninsular
                        War</title>.</note> as in the case of Nelson.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> It is somewhat stately, as it should be, stating the moral importance of the
                    subject, &amp; my own motive for undertaking it. The book is to be a splendid one, &amp; announced without delay, to prevent the
                        Historiographer<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Historiographer Royal, James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765&#8211;1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), whom Southey loathed.</note> from laying his unhallowed hands upon <del>the</del> &lt;a&gt; work
                    which belongs to me &amp; me alone. I expect more from the credit it will give me than from its immediate profit. The notoriety of
                    the subject will make me know by those who know me not at present, &amp; I think it will enable me ever after to put my own price
                    upon any thing. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> says he never published any book which gave such general
                    satisfaction as Nelson. he has sold 1200 copies.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am afraid there will be a hollow peace patched up at Prague<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> There was a
                        brief armistice between the forces of France and the Sixth Coalition 4 June &#8211; 13 August 1813, in order to allow both sides to
                        re-group their forces.</note> &amp; if Buonaparte be left with Holland, beyond all doubt we shall have to begin again as soon
                    as he has made a navy. No doubt we shall have an offensive &amp; defensive alliance with Spain, but he will have a fleet before
                    Spain will have funds for an army: for that country will be <del>in</del> left in a deplorable state, &amp; moreover will have
                    great efforts to make for <del>xxx xxx</del> recovering the revolted colonies. I have little doubt of her succeeding in this,
                    &amp; heartily hope she may. And this is a subject upon which I have framed a very unbiased opinion upon competent documents. The
                    horrors in Spanish America are the spawn of our American war.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The United Kingdom and
                        United States were at war 1812&#8211;1814. Southey had been writing about South America in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 367&#8211;421.</note> In Mexico the insurrection is very much like the last rebellion in Ireland,
                    &amp; the whole character of the contest marked with <del>a more</del> Irish ferocity. Some Anglo-Americans have been at the head
                    of the prison-massacres of the Europeans! Nathan is really so vile an animal that I could find in my heart almost to wish he did
                    not speak English.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> A comparison of the Mexican War of Independence (1810&#8211;1821) with the
                        rising by the United Irishmen in 1798. See <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 395, in which
                        Southey denounced the Mexican War of Independence as &#8216;too much resembling in its causes, conduct, and progress, the dreadful
                        scenes which, in our time, we have seen in Ireland; &#8211; a war of havock, cruelty and extermination&#8217;. His brief account of
                        affairs in Mexico is close to the wording in this letter. &#8216;Nathan&#8217; was a common characterisation of the United
                    States.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had a hearty shake by the hand from Ponsonby about the Chesapeake.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Lieutenant John Ponsonby (dates unknown) was living at Ormathwaite outside Keswick. The USS <hi rend="ital">Chesapeake</hi>
                        had been captured by HMS <hi rend="ital">Shannon</hi> on 1 June 1813.</note> Never was any thing <del>xx</del> better-timed,
                    better-placed, &#8211; or better-<hi rend="ital">personed</hi> if I may use such a word.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For your promotion, &#8211; you must wait patiently till the Gods send it. I make no doubt of getting it <del>at
                        last</del> some time or other. <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> I shall of course see in turn. Meantime make
                    yourself easy about your expences an odd 30 or 40 &#163; in the course of the year will set all to rights, &amp; this I shall be very
                    well able to supply. The Bank of Faith never fails.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Huntington (1745&#8211;1813;
                            <title>DNB</title>), preacher and religious writer. His <title>God the Guardian of the Poor and the Bank of Faith</title>
                        (1785&#8211;1802), in which he described how Providence had miraculously provided for his family, was vigorously denounced by
                        Southey in <title>Letters from England</title> 3 vols (London, 1807), III, pp. 20&#8211;29.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> &amp; the young ones. All well here.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-08-09">Aug 9. 1813</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>