<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2151</idno><idno type="nines">rce3422</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856).  Previously  published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    292–294.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2151" type="letter"><head>2151. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1812-09-27">27 September
                        1812</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb/>Previously published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                    292–294.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1812-09-27">Sept. 27. 1812.</date></dateline><salute>My Dear Neville,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I remember with some shame that you asked me a question, which, because it was not answered at the time (our
                    letters having crossed each other upon the road), was jostled out of remembrance, by the dissipation in which summer guests and
                    summer visitors involve me, when I am not occupied by my too numerous and pressing engagements. Let me now endeavour to make
                    amends. The best grammar of any language is the shortest. There is a Spanish one which professes to be of this description just
                    advertised for the use of the army, published by Davies, who publishes the “Military Chronicle.”<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> J. Davis (fl. 1810s), publisher and bookseller. He published the <title>Royal Military Chronicle; or British
                            Officer’s Monthly Register and Mentor</title>. The new Spanish grammar-book, emphasising ‘the omission of what is
                        superfluous, and the fullest exposition of what is necessary’ was advertised in Ibid., (July 1812), [i].</note> Procure a
                    grammar, a dictionary, and a Spanish Testament (the Bible Society<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British and Foreign
                        Bible Society announced in 1806 that they had printed 2,000 New Testaments in Spanish to give to Spanish prisoners of
                        war.</note> have printed one, so it may easily be got), and begin to read, without the irksome labour of <hi rend="ital">learning</hi> a grammar. Commit to memory some of the dialogues in the grammar, and you will soon be fitted for mercantile
                    conversation; translate some of the sentences which you will find in your grammar into Spanish, and compare them with the Spanish;
                    do the same with some verses in the Testament: you will acquire practice enough to write it. The language is very easy; perhaps of
                    all languages the easiest. Of course, I except its works of satire and low humour, which, in <hi rend="ital">all</hi> languages,
                    are exceedingly difficult to <hi rend="ital">all</hi> foreigners.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am very thankful to you for the two letters from Sicily; they are exceedingly interesting, and will be of great
                    service to me.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey included a chapter on Sicily in the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 422–437.</note> In the course of a month I shall have an opportunity of returning
                    them by a private hand (Mr. Dawe, the painter<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The history and portrait painter George Dawe
                        (1781–1829; <title>DNB</title>). Dawe’s residence at Greta Hall in autumn 1812 whilst he worked on the 9 foot by 8 foot canvas
                        ‘Mother Rescuing her Child from an Eagle’s Nest’ was not without controversy, with some members of the household complaining
                        about his habit of keeping windows open.</note>), and with them the poem,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Unidentified.</note> which I have not yet been able to read.</p><p rend="indent1"> Tell <ref target="people.html#ConderJosiah">Josiah Conder</ref> that I have no control whatever over any part of
                    the “Register” except my own department; and that the editors have not even shown me the due respect of informing me why they have
                    not inserted his poem and some others which I solicited and procured for them.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Conder had
                        given Southey a series of poems by himself and various friends for insertion in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1810</title>, 3.2 (1812); see Southey to Josiah Conder, 5 May 1812, Letter 2088. His poem was not included in the
                            <title>Register</title>.</note> I am hurt at the omission; it is an act of incivility to me, and of injustice to him. Of
                    all the verses in the volume there are none by any means so original as that piece of his which has been rejected. That sweet
                    fragment by one of his minstrel friends is exquisite in itself, but has not the originality of his poem;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Conder’s poem, ‘The Reverie’, was not included in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>. The ‘sweet
                        fragment’ was ‘A Character, a Fragment’, signed ‘A.’, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812), ci–cii.
                        The latter was written by Ann Tayor (1782–1866; <title>DNB</title>), a contributor to Conder’s <title>The Associate
                            Minstrels</title> (1810), and hence one of his ‘minstrel friends’.</note> for it is in Crabbe’s manner,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poet and clergyman George Crabbe (1754–1832; <title>DNB</title>).</note> though Crabbe has
                    written nothing so free from faults. The “Inchcape Rock” is mine.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812), lxxxiv–lxxxvi. It has originally appeared unsigned in the
                            <title>Morning Post</title>, 19 October 1803.</note> Some unknown person found it in a newspaper, tinkered it to his own
                    taste, sometimes for the better, sometimes for the worse, but to the destruction of the metre, and then inserted it in the
                    “Register.”</p><p rend="indent1"> Of the remaining gleanings from my manuscript,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> A MS by Henry Kirke White.
                        Southey was transcribing materials from it, see his letter to Neville White, 20 September 1812, Letter 2147.</note> the
                    longest poem is one entitled the “Hermit of the Pacific,”<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The ‘Hermit of the Pacific’ was
                        first published in the 9th edition of Kirke White’s <title>Remains</title>, 3 vols (London, 1822), III, 76–79.</note> and of
                    this I rather think you have a copy in another of <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry’s</ref> books. If this be the
                    case I need not transcribe it; if it be not, let me know. Sooner or later I shall produce an <hi rend="ital">inscription</hi> for
                    the “Illustrations.”<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s inscription for a tablet in Wilford churchyard was
                        intended as a tribute to a place commemorated by Henry Kirke White himself in ‘Lines Written in Wilford Church-Yard’; see
                            <title>Remains</title>, 2 vols (London, 1807), I, pp. 38–40. Southey had offered the inscription (which was never written)
                        for Neville White’s proposed volume of prints of places celebrated in his brother’s poems. This was intended to complement and
                        capitalise on the popularity of the <title>Remains</title>; see Southey to Neville White, 18 March 1812 (Letter 2062) and 12
                        April 1812 (Letter 2076).</note><ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames ">Ballantyne</ref> will do justice to the “Remains.”<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ballantyne printed the sixth edition of the <title>Remains of Henry Kirke White</title>, published in
                        1813.</note> We had better make our alterations, and reserve all additional matter for the “Illustrations.”</p><p rend="indent1"> I will soon write to <ref target="people.html#WhiteJames">James</ref>, and wish I had done it sooner: but I am
                    behindhand with all my engagements. The bulk of the “ Register”<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title> (1812).</note> will account for this; and my yearly task is no sooner
                    completed than I am called upon to begin it again, to the lamentable delay of my own greater historical works.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. the two final volumes of <title>The History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819) and the
                        unpublished ‘History of Portugal’.</note> The “ Omniana”<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Omniana, or Horae Otiosiores</title> (1812).</note> will soon be published, and my “Life of Nelson”<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> is in the press; and I have made some progress this summer in my poem, much
                    to my own satisfaction. It must be called “ Roderick, the last of the Goths,” not “ Pelayo,” as was originally intended.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Pelayo’ was the original title for <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                        (1814).</note> It is very unlike anything attempted yet in prose or rhyme. God bless you.</p><closer><signed rend="indent1"> R.S.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>