<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2101</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3372</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890 .  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 271&#8211;275 [misdated 12 May
                        1812].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2101" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2101" type="letter">
        <head>2101. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas
                    Southey</ref>, <date when="1812-05-27">27 May 1812</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Captain Southey. R.N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Helens/ Auckland/ Durham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890 <lb />Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 271&#8211;275 [misdated 12 May
                        1812].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-05-27">Wednesday May 27. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will see me, if no unforeseen cause should frustrate the
                    intention about the first week in July, with <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref>. We shall make a march of
                    it, seeing all the <del>things</del> seeables on the way, to Newcastle, cross
                    the Tyne at Shields that I may make a pilgrimage to Jarrow in honour of the
                    Venerable Bede,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Venerable Bede
                        (673/4&#8211;735; <title>DNB</title>), monk, historian and theologian, who spent
                        most of his life in the monastic community at Jarrow, in North East
                        England.</note> &amp; thence to Sunderland. But we will arrange all this so
                    that you may meet us at Durham. I shall leave <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> either at Kendal or
                    Lancaster on his way <del>to</del> back to Liverpool, &#8211; then taking the caves in
                    my homeward route. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> asks
                    if there be any objection to <ref target="people.html#JardineDavid">David
                        Jardine&#8217;s</ref> joining us in this expedition. Three upon a walk are better
                    than two, &#8211; &amp; at Durham there are inns to sleep at, &#8211; but how can &lt;he&gt;
                    be lodged at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Helens? If you can answer the question
                    favourably, <del>it will</del> save time by <del>doing</del> replying to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles</ref> himself without
                    delay.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My hopes were highly raised by a letter from the Consul at
                        Bahia<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The diplomat Frederick
                        Lindeman (dates unknown), who had taken up his post at Bahia in 1810.</note>
                    telling me the Directors of the Public Library<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Gomes Ferrao Castelo Branco (dates unknown),
                        Director of the Public Library in Bahia founded in 1811.</note> had
                    commissioned him to send me some Manuscripts. I consigned the parcel to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> &amp; they proved
                    to be no manuscripts at all. The obligation on my part is the same,
                        <del>the</del> &amp; the Consuls blunder the only cause of disappointment.
                    The contents were Anchietas Tupi Grammar,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been sent a copy of Jos&#233; de Anchieta (1534&#8211;1597),
                            <title>Arte de Grammatica da Lingoa mais Usada na Costa do
                            Brasil</title> (1595). This was no. 1530 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library, inscribed by him: &#8216;This singularly rare and curious book
                        was sent to me from the Public Library of Bahia de Todos, or Santos, by
                        desire of the Conde des Arcos, then Governor of that Captaincy.&#8217; The book
                        was a grammar of the Tupi language, widely-spoken in coastal Brazil when the
                        Portuguese arrived in the sixteenth century.</note> a book which I had
                    despaired of ever obtaining, from its exceeding rarity, &amp; O Valeroso
                        Lucideno,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manuel Calado
                        (1584&#8211;1654), <title>Valeroso Lucideno e o Triunfo da Liberdade</title>
                        (1648), a first-hand account of Brazil during the period of Dutch
                        rule.</note> &#8211; the same work which our Envoy M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Stewart<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Stuart, Baron
                        Stuart de Rothesay (1779&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), envoy at Lisbon
                        1810&#8211;1814.</note> contrived so ingeniously to forward me by the post, &#8211; a
                    very interesting book it is. The parcel came over with the dispatches, &amp; was
                    announced to me from the Secretary of States Office in a letter &#8216;on his
                    Majesty&#8217;s service.&#8221; which might &lt;have&gt; frightened <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> if she had been here.
                    &#8211; I have had another very interesting communication since my last; &#8211; a letter
                    from the Countess of Bureta, the Zaragozan,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mar&#237;a de la Consolaci&#243;n Azlor y Villavicencio
                        (1775&#8211;1814), a Spanish aristocrat who took an active role in the two sieges
                        of Zaragoza in 1808&#8211;1809.</note> inclosing the copy of the last intelligence
                    which she had received from that city, &#8211; &amp; offering <del>to</del> me as the
                    warm friend &amp; historian of the Spaniards in their struggles any services in
                    her power. I shall endeavour to collect materials for a full &amp; separate
                    account of the two sieges, thro this channel.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should perhaps have told you all this sooner, but my mind has
                    been opprest by <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Percevals</ref>
                        death,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Spencer Perceval was
                        assassinated on 11 May 1812.</note> &amp; the dreadful state of the mob
                    which it has disclosed. You know I am no aguish politician, <del>xxxxxx form the
                        despondency xxxxxxxxxxxxx but it is a d</del> but I fear the happiest days
                    of England are over: the abuse of liberty has uniformly been punished
                        <add>by</add> with the loss of liberty, now the crime has been committed,
                    &amp; if we escape the penalty it will be contrary to the whole experience of
                    history. In the rejoicings at Nottingham &amp; in Cornwall, &amp; in the attempt
                    to rescue Bellingham,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Bellingham
                        (c. 1769&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), the assassin of Spencer Perceval. When
                        he was hanged on 18 May 1812 the crowd was largely favourable to him.</note>
                    we see the effect which <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref> &amp;
                    Hunt, &amp; <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdett</ref> &amp; the Common
                    Council &amp;c<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> All the radicals whom
                        Southey disliked: William Cobbett; Henry &#8216;Orator&#8217; Hunt (1773&#8211;1835;
                            <title>DNB</title>); Sir Francis Burdett; and the Court of Common
                        Council of the City of London, which was dominated by radicals.</note> have
                    produced upon the feelings of the English mob. The speeches of the <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdettites</ref> &amp; the leading paragraphs
                    of the demagogue newspapers are printed like dying speeches &amp; sold in the
                    manufacturing districts. &#8211; Every pot-house also is supplied with
                        <del>these</del> &lt;the Sunday papers &#8211; &gt; doses of weekly poison: one
                    reader serves for a <del>xxx</del> tap &#8211; room full of open mouthed
                        <del>xxx</del> listeners, &amp; the consequence is that at this moment the
                    army is the single plank between us &amp; destruction. We are on the brink of
                    the most dreadful of all imaginable <del>xxxx</del> evils, &#8211; a war of the poor
                    against the rich, of brute ignorance against every thing above its own degraded
                    level. How long the army may be depended upon is a question which the Royal
                        Dukes<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The brothers: Frederick,
                        Duke of York (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>); William, Duke of Clarence
                        (1765&#8211;1837; King of the United Kingdom as William IV 1830&#8211;1837;
                            <title>DNB</title>); Edward, Duke of Kent (1767&#8211;1820;
                        <title>DNB</title>); Ernest, Duke of Cumberland, 1771&#8211;1851;
                            <title>DNB</title>); Augustus, Duke of Sussex (1773&#8211;1843;
                            <title>DNB</title>); Adolphus, Duke of Cambridge (1774&#8211;1850;
                            <title>DNB</title>). The cost of their upkeep and the disreputable
                        nature of their private lives made them unpopular.</note> &amp; the
                        floggers<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Flogging in the British
                        Army was extremely controversial and much-denounced by radicals.</note> may
                    tremble to ask themselves.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> has at this time a
                    letter of mine in his hands urging the necessity of winning the hearts of the
                    soldiers, &amp; recommending honorary distinction as one means, &amp; another
                    that a certain number of the oldest soldiers &lt;in every company&gt; employed
                    in <del>the</del> storming C Rodrigo &amp; Badajoz<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ciudad Rodrigo was stormed on the night of 19&#8211;20
                        January 1812; Badajoz on 6 April 1812.</note> should have their discharge
                    upon full pay, &#8211; or an increase if they chose to continue in the service: &#8211;
                        <del>&amp; xxxxxx xxxxx</del> I learn that my letter made an impression upon
                        <del>xxxx</del> poor <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Percevals</ref> secretatries to whom it was shown, &amp; <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> has taken it in the
                    hope that it may do its work in higher quarters. But this is a distant good, &#8211;
                    alterations <del>xxxx</del> are poor things to trust to in diseases which
                    require the knife &amp; the cautery.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This I feel assured of, that unless the licentiousness of the
                    press is stopt, &#8211; there will soon be an end of its liberty. Were I in the H of
                    Commons I would clear the <del>hou</del> gallery whenever <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdett</ref> rose, &#8211; if his speeches were
                    published, I would punish the publication as a breach of privilege, &#8211; &amp; if
                    he spoke elsewhere I would teach &lt;him&gt; that this privilege of exciting
                    rebellion <del>did not x</del> was confined to the walls of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Stephens.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> St Stephen&#8217;s
                        Chapel, in the Palace of Westminster, was the meeting-place of the House of
                        Commons.</note> It is absurd to talk of his virtues, or his motives now. By
                    the fruit we must judge of the tree,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Matthew</title>, 7: 16.</note> &#8211; &amp; the mob who attempted to
                    rescue an assassin, of them <del>xx</del> all that was known at that moment was
                    that he had committed a most atrocious assassination &#8211; <del>shouted</del> cried
                        <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdett</ref> for ever. As for Bellingham
                    I do not <del>con</del> class him with these wretches who applauded him: the man
                    had that in him which would have been greatness, if <del>his mind</del>
                    &lt;he&gt; had not been insane. It was an insanity &lt;however&gt; which ought
                    not to have exempted him from punishment.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the manufacturing districts there is clearly a system as well
                    laid as that of the United Irish<del>men</del>
          <note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The United Irishmen were the revolutionary organisation
                        responsible for the Irish rising of 1798.</note> &amp; carried on more
                    dangerously, &#8211; because it is carried on by Englishmen. Ryder<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Tory politician Dudley Ryder, 1st Earl
                        of Harrowby (1762&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>). A Pittite loyalist and member
                        of Perceval&#8217;s cabinet, he became Lord President of the Council on the
                        formation of Lord Liverpool&#8217;s ministry in June 1812. He had suffered a
                        serious head injury after a fall at the Foreign Office in 1804 and was known
                        to suffer from nervous problems. In 1805 he had asked to be recalled from a
                        mission to Berlin to forge a new continental alliance against France.</note>
          <del>we</del> is <del>a man of</del> &lt;in&gt; infirm health, &#8211; a nervous man,
                    &#8211; &amp; very unfit for his office in such times. I am told that the shock of
                        <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Percevals</ref> death will
                        <del>kill him</del> be fatal to him. &#8211; Poor <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> breathed his last upon
                    the green table in <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> H of
                    Commons&#8217;-room! But to return to the Luddites<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Luddites smashed textile machinery that they saw as
                        a threat to their livelihoods. The movement was based in the East Midlands,
                        Lancashire and Yorkshire.</note> &#8211; the danger is of the most imminent kind.
                    I would hang about a score in a county, &amp; send off ship-loads to B.
                        Bay.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The convict settlement at
                        Botany Bay in New South Wales, founded in 1788.</note> &amp; if there were
                    no other means of <del>cutting off there</del> checking the treasonable
                    practices which are carried on in the Sunday newspapers, I would suspend the
                    Habeus Corpus.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The legal principle
                        that people cannot be detained without charge.</note>
          <del>Cut off there</del> Shut up these bellows-blowers, &amp; the fire
                        <del>will</del> &lt;may perhaps&gt; go out.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here another danger stares us in the face. <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> might have been trusted
                    with that dictatorial power which is necessary to save the Commonwealth: &#8211; he
                    held his power as much by the virtues as his ability. Alas he has left no
                    successor. <ref target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lord Liverpool</ref> wants
                    his reputation, &#8211; Ld Sidmouth<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        former Prime Minister, Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757&#8211;1844;
                            <title>DNB</title>), who became Home Secretary later in 1812.</note>
                    &amp; Vansittart<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicolas Vansittart,
                        1st Baron Bexley (1766&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), who became Chancellor of
                        the Exchequer on 20 May 1812.</note> (all good men) want his talents. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M. Wellesley</ref> is a vicious man
                    &amp; a tyrant at heart. &#8211; My fears are <del>these</del> &#8211; that let what will
                    happen the liberties of England are in greater peril than they <del>have</del>
                    ever have been &lt;before,&gt; &#8211; &amp; that the alternative is whether we shall
                    have a despotism, before a civil war &#8211; or after it. The proudest days of England
                    are to come, but her happiest days &#8211; in my utmost heart I fear it &#8211; are over.
                        <del>We shall hav</del> Even if this thunder-storm should pass away, &#8211; &amp;
                    with as atmosphere charged like that of Padalon<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> The land of the dead in Southey&#8217;s <title>Curse of
                            Kehama</title> (1810).</note> itself &#8211; I do not see how <del>it is</del>
                    can pass without an explosion, &#8211; still I see great evil in store. We shall have
                    a glorious &amp; triumphant war. But <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M Wellesley</ref> will not hesitate at national bankruptcy, &#8211; &amp;
                    Catholic concessions will draw on the sale of tythes. that is in other words the
                    plunder of <del>the</del> Church property to relieve the necessities of the
                    state. A revolution in the religion of a country produces more evil than a
                    century is sufficient to allay. &#8211; The sale of the tythes leads immediately to
                    putting up the Establishment for the lowest bidder, &#8211; a measure of course, when
                    it is to be paid by the Government. The Methodists then come in; &amp; the reign
                    of the Saints <del>xxx</del> led to the reign of the Sinners in days when there
                    was more virtue &amp; more wisdom <del>than</del> in England than can be found
                    among us now<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is referring to
                        the common idea that the Puritan Commonwealth of 1649&#8211;1660 was succeeded by
                        (and led to) the licentiousness of the Restoration period.</note> &#8211; What is
                    the end of all this? &#8211; the best I can hope for myself is, that Portugal may be a
                    freer country, when I shall find it necessary to <del>leave my own</del> shake
                    off the dust of my own. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>