<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2079</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3350</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 25.  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                        262&#8211;264.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2079" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2079" type="letter">
        <head>2079. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1812-04-16">16
                        April 1812</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Bath.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 25<lb />Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                        262&#8211;264.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-04-16">April 16. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Heaved forbid that you should draw upon yourself the vexations of a printing establishment, which would involve you
                    in <del>more</del> troubles without end, &amp; for no adequate purpose, &#8211; scarcely indeed for any purpose! &#8211; It will be perfectly
                    easy for you to tell the public all which you wish to tell them, <del>in</del> with perfect security for yourself, your printer
                    &amp; publisher, provided only that you bear in mind what the laws of libel are.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor
                        was presumably thinking of self-publishing his <title>Commentary on Memoirs of Mr Fox</title>, which was ostensibly a response
                        to John Bernard Trotter&#8217;s (1775&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>) laudatory account of his erstwhile employer Charles James Fox
                        (1749&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>). Although the <title>Commentary</title> had been printed by Murray, he eventually suppressed
                        its publication, refusing to issue a book that attacked the Tory government and was dedicated to James Madison (1751&#8211;1836),
                        President of the United States 1809&#8211;1817, with whom Britain was about to go to war.</note> With regard to individuals they
                    give sufficient scope; all may be said of them that ought to be said. With regard to the state any thing may be said which does
                    not bear evident intention of a wish to over throw it. &#8211; Above all that you have to beware of is that the vehemence of your manner
                    do not belie your intentions.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is no difference in the end at which you &amp; I are aiming, but a good deal in the means. <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Earl Wellington</ref> is in his place, he is what Nature meant him to be, a
                    soldier, &#8211; likely to do greater things than Marlborough;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The comparison is between
                        Wellington and the British hero of the War of the Spanish Succcession (1701&#8211;1713), John Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough
                        (1650&#8211;1722; <title>DNB</title>).</note> if he be not prevented by a cowardly faction in this country, he will beat down the
                    power of France, &amp; England &amp; Spain will give the law to Europe. But as for establishing him on the throne of Portugal &#8211;
                    Heaven forefend not that the thing should be done, &#8211; which is impossible, &#8211; but that you should wish it to be done. In the first
                    place the Portugueze would not submit to a heretic, &#8211; &amp; in the second there are better things in store for Portugal. By one of
                    two possible events Portugal <del>is in</del> has at this time the prospect of being united with Spain, by the death of Ferdinand
                    &amp; his brother,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813&#8211;1833). He had two
                        brothers: Charles, Count of Molina (1788&#8211;1855) and Francisco, Duke of Cadiz (1794&#8211;1865). The three men were childless and prisoners in
                        France.</note> or their contracting any alliance with France, (both sufficiently probable) &#8211; in which case the succession
                    devolves upon the Princess of Brazil;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ferdinand VII&#8217;s eldest sister, Princess Charlotte
                        (1775&#8211;1830), wife of John VI (1767&#8211;1826), Prince Regent of Portugal 1799&#8211;1816, King of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826. In Southey&#8217;s
                        scenario their eldest son would become King of both Spain and Portugal, so uniting the two countries.</note> &#8211; or if the tide
                    of opinion should take a republican direction, &amp; the whole peninsula form itself into a great federal commonwealth, &#8211; the form
                    of polity which seems to be the best attainable in our present state. <del>xxx</del> This is far less likely than the former
                    means; either of them would effect the union without any sacrifice of pride or privilege on the part of the weaker state.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For the mother country I feel nothing but hope, &#8211; for the colonies I see nothing but a long series of evils. My
                    notions of colonial policy may very summarily be stated. It is as necessary for a flourishing country to send out colonies, as it
                    is for a hive to send out swarms, but no modern Government has ever proceeded wisely in the business. With the Cape, &amp; New
                        Holland<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Cape of Good Hope and Australia, both of which had substantial numbers of
                        British settlers.</note> for instance I would proceed thus, &#8211; Govern yourselves &amp; we will protect you as long as you need
                    protection &#8211; when that is no longer necessary, <del>we are</del> remember that tho we are different countries, each independent,
                    we are one people. Every Briton who sets foot among you shall instantly be entitled to all the privileges of a native, &#8211; every
                    person born among you becomes as an Englishman when he lands in G Britain. Every country in which English <del>was</del>
                    &lt;is&gt; the mother tongue shall be open to <del>the</del> every member of the Great English <del>xxx xx</del> race. &#8211; In fifty
                    years America would petition to be received back into the family.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You rate the American Spaniards too highly. I have just gone thro Humboldts Mexico,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander von Humboldt (1769&#8211;1859), <title>Essai Politique sur le Royaume de la Nouvelle Espagne</title>
                        (1811), translated as <title>Political History of New Spain</title> (1811&#8211;1812), no. 1463 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library.</note> &#8211; &amp; I had before perused the Mercurio Peruano;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Mercurio Peruano</title> (1790&#8211;1795), the first newspaper published in Peru.</note> &#8211; they have all the superstition,
                    all the immorality of the European Spaniards, &amp; some vices of their own to boot, which necessarily arise wherever there is a
                    distinction of casts. In <del>all</del> the <del>of</del> most flourishing of the Spanish colonies there are three hostile
                    parties, the Europeans &amp; <del>the</del> Creoles who hate each other; &#8211; the Indians who hate both &amp; outnumber both. In B
                    Ayres the Europeans &amp; the Indians are both <del>so</del> weak <del>xxx xxx x little can it be apprehended from this</del> to
                    what they are in all other kingdoms &amp; yet we see what barbarous bloodshed has taken place.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Since the May Revolution of 1810, Argentina had been riven by internal conflicts between different regions; and
                        between those who wished to maintain the link with Spain and those who wanted an independent state.</note> Peru may be
                        rebarbarized<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> There had been fourteen uprisings by the native peoples of Peru in the
                        eighteenth century, culminating in that of 1780&#8211;1782.</note> &#8211; made worse than it was under the Incas by the <del>xx</del>
                    victory of the Indians, &#8211; Mexico may become the theatre of long and obstinate wars,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Mexican War of Independence (1810&#8211;1821).</note> &#8211; Miranda<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sebastian Francisco de
                        Miranda Ravelo y Rodriguez de Espinoza (1750&#8211;1816), Venezuelan revolutionary. He had served in the French revolutionary army
                        in 1791&#8211;1792 and was a friend of the leading Girondins. In 1810&#8211;1812 he played a leading role in the struggle for Venezuelan
                        independence before being captured by the Spanish.</note> may introduce the French into Venezuela, each of these things is but
                    too likely to take place. My language to the <del>Amer</del> Colonies would be &#8211; ask little from <del>Spain in</del> the mother
                    Country at such a season as this, &#8211; to the mother country, grant every thing to the Colonies. In fact a reform at home insures
                    reform abroad, &amp; it is as cruel as it is unjust <del>to</del> in the Ame[MS torn] to <del>x</del> visit upon regenerate Spain
                    the sins committed by the old Adam of her Government.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did you ever see Cotton Mathers Hist: of New England?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Cotton
                        Mather (1663&#8211;1728), <title>Magnalia Christi Americana, or the Ecclesiastical History of New England from 1620 to 1698</title>
                        (1702); no. 1904 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> One of the oddest books I ever perused, but deeply
                    interesting. A history of a country given in the succession of <del>x</del>
          <hi rend="ital">Preachers</hi> instead of Princes. It was indeed a genuine Priest-archy &#8211; a word which for the very uncouthness of
                    its mongrel shape fits the <del>xxx</del> subject the better. Half the Anglo Americans went &lt;over&gt; red hot from the
                        <del>meeting hou</del> conventicle, &#8211; the other half flagrant from Bridewell, the Tertium quid<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;third thing&#8217;; a phrase associated with alchemy, referring to an unidentified element that combines with
                        two known ones.</note> has the roguery of the one side superinduced upon the hard vulgarity of the other.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; Once more &#8211; do not involve yourself with a press. Its cold-lead is more perilous than cold-iron. &#8211; I
                        <del>have</del> am slow in my progress with Pelayo<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early incarnation of
                            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> &#8211; only 200 lines since <del>you</del> the last portion.
                    However I look on to the end of another book ere long. &#8211; Remember me to <ref target="people.html#LandorJulia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Landor</ref> &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>