<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1964</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3235</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 229&#8211;230 [in
                        part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1964" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1964" type="letter">
        <head>1964. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1811-10-11">11 October
                        1811</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Captain Southey. R.N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        Helens/ Auckland/ Durham <lb />Stamped: [partial] KESWICK<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 229&#8211;230 [in
                        part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Tom, </salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wish when <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> comes to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> you could contrive to send those gaiters of mine by him, which were left behind us at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                    Helens, inasmuch as the pantaloons to which they belong are destined for this winters wear, &amp; without those gaiters I know not
                    how my poor hormangorgs are to be kept warm. &#8211; This for a beginning as being matter of business. I will now tell you as matter of
                    hepistolary communication that it would rejoice you to see how I am getting on <del>my</del> with my Dutch. I have attacked the
                    two folios of Peter Kolbe,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Peter Kolbe (1675&#8211;1726), <title>Naaukeurige en
                            Uitvoerige Beschryving van de Kaap de Goede Hoop</title> (1727), no. 1669 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library.</note> &amp; as I can make it out with the dictionary so as to read on &amp; get fairly at the contents, I expect to
                    be a good Mynheer by the time I get to the end. It is a great &amp; important step gained. <del>Xx</del>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Pelayo<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early incarnation of <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814).</note> also is progressive, very much to my satisfaction. You will be impressed with the manner in
                    which a widow is introduced among the ruins of Orense, &#8211; a sort of Judith who makes a vow of revenge. The poem will soon reach
                    1000 lines, &amp; to attain to four figures is as great an epoch in the progress of a poem, as being breeched is in the life of a
                    man.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have had two good Lakers. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lowe of Ludlow,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> a cidevant <del>xxxx</del> merchant at Middelburg in Walcherin. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> sent him here, &#8211; he gave me a lesson in Dutch as to the pronunciation.
                    Wakefield, a son of Priscilla Wakefield was the other.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The philanthropist, land agent and
                        writer on political economy, Edward Wakefield (1774&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>). His mother was the author and philanthropist
                        Priscilla Wakefield (1750&#8211;1832; DNB).</note> He has published a statistical account of Ireland<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Ireland, Statistical and Political</title> (1812), no. 3094 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; his
                    letter was from <ref target="people.html#HoggJamesEttrick">Hogg the Ettrick Shepherd</ref>, who besides being a man of very
                    considerable genius seems to have a right honest heart.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#GrahameJames">Grahame</ref>! you give me the first news of his death. I fear
                    straitened circumstances &amp; disappointed hopes may have brought on this catastrophe. His understanding was not equal to his
                    genius, &amp; it required the sunshine of a brighter fortune than ever fell to his lot to counteract a natural melancholy, the
                    constitutional mental disease of men whose feelings are stronger than their intellect. At <ref target="places.html#Teddesley">Teddesley</ref> I read his poem on the Abolition of the Slave Trade,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Poems on the Abolition of the Slave Trade</title> (1810).</note> not without sorrow at finding how poor a thing it was,
                    &#8211; almost utterly worthless. But his Sabbath<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Sabbath</title> (1804).</note> will always remain, &#8211; &amp; from all his other pieces, <del>about</del> a few rare
                    passages may be culled which the best of us might have been proud to have written. It was but the other day that I was talking
                    with <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> about the living poets, little thinking that one to whom I assigned so
                    honourable a place among them, was no longer of the number.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> is very probably drinking tea with you at this time. One <del>of</del> or two
                    books of yours were overlookd I perceive when that parcel was tied up, &#8211; some other opportunity will offer of conveying them. I
                    have been <del>busy upon the</del> taking part in the controversy about <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">Bell</ref> &amp; the
                        <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Dragon</ref>, as you will see in the Quarterly where I have <hi rend="ital">fibbed</hi> the Edinburgh (as the Fancy say) most completely, showing it as little mercy as it deserves at my hands.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s defence of Bell&#8217;s system over Lancaster&#8217;s (the &#8216;Dragon&#8217;) appeared in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (August 1811), 264&#8211;304. It was, however, severely edited before publication, and his
                            personal attacks on the <title>Edinburgh Review</title> were removed; see the account in <ref type="l" target="/reference/qr/index/11.html">Jonathan Cutmore, <title>The
                            Quarterly Review Archive</title>
            </ref>. Southey&#8217;s wrath had been
                        provoked by an article in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 17 (November 1810), 58&#8211;88, which had criticised Bell and
                        proclaimed Lancaster&#8217;s methods superior. Southey&#8217;s article in the <title>Quarterly</title> formed the basis of his <title>The
                            Origin, Nature, and Object, of the New System of Education</title> (1812).</note> For the next number I am going to write
                    upon the Inquisition, &#8211; a subject upon which I have a great deal of curious matter to bring forth.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The History of the Inquisitions; including the Secret Transactions of those Horrific Tribunals</title> (1810);
                            <title>Letter upon the Mischievous Influence of the Spanish Inquisition as it actually exists in the Provinces under the
                            Spanish Government. Translated from El Espa&#241;ol, a periodical Spanish Journal published in London</title> (1811);
                            <title>Narrativa da Persegui&#231;&#227;o de Hippolyto Joseph Da Costa Pereira Furtado de Mendon&#231;a, Natural da Colonia do
                            Sacramento, no Rio-da-Prata, prezo e Processado em Lisboa pelo pretenso Crime de Fra-Ma&#231;on, ou Pedreiro Livre</title>
                        (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (December 1811), 313&#8211;357.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It will require as much interest to get a ship, as it did to get made Commander. I have no correspondence with <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, &#8211; &amp; if the thing can be done it must be thro the same channel as before, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, &#8211;
                    upon the latter of whom by the bye you should have called that he might have shaken hands with you upon your promotion, &#8211; for it
                    originated with him, &amp; without him would not have been obtained.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Today I resumed the long-suspended Life of Nelson<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Life of
                            Nelson</title> (1813), an expansion of Southey&#8217;s article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810),
                        218&#8211;262.</note> with which I shall hurry on, that <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> may not lose the spring
                    sale. &#8211; Copy of the Omniana<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey and Coleridge, <title>Omniana, or Horae
                            Otiosiores</title> (1812).</note> was sent off last week, &amp; more is in hand, so that I shall carry that also thro the
                    press in the course of the season. I suppose Kehama<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of <title>The
                            Curse of Kehama</title>, 1811.</note> must be nearly ready. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> wrote
                    the other day to hurry <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames ">Ballantyne</ref>, saying he had only two copies left. <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> the bookseller is using me unhandsomely, a letter concerning money
                    matters which I wrote to him immediately on my return, &amp; which his father<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Ballantyne (1743&#8211;1817), a general merchant.</note> told me was directly forwarded to him in London, he has not thought proper
                    to answer; &#8211; a conduct, which if the proper answer should not arrive &amp; bring with it the proper apology, I shall certainly
                    resent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We shall see <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> of course before he leaves the North. I was
                    most disappointed that <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> could not stay with me longer. When we shall see you
                    God knows &#8211; all I can say is here is room for you all whenever you can come &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref>
                    love with mine to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> &amp; the young one. All well</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="right">
            <date when="1811-10-11">Oct. 11. 1811.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>