<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1836</idno><idno type="nines">rce3107</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously  published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 306–309
                        [misdated 5 December 1812].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1836" type="letter"><head>1836. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1810-12-05">5 December
                        1810</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey / with Samuel Castle Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Durham<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb/>Previously published: John
                        Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 306–309
                        [misdated 5 December 1812].</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I am sorry George Taylor<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Taylor (1772–1851), a Co. Durham farmer,
                        with literary tastes, father of Southey’s future friend and literary executor Sir Henry Taylor and acquaintance of Tom Southey. He had read a MS version of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), presumably the version
                        sent to Tom Southey, which is now British Library, Add. MS 36485.</note> should have read Kehama in its imperfect state, for
                    there &lt;are&gt; a good many parts in the manuscript in which the versification is defective, – not to mention the many
                    insertions in the printed copy. – It never will surprize <del>x</del> me to find that the poem is not relished, – it is just as
                    impossible to give a taste for works of imagination, as it is to give a taste for music, &amp; I who am without one shall never
                    quarrel with any body for being without the other. The sort of praise which I wish Kehama to obtain, &amp; the real value of such
                    works, is expressed in what <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> tells me his wife<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Turner, née Watts (c. 1768–1843).</note> said of the poem when he made her leave <del>of</del> it off at
                    midnight. She could have read it all night, she said, she felt it elevate her conceptions, &amp; occasion an excitement of mind
                    that made her feel superior to herself. This is there use, to take us out of ourselves, to carry us into the world of unrealities,
                    to busy us with some thing which is not immediately connected with flesh &amp; blood; – to elevate rather than to affect, – &amp;
                    to make us perceive our own imaginative powers instead of constantly referring us to ordinary feelings.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> has seen the review which <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> has written of it,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott had been commissioned by Gifford to review
                            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810). Bedford had also applied to review the poem and had been shown a
                        pre-publication version of Scott’s article. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> was concerned at
                        its emphasis upon narrative, rather than morality, and was allowed to make additions to it along the lines suggested in this
                        letter. Bedford remained, however, unhappy with the overall tone. For the review as published see <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 5 (February 1811), 40–61 (esp. 55–56, probably Bedford’s interpolation); see Southey to Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford, 1 January 1811, Letter 1848.</note> – &amp; which from his account tho a very friendly one, is like that of the Cid
                    very superficial.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott had reviewed <title>The Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808) in
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 134–153.</note> He sees nothing but the naked story, <del>x</del> the
                    moral feeling which pervades it has escaped him. I do not know whether <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> will be able to get a paragraph interpolated touching upon this &amp; showing that there is some difference
                    between a work of high imagination &amp; a story of mere amusement. – </p><p rend="indent1"> Since this was written I have had a letter from <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> himself, telling
                    me of his reviewal, &amp; how hastily he wrote it while the first impression of the poem was fresh upon him, – that he might be
                    beforehand with the Edinburgh in fixing its character with the public, as far as it is to be fixed by public criticism. – I do not
                    know who reviewed the Brazil, but I guess it was <ref target="people.html#HeberReginald">Reginald Heber</ref>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was correct, Heber was the reviewer of the first volume of the <title>History of
                            Brazil</title> (1810). The remainder of this paragraph is a response to the appraisal published in the <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 454–474 (esp. 472; 474).</note> He is wrong in complaining of the want of general &amp;
                    retrospective views, – or rather this is an imputation to which the work is subjected only because it has been published by
                    halves. In their fit time &amp; place they will come in. A coronal is not a coronet, for the last word is appropriate to rank
                    &amp; heraldry. A poitral is a <hi rend="ital">horses</hi> breast-flesh. A tambour is an <hi rend="ital">outlandish</hi> drum, not
                    such as the soldiers use. <hi rend="ital">Napery</hi> implies napkins &amp; tablecloths, either or both. Therefore properly used
                    when a comprehensive term was required. Harry will tell you that a <hi rend="ital">Broad</hi> is the spread of a river into a
                    sheet of water, – <del>someth</del> which is certainly neither lake nor lagoon. – The mistake about Lutheranism the Reviewer has
                    well accounted for by the constant <del>presence</del> &lt;use&gt; of the word Luteranos in the Portugueze writers. Araboutan he
                    might have seen in one of the notes is the indigenous name not of Brazil itself, but of the Brazil-tree.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey’s use of unusual words: <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), I:
                        ‘coronal’, p. 187; ‘poitral’, p. 122; ‘tambour’, pp. 89, 121; ‘napery’, p. 381; ‘broads’, p. 133; Southey inadvertently
                        referred to Dutch missionaries in Brazil as Lutherans rather than Calvinists on p. 567; The Tupi word ‘Araboutan’ for the
                        Brazil-nut tree is noted on p. 626.</note> On the whole I could not have desired a more favourable reviewal, nor one in which
                    the temper of the reviewer should, in the main, join better with my own. As for what he says concerning a change in my way of
                    thinking, he does not perceive that it is the times that have changed most.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am exceedingly tickled with the notion about Sir John Sinclair – alias Sir John Jackass – &amp; the Black ram in
                    the last article.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was amused by an extremely personal attack, authored by <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">George Ellis</ref>, <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">George Canning</ref> and
                        William Huskisson (1770–1830; <title>DNB</title>), on Sir John Sinclair’s (1754–1835; <title>DNB</title>) <title>Observations
                            on the Report of the Bullion Committee</title> (1810), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 534–535. The
                        review had noted the Berkshire custom that a widow of a customary tenant would forfeit her lifetime rights to her husband’s
                        copyhold land if she remarried or was discovered to be ‘unchaste’. She could reclaim her rights by riding into court seated
                        backwards ‘upon a black ram, with his tail in her hand’ and reciting a doggerel verse. The review suggested that Sinclair
                        atone for his errors on the bullion question by entering the lobby at Whitehall in the same fashion.</note> – My Evangelical
                    article has been hurt by mutilation<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s review of <title>Hints to the Public and the
                            Legislature, on the Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title> (1809), in <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 480–514.</note> – they have marred the whole sarcasm against Sidney Smith<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sydney Smith (1771–1845; <title>DNB</title>), one of the founders of and leading contributors to
                        the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>.</note> by leaving out, I cannot conceive why, the flea-bites, – pray write the words in
                    in <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> copy, – after “crackd him – ” in resentment for the flea-bites of
                    his small wit” – p. 486. <del>&amp;</del> They have also left out what I said about changing the condition of the Clerk, &amp;
                    restoring the old race of Catechists.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the Catholic Church, an assistant to the parish
                        priest, who helps instruct children in the basics of the Church’s teachings.</note> This does not much surprize me, &amp; I
                    shall find a place for it elsewhere, together with a proposal for abolishing the indiscriminate use of sermons, – which of course
                    was too bold to be proposed <del>xx</del> to the Quarterly.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> writes me a very high account indeed of Pasleys<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Charles William Pasley (1780–1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Essay on the Military Policy and
                            Institutions of the British Empire</title> (1810), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5 (May 1811),
                        403–457.</note> book &amp; urges me to review it, – in consequence of which I have written to <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> about it.</p><p rend="indent1"> Thursday last I received the box from Bristol, with 20 volumes from <ref target="people.html#Gutch">Gutch’s</ref>
                    catalogue – Oh there was joy in <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref> at the arrival. And that same evening there
                    came two parcels. I was too <del>xxxxxxx</del> happy, – it was happiness enough for three days. One was from Edinburgh, – a vol.
                    of the Somers Tracts,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Somers, Baron Somers (1651–1716; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A
                            Collection of Scarce and Valuable Tracts</title>, published in 13 volumes from 1809–1815. Southey’s copy was no. 2613 in
                        the sale catalogue of his library.</note> a vol. of <ref target="people.html#HoggJamesEttrick">Hogg the Ettrick
                        Shepherds</ref> poems<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hogg’s <title>The Forest Minstrel: A Collection of
                            Songs</title> (1810).</note> for which I subscribed long since, with a presentation copy &amp; a letter from poor <ref target="people.html#HoggJamesEttrick">Hogg</ref> himself. – The other from <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>
                    containing the Quarterly, &amp; a present from him of three volume of Metrical Romance, just published by Weber,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry William Weber (1783–1818; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Metrical Romances</title> (1810).
                        Southey’s copy was no. 2990 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> a two guineas worth, admirably edited, exceedingly
                    curious, &amp; <del>to xxxx</del> after my own heart. – I have got start enough with <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> to lay the Dutch aside<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. work on the Walcheren Campaign, an
                        unsuccessful British expedition to the Netherlands in 1809. The plan had been to open another front in the war against
                        Napoleon. Although there was little actual fighting, the British forces were severely depleted by a sickness quickly dubbed
                        the ‘Walcheren Fever’. For Southey’s account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 660–692.</note>
                    &amp; take a spell at <ref target="people.html#AbellaManuel">Abella’s</ref> documents, which are very clear &amp; good. – God
                    bless you. Our love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref>. The children have had a good deal of sickness in this
                    unusually sickly time, but they are now recovered God be thanked.</p><closer><signed rend="indent2"> Yrs RS. </signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1810-12-05">Dec. 5. 1810.</date></p><p>Many happy returns to you both. – my love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">Mary</ref>, – &amp; tell the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctor</ref> I am become a convert to his system of drinking beer with pastry –
                            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> still remembers that <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Aunt
                            Tom</ref> used to give her suga-<hi rend="ital">pumm</hi>.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>