<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2364</idno><idno type="nines">rce3635</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 56–58 [in
                        part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2364" type="letter"><head>2364. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1814-01-15">15
                        January 1814</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esqr M.P./ Wynnstay/
                        Wrexham<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 56–58 [in
                        part].</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Wynn</salute></opener><p rend="indent1">One of our poets says A dram of sweet is worth a pound of sour,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund
                        Spenser (1552–1599; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Faerie Queene</title> (1590–1596), Canto 3, stanza 30, line 4.</note> –
                    which if it be not good poetry is sound practical wisdom. I assure you you have gone far towards reconciling me to the Carmen by
                    praising the Dutch stanza, – of which I had conceived the only qualification to be that it was as flat as the country of which it
                    treated, as dead as the water of the ditches, &amp; as heavy astern as the inhabitants.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey’s first official poem as Poet Laureate, published as <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> in a quarto of 30 pages on 1 January
                        1814. Stanza 17 dealt with the Netherlands.</note> How often have I had occasion to remember the old apologia of the Painter
                    who hung up his picture for public criticism! – The conclusion also Laus Deo!<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Praise be
                        to god’.</note> Has found favour in your eyes.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have added three stanzas to the five which were struck out, &amp; made them into a whole, which is gone, <hi rend="ital">sine nomine</hi>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. anonymously.</note> to the Courier; where if the
                        Editor<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Either Daniel Stuart, owner of the <title>Courier</title>, or his associate
                        Thomas George Street (fl. 1796–1827).</note> is not afraid of calling murder &amp; tyranny by their proper names you will be
                    likely to see it sooner than if I were to transcribe the excerpts. The new stanzas are the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> second &amp;
                    seventh: &amp; there has been some little alteration to the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> &amp; 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to fit them into
                    their new place.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Carmen Triumphale</title> was much altered prior to publication. Five
                        stanzas were considered by Croker and Rickman to be inflammatory and were deleted from the published version. Southey incorporated them into a new poem, ‘Ode Written During the Negotiations with
                        Bonaparte’, published in the <title>Courier</title>, 3 February 1814.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> There was another stanza which I <del>would have</del> expunged myself, because it spoke with bitterness of those
                    “who deemed that Spain</p><p rend="indent1"> Would bow her neck before the Intruders throne,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> This did not appear in any
                        published versions of <title>Carmen Triumphale</title>.</note></p><p rend="indent1">&amp; which I should have been sorry to have had &lt;it&gt; applied in a manner to have wounded you: its direction
                    being against the Edinburgh Review. Upon this point your remarks have in no degree <del>expected</del> &lt;affected&gt; my
                    opinion, either as to the propriety of the attack itself, or of the place for it. However rash I may be you will I think allow
                    that my disposition is sufficiently placable; – but it would be absurd to suppose that I should ever receive anything but
                    impertinence &amp; hostility from that quarter. I continued upon courteous terms with <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> till that rascally attack upon the Register in which he recommended it for prosecution. – I speak of it as his
                    tho <ref target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> wrote the passage, – for he made it his own.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> A long aside (attributed by Southey to Brougham) in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 18
                        (August 1811), 420–423n, had questioned whether the ‘virulent personal abuse … levelled at the most respectable members of the
                        Legislature’ in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> was in breach of Parliamentary privilege and hinted that action
                        against the author and publishers might be taken. If it had, Southey, who had written the offending articles, would have been
                        summoned to attend parliament by the serjeant-at-arms (i.e. the chief law enforcement office in the Houses of Parliament). In
                        the event, the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>’s suggestion was not taken up.</note> I know these men feel the scourge, –
                    &amp; they shall fear me as well as hate me. As for the retaliation of which you are apprehensive do you suppose my dear Wynn,
                    that one who has never feard to speak his opinions sincerely can have any fear of being confronted with <del>himself</del> his
                    former self? – I was a republican. I should be so still if I thought we were advanced enough in civilization for such a form of
                    society: &amp; the more my feelings, my judgement, my old prejudices might <del>xxx</del> incline me that way, the deeper <del>of
                        a</del> would necessarily be my hatred of Buonaparte. Do you know that the Anti Jacobine treats my life of Nelson as infected
                    with the leaven of Jacobinism?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Anti-Jacobin Review and Magazine</title>, 45 (July 1813), 83–84: the review of the <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813)
                        had condemned Southey’s sneering references to the ‘“anti-jacobin war”‘ against revolutionary France, reminded readers of his
                        early radicalism and noted ‘So difficult is it to eradicate Jacobinical principles and prejudices, when they have once taken
                        root in the mind!’.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> If I were conscious of having been at any time swayed in the profession of my opinions by private or interested
                    motives, then indeed might I fear what malice could do against me. True it is that I am a Pensioner<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn had arranged for Southey to receive a government pension in 1807.</note> &amp; <del>also</del> Poet
                    Laureat. I owe the pension to you, the Laurel to the Spaniards. Whether the former has prevented me from speaking as I felt upon
                    the measures of Government when I thought myself called upon to speak at all, let my volumes of the Register<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> bear witness. – What a poor hand does
                        Perry<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Perry (1756–1821; <title>DNB</title>), owner and editor of the
                            <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, which had severely criticised Southey’s <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> on 8 January 1814.</note>
                    make in the Chronicle when he sets at the Carmen! Bad as it is I was half tempted to think well of it upon seeing so pityful a
                    criticism. And if he comes to his promised parallelisms with my Inscriptions he will not be more fortunate.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s ‘Inscriptions Triumphal and Sepulchral, recording the acts of the British army in the
                        Peninsula’ had been recently advertised as ‘nearly ready for publication’ (e.g. in <title>European Magazine</title>, 65
                        (January 1814), 77). However, the promised volume did not appear and only 18 of the proposed 30 inscriptions were
                        written.</note> The Whigs who attack me for celebrating our victories in Spain ought to expunge from the list of their toasts
                        <del>the Cause</del> that which gives the Cause of Liberty all the World over. The Inscriptions are for the Battles we have
                    won, &amp; the Towns we have <del>xx x</del> retaken, &amp; epitaphs for those who have fallen, – that is for as many of them as I
                        <del>know</del> can find any thing about, whose rank or ability distinguished them. In my next I will send you some specimens.
                    – Just now I am out of spirits – we have a house full of sickness. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My eldest girl</ref>
                    has had a slight attack of scarlet fever; – it has been very slight, – but if it should spread, the others may not have the
                    disease so favourably. And in her it has been immediately succeeded by a spurious croupe which this Nova Zemblaish weather has
                    made endemic. Three of my children have it at this moment, &amp; tho I believe &amp; have every reason to believe that it is a
                    trifling complaint, still it is so like what is <del>xxx</del> dreadfully dangerous, that I cannot feel at ease.</p><p rend="indent1"> You &amp; I are on the way to a coalition in politics, if the Catholic question were not in the way, &amp;
                        <del>x</del> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Drumdevil or whatever his name may be, with the rest of the Paddies who speak out, may in
                    time make us agree also upon that.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Dromgoole (d. 1824x9?; <title>DNB</title>),
                        Irish doctor and member of the Catholic Board, who vigorously opposed any concessions by Catholics in order to achieve full
                        civil equality. Widely lampooned as ‘Dr Drumsnuffle’.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1814-01-15">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 15. 1814.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>