<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1757</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3028</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850).  Previously  published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 278&#8211;281
                        [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1757" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1757" type="letter">
        <head>1757. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref> [fragment], <date when="1810-03-11">11 March
                        1810</date>
          </head><p>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850)<lb />Previously published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 278&#8211;281
                        [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1810-03-11">March 11. 1810.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your account of the Monthly Review interested me very much.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> An article on
                        the fourth edition of Southey&#8217;s <title>Remains of Henry Kirke White</title> (1808) had criticised both Southey and White and
                        dismissed the latter&#8217;s &#8216;On Being Confined to School&#8217; as showing &#8216;no evidence of extraordinary poetic genius&#8217;, <title>Monthly
                            Review</title>, 61 (January 1810), 71&#8211;84 (esp. 81).</note> If they rest the truth of their criticism upon that school poem
                    in plain, direct, <hi rend="ital">tangible</hi> language, I will most assuredly favour them with a few lines, first through the
                    medium of as many magazines as we can get access to, and ultimately in a note to the Life.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey neither sent a letter to magazines nor added a note to his biography of Henry Kirke White.</note> With regard to my
                    own works, I am a perfect Quaker, and fools and rogues may misrepresent and libel them in perfect security; but upon the subject
                    of <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry</ref>, the M. Review shall find me a very Tartar.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Till you informed me of it, I did not know that <ref target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> had amused himself
                    with lampooning me.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>English Bards and Scotch Reviewers</title> (London, 1809),
                        pp. 17&#8211;18: &#8216;Oh! SOUTHEY, SOUTHEY! cease thy varied song!/A Bard may chaunt too often and too long:/As thou art strong in
                        verse, in mercy spare!/A fourth, alas! were more than we could bear.&#8217;</note> It is safe game, and he may go on till he is
                    tired. Every apprentice in satire and scandal for the last dozen years has tried his hand upon me. I got hold of the
                        Simpliciad<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Mant (1776&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Simpliciad: a
                            Satirico-Didactico Poem</title> (1808). It attacked Southey, Coleridge and Wordsworth as leaders of the &#8216;Anti-Classical
                        School&#8217; of poets.</note> the other day, and wrote as a motto in it these lines, from one of Davenant&#8217;s<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir William Davenant (bap. 1606&#8211;1668; <title>DNB</title>). The quotation is from his <title>The Cruel Brother</title>
                        (1630), Act 1, scene 1, lines 193&#8211;196.</note> plays which I happened to have just been reading: &#8211;</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> Libels of such weak fancy and composure,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> That we do all esteem it greater wrong</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> To have our names extant in such paltry rhyme</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Than in the slanderous sense.</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1"> The manner in which these rhymesters and prosesters misunderstand what they criticise, would be altogether
                    ludicrous, if it did not proceed as often from want of feeling as from want of intellect.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I want your assistance in a business in which I am sure it will interest you to give it. A youth of Bristol, by
                    name <ref target="people.html#RobertsWilliamIsaac">William Roberts</ref>, died of consumption about two years ago, at the age of
                    nineteen. He was employed in a bank, and his salary, 70/. a year (I believe), was materially useful in assisting towards the
                    support of his father<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Roberts (dates unknown). He had been made bankrupt in
                        1793.</note> and mother,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ann Roberts (dates unknown).</note> and a grandmother, and
                    one only sister.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Eliza Roberts (dates unknown).</note> The family had known better days &#8230;
                    and one calamity following another, has reduced them very greatly. Yet still there remains that feeling which, if I call it pride,
                    it is only for want of a better word to express something noble in its nature. <ref target="people.html#RobertsWilliamIsaac">William</ref> was a youth of great genius, and a few days before his death he bequeathed his poems in trust to his two
                    intimate friends to be published for the benefit of his sister, that being all he had to bequeath, and his passionate desire (like
                    that of Chatterton)<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Chatterton (1752&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>), whose works had
                        been edited by Southey in Cottle in 1803 for the benefit of Chatterton&#8217;s sister and niece.</note> was to provide for her. You
                    must remember that at that time he did not foresee the subsequent distresses of his father and mother. These friends were a young
                    physician of the name of <ref target="people.html#HoggEdward">Hogg</ref>, settled somewhere near London, and <ref target="people.html#JamesPaulMoon">James</ref>, a banker of Birmingham, an acquaintance of mine, the author of that sweet poem
                    upon the Otaheitean Girl, of which some stanzas were quoted in the third Quarterly Review.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;The Otaheitan Mourner&#8217;: &#8216;Peggy Stewart, daughter of an Otaheitian Chief, and married to one of the Mutineers of the Bounty.
                        On Stewart&#8217;s being seized and carried away in the Pandora Frigate, Peggy fell into a rapid decay, and in two months died of a
                        broken heart, leaving an infant daughter, who is still living&#8217;, published in <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 26 (December
                        1808), 457&#8211;458. Two stanzas were quoted by Southey in his &#8216;Transactions of the Missionary Societies in the South Sea Islands&#8217;,
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809), 50 n*.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#JamesPaulMoon">James</ref> has arranged the poems and letters of the poor fellow for the press, and will
                    draw up a biographical memoir.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Poems and Letters: by the Late William Isaac Roberts, of Bristol, Deceased; with Some Account of his Life</title>
                        (1811).</note> He has consulted me upon the subject, and the plain statement which I have here made of the circumstances has
                    interested me very deeply &#8230; My opinion is that great things might have been done by <ref target="people.html#RobertsWilliamIsaac">William Roberts</ref>; that every one will acknowledge this; but that his Remains will not obtain a general sale. Of <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry&#8217;s</ref> I foresaw the success as much as such a thing could be foreseen. But <ref target="people.html#RobertsWilliamIsaac">Roberts</ref> has left nothing so good as <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry&#8217;s</ref> best pieces; in fact he died younger, and was precluded from the possibility of advancing himself as <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry</ref> did, in choosing a learned profession because his salary was wanted at home.
                    There is another reason too against their general sale; though he was most exemplary in all his duties, and, as far as I can
                    discover, absolutely without a spot or blemish upon his character, and a regular and sincere churchman, there is nothing of that
                    kind of piety in his writings to which the Remains are mostly indebted for their popularity. &#8230;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My hope is that such a sum may be raised as will be sufficient to place Eliza Roberts in a situation respectably to
                    support herself and her parents. I do not yet know what extent the publication will run to, but as soon as this is settled, I will
                    beg you to <hi rend="ital">beg</hi> subscriptions. &#8230; This whole account is written with such a cautious fear of saying too much,
                    that I fear I have said too little, and may unwittingly have led you to think slightingly of what poor <ref target="people.html#RobertsWilliamIsaac">William Roberts</ref> has left behind him. If I have done this I have done wrong, for
                    certainly he was a youth of great genius and most uncommon promise, which it is my firm belief, founded upon the purity of his
                    life and principles and the rectitude of his feelings, that he would amply have fulfilled, if it had not pleased God to remove him
                    so early from this sphere of existence.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you!</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yours affectionately,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> ROBERT SOUTHEY</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>