<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2409</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3680</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                  1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                  only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                  redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                        Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                  that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                  additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                  all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS 3885. Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey,
               6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 68&#8211;71 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript
               Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
               Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University
               Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
               Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University; the John Rylands Library,
               Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
               Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public
               Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
               Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne;
               the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the English Department of
               Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey&#8217;s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2409" type="letter">
        <head>2409. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, <date when="1814-04-27">27 April
                  1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Scott Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ near/ Melrose<lb />Stamped:
                  KESWICK 298<lb />Endorsement: Southey/ 27 April/ 1814<lb />MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 3885. ALS; 4p.<lb />Previously
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV,
                  pp. 68&#8211;71 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-04-27">April 27. 1814</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Scott</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank God we have seen the end of this long Tragedy of five &amp; twenty years!<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  i.e. the end of the upheaval caused by the French Revolution in 1789. Southey&#8217;s optimism was prompted by the abdication of Napoleon
                  on 6 April 1814 and his exile under the terms of the Treaty of Fontainebleu, 11 April 1814.</note> &#8211; the curtain is fallen, &amp;
               tho there is the after piece of the Devil to pay to be performed, we <del>xxx no expectations</del> have nothing to do with that, &#8211; it
               concerns the performers alone. I wish we had been &lt;within&gt; reach of a meeting upon the occasion. I would not have sung <hi rend="ital">Nunc dimittis</hi>
          <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Luke</title> 2: 29, &#8216;Nunc dimittis servum tuum&#8217;, &#8216;Now lettest thy servant depart&#8217;, expressing the speaker&#8217;s joy at the birth
                  of Christ and that he may now die happy.</note> with you because I hope we shall neither of us be dismissed yet, &#8211; but for an Oh be
                  joyful,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Psalm</title> 100, line 1.</note> I would have been your man. And yet the first feeling was not a joyous one. Too many
               recollections crowded upon the mind, &#8211; &amp; the sudden termination <del>which</del> putting an end at once to those hopes &amp; fears
               &amp; speculations which for many years past have made up so large a part of every mans intellectual existence, &#8211; seemed like a change
               in life itself. Much as I had desired the event &amp; fully as I had expected it, still when it came it brought with &lt;it&gt; an
               aweful sense of the instability of all earthly things, &#8211; &amp; when I remembered that that same newspaper might as probably have
               brought with it intelligence that peace had been made with Buonaparte, I could not but acknowledge that something more uniform in its
               operations than human councils had brought about the event. Well &#8211; God be praised for it. There is a spice of revengefulness in my
               nature which would have been well pleased if the Emperor of Russia<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander I (1777&#8211;1825; Tsar
                  of Russia 1801&#8211;1825).</note> had hanged Buonaparte by way of reprisal for the twelve men at Moscow.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> In September 1812, the French forces occupying Moscow shot 13 men they accused of setting fire to the city and
                  hanged their bodies from lamp-posts.</note> I thought he would set his life upon the last throw, &amp; die game, &#8211; or that he would
               kill himself; &#8211; or that some of his own men would kill him. And tho it had long been my conviction that he was a mean-minded villain,
               still it <del>xxxx</del> surprized me that he should live after such a degradation &#8211; after the loss not merely of empire but even of
               his military <del>xxxxxxxx</del> &lt;character&gt;. But let him live, &#8211; if he will write his own history he will give us all some
               information, &amp; if he will read mine, &#8211; the Devil I think may give him one days holiday if he pleads that as a set off.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I desired <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> to send you the Carmen Triumphale,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s first Laureate ode <title>Carmen Triumphale</title>, published, after much revision, in a
                  quarto of 30 pages on 1 January 1814. Southey&#8217;s letter to Longman requesting a copy appears not to have survived.</note> &#8211; In the
               course of this year I shall volunteer verses enough of this kind to entitle me to a fair dispensation for all task-work
                  &lt;<del>&amp;c</del>&gt; in future. I have made good way thro a poem upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#WalesCharlottePrincess">the Princess&#8217;s</ref> marriage in the olden stile, consisting of three parts the Proem, the
               Dream, &amp; L&#8217;Envoy,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince
                     Regent&#8217;s</ref> only child Charlotte, was engaged to the Hereditary Prince of Orange, William (1792&#8211;1849; King of the Netherlands
                  1840&#8211;1849), the husband selected for her by her father and his advisers. She broke off the engagement in June 1814. Southey&#8217;s poem
                  eventually appeared in 1816 as <title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen Nuptiale</title> (1816), in celebration of Charlotte&#8217;s
                  marriage to Leopold of Saxe Coburg (1790&#8211;1865; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; I am getting on with the series of Military
                  Inscriptions.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey only completed 18 of his planned 30 inscriptions on the heroes and
                  battles of the Peninsular War. They were not collected until the last lifetime edition of his poetical works in 1837&#8211;1838.</note>
               You <del>xx</del> saw perhaps an Ode in the Courier, beginning Who counsels peace &amp;c &amp; if you saw it you would recognize the
               author. It grew out of the castrations of the Carmen.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Ode Written During the Negotiations with
                  Bonaparte&#8217;, published in the <title>Courier</title>, 3 February 1814. This made use of five stanzas Southey had reluctantly removed
                  from <title>Carmen Triumphale</title>.</note> The conclusion of Peace will perhaps require another Ode,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not write an ode celebrating the peace of 1814, but he did produce a series of odes on the Prince
                  Regent; Alexander I; and Frederick William III (1770&#8211;1840; King of Prussia 1797&#8211;1840). The poems were published in book form as
                     <title>Congratulatory Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness The Prince Regent, His Imperial Majesty The Emperor of Russia, and His
                     Majesty the King of Prussia</title> (1814).</note> &amp; I shall then trouble <ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> with a few more notes. As yet I know nothing more of his reply than what some sturdy friend in the Times has
               communicated to me; but I shall not fail to pay all proper attention to it in due season.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  Southey&#8217;s feud with Jeffrey continued unabated. The notes to <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> had attacked the personalities and
                  politics of the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>. The review of the <title>Carmen</title> in <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 22
                  (January 1814), 447&#8211;454, retorted: &#8216;For our own parts, when we are seriously occupied with the destinies of Europe, or of mankind,
                  we should think very contemptibly of ourselves, if we could permit the recollection of our differences with Mr Southey to intrude
                  either into our writings or our thoughts&#8217; (452), before going on to criticise his support of the Spanish and acceptance of the
                  Laureateship. <title>The Times</title>, 7 April 1814 carried an article criticising the <title>Edinburgh</title>&#8217;s remarks; and
                     <title>The Times</title>, 21 April 1814, reprinted the &#8216;Ode Written During the Negotiations with Bonaparte&#8217;, in a corrected
                  version and retitled &#8216;Ode; Written in January, 1814&#8217;. A short headnote again defended Southey against the criticism levelled against
                  him in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>. Southey&#8217;s &#8216;sturdy friend&#8217; was probably John Stoddart (1773&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>),
                  who played a prominent role in <title>The Times</title> until 1817.</note> He may rest assured that I shall pay all my obligations
               to him with compound interest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The uses of newspapers will for awhile seem flat &amp; unprofitable. yet there will be no lack of important matter from
               abroad, &amp; for acrimonious disputes at home we shall always be sure of these. I fear we shall be too liberal in making peace. There
               is no reason why we should make any cessions for pure generosity. It is very true that Louis 18<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis XVIII (1755&#8211;1824; King of France 1814&#8211;1824) ascended the French throne after the abdication of Napoleon Bonaparte.</note>
               has not been our enemy, but the French nation has, &amp; a most <del>xx</del> inveterate &amp; formidable one. They should have
                  <del>Martini</del> their sugar islands,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Martinique and Guadelupe had been captured by
                  British forces in 1809&#8211;1810: both were returned to France in the Treaty of Paris, signed on 30 May 1814.</note> &#8211; but not without
               paying for them, &#8211; &amp; that a good grand sum, to be equally divided between Greenwich &amp; Chelsea,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Royal Hospital, Chelsea (founded 1682) and Royal Naval Hospital, Greenwich (founded 1694) for retired and
                  injured soldiers and sailors, respectively.</note> or to form the foundation of a fund for increasing the pay of army &amp;
               navy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am finishing Roderick,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> &amp; deliberating what subject to take up next, for as it has pleased
               you &amp; the <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> to make me Laureat I am bound to keep up my poetical
               character. If I do not fix upon a tale of Robin Hood,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey eventually collaborated with
                  Caroline Bowles on a romance on the legendary outlaw. It was left unfinished at his death, and a fragment published posthumously in
                  1847.</note> or a New England story connected with Philips War<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> King Philip&#8217;s War, or
                  Metacom&#8217;s Rebellion, 1675&#8211;1676. An armed conflict between English colonists and the native American inhabitants of New England. This
                  formed the backdrop to Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;, left incomplete at his death.</note> &amp; Goffe the Regicide,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Goffe (d. 1679?; <title>DNB</title>), Puritan, regicide and major general, who fled to New
                  England in 1660 after he was excluded from the Act of Indemnity after the Restoration. In Southey&#8217;s poem, he was the father of
                  Oliver Newman.</note> I shall either go far North or far East for scenery &amp; superstitions, &amp; pursue my old scheme of
               mythological delineations. &#8211; Is it not almost time to hear &lt;of&gt; something from you? I remember to have been greatly delighted
               when a boy with Amyntor &amp; Theodora,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> David Mallet [formerly Malloch] (1701/2&#8211;1765;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Amyntor and Theodora, or, The Hermit</title> (1747), a blank verse narrative set on the remote
                  Scottish island of St Kilda.</note> &amp; with Dr Ogilvies Rona,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Ogilvie (1732&#8211;1813;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Rona</title> (1777), a tragedy set on the Hebridean island of the same name.</note> &#8211; the main
               delight must have been from the scenes into which they carried me. There was a rumour that you were among the Hebrides, &#8211; I heartily
               wish it may be true.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">Mrs Scott</ref> &amp; your daughter.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charlotte Sophia Scott (1799&#8211;1837).</note> These children of ours are now growing tall enough
               &amp; intelligent enough to remind me greatly of the lapse of time. Another generation is coming on &#8211; you &amp; I however are not yet
               of the stage, &amp; whenever we quit it, it will not be to men who will make a better figure there.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yrs very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>