<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2560</idno><idno type="nines">rce3831</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42551
                        .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2560" type="letter"><head>2560. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1815-02-25">25 February
                        1815</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle
                        Street/ London <lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: E/ 28 FE 28/ 1815<lb/>Seal: red wax, design illegible<lb/>Watermark:
                        J DICKINSON &amp; Co/ 1811<lb/>Endorsement: 1815 Feb 25/ Southey, Rob<lb/>MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42551
                        <lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1815-02-25">25 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1815</date></dateline><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I return Mr Nuttalls MSS<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British botanist Thomas Nuttall (1786–1859;
                            <title>DNB</title>), who had emigrated to America in 1808. In spring 1811 Nuttall had travelled 1500 miles up the Missouri
                        river, plant collecting in hostile territory. Nuttall kept a journal of some of his travels; see J. E. Graustein (ed.),
                            <title>Nuttall’s Travels Into the Old Northwest: An Unpublished 1810 Diary</title> (1951). He had possibly approached
                        Murray with a view to publication of an account of his 1810 or 1811 expedition. In turn, Murray had sought Southey’s opionion
                        on Nuttall’s MS. Murray did not take Southey’s advice regarding publication.</note> by this mail, &amp; send with it my copy
                    of Bleda<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jayme Bleda (1550–1622), <title>Coronica de Los Moros de Espana</title> (1618);
                        no. 3346 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> for the use of your friend,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> &amp; a small packet for <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Mr Bedford</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Tho the Travels are not all that might be wished they <del>xxx</del> &lt;contain&gt; a great deal of curious
                    information. For my own taste I could wish the writer had been more of a journalist, &amp; given to his narrative that connected
                    interest which the recital of personal adventure can hardly fail to excite. But physical science is his favourite pursuit, &amp;
                    upon these things, I who know nothing, take it for granted that every man who writes at all writes with a competent knowledge of
                    his subject. A very considerable part of the book is thus <del>occupied</del> filled.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> In
                        1818 Nuttall published the pioneering <title>Genera of North American Plants, and a Catalogue of the Species, to the Year
                            1817</title>.</note> He has added a great deal to what Lewis &amp; Clarke told us,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Meriweather Lewis (1774–1809) and William Clark (1770–1838), <title>Travels to the Source of the Missouri River, and Across
                            the American Continent to the Pacific Ocean</title> (1814), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12
                        (January 1815), 317–368.</note> as far as his travels extended; &amp; possesses all that science which they wanted. On the
                    whole I should say that, tho not a first-rate book of travels, it is well worthy of publication</p><p rend="indent1"> Thank you for Gibbon,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A five volume edition of Edward Gibbon (1737–1794;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Miscellaneous Works: With Memoirs of His Life and Writings</title>, published by Murray in
                        1814; no. 1100 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> the E Indian Gazetteer<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Hamilton (bap. 1774, d. 1828; <title>DNB</title>), <title>East India Gazetteer</title> (1815); no. 1274
                        in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> &amp;c- &amp;c. The portrait of Gibbon which the Preface announces, is
                        wanting.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of the <title>Miscellaneous Works</title> (1814) was
                        supposed to contain a portrait of Gibbon as a frontispiece.</note> It may come in one of your next parcel, when you happen to
                    think of it, – &amp; likewise, if you please, the <hi rend="ital">third</hi> volume of the Somers Tracts.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Somers, Baron Somers (1651–1716; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Collection of Scarce and Valuable
                            Tracts</title>, edited by Walter Scott and published in 13 volumes from 1809–1815. Southey’s copy was no. 2613 in the sale
                        catalogue of his library.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The Jews &amp; the Catholics will both form prominent parts of the article upon Gregoires book,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henri Gregoire (1750–1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuses</title> (1810), reviewed by
                        Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), 1–46.</note> for which I have read largely, &amp; which is only
                    laid aside for Wellington<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed George Elliott (dates unknown), <title>The
                            Life of the Most Noble Arthur Duke of Wellington, from the Period of his first Achievements in India, down to his Invasion
                            of France, and the Peace of Paris in 1814</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815),
                        215–275.</note> &amp; Egypt, Egypt, in consequence of Miots second edition<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jacques
                        François Miot (1779–1858), <title>Mémoires pour servir à l’Histoire des Expéditions en Egypte et en Syrie</title> (1814).
                        Southey reviewed Miot in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 1–55.</note> having a sort of temporary interest,
                    which any lapse of time might <del>at</del> some degree abate.</p><p rend="indent1"> This young soldier is met with in happy time;<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> – it is
                    a piece of good fortune which I have always thought likely to turn up. In making out a list of subjects it would be necessary to
                    know what number of prints you would determine on. As for any <hi rend="ital">historical</hi> prints as they are called, &amp;
                    views of battles, they must of necessity be either so false, or so imperfect, that the book is better without them. <hi rend="ital">Plans</hi> of the great battles will doubtless be required, – these may all be obtained from the War office,
                    (indeed I have most of them) &amp; may perhaps like those of the War office, be as well &amp; more economically given in
                    stone-etching than in any other way. For views I should like a good head-piece to every chapter, better than a few large prints;
                    &amp; tail-pieces of costume (which might perhaps be more conveniently executed in wood) to be placed where the end of a chapter
                    happened to afford room for them.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> This paragraph and the remainder of the letter deals
                        with Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> With the regard to portraits, it will I suppose be indispensable that <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> should stand as a frontispiece to the book which records
                    his progress to a Dukedom well-deserved. But after giving him a whole copper to himself, may we not, <del>xxx xxx xx xxx xx</del>,
                    arrange several heads upon one plate, connected in some tasteful way, as in Bowyer’s Hume?<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Bowyer (1758–1834; <title>DNB</title>), miniature painter, who published a lavish illustrated edition of part of
                        David Hume’s (1711–1776; <title>DNB</title>) <title>History of England</title> in 5 folios (1793–1806). As this venture was
                        said to have lost £30,000 it was not, perhaps, the best example for Southey to use when presenting his project to
                        Murray.</note> In that case one plate might hold Sir J. Moore, Generals Hill, Grahame &amp; Beresford, &amp; perhaps Crawford
                    &amp; Mackinnon<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The following British generals: Sir John Moore (1761–1809;
                            <title>DNB</title>), commander of the retreat to Corunna in 1809; Rowland Hill, 1st Viscount Hill (1772–1842;
                            <title>DNB</title>); Thomas Graham, Baron Lydenoch (1748–1843; <title>DNB</title>); William Carr Beresford, 1st Viscount
                        Beresford (1768–1854; <title>DNB</title>); Robert Craufurd (1764–1812; <title>DNB</title>); and Henry MacKinnon (1773–1812;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> who both fell at Ciudad Rodrigo. Of Spaniards, the old King &amp; Queen, Ferdinand, the Prince
                    of Peace, (I have a print of him) – Jovellanos (a bust of him is at <ref target="places.html#HollandHouse">Holland House</ref>) – Palafox, Mina &amp; <del>xx</del> the
                        Empecinado.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The following figures: Charles IV (1748–1819; King of Spain 1788–1808);
                        Maria Luisa of Parma (1751–1819), wife of Charles IV; Ferdinand VII (1784–1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813–1833); Manuel
                        Francisco Domingo de Godoy y Alvarez de Faria, Prince of the Peace (1767–1851), First Secretary of Spain 1792–1798 and the
                        dominating force in its political life until 1808; Gaspar Melchor de Xove y Llanos (1744–1811), Spanish author and statesman,
                        who was imprisoned by Godoy 1801–1808; General Jose Rebolledo de Palafox (1780–1847); Francisco Espoz y Mina (1781–1836),
                        guerrilla leader; and Juan Martin Diez, ‘el Empecinado’ (‘the undaunted’) (1775–1825), guerrilla leader.</note> The Portugueze
                    who supplied such excellent men, gives us I think but one officer prominent enough for selection – which is Silveira,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Silveira, Conde de Amarante (1763–1821), Portuguese military leader.</note> &amp; they
                    will be woefully offended at any apparent disrespect. So let us have Silveira &amp; the Prince of Brazil.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> John VI (1767–1826), Prince Regent of Portugal 1799–1816, King of Portugal 1816–1826.</note> Two plates might
                    hold all these; one a royal one with the Prince of Peace, whom it would be a pity to divorce from the old King &amp; Queen, &amp;
                    Jovellanos with some emblem of captivity about him, to shew that he was their victim; the other might contain the four military
                    men, to whom we might add, if portraits are procurable Romana, Alburquerque, Blake &amp; Castaños.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The following Spanish military leaders: Pedro Caro y Sureda, 3rd Marquis of la Romana (1761–1811); Jose Miguel
                        de la Cueva, 13th Duke of Alburquerque (1774–1811); Joaquin Blake y Joyes (1759–1827); Francisco Javier Castanos
                        (1758–1852).</note> If there be any Frenchmen they should be Junot, Soult, Victor, Massena, Marmont, Jourdan, Suchet &amp;
                    King Joseph<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The following French military leaders: General Jean-Andoche Junot
                        (1771–1813); Marshal Nicolas Jean-de-Dieu Soult (1769–1851); Marshal Claude Victor-Perrin (1764–1841); Marshal Andre Massena
                        (1758–1817); Marshal Jean-Baptiste Jourdan (1762–1833); Marshal Louis Gabriel Suchet (1770–1826); and Joseph Bonaparte
                        (1768–1844; King of Spain 1808–1813).</note> himself, all of whom Wellington has beaten in succession, – &amp; all of whom may
                    show their faces out of one pillory.</p><p rend="indent1"> The views of most importance are Zaragoza, Gerona, <del>xxxxx</del>, Ciudad Rodrigo, Badajoz, Coruña, Valencia,
                    Cadiz, Salamanca, Victoria, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Sebastians, Pamplona, Burgos, Busaco, Talavera, Porto; – if you determine upon
                    having vignettes I would then add to the list, The Buen Retiro at Madrid, Aranjuez, the Escorial, Belem (from whence the Prince of
                    Brazil embarked) Hostatrich, Barcelona, Astorza, Bayonne, Santarem, the Bridges of Amarante, S Payo, &amp; Almarez, Tarragona,
                    Alcobaça; &amp; some of the passes which it is not possible that I can point out but which may easily be selected from the
                    soldier-article portfolios. The Puente del Corcul would give a good idea of the country thro which Sir J Moore fled: Neale<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had visited this spot in 1795, <title>Letters Written During a Short Residence in
                            Spain and Portugal</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp. 54–55. He had pointed out that the bridge had three arches, not four, in
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 452, thus correcting Adam Neale (1778?-1832;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Letters from Portugal and Spain</title> (1809), p. 305, an account of the retreat to Corunna
                        by one of the participants.</note> has a print of it, which according to my note made on the spot, &amp; a sketch which I
                    possess is incorrect in the number of arches. As he was in a greater hurry than we were I have no doubt that the inaccuracy is on
                    his part. – </p><p rend="indent1"> I shall wait for Egypt the first Receuil which L. Goldsmith published of Buonapartes Manifestos Proclamations
                    &amp;c; &amp; the last volume for Spain you know I have the intermediate four.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lewis
                        Goldsmith (1763/4?-1846; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Recueil de Decrets, Ordonnances, Traites de Paix etc de Napoleon
                            Bonaparte depuis 1799</title>, 5 vols (1813–1815), no. 1118 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> believe me my dear Sir yours very truly</salute><signed rend="indent1"> R Southey</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>