<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2407</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3678</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos,
                            The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 130&#8211;133; and Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 65&#8211;68 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2407" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2407" type="letter">
        <head>2407. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1814-04-25">25 April 1814</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 28AP28/ 1814; [partial] 10o AP.28/ 1814F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Watermark: C Wilmott/
                        1807<lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 171 1814/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April/rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        June<lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos,
                            <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 130&#8211;133; and Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 65&#8211;68 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-04-25">April 25. 1814</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If the King of France<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis XVIII (1755&#8211;1824; King of France
                        1814&#8211;1824).</note> has any stray cordon bleu to dispose of here is <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Herbert</ref>
                    has a fair claim to one, having been the first person in G Britain who mounted the white cockade.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Symbolic of support for the restoration of the Bourbon dynasty.</note> He appeared with one immediately upon
                    the news from <del>xxxxxxxxxx</del> Bourdeaux, &amp; wore it till the news from Paris,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Louis XVIII had first been proclaimed King in France at Bordeaux on 12 March 1814. Paris was occupied on 30 March and Napoleon
                        abdicated on 6 April 1814.</note> &#8211; my young ones were then all <del>xx</del> as happy as paper-cockades could make them,
                    &amp; to our great amusement all the white ribband in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> was bought up to follow
                    their example. &#8211; My own feelings on the first intelligence were unlike any thing that I ever experienced before, or can experience
                    again. The curtain had fallen after a tragedy of five &amp; twenty years; &#8211; those persons who had rejoiced most enthusiastically
                    at the beginning of the revolution were now deeply thankful for a termination which restored things as nearly as can be to
                        <del>their</del> the state from which they set out; &#8211; <del>&amp;</del> what I said with a voice of warning to my own country
                    is here historically true that &#8220;all the intermediate sum of misery is but the bitter price which folly pays for repentance.&#8221;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 10 (October 1813), 93. In its original context, Southey warns against the &#8216;moral and
                        religious anarchy&#8217; that would ensue if &#8216;the [Anglican] Church Establishment should &#8230; be overthrown&#8217;.</note> The mass of
                    destruction, of wretchedness &amp; of ruin which that revolution has occasioned is beyond all calculation, &#8211; our conception of it
                    is almost as vague &amp; inadequate as of infinity. This however occurred to me at the time less than my own individual history,
                    for I could not &lt;but&gt; remember how materially the course of my own life had been influenced by that tremendous earthquake,
                    which seemed to break up the great deeps of society, like a moral &amp; political deluge. I have derived nothing but good from it
                    in every thing, except <del>perhaps</del> the mere consideration of immediate worldly fortune, &#8211; which is to me as dust in the
                    balance. Sure I am that under any other course of discipline I should <del>neither</del> &lt;not&gt; have possessed half the
                    intellectual powers which I now enjoy, &#8211; &amp; perhaps neither the moral strength, nor the self respect. <del>without especial
                        favours</del> The hopes &amp; the ardour &amp; the errors &amp; the struggles &amp; the difficulties of my early life crowded
                    upon my mind, &#8211; &amp; above all there was a deep &amp; grateful sense of that superintending Goodness which had made all things
                    work together for good in my fortunes, &amp; will I firmly believe in like manner uniformly <del>upon the great scale</del> educe
                    good from evil upon the great scale of human events.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I fear we shall make a bad peace. Hitherto the people have borne on their <del>le</del> Governors, &#8211; (I except
                    Prussia where Prince<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frederick William III (1770&#8211;1840; King of Prussia 1797&#8211;1840).</note>
                    &amp; People have been worthy of each other) &#8211; the Rulers are now left to themselves, &amp; I apprehend consequences which will
                    fall heavy upon posterity tho not perhaps upon ourselves. I had rather the French Philosophy had left any other of its blessings
                    behind it than its <hi rend="ital">candour</hi> &amp; its <hi rend="ital">liberality</hi>. It was very natural that the Emperor of
                        Austria<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis I (1768&#8211;1835; Holy Roman Emperor 1792&#8211;1806; Emperor of Austria
                        1804&#8211;1835).</note> should not chuse to have his son in law<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Napoleon Bonaparte, whose
                        second wife was Marie-Louise (1791&#8211;1847), daughter of Emperor Francis I.</note> hanged, or broken upon the wheel, &#8211; which
                    would have been his appropriate death. But here is Alexander<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander I (1777&#8211;1825;
                        Emperor of Russia 1801&#8211;1825).</note> breakfasting with Marshall Ney<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Michel Ney
                        (1769&#8211;1815), Marshal of France. He had played a key role in the French campaigns in the Iberian peninsular in 1808&#8211;10, but in
                        April 1814 had been instrumental in forcing Napoleon to abdicate. <title>The Times</title>, 21 April 1814, reported Alexander I
                        had breakfasted with Ney on 16 April.</note> who if he had more necks than the hydra or <del>than</del> my Jaggernaut,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), Book 14, lines 82&#8211;84, where the idol of &#8216;Jaga-Naut&#8217; is described as a snake with
                        seven heads.</note> owes them all to the gallows for his <del>xxxxxxxx</del> &lt;conduct&gt; in Galicia &amp; in Portugal.
                        Caulaincourt<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French general and diplomat Armand-Augustin-Louis de Caulaincourt
                        (1773&#8211;1827). Minister of Foreign Affairs 1813&#8211;14 and March-June 1815. He was French Ambassador to Russia 1807&#8211;11. Caulaincourt
                        might have needed asylum in Russia because of his alleged involvement in the capture and execution of the Duc d&#8217;Enghien
                        (1772&#8211;1804) in 1804.</note> is to have an asylum in Russia &#8211; &amp; no doubt will be permitted to
                    chuse his latitude there. <hi rend="ital">Candour</hi> is to make us impute all the enormities which the French have committed to
                    Buonaparte, all the horrors, absolutely unutterable as they are which you know were perpetrated in Portugal, &amp; which I know
                    were perpetrated in Spain &#8211; but which I literally cannot detail in history &#8211; because I dare not outrage human nature &amp; common
                    decency by such details, &#8211; all these must in <hi rend="ital">candour</hi> be put out of remembrance; &#8211; all was Buonapartes doing,
                    &#8211; &amp; the most amiable of nations were his victims rather than his agents: &#8211; so this most voracious of nations tell us, &amp; so
                    we are to believe. But if the Devil could not have brought about all these crimes without the Emperor Napoleon, neither could the
                    Emperor <del>of</del> Napoleon have discharged the Devils commission without the most amiable of nations to act up to the full
                    scope of his diabolical desires. &#8211; It is not the individual, it is the national character which ought to be held up to
                    execration.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At present, I admit, our business is to conciliate, &amp; consolidate the counter revolution. But no visitings to
                    Marshall Ney, &#8211; no compliments to his worthy colleagues, &#8211; no asylums for the murderers of the Duc d&#8217;Enghien,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Antoine de Bourbon, Duc d&#8217;Enghien (1772&#8211;1804). A relative of the Bourbons, he took a
                        prominent part in campaigns by French &#233;migr&#233;s against the Revolutionary government. In March 1804 he was kidnapped from his
                        home in Germany and convicted by a French military tribunal of involvement in a recent royalist plot, even though the French
                        government knew he was innocent of the charges. He was shot on 21 March 1804. Caulaincourt was accused of being implicated in
                        the Duc&#8217;s kidnap &#8211; a charge he vigorously denied.</note> no revenue of 240,000 &#163; a year <del>as a</del> instead of a dungeon
                    &amp; dungeon fare for the foulest of all tyrants.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Treaty of Fontainebleu, signed on
                        11 April 1814, allowed Napoleon an annual pension of two million francs.</note> &#8211; In treating for peace liberality will not
                    fail to be urged by the French negociators as a reason for granting them terms which are inconsistent with the welfare of Europe:
                    &#8211; Alexander is a weak man, tho a good one; &#8211; &amp; our ministers will be <del>more</del> better pleased to hear themselves called
                        <hi rend="ital">liberal</hi> by the opposition, &#8211; than to be called <del>xx</del> wise by after ages. There is the peace of
                        Utrecht<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Treaty of Utrecht (1713) ended the long-running War of the Spanish
                        Succession. It was widely-criticised in Britain for being too lenient to the French.</note> before <del>th</del> our eyes. The
                    mischief which was done then, ought to be <del>done</del> &lt;undone&gt; now. I am very ready to give up colonies which are better
                    in the hands of the French than in ours, for the weal of the inhabitants themselves, &#8211; but it should be in return for continental
                    cessions on their part, they should <del>cede</del> &lt;be stript of&gt; Alsace Lorrain &amp; Franche-Comte. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This topic has led me on so far that little room is left for any thing else. There was nothing of mine in the last
                    Quarterly, &#8211; there might have been two short articles upon <ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomerys</ref> World
                    before the Flood,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Montgomery, <title>The World Before the Flood</title> (1813),
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 11 (April 1814), 78&#8211;87.</note> &amp; the Nicobar Isles.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Johann Gottfried Haensel (1749&#8211;1814), <title>Letters on the Nicobar Islands</title> (1812), <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 11 (April 1814), 57&#8211;72.</note> I am reviewing the collection of the poets by Chalmers,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander Chalmers (1759&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of the English Poets, from
                            Chaucer to Cowper</title> (1810), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 11 (July 1814), 480&#8211;504; and <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 12 (October 1814), 60&#8211;90.</note> &amp; about to take the Reports of your Society for bettering the Poor as
                    an excellent text, which will enable me to preach upon real, radical &amp; practicable reform.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Society for Bettering the Condition and Increasing the Comforts of the Poor. The essay was a long time in
                        gestation, eventually appearing as &#8216;The Poor&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 187&#8211;235. It attracted a great
                        deal of attention and was reprinted in Southey&#8217;s <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title>, 2 vols (London, 1832), II, pp.
                        159&#8211;247.</note> To this subject I am now girding up my loins. &#8211; I hope to do some good by it, &#8211; &amp; this reconciles me to
                    the necessity of employments which certainly as you will remark interrupt me in the progress of greater &amp; more important
                    works. I sincerely wish I could have continued the Register<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register</title>.</note> up to this period, &amp; perhaps it will one day be wished that this work had met with a better
                    sale, in which case the booksellers would have got money, &amp; I should not have lost the <del>of my labours</del> continued my
                    labour fatiguing as it was, &#8211; the defalcation in my revenue is very great, but it is only for a time &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> has promised fair, &amp; cannot break those promises <del>other</del>
                    without exposing himself as well as <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">his brother</ref> to a loss of character, which I
                    think he would not venture upon, &amp; a loss of custom with me as his printing business, which it is certainly his interest to
                    preserve. He asked for time &#8211; &amp; I wish the time were come, &#8211; part of this money having long been destined to be remitted to
                    you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. We are all well. Remember us to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        May</ref>. The Walpole<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Walpole (1736&#8211;1810), Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                        Plenipotentiary to Portugal, 1771&#8211;1800. Southey had promised to consider writing his biography.</note> papers will be three
                    weeks on the way. I shall set about them when they arrive. RS.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>