<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2163</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3434</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS
                    192.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2163" type="letter">
        <head>2163. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1812-10-25">25 October
                        1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS. 25 Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ 1812<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS
                    192<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1812-10-25">Oct 25. 1812. </date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> First I must thank you for your synopsis Parl: Proc: &#8211; I am in the middle of the mess, &#8211; busy to day with
                    Commercial Credit (about which I have something to say to the purpose) &#8211; Bullion follows &#8211; where my business must be cut the
                        <del>business</del> &lt;matter&gt; as short as I can, &amp; to take <del>care</del> especial care of not talking nonsense upon
                    a subject which has puzzled heads fitter for such discussions than mine.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The sections
                        mentioned here appeared in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 89&#8211;114. The question of whether
                        to restore the convertibility of paper money into gold was hotly-contested.</note> I am in the press &amp; four sheets out of
                    it, &#8211; meaning to publish in April, &#8211; for the good of the work, &amp; in the hope of seeing you in May.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have got possession of good MSS documents about Sicily<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> For his account of
                        events in Sicily, see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 422&#8211;437. Southey was provided with &#8216;two
                        letters&#8217; on this subject by Neville White; see Southey to Neville White, 27 September 1812, Letter 2151.</note> &#8211; &amp; about
                    Buenos Ayres.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had borrowed the unpublished journal of the merchant Thomas Kinder
                        (c. 1781&#8211;1846), who had witnessed at first-hand the events in Buenos Ayres in 1808&#8211;1810 that led to the independence of the
                        states of the Rio de la Plata. (In 1813 Southey had a copy made of the journal, no. 3162 in the sale catalogue of his library.
                        The copy was published as, Malyn Newitt (ed.), <title>War, Revolution and Society in the Rio de la Plata 1808&#8211;1810. Thomas
                            Kinder&#8217;s Narrative of a Journey to Madeira, Montevideo and Buenos Ayres</title> (2010).) Kinder had also lent Southey &#8216;a
                        volume of Noticias del Paraguay, and the prose Argentina, both in manuscript&#8217;, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols
                        (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, p. [v]. For Southey&#8217;s account of the revolution in Buenos Ayres, see <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 395&#8211;421.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Since the burning of Moscow I begin to have hopes of Russia.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Soon after
                        French troops entered Moscow on 14 September 1812 the city was in flames. It was widely assumed that the Russians had
                        deliberately burnt the city.</note> The people there are in a very untractable state for a conqueror, &amp; if Buonaparte does
                    not speedily give his army the slip &amp; <del>return to F</del> get into better quarters himself, he may find himself worse off
                    than he did in Egypt. What is Sweden about? at any rate pursuing a dilatory policy which in such times is a bad one.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> France had forced Sweden to declare war on Britain on 17 November 1810, but the Swedes had
                        refused to take any military action. The <hi rend="ital">de facto</hi> ruler of Sweden was Jean Bernadotte (1763&#8211;1844; King of
                        Sweden as Charles XIV 1818&#8211;1844), a former Marshal of Napoleon, who had been appointed Crown Prince in 1810. Despite his
                        former allegiance, Bernadotte was moving Sweden towards alliance with the anti-French forces and on 18 July 1812 Sweden and
                        Britain made peace in the Treaty of Orebro.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> is plagued with incapable Generals. Clinton<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British officer Henry Clinton (1771&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>).</note> whom he left at Cueller
                    let the French march back to Astorga &#8211; twelve hours earlier they would have brought off that garrison, &#8211; &amp; they did bring off
                    their garrisons from Torr &amp; Zamora; Maitland<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British general Frederick Maitland
                        (1763&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>). He had landed at Alicante in August 1812 with an army from Sicily, but achieved little and
                        resigned his command in November 1812.</note> has manifestly either put himself in the wrong place, or acted clumsily when he
                    got there; if it was not his object to prevent Soult<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicolas Jean-de-Dieu Soult, 1st Duke
                        of Dalmatia (1769&#8211;1851), overall commander of the French forces in Spain and Portugal.</note> from joining Suchet,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Gabriel Suchet, 1st Duc d&#8217;Albufera (1770&#8211;1826), Marshal of France and key figure in the
                        French campaign in the Iberian peninsula. He had captured Valencia in January 1812.</note> he ought to have landed in
                    Catalonia. If Donkin, who I think is second in command, be as I believe he is my old play fellow Rufan Donkin, he has some brains
                    in his head, &amp; is of a very odd breed on the one side, but <del>a very</del> one very likely to produce something good.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s erstwhile schoolfellow Rufane Shaw Donkin (1773&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>). He
                        was the son of General Robert Donkin (1726/7&#8211;1821) and of Mary, the daughter of the Revd Emanuel Collins. Collins was the
                        Vicar of Bedminster in Somerset in the mid-18th century and had scandalised local society by running a public house, &#8216;The Duke
                        of Marlborough&#8217;, conducting clandestine marriages for money and lampooning his neighbours in verse. Donkin was a career army
                        officer. He served as quarter-master general on the east cost of Spain from 1810&#8211;1813 and in 1811 was promoted to the rank of
                        Major-General.</note> &#8211; If Hill<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British general Rowland Hill, 1st Viscount Hill
                        (1772&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>), commander of the forces south of Madrid.</note> should have a battle to fight there will be
                        Ballasteros<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Ballesteros (1770&#8211;1832), one of the Spanish commanders in the
                        south of Spain.</note> to help him, &amp; to join in the pursuit.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Supposing Soult either afraid to attack Hill, or to be defeated by him, I apprehend <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> when he has compleated his dear purchase at Burgos, will
                    push for Vittoria, break up the depot there, &amp; then strike down upon Zaragoza, leaving Mina<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Espoz y Mina (1781&#8211;1836), since 1810 he had been commander of the guerrilleros of Navarre against
                        French troops.</note> &amp; Santocildes<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jose Maria Santocildes (1771&#8211;1847), Spanish
                        general, who had re-captured Astorga in August 1812.</note> to blockade Pamplona. &#8211; I should think some of these strong places
                    might be <hi rend="ital">bought</hi>, if the thing were set about properly, &amp; it would be oeconomical to pay a high price for
                    them. A Frenchman has now no honour to stand in the way of the bargain, &amp; it would from other causes be still easier to deal
                    with an Italian.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have begun an article for <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> about the Poor, the object of which
                    is to set off what has been done, &amp; is <del>going</del> doing towards the improvement of the lower orders &amp; bettering
                    their condition against the wretched generalities of the Agitators.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of
                        Patrick Colquhoun (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Propositions for ameliorating the Condition of the Poor: and For
                            Improving the Moral Habits, and Increasing the Comforts of the Labouring People</title> (1812), appeared in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356. Rickman had had some input, probably supplying notes and
                        ideas.</note> But at the very outset I <del>want</del> find myself in want of <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Pooles</ref> sum total of persons receiving parish pay &amp; of members of benefit societies. Will you send me these numbers,
                    &amp; also tell me what proportion of the community are capable of bearing arms.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will have the Omniana<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Omniana: or Horae Otiosiores</title> (1812).</note> next week I trust. The Life of Nelson is printing, &#8211; I have
                    corrected five proofs &#8211; <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> supplies plans of the three great battles for it.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> No battle plans appeared in the <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813). The biography,
                        commissioned by Murray, was a development of an article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218&#8211;262.</note>
                    I am trying through <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> to get <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my
                        brother</ref> either a ship, &#8211; or the next step, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> does not want
                    inclination to do me this service. Oh that he had been in the place of that blockhead of a boy in the Guerriere!<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British frigate HMS <title>Guerriere</title> had been captured and destroyed in battle
                        against the USS <title>Constitution</title> on 19 August 1812. The &#8216;boy&#8217; was her captain, James Richard Dacres (1788&#8211;1854),
                        who was from a famous naval family and had enjoyed rapid promotion. He rose to be a Vice-Admiral by the time of his
                        retirement.</note> a vile business, the effect of which nothing but the extinction of the Yankee navy can counteract.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I believe I must drop the Quarterly as soon as my engagements to it are discharged &#8211; else I shall never be able to
                    compleat my own historical works. This Register is as much as I ought to d[MS torn] task work.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Can you tell me any thing of the Committee of Taste who decide upon the designs sent in for public monuments?<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Committee for the Inspection of the Models for National Monuments (popularly known as
                        the &#8216;Committee of Taste&#8217;) had been established by parliament in 1802. Its purpose was to commission the design for public
                        monuments to national heroes, or on great national events, especially in St Pauls Cathedral and Westminster Abbey. It was
                        mainly made up of politicians rather than artists.</note> They are precious judges, &amp; indeed Parliament on these things
                    proceeds very absurdly. <del>By putting up</del> &lt;When&gt; these things &lt;are put up&gt; to competition, the best artists
                    hold back, not chusing to start for a prize, when the race is not to be to the swift, but the prize adjudged by men who are not
                    competent judges. An inferior artist on the contrary sends in several designs, upon the doctrine of chances. I heard a good
                    anecdote of one of the naval monuments &#8211; Ross<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Charles Felix Rossi (1762&#8211;1839;
                            <title>DNB</title>). Southey is probably referring to his design for the monument to Admiral George Bridges Rodney, 1st
                        Baron Rodney (1718&#8211;1792) in St Pauls Cathedral, sculpted in 1811&#8211;1815, which is flanked by figures representing Clio, the Muse
                        of History, and Victory.</note> (I think the sculptors name is) sent in several designs; the Committee pitched upon what he
                    thought the worst of them; sent for him, &#8211; admired one figure in this design which was on the side of the monument, &#8211; &amp;
                    desired him to place <del>xxx</del> exactly such another on the other side, &#8211; &amp; there the pair of figures stand
                    accordingly!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am looking for an increase of family in the course of a fortnight.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref> was born in November 1812.</note> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref> How did you fare the other day when old Thames was
                    attempting a radical reform in your neighbourhood, &amp; cleansing Westminster Hall, a-la-Hercules.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The comparison is between the flooding of Westminster Hall (part of the complex at the Palace of Westminster)
                        by the river Thames and Hercules&#8217;s cleansing of the Augean stables by rerouting the rivers Alpheus and Peneus.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharp</ref> &amp; Curwen<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> At the 1812 general
                        election, the wealthy colliery owner John Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>) had refused to stand for the
                        Carlisle seat he had held for 21 years. He did not return to parliament until 1816.</note> both <del>xxx</del> &lt;whisper&gt;
                    this damnable report about the D. of C. &amp; Sellis.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Ernest Augustus (1771&#8211;1851;
                            <title>DNB</title>), fifth son of George III and later King of Hanover 1837&#8211;1851. On 31 May 1810 the Duke&#8217;s valet, Joseph
                        Sellis, was found with his throat cut in Cumberland&#8217;s apartment at St James&#8217;s Palace. It was widely believed that the Duke had
                        murdered Sellis to prevent him revealing scandalous details about Cumberland&#8217;s private life &#8211; both incest and homosexuality
                        were rumoured.</note> Curwen lost his election solely because he could not stand election-stories. Urbi pater est urbique
                        maritus<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Father and husband to all the city&#8217;; Lucan (AD 39&#8211;65),
                            <title>Pharsalia</title>, Book 2, line 388.</note> being told of him in half the towns of the county. Moreover there is
                    some scandal about him &amp; the Bp. of Landaffs daughter, which he could not face.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Curwen was rumoured to have refused to stand for election because of gossip concerning his seduction of Dorothy Watson
                        (1777&#8211;1837), eldest daughter of Richard Watson (1737&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Llandaff, who owned a substantial
                        estate at Calgarth on the shore of Lake Windermere.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>