<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2386</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3657</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2386" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2386" type="letter">
        <head>2386. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, [<date when="1814-03-08">started before
                        and continued on] 8 March 1814</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Postmarks: 10 o&#8217;Clock/ MR 11/ 1814 FNn; E/ 11 MR 11/ 1814<lb />Seal: Black wax, arm holding a cross of
                        Lorraine<lb />Watermark: 1807<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have transcribed the Ode<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Ode Written During the Negotiations with
                        Bonaparte&#8217;, published in the <title>Courier</title>, 3 February 1814. This used stanzas deleted from Southey&#8217;s first Laureate
                        poem <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> prior to its publication in a quarto of 30 pages on 1 January 1814. The remainder of the
                        first paragraph deals with these changes.</note> for you, &amp; by means of a double inclosure franked it up to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, that he may send it by the three penny post. The two first stanzas
                    &amp; the last but one are additions made when the excerpts were formed into a whole, &amp; the beginning of the third st. was
                    added to connect it. In the original the third stanza ran thus</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> Dread was the strife for mighty was the foe</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Who sought with his whole strength their overthrow</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Foremost upon the stage of blood &amp;c.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>&amp; so it went till the line</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> No counsellor but his own wicked heart &#8211; </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">which is now transposed, &#8211; but then came in immediately before &#8216;The nations bowd before him. The uncastrated poem
                    instead of the last stanza as it now stands was turned off to France with A curse is on thee &#8211; &amp; so on to the end. Perhaps
                    they are better as two poems than as one, &#8211; but you will see that this is very far the best.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Coimbra Journal<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Jornal de Coimbra</title> (1812&#8211;1820); Southey eventually acquired an eight-volume set, no. 3498 in the sale catalogue
                        of his library.</note> has supplied me with the list on the following leaf. The Rio Janeiro Journal<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>O Patriota. Jornal Litterario, Politico, Mercantil &amp;c. do Rio de Janeiro</title> (1813&#8211;1814); no. 3641 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> is announced as selling in Lisbon at the same price as at the Rio. There are some
                    travellers journals in it, &amp; some historical papers upon the mines. The Coimbra J. has some admirable statistic accounts. It
                    has also a minute &amp; curious journal of the late Bp. of Para, during his Visitations, giving incidentally good information
                    respecting the state of the country.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The diocese of Belem do Para in Brazil was founded in
                        1720. Its &#8216;late Bp.&#8217; was Cayetano Da Annunciacao Brandao (1740&#8211;1805), who was Bishop of Belem do Para 1782&#8211;1790, before
                        becoming Archbishop of Braga in Portugal 1790&#8211;1805. His journal of a visitation in his diocese in 1784 appeared in
                            <title>Jornal de Coimbra</title>, 17 (May 1813), 19&#8211;55.</note> &#8211; I have lately been making way in my second volume<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second volume of the <title>History of Brazil</title>, published in 1817.</note> &amp;
                    shall very soon begin to transcribe &amp; put together my scattered collections for the press. Do you know who was the author of
                    the Papel Forte?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Papel Forte</title> (1648) urged the cession of Pernambuco to
                        the Dutch as the only means of obtaining peace in the war between Portugal and the Netherlands of 1634&#8211;1654. Its author was
                        the Jesuit missionary, diplomat and writer Antonio Vieira (1608&#8211;1697).</note> And can you guess of what the second
                        <del>xxx</del> part of the Castriosto Lusitano, which is announced at the end of the first as soon to be forthcoming, could
                    possibly be composed?<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rafael de Jesus (1614&#8211;1693), <title>Castriosto Lusitano</title>
                        (1679), no. 3621 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. The book dealt with the Portuguese-Dutch war in Pernambuco
                        1644&#8211;1654.</note> What Joam Fernandes Vieira can have done after the recovery of Recife to furnish matter for a second folio,
                    I am unable to conjecture, &#8211; he however furnished the documents himself, &amp; evidently employed Rafael de Jesus.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joao Fernandes Vieira (c. 1613&#8211;1681) was one of the leaders of the Portuguese struggle to expel
                        the Dutch from Pernambuco. After the success of this movement he was Governor of Paraiba 1655&#8211;1657, Governor of Angola
                        1658&#8211;1661 and Superintendant of Fortifications in North East Brazil 1661&#8211;1681.</note> &#8211; This <del>xxx</del> is rather a point
                    of curiosity than of importance, &amp; I shall be very glad in the course of a few days to dismiss him for his greater name-sake.
                    Part of Vieyras<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Jesuit missionary, diplomat and writer Antonio Vieira
                        (1608&#8211;1697).</note> history belongs to Brazil &amp; part to Portugal, &amp; it is impossible for me to present the whole of it
                    in either work, &#8211; however I shall endeavour to do it fully in both. It is unfortunate that we have not the Provas to Seebras
                        book,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jose de Seabra da Silva (1732&#8211;1813), <title>Deducao Cronologica, e
                            Analytica</title> (1768). This was a fiercely anti-Jesuit work by a Portuguese Minister, in five volumes, the final two of
                        which consisted of &#8216;Provas&#8217;, or supporting documents. Southey possessed only the first two volumes, no. 2599 in the sale
                        catalogue of his library.</note> &#8211; he falls foul of Vieyra in the prevailing spirit of abusing every thing which related to
                    the Jesuits. &#8211; I should suppose that many, &amp; those not the least important of Vieyras letters have not yet been brought to
                    light. I scarcely know any man who can be considered in so many completely distinct characters, statesman, author, religious
                    enthusiast, &amp; madman, &#8211; for of all Sebastianiriti he was surely the strangest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall have an amusing chapter upon the state of society after the recovery of Pernambuco:<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, pp. 632&#8211;692.</note> &#8211; a piece of mosaic of which the
                    materials will mostly be supplied by him &amp; by my old friend S. de Vasconcellos, &#8211; including the life of Almeida<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Simao de Vasconcellos (1596&#8211;1671), <title>Vida do Padre Joam de Almeida</title> (1658).</note>
                    &amp; the romance of Anchieta.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Simao de Vasconcellos, <title>Vida do Veneravel Padre Jose
                            de Anchieta</title> (1672), no. 3799 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. The book contained Jose de Anchieta&#8217;s
                        (1534&#8211;1597) 5,786 verse Latin poem &#8216;De Beata Virgine Dei Matre Maria&#8217;.</note> Travellers give me very little, &#8211; yet every
                    little is something, &amp; if the pictures of slavery &amp; superstition are not striking it will be my fault, &#8211; for God knows the
                    colours are strong enough with which I have to work.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you referred Sir C Stuart<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Stuart, Baron Stuart de Rothesay
                        (1779&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), envoy at Lisbon 1810&#8211;1814.</note> to your neighbour Ant. Ribeiro dos Santos;<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Antonio Ribeiro dos Santos (1745&#8211;1818), librarian, bibliographer and man of letters.</note> &#8211; the
                    [MS missing]st vol: of the Memorias<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Memorias de Litteratura Portugueza</title> (1792&#8211;1796), published by the Academia Real das Sciencias, Lisbon; no. 3532
                        in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> shows that he is alive, &amp; no man is better acquainted [MS missing]th
                    the literature of his country. The Academy have begun to print a body of their historians<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Collec&#231;a&#245; de Noticias para a Historia e Geografia das Na&#231;&#245;es Ultramarinas que vivem nos Dominios Portuguezes</title>
                        (1812&#8211;1813), no. 3273 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> in the manner of the last edition of J de
                        Barros,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joao de Barros (1496&#8211;1570), Portuguese historian and author of <title>Decadas
                            da Asia</title> (1552&#8211;1615). Southey possessed an edition of 1778&#8211;1788, no. 3180 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note> commencing with the M Lusitana of which 8 of these volumes are advertised.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bernardo de Brito (1569&#8211;1617), Antonio Brandao (1584&#8211;1637), Francisco Brandao (1601&#8211;1680), Rafael de Jesus
                        (1614&#8211;1693) and Manuel dos Santos (1672&#8211;1740), <title>Monarquia Lusitano</title> (1597&#8211;1729).</note> I wish they had
                    compleated Castanheda<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Fernao Lopes de Castanheda (c. 1500&#8211;1559), <title>Historia do
                            Descobrimento, e Conquista da India pelos Portuguezas</title> (1554).</note> first. As for Gil Vicente<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Portuguese playwright and poet Gil Vicente (c. 1465-c. 1536).</note> I am as desirous of
                    seeing him as Sir Charles can be, &#8211; perhaps more so, as I would give a good deal for an opportunity of reading him. The Academy
                    ought to reprint this author, &amp; also the Cancioneiro,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably the <title>Cancioneiro
                            Geral</title> (1516), collected by Garcia de Resende (1470&#8211;1536). This included several lyrics by Vicente.</note> &#8211; but if
                    ever they should do it there is a danger of their observing the directions of the old Inquisitor, &amp; omitting all that he has
                        expunged.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first editions of Vicente&#8217;s works in 1561&#8211;2 and 1586 were heavily
                        censored. There was no new edition until 1834.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This letter has lain for some time in my desk. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> will
                    have shown you the 12 &amp; 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> books of Roderick,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> the two following will set off <del>xxx</del> tomorrow in search
                    of him <hi rend="ital">vi&#226;</hi>
          <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn"> Rickman</ref>
          <hi rend="ital"> vi&#226;</hi> the <del>xxx</del>
          <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles"> Speaker</ref>. The <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Printer</ref> spurs me on,
                    &amp; I go on with quickened alacrity as being almost in sight of the end.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did I tell you that your neighbour wrote to me wishing that I would review Marshs book &amp; the Exposure in the
                        Quarterly!<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Barlow (1759&#8211;1839), a neighbour of Herbert Hill&#8217;s in Streatham. In
                        1813 Southey was commissioned by the Barlows to write a defence of the conduct of William Barlow&#8217;s brother, Sir George Hilaro
                        Barlow (1763&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>), Governor of Madras 1807&#8211;1813. The result was the anonymously published pamphlet
                            <title>An Exposure of the Misrepresentations and Calumnies in Mr Marsh&#8217;s Review of Sir George Barlow&#8217;s Administration at
                            Madras. By the Relatives of Sir George Barlow</title> (1813). This was a response to the barrister and MP, Charles
                        Marsh&#8217;s, (c. 1774&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Review of Some Important Passages in the Late Administration of Sir G. H.
                            Barlow, Bart., at Madras</title> (1813). Marsh was MP for East Retford 1812&#8211;1818 and was in serious financial
                        difficulties.</note> &#8211; I have seen an E Indian here of more intelligence than usually falls to the share of such men,<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> &amp; he told me that the persons for whom Marsh acts in England, are
                    men of broken fortunes. The Barlows need only wait a while &amp; they will see their hearts desire upon him. When he loses his
                    seat in Parliament, (for there is little probability of his getting in again) he will hardly be able to keep out of a prison.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This interminable winter has equally annoyed me &amp; the children with continual colds. We have snow every day,
                    with just sun enough to thaw it in the [MS missing] but the hills are covered, &amp; every thing is chearless. &#8211; Of public affairs
                    [MS missing] have hardly heart to speak. My hope is that Buonaparte may be elated with success, &amp; insist upon such terms that
                    the allies will prefer a continuance of the war. But if we have peace, there will yet be another &amp; perhaps a bloodier part of
                    the tragedy of the Fr. Revolution.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the three Bears.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Hills&#8217; three sons, <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref>, <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Herbert</ref> and <ref target="people.html#HillErrol">Errol</ref>.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent6"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1814-03-08">March 8. 1814. </date>
          </p>
          <p>Rela&#231;a&#245; de Revolu&#231;a&#245; do Reino do Algarve.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sebastiao Drago Valente de Brito Cabreira
                            (1763&#8211;1833), <title>Rela&#231;a&#245; Historica da Revolu&#231;a&#245; do Reino do Algarve</title> (1809).</note>
          </p>
          <p>O Tomo 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi> das Memorias Economicas.<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Memorias Economicas da Academia Real das Sciencias de Lisboa</title> (1799&#8211;1812); Southey eventually acquired a
                            copy, no. 3533 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note>
          </p>
          <p>Disserta&#231;a&#245; sobre a reforma dos Foraes do Reinado do St. D. Manoel pelo Desembargador Joam Pedro Ribeiro.<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joao Pedro Ribeiro (1758&#8211;1839), <title>Disserta&#231;a&#245; historica, juridicia e economica sobre a
                                reforma dos Foraes no Reinado do Sr. Rei D. Manoel pelo Desembargador</title> (1812).</note>
          </p>
          <p>Discursos sobre varios objectos relativos a cultura e melhoramento interno do Reino. Impressos por ordem do Principe
                            Regente<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jose Feliciano Fernandes Pinheiro (1774&#8211;1847), <title>Discursos
                                apresentados a meza da agricultura sobre varios objectos relativos a cultura e melhoramento interno do Reino.
                                Impressos por ordem do Principe Regente</title> (1800).</note>
          </p>
          <p>O Patriota. Jornal do Rio de Janeiro.<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>O Patriota. Jornal Litterario, Politico, Mercantil &amp;c. do Rio de Janeiro</title> (1813&#8211;1814); no. 3641 in the
                            sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
          </p>
          <p>Jornal de Coimbra, the latter numbers beginning with N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 20.</p>
          <p>Memorias para a Hist: do Estado de Maranham<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Memorias para a historia da capitania do
                            Maranhao&#8217; in <title>Collec&#231;a&#245; de Noticias para a Historia e Geografia das Na&#231;&#245;es Ultramarinas que vivem nos Dominios
                                Portuguezes</title>, 2 vols (Lisbon, 1812&#8211;1813), I, pp. 1&#8211;118, no. 3273 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                            library.</note>
          </p>
          <p>Mappa Alfabetico das Provoa&#231;o&#7869;s de Portugal, que tem Juiz de primeira Intrancia: contendo (alem dos Titulos) a Provincia,
                        Diocese, Comarca, Provedoria, Juiz e Donatorio, a que cade huir pertence<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Mappa Alfabetico das Povoa&#231;o&#7869;s de Portugal, que tem Juiz de primeira Intrancia</title> (1811); Southey did not
                            obtain a copy.</note>
          </p>
          <p>Origem da Revolu&#231;a&#245; de Port: para a expulsa&#245; do intruso Governo Francez.<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors">
                            Unidentified.</note>
          </p>
          <p>Roteiro e Mappa da Viagem da Cidade de S Luiz do Maranhao at&#233; a Corte do Rio de Janeiro. E outro Roteiro da Viagem do Para pelo
                        Rio Tocantius at&#233; Porto Real em Goyazes <note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sebastiao Gomes da Silva Belford
                            (1781&#8211;1825), <title>Roteiro e Mappa da Viagem da Cidade de S Luiz do Maranhao at&#233; a Corte do R Janeiro. E outro Roteiro da
                                Viagem do Para pelo Rio Tocantius at&#233; Porto Real em Goyazes</title> (1810).</note>
          </p>
          <p>Collec&#231;a&#245; de Viagens nos Dominios Ultramarinos<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note>
          </p>
          <p>Espia&#245; Patriota; on Cartas &amp;c at&#233; a retirada do Exercito Invasor por Jur&#233; Antonio da Silva Freire<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Paulo Mendes Mirrado&#8217;, <title>Espia&#245; Patriota; on Cartas &amp;c at&#233; a retirada do Exercito Invasor por
                                Jur&#233; Antonio da Silva Freire</title> (1811).</note>
          </p>
          <p>Codigo Braziliense.<note n="39" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Codigo Brasiliense, ou Collecao das leis, alvaras, decretos, cartas regias &amp;c. promulgados no Brasil desde a
                                feliz chegada do principe regente N. S. a estes estados com hum indice chronologico</title> (1811&#8211;1822). Southey
                            possessed the first two volumes of (1811&#8211;1812), no. 3357 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note>
          </p>
          <p>Memoria Economica sobre a ra&#231;a do Gado Lanigero da Capitaina do Cear&#225;.<note n="40" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joao da Silva
                            Feijo (1760&#8211;1824), <title>Memoria Economica sobre a ra&#231;a do Gado Lanigero da Capitaina do Cear&#225;</title> (1811).</note>
          </p>
          <p>Ensaio Historico, Politico e Philosophico do Estado de Portugal desde o mez de Nov. 1807 at&#233; o mez de Junho 1808.<note n="41" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Ensaio Historico, Politico e Filosophico do Estado de Portugal desde o mez de Novembro de 1807 at&#233; o mez de Junho
                                1808</title> (1808); Southey did not obtain a copy.</note>
          </p>
          <p>Reflex&#245;es sobre alguns dos meios propostos para o mais conducentes para melhorar o Clima da Cidade do Rio de Janeiro.<note n="42" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Reflex&#245;es sobre Alguns dos Meios Propostos para o Mais Conducente para Melhorar o Clima da Cidade do Rio de
                                Janeiro</title> (1808); Southey did not obtain a copy.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>