<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2530</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3801</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4871 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 425&#8211;428.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2530" type="letter">
        <head>2530. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1814-12-27">27 December
                        1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Norwich<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1
                        Mar<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4871 <lb />Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and
                            Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp. 425&#8211;428.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-12-27">27 Dec. 1814.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tho it is too long a time since you have heard from me, I hope you have duly received a proof in quarto that you
                    are not forgotten.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s last letter had been that of 18 November 1813, see Letter
                        2334. In the meantime, he had asked for Taylor to be sent a copy of the first, quarto edition of <title>Roderick, the Last of
                            the Goths</title> (1814).</note> In course of time I shall encroach upon your shelves if you will allow me room there. My
                    concluding volume of Brazil<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Two further volumes of the <title>History of Brazil</title>
                        appeared, in 1817 and 1819, respectively.</note> is fairly in the press (the eleventh proof is before me) &amp; I shall
                    henceforth be constantly in printers ink till the whole of my historical series<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        &#8216;historical series&#8217; included Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) and his unfinished histories
                        of Portugal and of the monastic orders.</note> is compleated, &#8211; that is if I live to compleat it. You will find in this volume
                    more detail than accords with your taste, but much that will interest you respecting the savage &amp; early stages of colonial
                    society, &amp; especially a fair account of the Jesuits in Paraguay. Upon a careful comparison of lies with lies, <del>x</del> it
                    is perfectly clear to me that their enemies outlied them; &#8211; which may be called out-Heroding Herod. If any of the monastic orders
                    are to exist, better this than any other. If I were the Pope I would restore them;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pius
                        VII (1742&#8211;1823), pontiff since 1800, restored the Society of Jesus (which had been suppressed in 1773), in a Bull of 7 August
                        1814.</note> &amp; if I were the English Minister I would not suffer them to establish themselves in Ireland.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Jesuit, Peter James Kenney (1779&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>), had just founded Clongowes Wood
                        College, County Kildare. It accepted its first pupil on 18 May 1814. It became the leading boarding school for Irish
                        middle class Catholics.</note> &#8211; The extinction of the order was unjust <del>&amp;</del> in its pretext, <del>&amp;</del> in
                    its manner little less cruel than the French deportations to Cayenne, &amp; in its consequences in South America exceedingly
                        injurious.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French revolutionaries used the colony of Cayenne (now in French
                        Guiana) as a place of deportation for political opponents from 1792 onwards. Hundreds of royalists and Catholic priests were
                        deported there in 1797&#8211;1799.</note> But this mischief is irreparable &amp; from their restoration I can <del>xxxx</del>
                    perceive no other political good than a dispute between Portugal &amp; Rome, which may possibly tend to separate that country from
                        <del>xx</del> its papal thraldom.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Portugal did not invite the Jesuits to return until
                        1829.</note> Literature will gain something: we shall probably have the sequel of those important works respecting <del>xx
                        A</del> various parts of America which were begun by the Ex Jesuits in Italy, &amp; discontinued for want of patronage.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> From the Pope to Lucien Buonaparte, the Popes poet.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucien Bonaparte
                        (1775&#8211;1840), brother of Napoleon and author of <title>Charlemagne, ou l&#8217;Eglise D&#233;livr&#233;e</title> (1814), dedicated to the Pope
                        by his &#8216;tr&#232;s-d&#233;vou&#233; fils en JC/ L.B.&#8217;. Southey had been asked to translate it into English and had refused.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> His Charlemagne has lowered him in my estimation, &amp; almost induced me to think that the great difference
                    between him &amp; the rest of his family is merely that he has been the best political calculator. The stanza is well constructed;
                    for this I give him great credit. The story is perfectly free from the ordinary vice of imitation; &amp; put together with
                    sufficient skill. But there is little character, little passion, little interest, little poetry. We were told of his antiquarian
                    researches for the costume, &amp; behold there is nothing antiquarian about the work; &amp; his Saxons have a Druid for their
                    priest. The philosophy of the poem is truly curious, &amp; lamentably characteristic of the age.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Never was the want of a commanding intellect likely to be so severely felt as in these our days. What a golden
                    opportunity of re-casting Europe has been lost! With Italy in one state, &amp; the North of Germany in another under Prussia as
                    its head, &amp; Poland reestablished as an independant state, we might have looked for a long peace, the indispensable precaution
                    having been taken of paring the claws &amp; drawing the teeth of France. Instead of this France has been left with all that Louis
                        14<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis XIV (1638&#8211;1715; King of France 1643&#8211;1715).</note> added to her; &amp; the
                    Government which she has gained after all her revolutions<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The allies had insisted that
                        France should have a Constitution: Louis XVIII (1755&#8211;1824; King of France 1814&#8211;1824) had responded with the Charter of 1814,
                        which guaranteed equality before the law, freedom of religion and a Parliament of two chambers, the Chamber of Deputies and
                        Chamber of Peers.</note> is so much better than <del>x</del> any of those by which she is surrounded, that in the common
                    course of things she must inevitably become too strong for the divided continent. All will then be to do over again; &amp; woe be
                    to the continent if they do not religiously preserve their hatred of the French as a nation. <del>It is a</del> For the last ten
                    years the madness has been Bunoapartes, but the atrocities have been those of the French. He was the God Hanuman,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The comparison is between Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821) and the monkey god in Hinduism.</note> &#8211;
                    the monkeys whom he commanded did the mischief.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I think of going to France about autumn next if the state of affairs public &amp; private will permit. A very
                    little of Paris will satiate me, but I would fain see the Pyrenees, ramble in Dauphiny, &amp; return down the Rhine. There are
                    very persons whom I shall be desirous of seeing Fayette<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French politician and solider
                        Marie-Paul-Joseph-Roch-Gilbert Motier, Marquis de La Fayette (1757&#8211;1834), celebrated figure in the American Revolution and the
                        early years of the French Revolution. Southey had admired him since he was a schoolboy.</note> would be one, Carnot
                        another.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lazare Nicolas Marguerite, Comte Carnot (1753&#8211;1823), member of the Committee
                        of Public Safety 1793&#8211;1794, Director 1795&#8211;1797, Minister of War 1800&#8211;1804. An old Jacobin, for whom Southey retained some
                        admiration.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will have heard of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> intended marriage. It
                        <del>brings</del> forces upon me a sense of the lapse of time, &#8211; for when I was last at Lisbon <ref target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa Gonne</ref> was a little child. Her mother<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Mrs Gonne, wife of William Gonne (d. 1815), Lisbon merchant and packet agent.</note> is my ideal of all that &lt;is&gt; lovely
                    in female nature.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I regret that I do not see the Monthly Review. From a newspaper advertisement of <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> I concluded that you gave the Omniana a good word there, where otherwise it
                    was not likely to have found one.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The notice of <title>Omniana, or Horae
                            Otiosiores</title> (1812) in <title>Monthly Review</title>, 73 (January 1813), 108&#8211;111.</note> I have not yet begun
                    another long poem, &#8211; a proof perhaps of lessening ardour, &#8211; but not yet of diminished power. My story is sufficiently before me in
                        outline;<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;, left uncompleted at Southey&#8217;s death.</note> I delay the
                    commencement partly for want of time, more from irresolution respecting the measure. In blank verse I shall be in danger of
                    repetitions &amp; mannerism; &amp; the story is too dramatic a character for rhyme. I therefore incline at present to that form of
                    verse which learnt from <ref target="people.html#SayersFrank">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sayers</ref>, &amp; which Milton calls
                        Apolelymenon,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Samson
                            Agonistes</title> (1671), &#8216;Of that sort of Dramatick Poem which is called Tragedy&#8217;: &#8216;The measure of verse used in the
                        Chorus is of all sorts, called by the Greeks Monostrophick, or rather Apolelymenon, without regard had to Strophe,
                        Antistrophe, or Epode&#8217;.</note> there would be a word on a title page.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I act the school master every day for an hour &amp; half. &#8211; a sad expence of time, but it is bringing back my lost
                    Greek.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> talks of having written a crushing review of the Excursion.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Jeffrey&#8217;s review of Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>The Excursion</title> (1814), see <title>Edinburgh
                            Review</title>, 24 (November 1814), [1]-30. It began: &#8216;This will never do&#8217; ([1]).</note> I desired <ref target="people.html#HoggJamesEttrick">my informant</ref> would tell him that he might as easily crush <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to James Hogg, [24 December
                        1814], Letter 2528.</note> &#8211; I am in the dark respecting Spain, &amp; cannot divine who are the movers of such folly &amp; so
                    much wickedness, change of men seeming to produce no change of measures.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ferdinand VII
                        (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813&#8211;1833). He had abolished the liberal Constitution of 1812 on 4 May 1814 and returned Spain
                        to absolute rule. He was also notoriously fickle in his choice of ministers. Jose Miguel de Carvajal Vargas y Manrique de
                        Lara, 2nd Duke of San Carlos (1771&#8211;1828) was dismissed as First Secretary of State (Prime Minister) on 15 November 1814 and
                        replaced by Pedro Cevallos Guerra (1760&#8211;1840), Secretary of State 1799&#8211;1808, 1814&#8211;1816.</note> I believe I should go there if
                    I were not somewhat afraid of my old Guerrilla friends upon the road.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you &#8211; affectionately yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>