<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2043</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3314</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 23.  Previously 
                        published: John Forster, Walter Savage Landor. A Biography, 2 vols (London, 1869), I, pp.
                    361&#8211;363.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2043" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2043" type="letter">
        <head>2043. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1812-02-21">21
                        February 1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bath<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 23<lb />Previously
                        published: John Forster, <title>Walter Savage Landor. A Biography</title>, 2 vols (London, 1869), I, pp.
                    361&#8211;363.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-02-21">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 21. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have reread &amp; re-reread the Commentary.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> At the request of Murray,
                        Southey had read and reread a MS of Landor&#8217;s <title>Commentary on Memoirs of Mr Fox</title>, which was ostensibly a response
                        to John Bernard Trotter&#8217;s (1775&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>) laudatory account of his erstwhile employer Charles James Fox. See Southey to Walter Savage Landor, 10 February 1812 (Letter 2034) and 11 February 1812
                        (Letter 2035), and Robert Southey to John Murray 15 February 1812 (Letter 2039) and 18 February 1812 (Letter 2041). Although
                        the <title>Commentary</title> was printed, Murray eventually suppressed its publication, refusing to issue a book that
                        attacked the Tory government and was dedicated to James Madison (1751&#8211;1836), President of the United States 1809&#8211;1817, with
                        whom Britain was about to go to war.</note> The Dedication &amp; the Postscript are so full of perilous matter that it will be
                    difficult to weed them clean: &amp; there is objection to both, that they, far more than the Commentary itself tend to produce
                    that state of feeling which such wretches as <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref> are continually labouring to excite
                    &amp; inflame for the worst purposes. &#8211; We are suffering for the Anti Jacobine war,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Britain&#8217;s war against France 1793&#8211;1802.</note> &#8211; the sins of the fathers are visited upon the children; &#8211; now it seems (p.
                    111) as if you designed to represent that the sins were our own. That we are not in peace &amp; abundance &amp; security, is the
                    effect of <hi rend="ital">that</hi> war, &#8211; <hi rend="ital">this</hi> is unavoidable, &#8211; &amp; so are the expenses which it
                        necessitates.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor had argued &#8216;Are the people in abundance? in security? If they
                        are, they are well governed&#8217;, <title>Charles James Fox. A Commentary on his Life and Character</title>, ed. Stephen Wheeler
                        (London, 1907), p. 6.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We rivet the chain in Sicily, &#8211; &amp; we do not break it in Portugal, &#8211; but certain it is that in Spain, we have
                    pressed upon the Government the necessity of liberal measures &amp; popular reform.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        British sea power was protecting absolutist monarchs in Sicily (since 1806) and Portugal (where Britain had helped the court
                        flee to Brazil in 1808). But the British government had supported the Cortes in Cadiz which gave Spain the liberal
                        Constitution of 1812.</note> Towards the Spanish colonies this country has not acted ill, &#8211; all it could do was to endeavour
                    to mediate. <del>It is a dismal subject</del> Those colonies offer a wretched prospect, &#8211; they are even more unfit for
                    independence than the Americans were, who have become independent (by our fault most assuredly) a full century before they
                        <del>xxx</del> were of age. See what it is to have a nation to take its place among civilized states before it has either
                    gentlemen or scholars! They have in the course of twenty years acquired a distinct national character for low &amp; lying knavery;
                    &#8211; &amp; so well do they deserve it that no man ever had any dealings with them without having proofs of its truth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is now a probability that the damned Junta of Cadiz will be crushed, &amp; the colonial trade thrown open. I
                    have no doubt that what you recommend America is looking to; &#8211; but I have as little doubt that it is under the direction of
                    Buonaparte &#8211; who keeps the American Government in pay. They dream of conquering Canada on the one hand, &amp; Mexico on the other:
                    &amp; happy would Buonaparte be if he could see them doing his work. But the more palpable consequences of that war with this
                    country into which he is bribing them would be, &#8211; the separation of the Northern States, &#8211; &amp; the loss of New Orleans, which it
                    would be our first business to secure, &amp; thus seal up the produce of the whole western territory.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have plucked G Rose most unmercifully.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the Postscript, Landor had
                        attacked George Rose (1744&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Christchurch 1790&#8211;1818, Treasurer of the Navy 1807&#8211;1818 and
                        Vice-President of the Board of Trade 1807&#8211;1812. He was the author of a volume criticising Fox (<title>Observations on the
                            Historical Work of C. J. Fox</title> (1809)): &#8216;I leave him [Rose] &#8230; where I found him, and where Mr. Fox too, I am
                        certain, would have left him. The King has been graciously pleased to distinguish him by the title of right honourable; I
                        should probably have distinguished him by one very different, and certainly much more lasting. But it would have been an
                        unworthy and most idle business; for it is only on soft and miry ground that such creatures can leave any impression. Their
                        impetuous attack is not courage, but stupidity, and their dissonant clamour is not for our security, but for their own
                        voracious and insatiable appetite. Perhaps it might be cruel to break the neck they stretch out so angrily and so awkwardly,
                        yet it would be a piece of good husbandry to pluck them well, and to turn them up again on their common&#8217;, <title>Charles James
                            Fox. A Commentary on His Life and Character</title>, ed. Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), pp. 235&#8211;236. Southey&#8217;s defence of
                        Rose was possibly connected to his important role in Rickman&#8217;s career &#8211; Rose had noticed Rickman&#8217;s proposal for a census and
                        brought the idea to the attention of <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbot</ref>, who became
                        Rickman&#8217;s main patron.</note> If I were asked what man in the H of Commons had done most good there I should <del>fix</del>
                    name this very hero, who according to a song sung by his company of Ch. Church volunteers to his praise, while he <del>gets</del>
                    &lt;used to get&gt; drunk with them drinking alternately his own health &amp; his wifes is &#8216;as brave as Alexander.&#8221;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander &#8216;the Great&#8217; (356&#8211;325 BC).</note> The encouragement of the Benefit Societies, the
                    population &amp; Poor returns, &amp; the naval schools we owe to G Rose,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Rose had:
                        promoted the first Act to regulate Friendly Societies in 1793; played a role in instigating the first census of 1800; pressed
                        for an annual account to Parliament of the Poor Law from 1803 onwards; and promoted the Royal Naval Asylum, founded in 1798,
                        for the children of orphaned seamen, and the training ships for boys donated by the Admiralty to the Marine Society since
                        1799.</note> he has actually <hi rend="ital">done</hi> more good than the whole gang of reformers have even proposed to do. &#8211;
                    The worst I know or think of <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> is that he seems to be laying out for popularity by
                    showing symptoms of falling in with that party whose oeconomy is injustice, &amp; who never hold out any nobler object to the
                    people than that of saving pounds, shillings &amp; pence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But I meant <del>more</del> to confine myself merely to those passages which are either <del>action</del> directly
                    actionable, or which after a while you would yourself be sorry to have published. They are that about <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Croker is not mentioned in <title>Charles
                            James Fox. A Commentary on his Life and Character</title>, ed. Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), so presumably Southey
                        removed this passage</note>. the recommendation to withhold supplies<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor had
                        recommended that the British people could force their government to change its policies by refusing to pay taxes,
                            <title>Charles James Fox. A Commentary on his Life and Character</title>, ed. Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), p. 7.</note>
                    &#8211; the mention of Ld Chatham<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pitt, 2nd Earl of Chatham (1756&#8211;1835;
                        <title>DNB</title>), army officer and elder brother of the former prime minister William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>).
                        The <title>Commentary</title> criticised his role in the ill-fated Walcheren expedition of 1809, <title>Charles James Fox. A
                            Commentary on His Life and Character</title>, ed. Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), p. 21&#8211;22.</note> &amp; Ld Riverdale<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Tonson, 2nd Lord Riversdale (1775&#8211;1848). His father, William Tonson, 1st Lord
                        Riversdale (1724&#8211;1787), was born William Hull and was probably the illegitimate son of the substantial Irish landowner, Robert
                        Tonson (1695&#8211;1773). Landor had referred to the 1st Lord Riversdale as &#8216;the bastard of a scullion&#8217;; <title>Charles James Fox. A
                            Commentary on His Life and Character</title>, ed. Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), p. 90.</note> &#8211; Fellowes<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> In a tirade against &#8216;Reviewers and magazine-men, the linkboys and scavengers of literature&#8217;
                        Landor singled out Robert Fellowes (1770&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>): &#8216;Of late years, if any one had paid any attention to such
                        people [reviewers] &#8230; one would imagine &#8230; that Aristotle only kept a box for Mr. Fellowes.// This reverent gentleman having
                        settled religion to his mind, but unhappily &#8230; driven out from the poets, is retaliating on them as their judge. He writes, or
                        did write, for I know not whether the work survives his hand, in <title>The Critical Review</title>; strange successor to the
                        gentle, but high-minded Southey&#8217;, Landor, <title>Charles James Fox. A Commentary on His Life and Character</title>, ed.
                        Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), p. 146. Landor&#8217;s dislike of Fellowes had undoubtedly been fuelled by learning (from Southey)
                        of the latter&#8217;s views on his poetry. Fellowes had observed in a letter to Seward of 1803 that: &#8216;The author of Gebir &#8230; has
                        lately made another attempt to convey the waters of Helicon by leaden pipes, and many dark subterranean ways &#8230; having trod the
                        dark profound of Gebir, I feel no inclination to begin another journey, which promises so little pleasure, and probably where
                        only a few occasional flashes will enlighten the road&#8217;, <title>Letters of Anna Seward: Written Between the Years 1784 and
                            1807</title>, 6 vols (Edinburgh, 1811), V, p. 77 n. *.</note> &amp; Kett<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry
                        Kett (1761&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), Fellow of Trinity College, Oxford, and writer on education. Landor had encountered him
                        during his time at Oxford. Kett features regularly in Landor&#8217;s satirical writings and the <title>Commentary</title> related an
                        anecdote about his unprofessional, self-serving conduct; <title>Charles James Fox. A Commentary on His Life and
                            Character</title>, ed. Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), pp. 220&#8211;222.</note> &amp; what is said of the Irish Attorney
                        General.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Saurin (1757&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), Attorney General for
                        Ireland, 1807&#8211;1822, a leading figure in the Irish administration and staunch opponent of Catholic emancipation. Although
                        Landor did not mention him by name, he drew attention to the Irish &#8216;attorney general, who brought gentlemen of the first
                        respectability to trial, when, according to his own confession, he believed them to be perfectly innocent of all the charges,
                        and wanted only to prove the <hi rend="ital">validity</hi> of an unconstitutional and most tyrannical law&#8217;; <title>Charles
                            James Fox. A Commentary on His Life and Character</title>, ed. Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), pp. 240&#8211;241. This was
                        probably a reference to his prosecution of two members of the Catholic Board in 1811&#8211;1812 under the Convention Act of
                        1793.</note> About Irish affairs the English can never be made to take any strong interest. I sho[MS torn] <del>xx as</del>
                    your parallel of <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Wellington</ref> with Peterborough substituted as
                        <del>the</del> Appendix.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor discarded the comparison between Wellington and
                        Charles Mordaunt, 3rd Earl of Peterborough (1658&#8211;1735; <title>DNB</title>), a controversial British commander in Spain during
                        the War of the Spanish Succession, 1701&#8211;1713.</note> It would do good: for the great good which is now to be done is to keep
                    up the spirit of the country. Thank God England is not upon her stumps like Witherington,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        In the fifteenth-century &#8216;Ballad of Chevy Chase&#8217;, Part 2, verse 10, Richard Witherington lost both his legs in battle and
                        &#8216;fought upon his stumps.&#8217;</note> but we must fight on till we bring France into that condition.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your prose is as much your own as your poetry. There is a life &amp; vigour in it to which I know no parallel. &#8211; It
                    has the poignancy of champagne, &amp; the body of English October. Neither you nor <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> gave me any hint that the Commentary was yours, but I <del>had</del> could not look into those papers without
                    knowing that it could &lt;not&gt; be the work of <del>xxx</del> any other man.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent5"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent7"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>