<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1733</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3004</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1733" type="letter">
        <head>1733. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, [started before and continued on] <date when="1810-01-13">13 January 1810</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert
                        Hill/ with William Burn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 7. George Street/ Hanover Square/ London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Postmark: [partial] 1810<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a stupid oversight of mine in the first sheet of the Notes. The Zarate<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan Ortiz de Z&#225;rate (c. 1521&#8211;1575), Basque explorer and conquistador, whose exploits are described in
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), I, pp. 331&#8211;349. Southey had &#8211; late in the day &#8211;
                        realised that he was the same person as the &#8216;old Zarate&#8217; (<title>History of Brazil</title>, I, pp. 628&#8211;629 n. 14) in the
                        &#8216;Epistle Dedicatory to Sir Francis Walsingham&#8217;, prefixed to <title>The Conquest of the Weast Indies</title> (1576), an English
                        translation of Francisco Lopez de Gomara (c. 1511&#8211;1566?), <title>Hispania Victrix</title> (1552).</note> of the old
                    Translators Epistle Dedicatory, is certainly the Zarate mentioned in Ch. XI, &#8211; &amp; this never occurred to me till half an hour
                    after the proof was returned. The extract was made eight years ago when of course I could not know who he was, but I am vexed at
                    my own dullness in not recognizing him in time. &lt;However I have sent up an additional note to identify him.&gt;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The new note clearing up the confusion was included; see <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols
                        (London, 1810&#8211;1819), I, p. 649 n. 110.</note> &#8211; Authors in general are more impatient to see their works launched than their
                    friends are for them. I however have learnt to be as patient as the public, &#8211; now &amp; then I give <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> a hint to quicken his pace, &amp; sometimes set the <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmen</ref> of the Row to goad him on: &#8211; you have seen enough of his promises to know
                    what they are worth; &#8211; but other Printers are quite as bad in this respect, indeed rather worse upon the whole, &amp; I have never
                    found any one so attentive to his work. The remaining notes I cannot arrange &amp; send off till my sheets are compleated, &#8211; they
                    are ready &#8216;cut &amp; dried&#8217; &#8211; &amp; when this expected parcel arrives may be sent off in half an hour. By way of gaining time I
                    will forthwith dispatch what little is to be said <del>in the</del> as Preface &#8211; with the title &amp;c. The notes will not I think
                    exceed six sheets in the whole, so that <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Poples</ref> part may easily be finished by the end
                    of this month; &amp; allowing the whole of February to the binders, we may start by the beginning of March. There is no better
                    season for publishing, &amp; <del>xx</del> seasons are of little consequence to works of permanent interest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have given <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> a commission for Labats<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-Baptiste Labat (1663&#8211;1738), <title>Nouvelle Relation de l&#8217;Afrique Occidentale</title> (1728);
                            <title>Relation Historique de l&#8217;Ethiopie Occidentale</title> (1732); <title>Nouveau Voyage aux Iles de l&#8217;Amerique</title>
                        (1722), nos 1578, 1580 and 1582 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> publications respecting Africa &amp; the W
                    Indies, &#8211; for Gregory of Tours,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">St Gregory of Tours (c. 538&#8211;594), historian and bishop. An
                        edition of his <title>Historiae Francorum</title> (1561), was no. 1240 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
                    &amp; the Hist. of the Buccanneers.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexandre Esquemeling (c. 1645&#8211;1707), <title>De
                            Americaensche Zee-Roovers</title> (1678).</note> A Collection of the various works relating to these men, &amp; to the
                    Pirates also, would be very useful &amp; doubtless furnish some information respecting our parts of S America. Dampier<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The buccaneer and explorer William Dampier (1651&#8211;1715; <title>DNB</title>). A 1697 edition of his
                            <title>Voyages Round the World</title> is no. 782 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> is the only author
                    whom I have. I should be glad of any others which you might happen to meet with. There is a voyage to Brazil by Atkyns<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The naval surgeon John Atkins (bap. 1685, d. 1757; <title>DNB</title>). He published accounts of
                        his travels as <title>Voyage to Guinea, Brasil and the West Indies</title> (1735). It contained little about Brazil, but there
                        was no earlier volume on this subject.</note> &#8211; a surgeon in the navy some fourteen years ago, which I sent for in vain from a
                    Bristol Catalogue.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Charles Danvers, 20 March 1809, <title>The Collected
                            Letters of Robert Southey. Part Three</title>, Letter 1603.</note> he published another vol concerning the Gold Coast
                    &amp; the W Indies, &#8211; Brazil is mentioned in the title page of this work, &#8211; in consequence of which I sent for the book, &#8211; &amp;
                    there found myself referred to his former publication. I am at a loss to conceive how he can have filled a seperate volume about
                    Brazil, but his other book is a good one &amp; has raised my curiosity for this. Cuthell,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cuthell (d. 1818), a bookseller whose premises were in Middle Row, Holborn.</note> in that <del>xxxx</del> alley which
                    you pass thro in Holborn, should be forthcoming with a Catalogue about this time, &amp; I have generally found his collection of
                    books the cheapest as well as best of any in town. Dulan in Soho Square has the most foreign books.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The London-based booksellers and publishers A. Dulan &amp; Co., who specialised in books in French.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for Kehama<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> there is no
                    trouble in sending the sheets as they are struck off, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharp</ref> expects to receive
                    &amp; forward them, &amp; will be gratified by seeing them as they pass &amp; talking <del>xx</del> &lt;about&gt; them. I have had
                    no proof yet, tho daily expecting one for the last three weeks.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am at present a good deal interested about an affair in which you can render me some service, &amp; <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> perhaps more, women in such cases being the most useful friends. A young
                    Bristol man (boy he might be called) dying at the age of one &amp; twenty, has bequeathed his papers to two young friends<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Paul Moon James and <ref target="people.html#HoggEdward">Edward Hogg</ref>.</note> in trust as a legacy to his sister,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Eliza Roberts (dates unknown).</note> to be published for her benefit. It is a dismal story. <ref target="people.html#RobertsWilliamIsaac">Roberts</ref> was his name, &#8211; his father formerly a Brewer in Horfield Lane had
                        failed,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">William Roberts (dates unknown). He had been made bankrupt in 1793.</note>
                    &amp; the sons salary as a Bankers clerk (70&#163; a year) was so essential towards the support of the family, that since his death
                    they are sinking fast into absolute poverty, the father being disabled by an apopletic stroke. There was every thing that was good
                    in <ref target="people.html#RobertsWilliamIsaac">William</ref>, every thing that was promising, &amp; as far as I can learn,
                    nothing but what was promising &amp; good. <ref target="people.html#JamesPaulMoon">James</ref> a Banker of Birmingham (the author
                    of that sweet poem upon the Otaheitian Girl which I quoted in the Quarterly<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;The Otaheitan
                        Mourner&#8217;: &#8216;Peggy Stewart, daughter of an Otaheitian Chief, and married to one of the Mutineers of the Bounty. On Stewart&#8217;s
                        being seized and carried away in the Pandora Frigate, Peggy fell into a rapid decay, and in two months died of a broken heart,
                        leaving an infant daughter, who is still living&#8217;, published in <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 26 (December 1808), 457&#8211;458.
                        Two stanzas were quoted by Southey in his &#8216;Transactions of the Missionary Societies in the South Sea Islands&#8217;,
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809), 50 n*.</note> has the charge of the papers &amp; manages the
                    publication. I have seen them, &#8211; &amp; they are as good both the verses &amp; letters as they could be for one so young, &#8211; far
                    better I am sure than any of mine were at the same age. &#8211; Now I want subscribers for this volume, &#8211; a ten or twelve shilling
                    business &#8211; to be paid on delivery of the book. This mode of publication is adopted at my suggestion, because he has left nothing
                    like poor <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">White</ref> for the Evangelicals, &amp; that reptile generation<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">An adaptation of <title>Matthew</title> 3: 7 and 12: 34.</note> have no ears for any thing except
                    Tabernacle music. We cannot draw upon the canters, so we must levy contributions upon the benevolent. The book I am certain will
                    interest all who see it, but we cannot trust to this &#8211; such books never sell to any extent unless fashion, or fanaticism, or
                    something worse carry them off. Get me subscribers where you can, &#8211; &amp; if they happen to be above the rank of simple commoners
                    get the money too if they offer it &#8211; for with such persons it is usually &#8216;If you will not when you may&#8217; &amp;c &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="center"> _____</p>
        <p>
          <date when="1810-01-13">Saturday 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>.</date>
        </p>
        <p>
          <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> is instructed to send you a proof of the Preface,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">To the <title>History of Brazil</title>. It was dedicated to Herbert Hill.</note> in which you will make any
                    alteration that you may make expedient. There is a <del>dedi</del> dedication in which I think you will find nothing that ought to
                    be objected to, &amp; which &#8211; with your leave &#8211; must stand. You will see that I have advertised for the books<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), I, p. vi.</note> which are still
                    wanting, it will probably bring in some of them.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>