<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2136</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3407</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2136" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2136" type="letter">
        <head>2136. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert
                    Hill</ref>, <date when="1812-08-16">16 August 1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To / The Reverend Herbert Hill /
                        Streatham / Surry<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-08-16">Aug. 16. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The last tidings which I heard of you was by your letter to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>, which he brought to St
                    Helens on the day of its arrival. His removal may now be looked upon as a thing
                    determined, &amp; the determination seems on his part a wise one.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Herbert Southey had moved from Durham
                        to London; see Southey to John May, 30 July 1812, Letter 2129.</note>
                    No man can better understand that part of the world with which he will have to
                    deal, his manners will bring his talents into play, &amp; his talents support
                    his professional character against any injury that it might suffer from his
                    manners. I have little doubt of his success, &amp; in case of failure a
                    staff-appointment which there could be no difficulty in obtaining would amply
                    indemnify him for all he leaves at Durham.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> On my way back I past a day with Morritt (the Trojan) at
                        Rokeby,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Bacon Sawrey Morritt
                        (1771&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), traveller, classical scholar and member of
                        the Society of Dilettanti. He had gained the nickname &#8216;Troy&#8217; for his
                        endeavours to prove that the city had been a real place, not an invention of
                        Homer. He owned the Rokeby estate, where he entertained a large circle,
                        including Humphry Davy and Walter Scott.</note> one of the finest places I
                    ever saw. Having seen Teesdale &amp; Richmond (a singularly beautiful town,
                    partaking in its character of the features of Ludlow, Glastonbury &amp; Durham)
                    I returned thro Wensley dale, went a little out of my way to see the Yorkshire
                    Caves &amp; Gordale Scar &amp; <del>xxxxx</del> returned home after an absence
                    of twelve days, &amp; a round of 300 miles, 200 of which I had walked. This
                    journey seems to have braced me up &amp; put me (as the fancy would say) in fine
                    condition for the season. I have been writing with new spirits since my return.
                    The long-delayed life of Nelson<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> is sent to the press, &amp;
                    will as far as I am concerned be finished by the end of the month. I am also
                    running a good heat with Pelayo, or rather with Roderick<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                        (1814).</note> as the poem ought to be called. &#8211; Kehama<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The third edition of <title>The Curse of
                            Kehama</title> (1810) appeared in 1812.</note> is gone to the press
                    again, which omens well for this next adventure.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The third years Register<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title> (1812).</note>
                    reached me last week. The ballad of the Inchcape rock<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2
                        (1812), lxxxiv&#8211;lxxxvi. It had first appeared in <title>Morning Post</title>,
                        19 October 1803.</note> which some unknown person has thought proper to
                    touch up &amp; transmit for insertion, is an old newspaper composition of mine,
                    which has lain uncorrected among my papers for the last ten years. The life of
                        <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref>
          <note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Life of Beddoes&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1810</title>, 3.2 (1812), 516&#8211;537.</note> is by <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref>. &#8211; For the life of
                        Aguirre<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;History of the Life of
                        Lope de Aguirre&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2
                        (1812), i&#8211;l. Lope de Aguirre (c. 1510&#8211;1561) was a Spanish conquistador in
                        South America. Southey had originally intended to include this account of
                        his life in the first volume of his <title>History of Brazil</title>
                        (1810&#8211;1819). His essay was prefaced by a brief introduction, which asserted
                        &#8216;Power, which intoxicates weak men, makes wicked ones mad&#8217; (p. l).</note> I
                    got about 33 &#163;, &#8211; so many weighty reasons why it is better there than in its
                    original place. &#8211; The observation respecting madness with which it is introduced
                    seems to me to be a very important one. You will it see it repeated &amp;
                    illustrated in the last number of the Quarterly.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Biographie Moderne: Lives of
                            Remarkable Characters who have distinguished themselves from the
                            Commencement of the French Revolution to the present time</title>,
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (June 1812), 412&#8211;438. The alteration
                        that Southey objected to concerned his remarks about William Pitt
                        (1759&#8211;1806; Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), of
                        whom he was a constant critic.</note> &#8211; Pray make one alteration in your
                    copy page 413 &amp; instead of &#8220;<hi rend="ital">transcendant as</hi> may have
                    been the pilots merits&#8221;, read as I wrote &#8220;<hi rend="ital">whatever</hi> may have
                    been &amp;c. I am displeased &amp; hurt at this alteration, which belies me
                    &amp; makes me imply commendation where I have most studiously avoided it. The
                    article is in other respects a good deal the worse for the omissions which have
                    been made in it, &#8211; these however are trifles compared with a liberty of this
                    kind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For the next number I have a weighty task before me, &#8211; the state
                    of the poor.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of
                        Patrick Colquhoun (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Propositions for
                            ameliorating the Condition of the Poor: and For Improving the Moral
                            Habits, and Increasing the Comforts of the Labouring People</title>
                        (1812), appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812),
                        319&#8211;356. Rickman had had some input, probably supplying notes and
                        ideas.</note> You may be sure I shall not write like a political oeconomist
                    a breed of Scotch origin who seem to have succeeded the casuists &amp; the
                    schoolmen, having all <del>their</del> &lt;the&gt; dullness &lt;&amp;&gt;
                        <del>xxxx xxx</del> prolixity of both, but neither the depth of the one, nor
                    the acuteness of the other. I have that sort of unwillingness about beginning
                    this subject, which is the best symptom that I shall get thro it to my own
                    satisfaction. &#8211; The Greek in the last number is my old friend <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley&#8217;s</ref>.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Elmsley&#8217;s review of Jeremiah Markland (1693&#8211;1776;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Euripides Supplices Mulieres, Iphigenia in
                            Aulide, et in Tauris, cum Notis Jer. Marklandi</title> (1811) in
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (June 1812), 441&#8211;464.</note> &#8211; Does
                    it not surprize you to see Warburtons Julian spoken of as <hi rend="ital">convincing</hi>?<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the review
                        of Richard Hurd (1720&#8211;1808; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of the
                            Right Rev. William Warburton, D. D., Lord Bishop of Gloucester</title>
                        (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (June 1812), 383&#8211;407, esp. 404.
                        This was a comment on William Warburton (1668&#8211;1779; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Julian: or a Discourse Concerning the Earthquake and Fiery
                            Eruption</title> (1750). The book was a very controversial endorsement
                        of the idea that divine intervention stopped Julian (331&#8211;363; Roman Emperor
                        361&#8211;363) rebuilding the Temple at Jerusalem.</note> &#8211; The first article is
                    written by <ref target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco</ref>.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Blanco White&#8217;s review of William Walton
                        (1783/4&#8211;1857; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Present State of the Spanish
                            Colonies; Including a Particular Report of Hispanola, or the Spanish
                            Part of Santo Domingo</title> (1810), appeared in <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 7 (June 1812), 235&#8211;264.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The remarks in the Register upon the two penny Reformers Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Bankes &amp; C<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
          <note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Bankes (1757&#8211;1834;
                            <title>DNB)</title>, MP for Corfe Castle 1780&#8211;1826. Southey expressed
                        his disapproval of Bankses&#8217; campaign to abolish sinecures and the granting
                        of reversion to state offices in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1810</title>, 3.1 (1812), 207&#8211;218.</note>&#8211; come from <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have heard of a set of Muratori,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lodovico Antonio Muratori (1672&#8211;1750). Southey hoped
                        that May could buy <title>Rerum Italicarum Scriptores, Ab. Anno 500 Ad Annum
                            1500</title>, 36 vols (1723&#8211;70). In fact, May purchased Muratori&#8217;s
                            <title>Annali d&#8217;Italia dal Principio dell&#8217;era Volgare sino all&#8217;anno
                            1750</title> (1786); no. 1894 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library, though this lacked the first volume; see Southey to John
                        May, 16 September 1812, Letter 2145. Southey later did manage to obtain a
                        copy of <title>Rerum Italicarum Scriptores</title>, no. 1922 in the sale
                        catalogue of his library.</note> wanting one volume &amp; therefore to be
                    sold marvellously cheap, so I have desired <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> if it be not gone to secure it for me, as it lies in his
                    weekly walk &#8211; thro Holburn. This will be a treasure if I can obtain it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> is coming
                    here for a week. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>
                    arrived this morning &amp; thro him I am about to try for a ship for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, or for the next step, tho with
                    less prospect of success than if <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Perceval</ref> had been living. <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> however is my friend, &amp; Scott
                    tells me that I am in the good graces of Lord Melville.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Saunders Dundas, 2nd Viscount Melville
                        (1771&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), who had become First Lord of the Admiralty
                        earlier in 1812.</note> I need not say to you how little I can brook the
                    late measures <del>xx xxxx</del> as they regard America,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The United States had declared war on Britain on 18
                        June 1812, in ignorance of Britain&#8217;s decision, on 16 June 1812, to try and
                        avoid this event, by suspending the Orders in Council which prevented
                        American trade with French-controlled territories.</note> &#8211; still worse as
                    they regard the Catholicks.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The new
                        Cabinet formed by Robert Jenkinson, 2nd Earl of Liverpool (1770&#8211;1827;
                            <title>DNB</title>) on 8 June 1812 was &#8216;neutral&#8217; on the question of
                        Catholic Emancipation.</note> Things could hardly look better abroad &#8211; or
                    worse at home. It seems to me that the proudest days of England are to come but
                    that her happiest days are over &#8211; &amp; that neither Church nor State will last
                    half a century longer. God grant that I may be mistaken.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my
                        Aunt</ref>. I shall not see her before April for the
                        Register<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1811</title> (1813).</note> must be finished by that
                    month. &#8211; How go on my cousins? <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> is learning Greek, in easy lessons, at a slow &amp;
                    sure rate. </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>