<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2209</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3480</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 28603.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 44&#8211;46.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2209" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2209" type="letter">
        <head>2209. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1813-01-22">22 January
                        1813</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To / Colonel Peachy/ Bath.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 28603<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 44&#8211;46.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-01-22">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 22. 1813.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been very desirous of thanking you &amp; <ref target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Peachy</ref> for some excellent brawn, &amp; for want of any certain direction was about to address my letter <del>x</del> to
                    Bury, with a sort of roving-commission upon the cover, by virtue of which it might have hunted you out; &#8211; when luckily the desired
                    information has reached me thro a very unexpected channel. On Monday I met <ref target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calvert</ref>
                    at <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLord">Lord Sunderlin&#8217;s</ref>, &amp; he had heard of you from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Spence.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Spence (dates unknown), the builder of &#8216;Pigmy Hall&#8217; near Keswick.</note>
                    I should have written the next day, but delayed it till this evening that I might give you some account of our <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> gaieties in the preter perfect tense, rather than in the future, &#8211; for yesterday we
                    had a grand entertainment at Derwent Bank.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLord">Lord Sunderlin</ref> to lighten a few of the weary hours which his poor sister<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henrietta Malone (c. 1745&#8211;1824).</note> passes, caught hold of the players on his return from
                    Ireland, just as they were packing off from a most unsuccessful campaign in this little town. The drawing room which had luckily
                    in the Pocklington fashion<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. in the fashion of the eccentric Joseph Pocklington
                        (1736&#8211;1817). Son of a wealthy Nottinghamshire banker, Pocklington moved to the Lake District, where he built a number of
                        unique houses, including one on Derwent (Vicar&#8217;s) Island, on Derwentwater, near Keswick.</note> a door at either end, &#8211; &amp;
                    more luckily still a back-stairs communication, made a better theatre, than any of the alehouses or barns in the country could
                    have supplied. They had respectable scenery, &amp; <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> ornamented the room with
                    festoons of evergreens &amp; artificial flowers, which had a very <del>beautiful effect</del> pleasing effect. Ours you know
                        <del>xx</del> is but a scanty neighbourhood at all times, &#8211; the good-natured <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLord">old
                        Lord</ref> however invited every person with whom he had any <del>xxxx</del> intercourse, &#8211; &amp; we mustered about fifty
                    persons besides some dozen or score of children to see Romeo &amp; Juliet &amp; No Song No Supper.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A light opera first performed in 1790: music by Stephen Storace (1762&#8211;1796; <title>DNB</title>), libretto by
                        Prince Hoare (1755&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>).</note> Romeo was the <hi rend="ital">best bad</hi> actor I ever saw, &#8211; that is
                    he was the very worst, &amp; in these cases you know the worse the better. To add to his other accomplishments, <del>the
                        compa</del> he had indulged a little too freely in <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLord">my Lords</ref> kitchen, &amp; was
                    in liquor as well as in love. The company were in good humour &amp; the players, never perhaps before having been either so well
                    paid or so well fed were in high spirits. &#8211; The upstairs entertainment concluded with God save the King in full chorus. We then
                    went down to a cold supper &#8211; which did honour to <del>the good things of</del> Ireland, &amp; to <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLord">Ld S&#8217;s</ref> good housekeeper, &#8211; who it seems when he was setting out <del>from</del> for
                    England stuffed his carriage so full of good things, that she hardly left room for himself. There were two long tables in the
                    dining room, &#8211; the children had their feast in the room within (<ref target="people.html#SunderlinLord">Lord S&#8217;s</ref>
                    bed-chamber) &#8211; &amp; the players &amp; servants made merry the while in the kitchen. We broke up about one o clock.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This has been a great event in our little circle. The few other events which have taken place in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> since your departure are of a different character. First &#8211; as what concerns me most
                    nearly, &#8211; our chickens were all stolen one night &#8220;at one fell swoop&#8221;.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Macbeth</title>, Act 4, scene 3, lines 218&#8211;219, &#8216;What, all my pretty chickens, and their dam,/At one fell
                        swoop?&#8217;</note> &#8211; The Whitehaven mail has been robbed, &#8211; the Maryport post-boy shot at; &#8211; a <del>xxxxx xxxx</del> &lt;house&gt;
                    has been broken open in the town, &amp; two others at <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>, &#8211; but happily a gang
                    has been apprehended, to whom these burglaries are imputed. We have had riots about the passage of corn from Cockermouth
                        southwards,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a reference to the disturbances in Carlisle on 6 April 1812. One
                        woman was killed when soldiers opened fire.</note> &#8211; women &amp; boys were the ostensible ringleaders; &#8211; but there has been
                    something very like a Luddite spirit<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Luddites were a movement that smashed textile
                        machinery, believing that it threatened employment. It was based in the East Midlands, Yorkshire and Lancashire.</note> at the
                    bottom of this, originating half in mistake &amp; half in mischief &#8211; &amp; leading to every kind of evil. <ref target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calvert</ref> behaved very well upon the occasion his property was threatened, &amp; some
                    hints of a bloodier <del>xxxxxxxxx</del> &lt;nature&gt; were scattered abroad, &#8211; but he showed a proper spirit, such indeed
                        <del>that if he had half a dozen</del> as in case of necessity would do wonders. At present all is quiet, &amp; has been so
                    for some weeks. The examples at York,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Fourteen Luddites were hanged at York on 16 January
                        1813.</note> the proclamation,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> A Proclamation on 19 January 1813 offered a pardon to
                        all Luddites who surrendered to local magistrates before 1 March 1813, confessed their activities and took the Oath of
                        Allegiance.</note> &amp; above all, the prospect of deliverance which has opened upon Europe, &amp; the effects of which must
                    be instantly felt in our manufactories, &#8211; will it is to be hop[MS torn] keep peace at home. And soon I trust we shall set
                    thoroughly to [MS torn] about a radical reform &#8211; of the lower classes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will see a paper of mine in the next Quarterly upon this subject. It enters into the moral &amp; political
                    state of the populace, &amp; draws a faithful picture, which I shall be very sorry if any misjudging timidity should weaken or
                        suppress.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the first of a series of Southeyan articles on the poor,
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356. It was republished in an expanded, retitled form as &#8216;On the
                        State of the Poor, the Principle of Mr. Malthus&#8217; Essay on Population, and the Manufacturing System&#8217; in Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title>, 2 vols (London, 1832), I, pp. 75&#8211;155.</note> In the last number I reviewed the
                    Calamities of Authors.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac D&#8217;Israeli (1766&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Calamities
                            of Authors; Including some Inquiries Respecting their Moral and Literary Characters</title> (1812), reviewed by Southey in
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (September 1812), 93&#8211;114.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you seen Rokeby yet?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>Rokeby: A Poem</title> (1813),
                        set during the civil war of the seventeenth century. Southey had visited Yorkshire, where a good deal of the poem is set in
                        the summer of 1812.</note> I enjoyed it the more from having so recently trod over the ground.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have letters from Cadiz to day, which tell me that Ballasteros acted not so much from his own erroneous
                    judgement, as at the instigation of evil counsellors;<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Ballasteros (1770&#8211;1832)
                        had led a mutiny in the Spanish army on 12 October 1812, in protest at the decision to accept Wellington as supreme commander.
                        He was defeated and imprisoned.</note> &amp; which make a melancholy distinction between the character of the soldiers &amp;
                    the officers, &#8211; the former like the peasantry of Portugal, patient hardy &amp; patriotic, &#8211; the latter like the verminous race
                    whom Costigan<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Arthur William Costigan (fl. 1778&#8211;1814), <title>Sketches of Society and
                            Manners in Portugal: in a Series of Letters</title> (1787).</note> describes, &amp; of whom you have seen something, &#8211;
                    idle, dissolute &amp; worthless. The Cortes have made an unhappy experiment at Constitution-making,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Cadiz Cortes had adopted the liberal Constitution of 1812.</note> whereas the simple adoption of two of
                    our blessings would have conferred more benefit upon the people than any thing that all the Constitution-makers from Locke<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Locke (1632&#8211;1704; <term>DNB</term>), <title>Two Treatises of Government</title>
                        (1689).</note> to these Diputados could have devised among them; &#8211; Trial by Jury, &amp; the Habeus Corpus,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The legal principle that nobody should be imprisoned without being charged and brought to
                        trial.</note> &#8211; one to secure the freedom of the press, the other the freedom of the subject. Salvation however seems to be
                    coming from the North, &amp; Spain may ere long be left to ferment &amp; purify itself at leisure. Of her establishing her
                    independence I should have no doubt, even if Buonaparte were now what he was in July last; but of her internal settlement I think
                    with heavier feelings: Popery has destroyed the morals of the people, &amp; it is in vain to form fine governments for those who
                    are corrupted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What a change have the last few months produced!<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. the defeat of the
                        French army in Russia in 1812.</note> Surely we have seen the fourth act of the Tragedy of Buonaparte. I look to see the whole
                    North of Germany throw off the yoke; &#8211; &amp; expect a catastrophe as sudden as the elevation of this monster, &amp; as aweful as
                    his guilt.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Our Ladies<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and
                            <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> join me in kind remembrances to yourself &amp; <ref target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent4"> yrs very truly,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent6"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>