<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2011</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3282</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Beinecke Library, GEN MSS 298, Series I, Box 1, folder 21.  Previously 
                        published: John Holland and James Everett, Memoirs of the Life and Writings of James Montgomery, 7 vols
                        (London, 1854&#8211;1856), II, pp. 319&#8211;322 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2011" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2011" type="letter">
        <head>2011. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">James Montgomery</ref>, <date when="1812-01-02">2 January
                        1812</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> James Montgomery/
                        Sheffield<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Beinecke Library, GEN MSS 298, Series I, Box 1, folder 21<lb />Previously
                        published: John Holland and James Everett, <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of James Montgomery</title>, 7 vols
                        (London, 1854&#8211;1856), II, pp. 319&#8211;322 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-01-02">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 2. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Montgomery</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You talk of yourself &amp; of me in terms of comparison upon which I must not comment, lest you should be as much
                    pained by the comment as I was by the text. &#8211; Let that pass. If I had not admired your poetry, &amp; felt it &amp; loved it, &amp;
                    loved you for its sake, I should not so often have thought of you &amp; spoken of you, &amp; determined to see you, &#8211; nor have
                    broken thro the belt of ice at last.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You wish me a sounder frame both of body &amp; mind than your own. My body God be thanked is as convenient
                        <del>as</del> a tenement as its occupier could desire. When you see me you will fancy me far advanced in consumption so little
                    is there of it, &#8211; but there has never been more; &#8211; &amp; tho it is by no means unlikely (from family pre-disposition) that this
                    may be my appointed end, it is not at all the more likely <del>for xx xxxxx</del> &lt;because of&gt; my lean &amp; hungry
                    appearance. I am in far more danger of nervous diseases, from which nothing but perpetual self-management, &amp; the fortunate
                    circumstances of my life &amp; disposition preserve me. Nature gave me an indefatigable activity of mind, &amp; a buoyancy of
                    spirit, which has ever enabled me to <del>make light</del> &lt;think little&gt; of difficulties, &amp; to live in the light of
                    hope; these gifts too were accompanied with an hilarity which has enabled me to retain a boys heart to the age of eight &amp;
                    thirty: but my senses are perilously acute, &#8211; impressions sink into me too deeply, &amp; at one time ideas had all the vividness
                    &amp; apparent reality of actual impressions to such a degree, that I believe a speedy removal to a foreign country
                        <del>where</del> bringing with it a total change of all external objects, saved me from imminent danger. The remedy, or at
                    least the preventitive of this is variety of employment, &amp; this it is which has made me the various writer that I am, even
                    more than the necessity of pursuing the gainful paths of literature. If I fix my attention morning &amp; evening upon one subject,
                    &amp; if my latest evening studies are of a kind to interest me deeply, my rest is disturbed &amp; broken, &amp; those bodily
                    derangements ensue which indicate great nervous susceptibility. Experience having taught me this I fly from one thing to another,
                    each new train of thoughts neutralizing as it were the last, &amp; thus in general maintain the balance so steadily that I lie
                    down at night with a mind as tranquil as an infants.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> That I am a very happy man I owe to my early marriage. When little more than one &amp; twenty I married under
                    circumstances as singular as they well could be, &amp; to all appearance as imprudent, &#8211; but from that hour to this I have had
                    reason to bless the day. The main source of disquietude was thus at once cut off &#8211; I had done with hope &amp; fear upon the most
                    agitating &amp; most important action of life, &amp; my heart was at rest. Several years elapsed before I became a father, &amp;
                    then the keenest sorrow which I ever endured was for the loss of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">an only
                        child</ref> at twelve-months old. Since that event I have had five &lt;children&gt; more, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">one</ref> of whom has been taken from me. Of all sorrows these are the most poignant. but I
                    am the better for them, &amp; never pour out my soul in prayer without acknowledging that these dispensations have drawn me nearer
                    to my God.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But I will not pursue this strain <del>f</del> too far. The progress of my mind thro many <del>maz</del> changes
                    &amp; mazes of opinion you shall know hereafter, &amp; the up-hill work which I have had in the world, up-hill indeed, but by a
                    path of my own chusing, &amp; always with this comfort that I felt myself gaining the ascent, as well as toiling for it. Something
                    I must say, while there is yet room for it concerning the World before the Flood. You say that you are about to begin it
                        again.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In response to comments from friends who had seen an early version of the poem in
                        MS, Montgomery had decided to recast his epic <title>The World Before the Flood</title> (1813).</note> &#8211; before you do this,
                    re-consider during one half hour, what doubtless you have considered long ago, &#8211; whether it would not be better to make the Flood
                    itself the termination of the poem, which would <del>involve</del> &lt;render&gt; no other <hi rend="ital">alteration</hi> of the
                    story (as far as I understand it than that of relating the assumption of Enoch<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Genesis</title> 5: 22&#8211;29 describes Enoch as Noah&#8217;s great-grandfather, who did not die but was carried up into
                        Heaven.</note> in the person of a narrator instead of in your own. It seems to me that you would gain a grandeur &amp; even a
                    unity beyond what your present design affords. &#8211; My intention was to assume Burnetts Theory<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Burnet (c. 1635&#8211;1715; <title>DNB</title>). His <title>Telluris Theoria Sacra</title> (1681) was divided into four
                        sections, describing paradise, the flood, the apocalypse, and the new heavens and earth created afterwards. Burnet claimed
                        that Noah&#8217;s flood was caused by waters rising from within the earth.</note>
          <del>of</del> (a book almost unequalled for its powers of imagination) &amp; to have connected Whistons<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Whiston (1667&#8211;1752; <title>DNB</title>), natural philosopher and theologian. His <title>A New Theory
                            of the Earth</title> (1696) applied Newtonian physics and new geological scholarship to demonstrate the rationality of
                        biblical accounts of the flood, which it attributed to the effects of a comet.</note> with it. I have conceived a youth, the
                    bosom-friend of Japhet,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>Genesis</title>, Japheth is described as one of Noah&#8217;s
                        three sons. In legend he was considered to be the ancestor of all Europeans.</note> perfectly convinced by Noah, but refusing
                    to flee from the wrath <del>of</del> to come, because the maid whom he loved (tho herself convinced also) would not forsake her
                    parents. Their death, followed by their immediate beatitude would have made an impressive scene. The outstanding
                        <del>picture</del> figure of the Anti-Anakim<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. the group opposed to the Anakim. In
                            <title>Numbers</title> 13, the Anakim are described as the descendants of Anak, who inhabited the south of Canaan. The
                        passage can be interpreted as suggesting they were giants.</note> or Jacobinical party (for I had the parallel strongly in my
                    mind, was a man with the best feelings &amp; the best intentions, &#8211; but erring in this, that he lived without God in the world, &#8211;
                    that he trusted in his own strength, &amp; provided he were likely to attain his end, was regardless of the means.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s plan for a hexameter poem on &#8216;Noah&#8217;, <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John
                        Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 2&#8211;3.</note> He, after a S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bartholomews massacre<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The massacre of Protestants in Paris, which began on 23 August (the eve of the feast of St
                        Bartholomew) 1572.</note> of all his party was to have burnt alive in sacrifice to the God-Tyrant. The great temple-palace was
                    to have been some Tower-of-Babel edifice, built in despite of prophecy, <del>&amp; a</del> &amp; as if defying the vengeance which
                    was denounced. It would have resisted the weight of the waters of the flood &amp; have overlived all things, till (<del>xxx</del>
                    following Burnetts sublime vision) the <del>xxx</del> shell of the <del>gl</del> earth gave way. You have here all that is worth
                        <del>recollecting</del> &lt;remembering&gt; of a plan which never went farther than this. If any part of it <del>should</del>
                    could serve you as a hint, believe me Montgomery I should feel proud at having contributed one unhewn stone to your building. &#8211;
                    God bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yr affectionate friend</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> I have a book of Pelayo<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early name for <title>Roderick, the Last of
                                the Goths</title> (1814).</note> transcribed for you which must take a long journey in quest of a frank.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>