<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1837</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3108</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS
                    157.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1837" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1837" type="letter">
        <head>1837. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1810-12-07">7 December
                        1810</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS./ 7 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1810 &#8211; <lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS
                    157<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1810-12-07">Dec. 7. 1810.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Concerning the good custom of Bride-wains<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The waggon in which a bride was
                        driven to her new home. Also, the tradition by which a newly-wed poor couple drove around their village collecting small sums
                        of money or articles of furniture towards their new home.</note> the arrangement you propose is not practicable, &#8211; it having
                    long been understood that the opera omnia<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;complete works&#8217; of Southey.</note> were
                    delayed till my journey to London, when I might have them bound to my own taste, &#8211; a present thereof to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> H. Southey</ref>, which was ordered at hap-hazard not having
                    altogether pleased me. There is also another objection quoad<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;with respect to&#8217;.</note> the
                    proposed mode of package, &#8211; for the Operas are to grow, I trust, &#8211; &amp; the case would not. &#8211; But that you may not think I mean
                    to divert you from a good purpose I will mention that <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> T.S.</ref>
                    has not got <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> poems,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably
                        Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>Poems in Two Volumes</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; &amp; I have no doubt she would be much gratified in
                    receiving them from you. She goes in a few days to her fathers (M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Castle)<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Castle (d. 1815), a solicitor in County Durham, where he was Clerk of the Crown and held various legal
                        appointments in the Bishop of Durham&#8217;s household.</note> at Durham, &amp; there they should be directed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Malaga &amp; Santona <del>xxx</del> expeditions seem both to have failed from mismanagement. In the former Lord
                    B&#8211; was duped by a stratagem against which he ought to have been on his guard;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andrew
                        Thomas Blayney, 11th Baron Blayney (1770&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), was defeated and captured when he attacked Fuengirola in
                        October 1810, using a mixed force of British, Spanish, German, Italian and Polish soldiers. Some of these troops were formerly
                        in the service of the French and re-deserted to their old allegiance.</note> &#8211; for the second bad weather &amp; Spanish sea
                    manship or rather no-seamanship sufficiently account.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A party of British marines and
                        Spanish troops had briefly occupied the Spanish port of Santona in July 1810, but withdrew when attacked by French
                        forces.</note> Doyles Catalonian expedition of the same kind was uniformly successful.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Sir Charles William Doyle (1770&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>), British liaison officer to Spanish forces in Catalonia 1809&#8211;1811.
                        He played an important role in the allied victory at La Bisbal, 14 September 1810.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am well pleased with <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellingtons</ref> conduct; &#8211; if it
                    appears doubtful in any thing it is in not having defended the passage of the Zezere from the side of Abrantes. Do you believe
                    that string of questions &amp; answers? To me it seems very suspicious, &#8211; I cannot conceive why the &lt;messenger&gt; should be
                    provided in writing with <del>xxxxxx</del> information, every part of which he might have delivered just as well by word of mouth,
                    &#8211; for one cannot suppose such a blockhead was sent that it was necessary he should con his lesson the whole way. &#8211; Massena<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French Marshal Andr&#233; Massena (1758&#8211;1817), one of the commanders of the invasion of
                        Portugal in 1810.</note> I think is retreating across the Zezere, &amp; probably cross the Tagus if he can effect the passage.
                    In falling back to Santarem merely to be nearer his reinforcements there could be no possible advantage, &#8211; especially after he had
                    entrenched himself strongly in his former position. Want of provisions, hopelessness of beating the English if he attacked them,
                    &amp; fear of being attacked himself, &#8211; these explain his movements satisfactorily to me. They talk of reinforcements from the
                    side of Andalusia, &#8211; if any considerable force is detached the siege of Cadiz must be raised, &amp; Seville will not improbably be
                    recovered. On the whole things look well. The Portugueze army will every day improve. In Spain I trust the Cortes &amp; Blake<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joaquin Blake y Joyes (1759&#8211;1827), Spanish general who was constructing a General Staff
                        for the scattered Spanish armies. He was also a member of the Council of Regency.</note> who has now the power &amp; must have
                    the knowledge &#8211; will put their army on the right footing &#8211; that is that they will do as the French did, neglect rank altogether in
                    their promotions, &amp; <del>pick out</del> &lt;raise&gt; officers &amp; generals from the ranks, as fast as men can be found to
                    merit <del>promotion</del> command.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do not forget Malthus &amp; the Poor Laws,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The political economist Thomas
                        Robert Malthus (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>). Southey was encouraging Rickman to write about the Poor Laws. It was a subject
                        Southey too pursued. The first of a series of Southeyan articles on the poor appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>,
                        8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356. It was possible co-authored with John Rickman and was intended as &#8216;an attack upon Malthus&#8217;,
                        amongst others; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 5 January 1813, Letter 2199.</note>&#8211; subjects which hang together. The
                    Edinburgh Review which seems destined to be wrong upon every subject that requires either sound knowledge, or <del>decent</del>
                    &lt;good&gt; feeling, has just been taking up the cause of this doughty philosophicide.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        See, for instance, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 16 (August 1810), 464&#8211;476.</note> There cannot be a better opportunity of
                    knocking down two dodos with one stone.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref> I am truly glad to hear
                    of her well-doing. You &amp; I are got into the female-line.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rickman and Southey had both
                        fathered more daughters than sons. Rickman&#8217;s marriage eventually produced three daughters and one son; Southey&#8217;s six daughters
                        and two sons.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> sent me a not-very-wise message the other day that <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> was certainly to be prime-minister, he <hi rend="ital">knew</hi> it to be
                    so &amp;c &#8211;. upon which you may guess what sort of reliance I should have placed, even if he had known also that it was certain
                    the King<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of the United Kingdom 1760&#8211;1820;
                        <title>DNB</title>). His mental health had collapsed again in October 1810 and he was incapable of conducting public
                        business.</note> would not recover: &#8211; of <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Ld Grenvilles</ref> disposition as to war or
                    peace all I know is that when <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> wrote to me of the Register he said he excused my
                    Spanish fever; &#8211; in reply to <del>which</del> &lt;this&gt; I talked of his French ague.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        See Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 11 November 1810, Letter 1826.</note> &#8211; We have only to fight on, &amp; the end
                    must be in our favour.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am getting on with the vile business of the D of York.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1809, Prince
                        Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>) had been forced to resign as commander-in-chief of the
                        British army in the wake of allegations that he had profited from office trafficking. After a lengthy investigation, the
                        charges were found to be unproven. It had, however, become apparent that his former mistress Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852;
                            <title>DNB</title>) had received money from individuals keen for her to use her influence with the Duke, and that the Duke
                        himself had known of her actions. For Southey&#8217;s account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811),
                        109&#8211;301.</note> The channels of communication which <ref target="people.html#RobinsonHenryCrabb">H. Robinson</ref> has opened
                    to me make me throw the whole of the peninsular affairs together at the end of the volume, &#8211; in order to gain time for
                    communications from Cadiz &amp; from Col. Carol.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. from the seat of the Spanish Junta
                        in Cadiz; and from William Parker Carrol (1776&#8211;1842), liaison officer between the British and Spanish forces. He was later promoted
                        to Major-General and Field Marshal in the Spanish Army.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My advertisement for books has brought me a Brazilian grammar<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> An edition
                    from 1795 of Luiz Figueira (1573&#8211;1643), <title>Arte de Grammatica da Lingua Brasilica</title> (1687), no. 3396 in the sale catalogue of
                    Southey&#8217;s library. Southey had been lent a copy of this edition by the merchant Thomas Kinder (c. 1781&#8211;1846), who had lived in
                    South America 1808&#8211;1810. Southey had not asked for this book in his &#8216;advertisement&#8217;, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols
                        (London, 1810&#8211;1819), I, p. vi. It was a grammar of the Tupi langauage, widely spoken in coastal regions of Brazil when the
                        Portuguese arrived in the early sixteenth century.</note> &#8211; there is one thing in it truly Tupinamban, &#8211; an interjection
                    expressive of joy at the sufferings of another. The language is excellently barbarous. I shall very shortly refresh myself from
                    these home-politics by a run in Brazil. &#8211; it is a sort of intellectual change of air, which gives new strength &amp; keener
                    appetite.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> About the Annual Accounts<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> The detailed information on state finances
                        required by Southey for his section of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>. Rickman supplied the necessary
                        figures and they appeared in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title> 2.1 (1811), &#8216;Appendix&#8217;, i&#8211;viii.</note> &#8211; I
                    have as decided a no-genius for these things as you have an aptitude for them. The utmost I can do <del>in xxxxxx</del>
                    &lt;upon&gt; finance is to follow the debates closely, without attempting even to form an opinion about them. <del>If you send me
                        any</del> Being incapable, the best thing is to be sensible of that incapacity. So if you send me any thing let it be in such
                    a shape that I have only to transcribe, &#8211; to understand is out of my power.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>