<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1951</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3222</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS 3881.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp.
                    314&#8211;317.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1951" type="letter">
        <head>1951. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, <date when="1811-09-08">8 September
                        1811</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Scott Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Ashistiel/
                        Selkirk<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Watermark: IPING/ 1806<lb />Seal: [illegible] Black wax<lb />Endorsement: Southey/ 8
                            Sept.<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 1811<lb />MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 3881<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp.
                    314&#8211;317.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1811-09-08">Sept. 8. 1811.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Scott</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will have thought me very remiss in not thanking you sooner for the Vision,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>Vision of Don Roderick</title> (1811), which covered similar territory to that in Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> &#8211; if you did not remember that I had been travelling from
                    Dan to Beersheba,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> A common biblical phrase to describe the whole land of Israel, from
                        North to South, e.g. <title>Judges</title> 20: 1. Southey had been to London and back.</note> &amp; take into consideration
                    how little opportunity can be found for the use of pen &amp; ink in the course of a series of run-away visits during a journey of
                    nine hundred miles. It was given me at the Admiralty the very day that it arrived there, <del>xx</del> I opened it on the spot,
                        <del>in xxxx to</del> &amp; discovered that a letter to Polwhele<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poet, historian
                        and contributor to the <title>Anti-Jacobin</title>, Richard Polwhele (1760&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>). He was a clergyman, with
                        several livings in Cornwall.</note> had been inclosed to me, in time for <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> to rectify his mistake by making a fair exchange &amp; thus saving mine from a journey to the Lands End. &#8211; If
                    however I have not written to you about D Roderick I have been talking to every body about him. The want of plan &amp; unity is a
                    &lt;defect&gt; inherent in the very nature of your subject, &amp; it would be just as absurd to censure the Vision for such a
                    defect as it is to condemn Kehama<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> because all the agents are not human personages. The execution is a
                    triumphant answer to those persons who have supposed that you could not move with ease in a metre less loose than that of your
                    great poems. To me it appears, on the whole, better written than those greater works for this very reason. you have taken fewer
                    licenses of language, &#8211; &amp; have united with the majesty of that fine stanza (the most perfect that ever was constructed) an
                    ease which is a perfect contrast to the buckram &amp; barbarisms of Gertrude of Wyoming.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Thomas Campbell (1777&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Gertrude of Wyoming</title> (1809), a poem set in
                    Pennsylvania.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is remarkable that three poets should at once have been employed upon Roderick.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Roderick (d. 711/ 712), Visigothic king of part of Spain from 710. He was defeated and killed by Muslim
                        invaders who went on to conquer most of the Iberian peninsula.</note> I have a tragedy of <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landors</ref> in my desk of which Count Julian is the hero,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Count Julian: A Tragedy</title> (1812).</note> &#8211;it contains some of the finest touches both of passion &amp;
                        <del>high</del> poetry that I have ever seen. Roderick is also the prominent personage of my own Pelayo,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early incarnation of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> as far as
                    it has yet proceeded. Differing so totally as we do in the complection &amp; management of the two poems, I was pleased to find
                    one point of curious comparison, in which we have both represented Roderick in the act of confession &amp; both finished the
                    picture highly, <del>xx</del> our representations are so totally different as to form a perfect contrast, yet each so fitted to
                    the temper <del>of</del> in which the confession is made, that it might be sworn, if you had chosen my point of time you would
                    have written as I have done, &amp; that if I had written of the unrepentant king I should have conceived of him exactly
                        <del>in</del> like yourself. I copy my own lines, because I think you will be gratified at seeing a parallel passage which
                    never can be produced except to the honour of both</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent5"> Then Roderick knelt</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Before the holy man, &amp; strove to speak.</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Thou seest, he cried, &#8211; thou seest, &#8211; but memory</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And suffocating thoughts represt the word,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And shudderings, like an ague fit, from head</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> To foot convuls&#8217;d him. Till at length, subduing</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> His nature to the effort, he exclaim&#8217;d,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Spreading his hands, &amp; lifting up his face,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> As if resolved in penitence to bear</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> A human eye upon his shame, &#8211; thou seest</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Roderick the Goth. That name would have sufficed</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> To tell its whole abhorred history.</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> He not the less pursued, &#8211; the ravisher!</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The cause of all this ruin! &#8211; Having said,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> In the same posture motionless he knelt,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Arms straightened down, &amp; hands dispread, &amp; eyes</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Rais&#8217;d to the monk, like one who from his voice</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Expected life or death.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> An early version of an incident in
                                <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 1, lines 220&#8211;237.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1"> I see but little of <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> in town, because he was on the point of
                    taking wing for the Isle of Wight when I arrived. The review seems to have shaken the credit of the Edinburgh, &amp; might shake
                    it still more.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The review&#8217;s identity is not certain. It is one of Southey&#8217;s reviews of:
                            <title>Hints to the Public and the Legislature, on the Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title>
                        (1809), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 480&#8211;514; and Sir Charles William Pasley (1780&#8211;1861;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Essay on the Military Policy and Institutions of the British Empire</title> (1810),
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5 (May 1811), 403&#8211;457.</note> The way to attack the enemy with most effect is to take up
                    those very subjects <del>xx</del> which he has handled the most unfairly, &amp; so to treat them as to force a comparison which
                    must end in our favour. I am about to do this upon the question of <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">Bell</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Lancaster</ref>, &#8211; a question on which <ref target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> has grossly committed himself.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Brougham was an advocate for Joseph
                        Lancaster&#8217;s system and a member of the board of directors of the Royal Lancastrian Institution (later the British and Foreign
                        Schools Society). He had severely criticised Andrew Bell in &#8216;The Education of the Poor&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 17
                        (November 1810), 58&#8211;88. Southey responded with <title>The Origin, Nature and Object of the New System of Education</title>
                        (1812), especially, pp. 153&#8211;180.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You may well suppose that three months idleness has brought upon me a heavy accumulation of business. Meantime good
                    materials for the third years Register<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title> (1812).</note> have reached me from Cadiz,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Diario de las Discusiones y Actas de las Cortes, 1810&#8211;1813</title> (1811&#8211;1813), no. 3288 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; I &lt;have&gt; collected others respecting Sicily &amp; the Ionian islands. I saw the last
                    volume on my road &amp; thought I could trace your hand in a powerful but too lenient essay upon <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrays</ref> journal.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;On the Present State of
                        Periodical Criticism&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.2 (1811), 556&#8211;581. It concluded: &#8216;Its surprising
                        and unprecedented success has rendered the Edinburgh Review the mirror in which the others dress themselves &#8230; The tone of
                        critcism &#8230; at the commencement of the nineteenth century may be characterized as harsh, severe and affectedly contemptuous,
                        dwelling rather in general and excursive discussion, that in that which applies itself to the immediate subject; but
                        requiring, from those very circumstances, an elevation of talent and extent of information, unknown, or at least unnecessary,
                        to the humble labourer of the preceding period&#8217; (581).</note> It is well for him that I am employed upon worthier subjects or
                    he would ere this have been gibbetted to all generations.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey</ref> joins me in remembrances to <ref target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Scott</ref>
          </salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> believe me yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>