<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2592</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3863</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of
                            Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 405&#8211;407 [in part; dated 1 May 1815].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2592" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2592" type="letter">
        <head>2592. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1815-05-01">1[&#8211;2] May 1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster.<lb />Postmark: [illegible]<lb />Endorsement: May 1. &amp; 2. 1815<lb />MS:
                        Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 405&#8211;407 [in part; dated 1 May 1815].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I give you joy of your journey &amp; I give myself joy of your return, for tho we are even now three hundred miles
                    apart, &amp; tho a fortnight might easily have past without any communication between us, yet the knowledge that you were not in
                    England, made me feel that something in the system of my microcosm was changed, &amp; as it were out of order.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> During your absence I have been as usual making progress, &amp; consuming ink &amp; quill barrel <del>xxxx</del> at
                    the regular rate. Eighteen inscriptions are now written, &amp; <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> will probably
                    be making up his mind at this time whether to print them in quarto, or in a smaller form.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s series of Inscriptions on the Peninsular War. Southey only completed 18 Inscriptions (30 were planned) and they were
                        not collected together until they were published in <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), III, pp.
                        122&#8211;156.</note> I prefer the statelier form, in which case some 20 pages of notes may be added to some fourscore of text. You
                    shall have what are done in my next consignment to <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>; &amp; perhaps you can
                    help me in the only part of the undertaking which requires help, &#8211; which is in finding out something for me about one or two
                    persons upon whom I have to write epitaphs &amp; of whom I find <del>xx</del> no memoir in my Magazines. <del>I will make out a
                        list at the end of this letter</del>. Tell me from what branch of Cromwells family the Franklands are descended.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Frankland Baronets of Thirkelby. Sir Thomas Frankland, 2nd Baronet (1665&#8211;1726), married in
                        1683 Elizabeth Russell (d. 1733), daughter of Frances Cromwell (1638&#8211;1720), Oliver Cromwell&#8217;s (1599&#8211;1658; Lord Protector
                        1653&#8211;1658) youngest daughter.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> no doubt can answer the question. <del>Xx</del> Major Nicholas<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Major William Nicholas (1785&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), died 14 April 1812 from wounds received
                        at the siege of Badajoz. His mother was Charlotte Frankland, daughter of Admiral Sir Thomas Frankland, 5th Baronet (1718&#8211;1784;
                            <title>DNB</title>). Southey did not write an epitaph to commemorate him.</note> (a friend of <ref target="people.html#BunburySirHenryEdward">Gen. Bunbury&#8217;s</ref>) who fell at Badajoz, &amp; who was a highly interesting
                    character was of that stock, &amp; my poem may be the better for his genealogy, if he comes either from Ireton,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Ireton (bap. 1611&#8211;1651; <title>DNB</title>), Parliamentarian general and Cromwell&#8217;s
                        son-in-law.</note> or from Richard Cromwell.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Cromwell (1626&#8211;1712;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Cromwell&#8217;s third son and his successor as Lord Protector 1658&#8211;1659.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have pleased myself well in most of these poems, &amp; diversified them with some skill. I may praise <del>my
                        poems</del> &lt;myself&gt; to you, as I do <del>my beauty</del> &lt;<del> xxxxxxx</del>&gt; to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">my daughter Isabel</ref>, when we agree that she is my Beauty Bell, &amp; I am her Beauty
                    Pappa. They are not in their nature things that can be popular, but I do not doubt that those who are capable of appreciating
                    them, will think them good, &amp; that they will hold a respectable place among my works hereafter. Sometimes I half resolve to
                    say something in a proud preface respecting the Laureateship,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not write a
                        Preface or dedication for the Inscriptions.</note> in consequence of which these are written: but with any feelings of
                        <del>pride</del> worthy pride, or indeed with any worthy feelings, <del>the</del> what is called the public has little
                    sympathy. Sometimes too I think of dedicating them, but cannot determine to whom. The <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">D of Wellington</ref> obviously occurs; &#8211; &amp; it is as obvious that there is
                    something like flattery in inscribing a book to <del>w</del>him which is all to his <del>honour</del> &#8220;praise &amp; glory&#8221;.
                    Sometimes I think of doing it in some verses to the memory of <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref>, &#8211; &amp;
                    this seems the favourite idea. Sometimes to the Army, <del>&amp;</del> or to the British people. Perhaps it will end in no
                    dedication at all. Sometimes I have a half mind towards <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref>, &#8211; upon this point
                    that I trust his voice will soon be heard as powerfully in behalf of another war, as just, as inevitable &amp;c &#8211;. If you see any
                    fitness or unfitness in any of these embryo intentions tell me. Your opinion will have, as you well know, much weight.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Ten o clock &amp; I must go to the <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhoras</ref> to supper &#8211; Good night.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> May 1. 1815. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Shedaw</ref> is this day eleven years old</p>
        <p> Tuesday evening</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You being my First Lord of the Treasury &amp; Chancellor of the Exchequer will you leave 4 &#163; with <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> for <ref target="people.html#LovellRobertJr">Robert Lovell</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall not see you before the fall of the year unless you pay your devoirs to the Mountains. I have too much
                    before me to allow of rambling, <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> has one article in his hands &amp; must
                    have that upon <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Ld Wellington</ref> for which I am to be paid so
                        ridiculously,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was paid &#163;100 for his review of George Elliott (dates unknown),
                            <title>The Life of the Most Noble Arthur Duke of Wellington, from the Period of his first Achievements in India, down to
                            his Invasion of France, and the Peace of Paris in 1814</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815),
                        215&#8211;275.</note> &#8211; but nevertheless so conveniently to my necessities at this time. My heart meantime is in Brazil,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> where I am got into the most
                    interesting part, &amp; working away with some thing like that relish which is said to belong to forbidden fruit. <del>That
                        is</del> I mean that upon the mere question of profit &amp; loss, this is very imprudent work. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A <ref target="people.html#LockerEdwardHawke">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Locker</ref> who knows <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> &amp; who was Ld Exmouths<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Admiral
                        Edward Pellew, 1st Viscount Exmouth (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), commander of the British fleet in the Mediterranean
                        1811&#8211;1814, 1815&#8211;1817.</note> Secretary brought an introduction to me yesterday, &amp; offered me his services, &amp;c in
                    London. I shall get something from him respecting our operations in Catalonia.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the Canada paper: of which more hereafter. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> is to be at Oxford on the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> he has a
                    post-mastership at Merton, worth not less than 50 &#163;. upon which with 40 from his Uncles at Ottery,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hartley Coleridge&#8217;s paternal uncles, especially George Coleridge.</note> 30 from <ref target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMary">Lady Beaumont</ref>, <del>&amp;</del> 10 from his godfather <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Poole</ref>, &amp; 5 from poor <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref>, it is
                    supposed he may live <del>f</del> with frugality. If more be necessary, it will be forthcoming, <del>but</del> And to his disgrace
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">the father</ref>, quietly reconciles himself, &amp; talks of what he will do,
                    &#8211; just as <del>x</del> a man would who could rely upon his own intentions &amp; efforts. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> has luckily a <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeWilliamHart">cousin</ref>
          <note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Hart Coleridge had taken his MA in 1814.</note> at Ch Church
                    both able &amp; desirous to render him every good office in his power. It will be his own fault if he does not provide for himself
                    at College, &#8211; but O c&#230;lum O terra O maria Neptuni<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Publius Terentius Afer (195/185&#8211;159
                        BC), <title>Adelphoe (The Brothers)</title> (160 BC), line 790: &#8216;O Heaven! O Earth! O sea! O Neptune!&#8217;</note> what a fish it
                    is!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Moon</ref> goes on as you could wish, &amp; makes excellent progress
                    in Greek.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to all at home. I shall look for a letter from you tomorrow.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>