<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2515</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3786</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42551 .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2515" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2515" type="letter">
        <head>2515. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1814-12-12">12 December
                        1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle
                        Street/ London <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb />Postmark: E/ 15 DE 15/ 1814 <lb />Watermark: J DICKINSON &amp; Co/
                        1811<lb />Endorsement: 1814 Dec 12/ Southey Rob:<lb /> MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42551 <lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-12-12">12. Dec. 1814</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have finished Eulia, &amp; return it by tomorrows coach. The parts which would probably serve to collate with the
                    Spanish traveller<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Domingo Badia y Leblich (1766&#8211;1818), who Rickman had met in London. He
                        was a Spaniard who had travelled extensively in North Africa and the Middle East under the pseudonym &#8216;Ali Bey al-Abbasi&#8217; and
                        published <title>Travels of Ali Bey: in Morocco, Tripoli, Cyprus, Egypt, Arabia, Syria, and Turkey, between the years 1803 and
                            1807</title> (1816) reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (July 1816), 299&#8211;345. Longman published
                        this book, though, rather than Murray.</note> are in the two first volumes, relating to Mecca &amp; Medina.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Murray had asked for Southey&#8217;s opinion on an unpublished translation by the Austrian orientalist
                        Ritter Joseph von Hammer-Purgstall (1774&#8211;1856) of Evliya &#199;elebi (1611&#8211;1682), <title>Seyahatname</title>, which described the
                        latter&#8217;s travels through the Ottoman empire. Von Hammer-Purgstall had published a German translation of &#199;elebi in 1814 and his
                        English version, <title>Narrative of Travels in Europe, Asia and Africa</title>, appeared in 1834. See also Southey to John
                        Murray, 4 December 1814, Letter 2510.</note> However I have made many extracts, &amp; shall find means on more occasions than
                    one to speak usefully of the work.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey kept his word. For example, an extract from
                        Eulia Effendi appeared in the &#8216;Fragment of Interchapter&#8217; on the &#8216;History of Cats&#8217; in <title>The Doctor</title>, 7 vols
                        (London, 1834&#8211;1847), VII, p. 579. This dealt with the value assigned by various cultures to cats, concluding:
                        &#8216;Notwithstanding that high reputation and price of the Cats of Diorigi, they meet with dangerous enemies in their native
                        place, where sometimes forty or fifty of them are killed secretly, tanned and converted into fur for the winter time. It is a
                        fur scarce to be distinguised from Russian ermelin, and that of the red cats is not to be distinguished from the fox that
                        comes from Ozalov.&#8217;</note> Should you publish it I hope you will prevail upon the translator to fill up the gaps which he has
                    left, for he (in my opinion very injudiciously) omitted historical circumstances, legends, &amp; details of the authors personal
                    adventures, because they contain nothing geographical; as if none but mere geographers were to read the book. It is certainly a
                    most curious &amp; valuable work, but as certainly it is suited for the curious &amp; not for the public.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Murray did not publish the translation of Effendi.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I sincerely thank you for your offer of an advance upon the Spanish war.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> In case of need I will not scruple to avail myself
                    of it, &#8211; but I would rather make unusual exertions than incur that need. You lead me into <del>xx</del> Temptation when you hint
                    at a continuance of the Register.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Murray was proposing either to take over or continue
                        the failing <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> or to establish a new annual publication. He was sounding out Southey,
                        who had written for the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> from 1810&#8211;1813, as a possible lead contributor. In the end,
                        nothing came of the idea.</note> I threw it up because my payments were stopt in an unhandsome way.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had ceased working for the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> at the end of 1813.</note> It was
                    an employment which left me too little time for other avocations, but I pursued it <hi rend="ital">con amore</hi>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;with love&#8217;.</note> &amp; it constituted the greater part of my ways &amp; means. Whether I ought
                    in prudence <del>xx</del> again to take upon myself such a burden is not easily to be determined. For tho&#8217; sufficiently inclined,
                    still it should seem that with my reputation, &amp; with my powers both in verse &amp; prose I ought to be better remunerated for
                    avowed than for anonymous publications.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At present I have but too much in hand. Indeed I never have any prospect of finishing a work till it is fairly in
                    the press: then, other things must give way. For this reason I shall wish to put the Spanish War in, as soon as the Brazil<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The final two volumes of the <title>History of Brazil</title> appeared in 1817 and
                        1819.</note> comes out.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know of no continuous &amp; laborious work in which I should so willingly engage as in the Cosmorama of which we
                    talked; this if it were properly executed might form a source of permanent income. I have borne it in mind &amp; the notes which
                    have from time to time been collected are become numerous.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Also known as &#8216;A View of the
                        World&#8217;, nothing came of this; see Southey to John Murray, 31 March 1813, Letter 2238.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You need not send Charlemagne, for <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has given me a copy. I
                    think it a bad poem, &#8211; defective in all the higher requisitions of the art. The stanza is well constructed, &amp; the fable, tho
                    without <del>xx</del> any interest, put together with <del>tolerable</del> &lt;some&gt; ingenuity. But Lucien Buonaparte is
                    neither a poet nor a philosopher. Would you wait for the translation before it is reviewed? it is not yet gone to the press.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucien Bonaparte (1775&#8211;1840), brother of Napoleon and author of <title>Charlemagne, ou
                            l&#8217;Eglise D&#233;livr&#233;e</title> (1814). Southey had been asked to translate it into English and had refused. He did not review
                        Bonaparte&#8217;s poem but did insert a swipe at it in his review of accounts of Wellington and Waterloo, <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 13 (July 1815), 448&#8211;526: &#8216;The publication of Charlemagne, so ostentatiously announced, was fatal to his
                        literary character &#8230; his poem &#8230; proved him to be a sorry Homer&#8217; (489).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>I inclose with the MSS a small packet for <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Mr Bedford</ref>, &amp; request
                        that when you are sending to <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Mr Gifford</ref> you will have the goodness to let it be
                        dropt at his door.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 11 December 1814, Letter
                            2513.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>