<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2485</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3756</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.
                        .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2485" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2485" type="letter">
        <head>2485. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeGeorge">George Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1814-10-12">12 October
                        1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend George Coleridge/ Warden House/ Ottery
                            S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Mary/ Honiton/ Devonshire<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: Oct. 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.
                        1814/ From M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Southey<lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.
                        <lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. Cumberland.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-10-12">12 Oct. 1814.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should have written to you immediately upon the receipt of <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Mays</ref> letter, if a hope had not been held out that an exhibition of &#163;50 a year might be obtained by <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> if he went for six months to Haversham School,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Haversham Grammar School, a 17th-century foundation, which provided two &#8216;closed&#8217; scholarships for
                        ex-pupils to Oxford and Cambridge Universities.</note> in the adjoining county of Westmoreland. We have but just obtained the
                    necessary information upon this subject; &amp; I am sorry to say that it totally excludes him, &amp; offers but little chance for
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">his brother</ref>. The endowment gives a preference to boys born in the parish; in
                    default of such claimants others are admitted; but it is required that they shall have received the chief part of their education
                    at the school, &amp; even then it appears that every thing is decided not by a fair competition, but by direct favour, the
                    exhibition to Oxford being promised for the next three years, &amp; that to <del>Oxford</del> &lt;Cambridge&gt; pledged in like
                    manner six deep. &#8211; Things therefore are as they were when I first wrote to our excellent friend <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> May</ref>.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to John May, 10 September 1814,
                        Letter 2480.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The task of addressing you upon this subject Sir, is a painful one. It would be more so if I did not verily believe
                    that <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">your brother</ref> labours under a species of insanity. His intellect is as
                    powerful as it ever was, &amp; perfectly unclouded, &#8211; but all moral strength is paralyzed in him; &amp; when any thing comes
                    before him in the form of duty, it seems to take away from him not merely the inclination but even the power of performing it. It
                    would scarcely be speaking too strongly were I to say that he has abandoned his family to chance &amp; charity. He never writes to
                    them; &amp; it is in vain to importune him with letters when by chance we learn the place of his abode; for it has very long been
                    his custom never to open any letter which he thinks may by possibility contain any thing that he does not wish to hear, or relate
                    to any thing of which he does not chuse to be reminded.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All that <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S. Coleridge</ref> receives for the
                    maintenance of herself &amp; her three children is an annuity of &#163;75 <del>which was</del> left to your brother by <ref target="people.html#WedgwoodThomas">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Thomas Wedgwood</ref>; &#8211; an equal sum which was for many years
                    granted by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Josiah Wedgwood<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Josiah Wedgwood (1769&#8211;1843) had
                        withdrawn his share (&#163;75 p.a.) of Coleridge&#8217;s annuity in 1812.</note> having been withdrawn three or four years ago. From this
                    the income tax is deducted, &#8211; &amp; it can scarcely be necessary to add that the whole is consumed in the inevitable expences
                    incurred by the two boys, tho the schooling of the elder has been gratuitously afforded him</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> is now eighteen years of age. His talents are extraordinary, &amp;
                    wherever he has been, he has been remarkably fortunate in making friends. But he is not one of those fortunate persons whose
                    talents are convertible to any course, &#8211; in any other pursuit than that of letters, (the army perhaps excepted) he would be
                    helpless. His father has just so far interfered with his education as to derange it: in consequence of which while he was a
                    well-taught Grecian, he acquired for a long time no <del>x</del> other Latin than what was accidentally picked up. His Greek
                    however will more than cover his defects, &amp; from his acquirements, his talents &amp; his application, he must (in my
                    judgement) infallibly succeed at the University, if he takes the right course. It is, I am well aware, an expensive course of life
                    to propose for one who must be indebted to the bounty of relations who know him not, for the chief means of his support. But no
                    other course could so soon, or so surely enable him to obtain a provision for himself; &#8211; &amp; I know not what alternative could
                    be <del>proposed</del> suggested.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMary">Lady Beaumont</ref> has offered for this purpose 30&#163; a year, &#8211; an act of great &amp;
                    [MS torn]cited kindness. <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Mr Poole</ref>, who is his godfather has pr[MS torn] &#163;10 more. The
                    duty &amp; the absolute, imperious, necessity of strict frugality must be impressed upon him. He will be able to practise it,
                    because under whatever circumstances he may appear, his acquirements &amp; his understanding will command attention &amp; respect;
                    &amp; I trust that feeling the duty &amp; the necessity he will practice it. It is so long since I left college that I am little
                    able to estimate what the inevitable expences at this time would be. Should Cambridge be preferred for him he must go as a
                        Sizar,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A student who received assistance (e.g. meals, lodgings or reduced fees) in
                        return for college duties, originally of a menial nature.</note> &#8211; but he has no predilection for mathematics: &amp; wherever
                    he goes enquiry must be made concerning exhibitions, scholarships &amp;c. He was born in Gloucestershire. My friend <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Heber</ref> has been made acquainted with this, &amp; will make
                    enquiry at Oxford. On this subject I shall be happy to receive your opinion &amp; advice.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have written so fully concerning <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref>, the immediate
                    &amp; pressing object being to provide for him &#8211; that there is scarcely room to say anything of the other two children. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref> who is in his 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year, is an excellent boy, quick at
                    every branch of learning, &amp; fond of mathematics: he has no eccentricities (in this respect unlike his brother) &amp; his
                    temper &amp; talents &amp; steadiness will ensure his success in any way of life. The <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">little girl</ref> is uncommonly clever. At the age of 12 she is a good Italian
                    scholar, a tolerable one in French &amp; in Latin. She is at this time learning music, &amp; if her health fail her not, will be
                    admirably qualified for a Governess. I consider it as peculiarly unfortunate that these interesting children should be totally
                    unknown to all their fathers family: if however their present state of abandonment should lead to a renewal of that connection
                    which ought never to have been interrupted, good will arise from evil.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">George Coleridge&#8217;s
                        reply, 24 October 1814, is in the Ransom Center (MS (Coleridge, H), Misc): [extract] &#8216;I beg to acknowledge &lt;your
                        letter&gt; and to return you my Brothers&#8217; and my thanks for your explicit account of Samuel Coleridge and his family &#8211; To
                        ascertain the causes of his malady would it seems, be useless, since he refuses to hear such able and affectionate reasoning,
                        as you have occasionally offered him: and what is more melancholy, he has but little apology to make to the public for his
                        conduct, none to his family; none, I judge, to himself &#8211; none, I fear, to his God. &#8211; The effects however of his misconduct in
                        the course of things must be deplorable enough in every way. Hitherto indeed your most friendly and benevolent interposition
                        has prevented any great evil to his family: and it is to anticipate any ulterior harm that may arise from a continuation of
                        such dereliction of paternal duty that we wish to join you in the holy compact of providing for the fatherless.&#8217;</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Present my respectful remembrances to your brothers &amp; believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> My dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent4"> Yours with the truest respect</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>