<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2609</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3880</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Don. d.
                        3.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2609" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2609" type="letter">
        <head>2609. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1815-06-02">2
                        June 1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ Queen Anne
                        Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 5 JU 5/ 1815<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, Don. d.
                        3<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1815-06-02">2 June 1815</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope your Lordship goes on well with your contested election for Middlesex,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Herbert Southey was standing for election to the post of Senior Physician at the Middlesex Hospital.
                        Although the election was initially contested, by the time of the actual vote Southey was the only remaining candidate.</note>
                    which the Bp of Chester<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Henry Law (1761&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of
                        Chester 1812&#8211;1824, Bishop of Bath and Wells 1824&#8211;1845.</note> (who gives you his vote) tells me is very warmly contested. You
                    should have sent <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> when you wrote to me, &#8211; for we were too late in that quarter, &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> was too late with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pike Watts,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        David Pike Watts (1754&#8211;1816), a wealthy brewer and vintner.</note> but he promises for the Lord &amp; the Baronet, &#8211; who the
                    former is I know not unless it be Ld Calthorpe,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Gough-Calthorpe, 3rd Baron
                        Calthorpe (1787&#8211;1851).</note> the latter I suppose to be Sir T Bernard.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Thomas
                        Bernard (1750&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), lawyer and philanthropist.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have made an ugly discovery of a swelling in my neck, just above the collar bone, &amp; a little to the right of
                    the windpipe, which I found out by my shirt collars becoming tight upon me. <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmondson</ref>
                    saw it yesterday. You know I just know enough of nosology to have in turn every imaginable disease; &#8211; however I persuaded
                        <del>x</del> myself that this was not an aneurism, because I could find no pulsation. <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmondson</ref> is not certain whether it is an enlargement of some muscle whose name I do not remember, &#8211; or if it be
                    something under that muscle which protrudes it, &amp; which he imagines may be some of those hydatids who seem to have taken a
                    fancy to me. You know I have two lumps of them on my head &amp; there is a third coming. If it be so, he says, they will make way
                    to the surface &amp; suppurate. But there is no soreness nor any pain whatever. He has given me a discutient lotion, &amp; if that
                    fail will apply a mercurial plaister for the same purpose, &#8211; &amp; he desires me to use no muscular exertion that I can avoid. I
                    am not sensible of having straind myself, &#8211; tho it is very possible I may have done so, for I am fond of muscular exertion, such
                    as hanging by the hands from a bough &amp;c. Aneurism, he says, it is not: which of course he would say, &#8211; but I believe him; &#8211;
                    nor is it any thing in the nature of a wen. In short it is some damned thing or nother, as the Hampshire foxhunter said of his
                    dyspepsy, &#8211; &amp; I cannot button my shirt-collar &amp; must not row in a boat, &#8211; which prohibition at this season is an evil.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have worked very hard this quarter for the Review for a reason which you may easily conjecture.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s work for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> was driven by his need for money.</note>
                    And this reminds me of the pleasant Captain whom you saw here; it seems that having exhausted his credit in England he was on his
                    way to the continent, &amp; died at Dover of apoplexy.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Perkins (1778&#8211;1815), a
                        Captain in the Royal Navy and a cousin of Edith Southey. He had visited Keswick earlier in 1815 and Southey had lent him money
                        that was not repaid. Perkins died at Dover on 3 April 1815, so he may have been prevented from reimbursing Southey because of
                        ill-health, rather than as part of a fraud.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> means I believe to announce my Hist: of the Peninsular War in this forthcoming
                        number.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832). It was not advertised in the <title>Quarterly Review</title> at this
                        time.</note> I care not how soon it goes to press, the introductory chapter indeed is not written, &#8211; but so much of the
                    history itself is ready that the spur of the printer would <del>xxx</del> keep me in a steady jog trot to the end of the journey.
                    To days proof of Brazil<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The History of Brazil</title>; the second volume appeared in 1817.</note> brings me to page 216. <ref target="people.html#KosterHenry">Henry Koster</ref> has brought me a MSS from Pernambuco relating to the disturbances in that
                    Captaincy in 1710, &#8211; it is a good paper, &amp; gives me as much <del>x</del> information as I could desire upon that subject.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably a narrative of the Mascate War, or &#8216;War of the Peddlers&#8217; in Pernambuco in
                        1710&#8211;1711, &#8216;transcribed from the original mauscript&#8217;. Koster was thanked for providing Southey with this work in
                            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, p. vi. It appears as &#8216;Guerra Civil ou Sedissoens de
                        Pernambuco Exemplo Memoravel aos vindouros 1710&#8217;, no. 3840 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s Library.</note> I am getting on
                    well with this work.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the Panorama (which is on my <del>xxxx xx</del> establishment of Periodicals) it is stated that a late Brazil
                    packet when 1000 miles from any land was covered with a yellow dust in some places half inch deep. A volcano is supposed:<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Literary Panorama, and National Register</title>, 2 (May 1815), cols 317&#8211;318. This phenomenon was possibly caused by
                        the huge volcanic eruption at Tambora in Indonesia in April 1815.</note> &#8211; if <del>any volum</del> there was an eruption at
                    the time either in the Canaries or the Azores, <del>xx</del> we should have heard of it ere this, &#8211; or certainly shall hear.
                        <del>If</del> I believe that these showers proceed from the same cause as the sky-stones,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meteorites.</note> &amp; are precipitated from the atmosphere.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Scoresby of Whitby proposes to travel over the ice to the North Pole in sledges. I like
                    his scheme &amp; his reasonings better than I should like the journey. He has often been in the Whalers as far North as they go,
                    &amp; therefore has some experience of the climate.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Scoresby Jnr (1789&#8211;1857;
                            <title>DNB</title>), sailor and scientist, undertook several voyages to the Arctic on Whitby whalers captained by himself
                        or his father. He wished to lead a government sponsored expedition, and in 1817&#8211;1818 corresponded at length about this with
                        Joseph Banks (1743&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>). His idea was taken up, but command was given to the naval officer David Buchan
                        (1780&#8211;1838). In spite of this, Scoresby continued his Arctic researches, publishing numerous scientific papers and an
                            <title>Account of the Arctic Regions</title> (1820) and <title>Journal of a Voyage to the Northern Whale-Fishery</title>
                        (1823). Southey&#8217;s information was from a report in the <title>Literary Panorama, and National Register</title>, 2 (May 1815),
                        cols 290&#8211;291.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Shall we see you in August? Have you got a new house, or got rid of your old one? How is <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref>? &#8211; I shall certainly be in town at the fall of leaf, if not prevented by any
                    unforeseen ill. The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">childs</ref> ear continues in the same state, &#8211; &amp; a similar
                    discharge now takes place from the other. The hearing is not affected, &amp; therefore I suppose not in danger, &#8211; but I wish the
                    disease were removed &#8211; <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmondson</ref> will do nothing, &amp; evidently dislikes to be
                    spoken to about it. Excepting this &amp; my own neck we are doing well. My complaint you see is neck or nothing, &#8211; which is as bad
                    a pun as ever was laughed at by virtue of our old contract. Remember me at Champion Hill<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The family home of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa Gonne</ref>, soon to be Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s second
                        wife.</note> &amp; at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>