<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2578</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3849</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos,
                            The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 141&#8211;143.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2578" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2578" type="letter">
        <head>2578. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1815-03-20">20 March 1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Richmond/ Surrey<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 24MR24/ 1815; 10o&#8217;Clock/ MR.24/ 1815F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 179 1815/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> March/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June<lb />Watermark: J Dickinson &amp;
                        Co/ 1811<lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos,
                            <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 141&#8211;143.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1815-03-20">20 March 1815</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I replied to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridges</ref> part of your letter by the next
                        post.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to John Taylor Coleridge, 14 March 1815, Letter 2571.</note> My own
                    opinion is that <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> should go to Merton, &amp; be <del>to</del> removed
                    to Corpus as soon as opportunity offers,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> This plan was not followed. Hartley Coleridge
                        enrolled at Merton College, Oxford in 1815 and spent his undergraduate life there.</note> &#8211; but that he cannot afford to lose
                    time, being already <hi rend="ital">half past eighteen</hi>. But I see all the objections which <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">J. Coleridge</ref> has pointed out, &amp; see also, which he cannot so well do, what
                    additional force they derive from <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartleys</ref> character: Of this I endeavoured
                    to give him some knowledge, &amp; referred the decision finally to his own &amp; his cousin <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeWilliamHart">Williams</ref> judgement. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> is in many respects ominously like <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">his father</ref>; he has
                    indeed no bad habits, nor perceptible propensity to any; &amp; his principles at present are good. But he has a disposition to
                    justify whatever he does &amp; whatever he likes to do, &#8211; <del>&amp; there is a metaphysical xxxx</del> &amp; I fear <del>the
                        moral scr</del> that metaphysics are bred in the bone in him, like a moral scrofula.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A provoking occurrence has prevented me from sending you a draft for my first insurance.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John May was handling Southey&#8217;s life insurance payments in London.</note> I indorsed one for a Captain in the
                    Navy, (a cousin of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref>)<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Perkins
                        (1778&#8211;1815), a Captain in the Royal Navy. Perkins died at Dover on 3 April 1815, so he may have been prevented from repaying
                        Southey because of ill-health, rather than as part of a fraud.</note> which has been dishonoured; &amp; there seems reason to
                    suspect that this was foreseen, &amp; that my thirty pounds are lost. This could not have happened at a worse time, after the
                    failure of my Register income, my loss in the Register,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had lost the money he
                        invested in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> and his annual salary from writing for it.</note> &amp; when my main
                    employment (the Brazil<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The three-volume <title>History of Brazil</title>, published
                        between 1810&#8211;1819.</note>) might almost be called unproductive. With life &amp; health a short time will bring me fairly
                    round, for whenever my history<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>
                        (1823&#8211;1832).</note> is compleated I shall clear off all arrears. &#8211; At present I must draw for my own running expences what
                        <del>I</del> would else have been remitted to you. It is enough to state the fact &#8211; <del>I am sure</del> you know how I feel
                    respecting these obligations, I trust, &#8211; &amp; that I shall never be unmindful of them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should like to show you the mass of my Brazilian papers lying on yonder table: the quantity of labour which has
                    been bestowed upon them is what no person would believe unless he saw the extent of the materials. <del>In proportion to</del> The
                    time bestowed upon this work, <del>an equal quantity</del> is three, perhaps four times, as much as upon an equal quantity of
                    reviewing, &#8211; the utmost remuneration that I can expect not a third part of the common review price. Yet you may be sure that I do
                    not think the time misemployed, &#8211; &amp; perhaps work at it with a prouder feeling. I am at present busy upon the Jesuits in
                    Paraguay, &amp; this part of the subject with the chapters immediately subsequent respecting the state of manners &amp;c in Brazil
                    &amp; Paraguay, will form the most interesting portion of the whole work.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, pp. 333&#8211;380, 632&#8211;692.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not know who succeeded to my task in the Register, nor have I as yet seen the volumes.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1812</title> (1814). The historical section was written by the Scottish lawyer and writer,
                    James Russell (1790&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; The two articles on Chalmers are in fact but one, for the
                    whole of which there was not room in the one number.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander Chalmers (1759&#8211;1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of the English Poets, from Chaucer to Cowper</title> (1810), <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 11 (July 1814), 480&#8211;504; and <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (October 1814), 60&#8211;90.</note> The new
                    number now on the point of appearing has an article of mine upon Lewis &amp; Clarkes Travels<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meriweather Lewis (1774&#8211;1809) and William Clark (1770&#8211;1838), <title>Travels to the Source of the Missouri
                            River, and Across the American Continent to the Pacific Ocean</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (January
                        1815), 317&#8211;368.</note> &amp; (I believe) a shorter &lt;one&gt; upon an unpublished book by <ref target="people.html#RobertsBarreCharles">Barre Roberts</ref>, a cousin of my friend <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref>.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters and Miscellaneous Papers of Barr&#233; Charles Roberts</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (January
                        1815), 509&#8211;519.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are going on well, thank God, upon the whole. I find it no unprofitable task to <del>turn</del> have turned
                    schoolmaster: <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> has brought back my Greek, which had been almost forgotten,
                    &amp; <del>we</del> I learn German in the act of teaching him. Never did any boy promise more happily both in his intellectual
                    &amp; moral nature. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your God-daughter</ref> too grows up as I could wish her; she is as
                    good a Latin scholar as any boy of the same age, reads French &amp; Spanish with facility, &amp; is making some progress in
                    Italian. There is however no <hi rend="ital">cramming</hi> with all this, very little restraint &amp; very little confinement. All
                    is done easily &amp; almost <hi rend="ital">playfully</hi>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should be glad to hear that you were fairly settled in London. When the removal is over, <del>there will</del>
                    the <del>evil</del> &lt;pain&gt; will be past, <del>&amp; you will begin t</del> &amp; like all pain that has been induced by
                    worthy motives it will then become a source of satisfaction. I shall see more of you in my visits to town, &amp; find my way often
                    to your breakfast table, from <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To day brings us no London post &#8211; a cruel suspense at this time! I fear Buonaparte will get into Italy, where the
                    Italians have but too much reason to join him.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Napoleon had escaped from Elba on 26
                        February 1815, but he went to France, not Italy. Southey supported the idea of a united Italy and so feared Napoleon would be
                        able to gather support there.</note> &#8211; Looking at things with an eye to that moral order which pervades them, I could almost
                    expect a longer struggle in France than the last advices promise; &#8211; it would be a fine scene of retribution to see the soldiers
                    &amp; officers of that accursed school fighting against each other, &amp; thus taking vengeance for the rest of the world. &#8211; This
                    breaking lose of the Old Dragon<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Napoleon Bonaparte.</note> has put the Corn Bill<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Government had introduced its proposal for a sliding scale of duties on imported corn
                        on 1 March 1815. The Bill passed on 23 March 1815, despite much urban opposition.</note> out of sight &amp; out of mind. I
                    have scarcely room to speak of it. In my judgement nothing but the most clear &amp; convincing necessity could justify such a
                    Bill, for whether right or wrong, a Bill the avowed object of which is to raise the immediate price of Bread, must appear the
                    height of injustice to the multitude. To quarrel with the multitude upon such a question, &amp; in such times, is little better
                    than madness! But neither the Government nor the people know to what an extent the evil which I pointed out in that paper on the
                    State of the Poor,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December
                        1812), 319&#8211;356.</note> has proceeded. They tell you in Brazil of the <hi rend="ital">feiticeiros</hi>
          <note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Sorcerers or witches.</note> undermining the floor of a house &amp; filling it with poisonous spells. The
                    fabric of society in this kingdom is actually in that state. And if the riots had continued the <del>disaffected</del> &lt;mob&gt;
                    would soon have learnt the science of insurrection as perfectly as they understand that of <hi rend="ital">combination</hi> &amp;
                    of <hi rend="ital">finance</hi>. Our Government means well in every respect, &amp; in many respects is doing well: but it has
                    begun late; &amp; if another generation be allowed to pass before effectual means are taken for educating the people, carrying off
                    our superfluous population, &amp; providing the means of well-being for all who remain at home, I have a deep &amp; most mournful
                    conviction that England must go thro the horrors of a <hi rend="ital">Jacquerie</hi> &#8211; a Bellum Servile.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Literally a &#8216;Slave War&#8217;, i.e. a rebellion by the lower classes of society.</note> I could say much upon this
                    danger. &#8211; Remember me to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &#8211; &amp; believe me </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> most affectionately yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> means well &#8230; R. Southey: written on fol
                        1r.</note>
          </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>