<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2580</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3851</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2580" type="letter">
        <head>2580. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1815-03-25">25 March 1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9. Stafford Row/ Buckingham Gate/ London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 28 MR 28/
                        1815<lb />Endorsement: 25. March 1815<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1815-03-25">25. March 1815.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have received yours with the ten &#163;, &amp; am in no hurry for more, but when <del>my</del> the next payment is
                    made at the Exchequer I shall be obliged to you to pay Hyde<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hyde (d. 1820) was Southey&#8217;s
                        London tailor.</note> for a suit of clothes which I had in the summer (coat, waistcoat &amp; pantaloons) &#8211; &amp; when you may
                    be going that way I shall also be obliged to you to send from Twinings<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The London tea and
                        coffee merchants.</note> 24 pounds of 7<hi rend="sup">s</hi> souchong, &amp; four pounds of 13/<hi rend="sup">s</hi>
                    green.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I cannot but wish <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M Wellesley</ref> were Minister at this time. We want
                    a man capable of acting with vigour abroad &amp; with decision at home; &amp; I do not see what should at this time hinder either
                    him, or the <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Grenvilles</ref>, or both, from coming into power. The war I can contemplate
                    without fear, &amp; even with confidence, &#8211; the consequence at home I can<hi rend="ital">not</hi>. On this subject you know what
                    my apprehensions are: there are but few persons who agree with me in believing to how tremendous an extent the principle of
                    disaffection is diffused among the populace; the men in power either are ignorant of the danger, or like the ostrich they shut
                    their eyes to it. Do you remember what the parts were which <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> cut out of my
                    paper upon the state of the lower orders?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s article in <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356.</note> Precisely those which pointed out with most force the danger, &amp;
                    indicated the most effectual means of prevention. The first thing which ought to be done is to make transportation the punishment
                    for seditious libel. That being done, the <del>H</del> Gallery of the H of Commons should be cleard whenever <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdett</ref>, or any man like him rose. If they speak out of the house, or print what they have
                    said &lt;in&gt; it, there is no privilege to cover them. Government ought to restrain the license of the press as far as the laws
                    allow them; &amp; to counteract it by as much influence as possible. They are as insecure with a &lt;Jacobine&gt; press
                        <del>arrayed against them</del>, as Louis XVIII<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis XVIII (1755&#8211;1824; King of France
                        1814&#8211;1824).</note> was with an army of Buonapartes soldiers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Abroad, the prospect is better, tho Buonaparte will find allies in Belgium <del>&amp;</del> in Italy &amp; in
                    Switzerland. Still the great powers are now perfectly aware of his character, &amp; of their own interest. The question is a very
                    simple one, &#8211; it is whether you will suffer a Mamaluke Government<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mamluks were soldiers of
                        slave origin who dominated a variety of States in the Muslim world between the 9th and 19th centuries &#8211; hence a military
                        government.</note> to be established in the heart of Europe, &amp; in the most <del>will</del> formidable &amp; restless of
                    the European states. No sophistry can now conceal from the French this plain, that under the Bourbons they were enjoying peace, a
                    regular government, &amp; prosperity, under Buonaparte the whole evil of war, &amp; solely <del>for</del> thro his means. I only
                    fear that they will allow him to act on the offensive, whereas every principle of policy requires that France should be made the
                    theatre of war; &#8211; I talk not of the finger of Providence, &#8211; but am accustomed to contemplate the moral order of events, which is
                    perceptible to me, upon the great scale, throughout the course of human history. And I felt with indignation that an outrage had
                    been committed against the feelings of mankind when Buonaparte was not merely suffered to live, but honourably provided for as a
                        Prince;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1814 Napoleon had been allowed to retire to Elba and keep the title of
                        Emperor, a pension and a private guard</note>. &#8211; &amp; that vengeance had not been duly taken upon the ruffians who had
                    faithfully served him in all the abominations which he enjoined. I cannot venture to say what Marshals will follow the fortunes of
                    the King, but I fully believe that Massena, Soult &amp; Suchet<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Marshal Nicolas
                        Jean-de-Dieu Soult (1769&#8211;1851); Marshal Andre Massena (1758&#8211;1817); Marshal Louis Gabriel Suchet (1770&#8211;1826). Soult and Suchet
                        supported Napoleon in 1815; Massena was neutral. All had been prominent French commanders in the Peninsular War.</note> will
                    give in their <hi rend="ital">adhesion</hi> to Buonaparte. And if the war in its progress should cut off this generation of
                    ruffians from the earth, as I hope &amp; trust it will, I (who am no Methodist, &amp; far too heretical to subscribe to the Church
                    which nevertheless I would most zealously uphold in the present state of things,) &#8211; should certainly see in such a catastrophe a
                    proof of that all-disposing Wisdom, in which I believe &amp; trust.</p>
        <p rend="indent5"> ____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must not forget to ask you to learn for me what encouragement Government mean to give for emigrants to Canada. My
                    motive for enquiring is for <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> who has a brother here, a very fit subject for
                    such deportation; &amp; another in Staffordshire who in a better sense, would be a very good one to profit by it.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Barker&#8217;s brother, Frederick Barker (dates unknown) was a constant source of worry to his
                        sister. The names of her two other brothers are unknown.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. I <del>am</del> feel certain workings of the spirit towards sending out something in the way of a
                    political ode. By the bye I have recovered Greek enough in teaching <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, to be
                    at this time reading Pindar.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Greek lyric poet Pindar (c. 522&#8211;443 BC). Henry
                        Huntingford (1787&#8211;1867; <title>DNB</title>) published an edition of his poems in 1814, no. 2245 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Remember me to all at home.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> Did you receive a portion of Brazil<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> thro <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>? &#8211; The
                            <del>xxx</del>
            <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Printer</ref> waits for it.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>