<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2089</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3360</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2089" type="letter">
        <head>2089. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, [<date when="1812-05-06">early May
                        1812</date>]<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsements: Not dated; Written before the letter of Aug. 21.
                        1812 &amp; after that of March 10. 1812 wch states M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Goodens&#8217; books to be <hi rend="ital">on the
                            road</hi>
            <lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note: this letter was written the day after Southey
                        received a letter from Bahia, concerning some books on Brazilian history. Southey to Charles Danvers, 9 May 1812 (Letter 2093)
                        stated that he received the letter from Bahia &#8216;a few days ago&#8217;.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> I can make out nothing satisfactory respecting the Dutch &amp; Portugueze boundaries in Africa. Ereceyra has not a
                    word upon the subject.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luis de Meneses, 3rd Earl of Ericeira (1632&#8211;1690), <title>Historia
                            de Portugal Restaurado</title> (1679&#8211;1698), no. 3587 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
          <del>Xx</del> The Treaty of 1648<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Treaty of Munster (1648) between Spain (which still
                        claimed to rule Portugal, despite its declaration of independence in 1640) and the Netherlands.</note> which is the only one I
                    can discover that touches upon it, has some precise stipulations on the part of the Dutch, &#8211; but the Portugueze seem not to have
                    assented to them, &amp; the Treaty itself was never ratified. You will find an extract on the next leaf, &#8211; tho I might have spared
                    myself the trouble of making it; &#8211; for the Portugueze reply to these proposed articles that things shall be upon the same footing
                    as they were found by the ten years truce.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Treaty of The Hague (1641) stipulated a
                        ten-year truce between the Netherlands and Portugal &#8211; though, in effect, it only applied to Europe.</note> &#8211; Treaties between
                    the Dutch &amp; Portugueze respecting their boundaries were as little observed by one people as by the other, it is evident from
                    the historians of both people that they <del>both</del> &lt;each&gt; equally aimed at deceiving the other, &amp; the Portugueze
                    right to any part of Africa has always been exactly what it is now &#8211; the right of occupancy &amp; nothing else.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You make me smile by your news of Pelayo<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early name for
                            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> upon &#8216;good authority.&#8217; Upon all my concerns no authority can
                    be better than your own as I seldom fail to report progress to you when it is made in any of my numerous undertakings. The real
                    state of the poem is that the fifth book is just finished, which as the books are very short, may be considered <del>xxx</del>
                    &lt;to be&gt; about the proportion of one act to the whole tragedy. It has gone on like Kehama<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> had been started in 1801, but was not published until 1810.</note> very slowly &amp; for
                    the same reasons, that I give very little time to it, &amp; very often feel myself under a cloud respecting what is done.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Yesterday I received a letter from the Consul at Bahia,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frederick Lindeman
                        (dates unknown).</note> informing me that the Directors of the Public Library there had commissioned him to send me some MSS.
                    respecting S. America. A note from the Foreign Office accompanied this agreable intelligence, saying that a large packet of papers
                    was awaiting my direction. I write by this nights post to request they may be sent to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref>. I cannot make use of them, be they what they may, for the next two months &#8211; but you will like to overhaul
                    them. Give me some account of their contents that I may know in what manner to express my thanks to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                    Frederick Lindeman his Letter is a very civil one, offering me his services in any way that may promote my object, &amp; indeed
                    whether the Papers may prove of much value or not, it is a very gratifying circumstance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall give M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Rose in due time a proper wipe for the manner in when he has mentioned the
                    Epsom meeting.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the House of Commons on 25 February 1812, George Rose (1744&#8211;1818;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Vice-President of the Board of Trade 1807&#8211;1813, had defended his Parish Registers Bill, which
                        tightened up the regulations for recording births, marriages and deaths, and dismissed the protests of a meeting of Anglican
                        clergy at Epsom.</note> &#8211; What a business is this of Ponsonby<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Ponsonby
                        (1755&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor of Ireland 1806&#8211;1807 and leader of the Whigs in the House of Commons
                        1807&#8211;1817. He had stated in a Commons debate on 24 April 1812, that when he was in office in 1806&#8211;1807, he and the Duke of
                        Bedford had been told by the Prince Regent (George IV (1762&#8211;1830; Prince Regent 1811&#8211;1820, King of the United Kingdom
                        1820&#8211;1830; <title>DNB</title>) to communicate to Irish Catholics the Prince&#8217;s &#8216;favourable intentions&#8217; towards them.</note>
                    &amp; your friend the D.!<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford (1766&#8211;1839), leading Whig in
                        the House of Lords and Herbert Hill&#8217;s patron. Lord Lieutenant of Ireland 1806&#8211;1807.</note> &amp; what a state must parties be
                    in, when you find one set of men apologizing for what, if they do not take care, threatens to become an English <hi rend="ital">Jacquerie</hi> in the manufacturing districts;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Luddite movement, in the East
                        Midlands, Yorkshire and Lancashire. The Luddites smashed textile machinery as a threat to workers&#8217; livelihoods.</note> &#8211;
                    another continually goading on the Irish to rebellion, &#8211; &amp; a third taking up this rascal Henry&#8217;s business<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Henry (c. 1776&#8211;1853) was employed by the Canadian administration as a spy in Massachusetts,
                        to sound out the strength of opposition to war with Britain in the United States. When he was refused payment he revealed his
                        role to the United States government on 2 February 1812 in return for $50,000. The forged letters he produced suggested he had
                        been employed to actively promote the secession of the New England States from the Union and played an important role in
                        heightening Anglo-American tension.</note> &amp; making that a crime of our own Government, which is in reality (even if
                    admitted in the fullest extent), no more than what they would themselves have done &lt;had they been&gt; in administration; &#8211; what
                    they ought to have done, &#8211; &amp; what any men under such circumstances must have done. And yet this high &amp; flagrant
                    misdemeanour <del>xxx xxx xxx xxx</del> to give it the lightest appellation, passes unnoticed. The ministry cannot notice it,
                    because the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> himself has acted so culpably, &amp; not a man is found
                    independent enough &amp; constitutional enough to lift up his voice in Parliament.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You said something to me of some remarks of Burns<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Burn (fl.
                        1770s-1810s), a member of the British Factory in Lisbon.</note> upon Ld Strangfords Treaty.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Percy Clinton Sydney Smythe, 6th Viscount Strangford (1780&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>), British
                        envoy-extraordinary to the Portuguese court 1806&#8211;1814. He was responsible for the Treaty of 1808 between Portugal and Britain,
                        which opened Brazil to commerce with friendly nations (i.e. primarily Britain).</note> They would be of great use to me just
                    now.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have promised <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">J May</ref> to draw up a memoir of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Walpoles<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Walpole (1736&#8211;1810), Envoy Extraordinary to Portugal
                        1771&#8211;1800.</note> life for the Register, &#8211; but it must be next year. His correspondence will be sent me for this purpose,
                    &amp; will be useful in a more important business. I have some of his papers, &#8211; all of no value, except a <del>xxx</del> history
                    of Comte la Lippe&#8217;s campaign,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> William, Count of Schaumburg-Lippe-Buckeburg (1724&#8211;1777),
                        leading commander during the Seven Years War 1756&#8211;1763. He led the Portuguese army in 1762&#8211;1763 in a successful defence
                        against a Spanish invasion.</note> which <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is transcribing for me, &amp; a
                    letter of W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Stephens&#8217;<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Stephens (1731&#8211;1803), owner and
                        developer of the main glassworks in Portugal, known as the &#8216;Fabric&#8217;.</note> containing a <del>xxx xxxx</del> describing a
                    visit to Pombal<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sebastiao Jose de Carvalho e Melo, Marquess of Pombal (1699&#8211;1782), Prime
                        Minister of Portugal 1750&#8211;1777.</note> in his disgrace.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#GoodenJames">Goodens</ref> books<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey later publicly thanked
                        Gooden for &#8216;the Life of F. Joam d&#8217;Almeida, among other books, and a manuscript Apology for the Jesuits in Paraguay and
                        Maranham, of great importance&#8217;, see Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, p. [v]. Also,
                        Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 1 February 1812, Letter 2027.</note> prove very useful. The long sought life of P Joam de
                        Almeida,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Simon de Vasconcellos (1599&#8211;1670), <title>Vida do Joam d&#8217;Almeida</title>
                        (1658). This was a life of the English-born Jesuit missionary, John Almeida (1571&#8211;1653).</note> tho it does not give what I
                    expected to find there, nevertheless gives me much which is highly interesting. Jaboatam<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Antonio de Santa Maria Jaboatao (1695&#8211;1763/1765), <title>Novo Orbe Serafico Brazilico ou Chronica dos Frades Minores da
                            Provincia do Brazil</title> (1761).</note> is by far the best author extant respecting Brazil. And the MS. apology of the
                        Jesuits<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> An unidentified manuscript that Southey thanked Gooden for supplying in
                            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, p. [v].</note> which I am now perusing contains much
                    valuable information respecting that abominable business of the 7. Povos.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Treaty of
                        Madrid (1750) transferred to Portugal a tract of land on the east side of the Uruguay River. This contained seven Jesuit
                        settlements, which were to be dismantled and rebuilt on Spanish territory on the other side of the river. The inhabitants
                        resisted, leading to the War of the Seven Reductions, or Guarani War, in 1756&#8211;1757.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; When we take towns by storm we should let our allies pay off part of their long score.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> This may be a reference to the events following the storming of Badajoz on 6 April 1812, when the
                        Anglo-Portuguese army indulged in 72 hours of murder, rape and looting against the civilian population.</note> My Love to <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the young ones. </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>