<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2172</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3443</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                  1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                  only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                  redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                        Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                  that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                  additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                  all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Robert H. Taylor Collection, Princeton University Library. Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
               Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 350&#8211;352 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript
               Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
               Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University
               Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
               Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University; the John Rylands Library,
               Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
               Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public
               Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
               Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne;
               the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the English Department of
               Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey&#8217;s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2172" type="letter">
        <head>2172. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LongmireJohnMartyn">John Martyn Longmire</ref>, <date when="1812-11-04">4
                  November 1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend J. M. Longmire/ Hargrave/ near/ Kimbolton<lb />Stamped:
                  KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Robert H. Taylor Collection, Princeton University Library. ALS; 4p.<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                  Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 350&#8211;352 [in
                  part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-11-04">Nov. 4. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am duly sensible, Sir, of the honour you have conferred upon me by your letter of Oct 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, &amp;
               shall be still farther gratified by a communication of the Sketch which is there mentioned.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  This had read <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801) as an allegory of the powers and virtues of Faith, and drawn parallels
                  between events and characters in Southey&#8217;s poem and the bible.</note> My aim has ever been <del>xx</del> to diffuse thro my poems a
               sense of the beautiful &amp; good, (<del>x</del> &#964;&#959; &#954;&#945;&#955;&#959;&#957; &#954;&#945;&#953; &#945;&#947;&#945;&#952;&#959;&#957;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A common phrase in
                  classical Greek, which translates as &#8216;the beautiful and the good&#8217;.</note>) rather than to aim at the exe[MS missing]fication of any
               particular moral precept. It has however so happened that both in Thalaba &amp; Kehama, the nature of the story led me to represent
               examples of faith.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Islam in <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801) and Hinduism in
                     <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At a very early age, indeed while I was a school-boy, my imagination was strongly impressed by the mythological fables
               of different nations. I can trace this to the effect produced upon me when quite a child by some prints in the Christians
                  Magazine,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Christian&#8217;s Magazine</title> (1760&#8211;1767) was almost entirely the work
                  of William Dodd (1729&#8211;1777; <title>DNB</title>).</note> copied as I afterwards discovered from the great work of Picart.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bernard Picart (1673&#8211;1733), <title>Ceremonies et Coutoumes Religieuses de Tous les Peuples du
                     Monde</title> (1723&#8211;1743).</note> I got at Picart when I was about fifteen, &amp; soon became as well acquainted with the Gods of
               Asia &amp; America as &lt;with those&gt; of Greece &amp; Rome. This led me to conceive a design of rendering every mythology which had
               ever extended itself widely &amp; powerfully influenced the human mind, the basis of a narrative poem. I began with the religion of the
               Koran, &amp; consequently founded the interest of the story upon that resignation which is the only virtue it has produced. Had Thalaba
               been more succesful, my whole design would <del>xx</del> by this time have been effected, for prepared as I was with the whole
               materials for each, &amp; with a general idea of the story, I should assuredly have produced such a poem every year. &#8211; For popular
               praise, quoad praise I cared nothing, &#8211; but it was of consequence to me inasmuch as it affected those emoluments with which my worldly
               circumstances did not permit me to dispense. The sacrifice therefore was made to prudence, &amp; it was not made without reluctance.
               Kehama lay by me in an unfinished state for many years, &amp; but for a mere accident might perhaps for ever [MS torn]ve remained
               incompleat.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Whether the design may ever be accomplished is now very doubtful. The inclination &amp; the power remain, but time has
               past away. My literary engagements are numerous &amp; weighty, beyond those of any other individual, &amp; tho by Gods blessing I enjoy
               good health, never-failing chearfulness, &amp; unweariable perseverance, there seems to be more before me than I shall ever live to get
               thro, &#8211; <del>for the</del> being of a short-lived race. I have published no poem since Kehama, but have one in considerable forwardness
               upon the Restoration of Spain by Pelayo,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> This became <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                     Goths</title> (1814).</note> &#8211; of heroic (not mythological) cast <del>x</del>, &amp; bearing by a sort of reflected feeling upon
               the present struggle in the peninsula.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#LloydCharles">Mr Lloyd</ref> I am sorry to say suffers under a dreadful nervous malady. I have often
               accompanied him in the car which is now in your possession.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Believe me Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yours with due respect</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> My next mythological poem, should I ever write another, would be founded upon the system of Zoroaster.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s wording here is close to his note in <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood
                     Warter, 4 series (London, 1849&#8211;1851), IV, p. 12. The idea for a poem on the prophet Zoroaster did not proceed any further.</note>
                  A son of the Great King would be the chief personage, I should represent him as persecuted by the Evil Powers, &amp; make every
                  calamity which they brought upon him the means of evolving <del>in him</del> some virtue which would else never have been called
                  into action. In the [MS torn] paths of false religion may be made subservient to the pa[MS torn]ly exciting &amp; strengthening
                  Christian feelings.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>