<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1846</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3117</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1846" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1846" type="letter">
        <head>1846. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1810-12-28">28 December
                        1810</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Postmark: [illegible]<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1810-12-28">Dec. 28. 1810.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have got half a dozen books from a Catalogue of which Wynn sent me a frank full containing all the Sp. &amp; P.
                    articles. Ordenanzas de Marina para los Navios de las Philipinas que hacen viages al R. de la N Espa&#241;a in otro destino &#8211; a book
                    with no date of place but apparently printed at Manilla, &amp; with two charts<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">.
                            <title>Ordenanzas de Marina para los Navios del Rey de las Islas Philipinas, que en Guerra y con Reales Permissos hacen
                            Viages al Reyno de la N. Espa&#241;a In Otro Destino del Real Servicio</title> (1757); no. 3603 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Arte de Navigar del Rodrigo Camorano, Cosmografi y Peloto Mayor. 1588.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The cosmographer Rodrigo &#199;amorano&#8217;s (1542&#8211;1623) <title>Compendio del Arte de Navigar</title> (1588); no. 3243
                        in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Imperio de la China &amp; cultura Evangelica en el por los Rel. de la Comp.
                    por el D. Alvaro Semmedo publicado por M. de Faria y Sousa<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alvaro Semmedo (1585/6&#8211;1658),
                            <title>Imperio de la China</title> (1642); no. 3686 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; Gentio de Angola
                    sufficientemente instrucdo nos mysterios de nossa S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fe. 1642.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Francesco Paccoino (d. 1641), <title>Gentio de Angola</title> (1645); no. 3440 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library.</note> Esperan&#231;a de Israel &#8211; a treatise by Menasseh Ben Israel, &#8211; containing an account of a Jewish El-Dorado in S.
                        America,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manasseh ben Israel (1604&#8211;1657), <title>Esperance de Israel</title> (n.d.);
                        no. 3177 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; which I had seen in one of R. B&#8217;s (Burton&#8217;s) little books,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Robert Burton&#8217; and &#8216;R.B&#8217; were pseudonyms used by the bookseller and writer Nathaniel
                        Crouch (c. 1640&#8211;1725?; <title>DNB</title>). They were chosen in reference to Robert Burton (1577&#8211;1640; <title>DNB</title>),
                        author of the <title>Anatomy of Melancholy</title> (1620), which incorporated hundreds of translations from Latin and Greek
                        sources, thus making classical knowledge more widely available to the less privileged classes. Crouch was equally keen to
                        democratise learning, producing simplified versions of more learned works and histories and publishing these cheaply, thus
                        ensuring a wide circulation.</note> &amp; a few other facts bearing upon Brazil &amp; Portugal. Lastly, a book which the
                    former possessor has very properly lettered Figmente Annii Viterbensis,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;An invention of
                        Annius Viterbus&#8217;. Annius of Viterbo was the pseudonym of Giovanni Nanni (1432/1437&#8211;1502). He gained notoriety through his
                            <title>Commentaria Super Opera Diversorum Auctorum de Antiquitatibus Loquentium</title> (1506), a revisionist account of
                        European history. It purported to have discovered a series of &#8216;lost&#8217; authors, including Chaldaeus Berosus (a historian,
                        astrologer and philosopher). A series of commentaries by Annius linked these &#8216;new&#8217; writings to actual biblical and classical
                        authorities. In fact, they were fakes. For the impact of Annius&#8217;s forgeries on European thought in the early Renaissance and
                        later see Walter Stephens, &#8216;When Pope Noah Ruled the Etruscans: Annius of Viterbo and his Forged Antiquities&#8217;, <title>Modern
                            Language Notes</title>, 119.1 (January 2004), 201&#8211;223.</note> containing the whole of his forgeries with his commentary
                    thereon. Antwerpi&#230;. 1545.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The pseudo-Chaldaeus Berosus, <title>Antiquitatum Italiae ac
                            Totius Orbis Libri Quinque</title> (1545); no. 274 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This purported to be by the
                        Chaldean historian, but was in fact a forgery.</note> &#8211; I have long been on the look out for this, which is necessary for the
                    sketch of the fabulous history of Portugal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A larger cargo from a Bristol catalogue is on the road.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has sent me a Political Essay on the Kingdom of Peru (so entitled in
                    imitation of Humboldt)<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. to imitate Alexander von Humboldt (1769&#8211;1859),
                            <title>Political Essay on the Kingdom of New Spain</title>, an English translation of which was published by Longman in
                        1811.</note> by Walton who has lately published a bad book upon the Sp. Colonies.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        William Walton (1783/4&#8211;1857; <title>DNB</title>). He had been junior secretary to the British expedition which captured Santo
                        Domingo from the French in 1802, and had remained there as British agent. He returned to England in 1809 and developed a
                        career as a political journalist, arguing against ministerial policies towards Spain and Portugal. His writings included
                            <title>Present State of the Spanish Colonies; Including a Particular Report of Hispaniola, or the Spanish Part of Santo
                            Domingo</title> (1810). His &#8216;Political Essay&#8217; on Peru was not published, but some of its ideas were probably incorporated
                        into his <title>An Expos&#233; of the Dissentions of Spanish America</title> (1814).</note> He has got materials, but is neither
                    well read in any thing, nor has he judgement enough to put together what information he possesses in a tolerable shape. I wish his
                    MS. was printed, &amp; yet I think it will not pay for publication. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> possibly
                    suspects this, or after having published one work for him, he would not have referred this to me for an opinion. About three parts
                    of it are taken from the Lima Almanachs, &#8211; a collection of which <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> lent me,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Descripcion de las Provincias Pertenecientes al Arzobispado di Lima&#8217;; no. 3645 in the
                        sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, inscribed in his hand: &#8216;This book of which perhaps a duplicate is nowhere to be found,
                        was given me by Mr Murray; it contains the fullest account which has yet been published on the old Vice-royalty of Peru,
                        province by province. The information was obtained from the respective Corregidores, and printed for many successive years in
                        the Lima Almanack, from whence some curioso cut out the whole collection, and formed them into this <hi rend="ital">most
                            valuable volume</hi>&#8217;.</note> the author has got at some documents of later date, &#8211; very probably published in the same
                    manner, &#8211; &amp; from &lt;with&gt; these, one or two ill-digested essays, Sobrevielas<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Spanish Franciscan missionary Manuel Sobreviela (fl. 1783&#8211;1803). His &#8216;Mapa de las Misones del Peru&#8217; was published in the
                            <title>Mercurio Peruano</title>, 81 (13 October 1791).</note> map from the Mer. Peruano, one or two prints from Spanish
                    books &amp; a few wretched drawings he has made up his &#8216;Political Essay upon the Kingdom of Peru,&#8217; &#8211; borrowing his title from
                    Humboldt.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had a letter the other day from <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> telling me (in perfect
                    confidence was his phrase) that &#8220;some perfectly independent country gentlemen of good political information &amp; whose views were
                    in every respect pure &amp; free from party&#8221; were about to undertake a new review,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                            <title>British Review and London Critical Journal</title> (1811&#8211;1825). Southey did not contribute.</note> which they had
                    applied to him to publish &#8220;the laziness, the occupations, or the partial knowledge of the gentlemen &amp; <hi rend="ital">gratuitous</hi> writers would render essential the support of a sterling literary character&#8221; &#8211; &amp; he should prefer me to
                    any other man, &#8211; if I would regularly or occasionally assist him, at the ten guineas per sheet price. &#8211; I told him that I did not
                    think a neutral review (supposing un-party profession were to be believed) &#8211; would succeed; &#8211; that both the Edinburgh &amp; the
                    Quarterly found it necessary to set out with excluding all gratuitous matter, &#8211; &amp; necessarily paid 20 guineas per sheet, &#8211;
                    which price I had received for the reviewal of the life of Nelson;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of
                        John Charnock (1756&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Biographical Memoirs of Lord Viscount Nelson, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.;
                            with Observations, Critical and Explanatory</title> (1806); James Harrison (d. 1847), <title>The Life of Lord
                            Nelson</title> (1806); T. O. Churchill (fl. 1800&#8211;1823), <title>The Life of Lord Viscount Nelson, Duke of Bront&#233;,
                            &amp;c</title> (1808); and James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>) and John McArthur (1755&#8211;1840;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of Admiral Lord Nelson, K.B. from his Lordship&#8217;s Manuscripts</title> (1809), see
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218&#8211;262. It was later expanded into a full-scale <title>Life of
                            Nelson</title> (1813).</note> &#8211; that having been engaged with the Quarterly from its commencement, I could not with
                    propriety withdraw from it, &#8211; &amp; that it was impossible to spare time for writing for another. &#8211; In fact if there were no other
                    objection, I should never consent to bear the burthen of such a work upon my shoulders, (which is clearly what is wanted here)
                    while the power &amp; the management were vested in others. I suppose they thought their politics would tempt me, &#8211; but I am not
                    intolerant in these matters, &amp; the Pitt-idolatry<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gifford and Canning were both
                        admirers of William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), while Southey was an unsparing
                        critic.</note> of <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref>
                    is of no consequence to me. I care little for any temporary politics except the <del>xxxxxxx</del> &lt;point&gt; of standing by
                    the Spaniards, &amp; carrying on the war with Buonaparte <del>xxxxxxxx xxxxxxxxxx</del>; there is nothing else which is worth a
                    thought now or can excite any interest hereafter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will see an Article of mine upon Methodism in the next Quarterly, in which I have hinted at the propriety of
                    borrowing some parts of the Methodist system, in a manner that might easily &amp; unexceptionably be done.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Hints to the Public and the Legislature, on the Nature and Effect of
                            Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title> (1809), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 480&#8211;514.
                        Southey recommended the circulation of popular histories of the English Reformation. This article appeared at the end of
                        December 1810.</note> &#8211; I shall soon make a deadly blow at Malthus, whose book I consider as both in its principle &amp; its
                    tendency one of the most detestable that ever was written.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The political economist Thomas
                        Robert Malthus (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>). The &#8216;book&#8217; was his <title>Essay on the Principle of Population</title>, first
                        published in 1798, it had gone into four editions by 1807.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> tells me that its details are as erroneous as its deductions &amp; will supply
                    me with detections for that portion of the work. I expect to produce something that will give the Quarterly a considerable lift,
                    for this is a subject of which I feel myself thoroughly master.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first of a series of
                        Southeyan articles on the poor appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356, was intended as
                        &#8216;an attack upon Malthus&#8217;, amongst others; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 5 January 1813, Letter 2199.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you wish to give away any copies of Kehama<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> let <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> place them to the
                    account of the publication. How is <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">my young cousin</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">his mother</ref>? We have had a general sickness thro the whole of the children, &#8211; an
                    influenza, &#8211; accompanied in <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> with a return of the croupe, &#8211; but this does
                    not alarm us now, &#8211; the return of the complaint being always in a mitigated form, &#8211; &amp; indeed I am disposed to think (in
                    opposition to our medical assistant who is a very skillful practitioner) that the croupe which we have in this valley, resembles
                    that of the Shetlands rather than that of the South of England, &amp; is in fact a much less dangerous disease.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Many happy returns of the season to you &amp; <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>