<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1807</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3078</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS
                        1817.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1807" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1807" type="letter">
        <head>1807. Robert Southey to [<ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn  ">John Ballantyne</ref>], <date when="1810-09-19">19 September
                        1810</date>
          </head><p>MS: National Library of Scotland, MS
                        1817<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Note on MS: MS exists only in a copy in an unknown hand in the Ballantyne papers, National Library
                        of Scotland. A note makes it clear that the copy was made to be sent to Ballantyne&#8217;s friend, business associate and writer for
                        the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>, Robert Lundie.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1810-09-19">19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Sept 1810</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My Dr Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> With respect to most of the objections which have been made to the History, I can reply in a manner that will be
                    quite satisfactory.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The letter deals with Southey&#8217;s work for the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register</title>, for which he wrote the historical section. It is part of an exchange with Ballantyne over the content
                        and tone of Southey&#8217;s contributions and also the structure and contents of the <title>Register</title> itself. In particular,
                        the potential overlap between Southey&#8217;s account in part 1 of the <title>Register</title> of British and continental events in
                        1808 and the &#8216;Chronicle&#8217; that appeared separately in part 2. See also Southey to Robert Lundie, 14 October 1810, Letter
                        1817.</note> The season of Proclamations is past and no temptation exists to a repetition of the fault if fault it be, &amp; I
                    am afraid it is so because it is the only objection which I wish had not been made.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        subject being discussed here is obscure.</note> Of <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Sir Francis Burdett</ref> I am most
                    assuredly disposed to speak and think with great severity. If I remember rightly I expressed this opinion to you when I first made
                    use of the very mischievous phrase which you have noticed, but of the Duke of York I will speak with careful decorum &#8211; indeed it
                    is not a subject, whatever its immediate importance, on which I am capable of feeling strongly.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1809, Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>) had been forced to resign
                        as commander-in-chief of the British army in the wake of allegations that he had profited from office trafficking. After a
                        lengthy investigation, the charges were found to be unproven. It had, however, become apparent that his former mistress Mary
                        Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) had received money from individuals keen for her to use her influence with the
                        Duke, and that the Duke himself had known of her actions. For Southey&#8217;s account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 109&#8211;301.</note> An opinion as you say must be expressed but it will be done as briefly as that
                    upon the Copenhagen question without any asperity and in a manner which I am confident cannot give offence.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. The parliamentary debates over the controversial British attack on Copenhagen, 16 August&#8211;5
                        September 1807. The government claimed this was an attempt to secure British access to the Baltic, the opposition
                        argued that it had turned hitherto neutral Denmark into an enemy. For Southey&#8217;s account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 31&#8211;53.</note> &#8211; Concerning other individuals I will endeavour to write more temperately provided
                    every now &amp; then I may be allowed <del>xxx xxxxxx</del> to speak plainly concerning the admirers of Bonaparte particularly
                        M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Whitbread.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The radical MP Samuel Whitbread (1764&#8211;1815;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> To think about them opens the gall and pouring off two or three bitter sentences may prevent a
                    bilious attack. To the remaining objections that there is a democratical colouring thrown over the whole I know of no better
                    answer than that such a colouring must needs be the sunshine and life of whatever proceeds from me. Yet I have no fear that this
                    can be injurious, sure as I am that it is true English Democracy unconnected with faction or even with party, true to the interest
                        <del>of</del> &amp; to the honour of England &amp; going head &amp; heart with the King<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of the United Kingdom 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; with &lt;the&gt; Government.
                    Depend upon it the heaviest complaints against the Register will come from the <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobettites</ref>,
                    the Emancipators, (who may truly be called the agitators) and the peace mongers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If I had planned the Register I should have endeavoured to make it strictly correspond with its title &amp;
                    excluded whatever did not belong to the history of the times, taking the word history in its evident acceptation. In the Chronicle
                    if it be thought necessary to insert the Gazette accounts (which I rather incline to think superfluous their substance being
                    included in the History) I would arrange them by themselves consecutively.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> This idea was
                        not adopted in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.2 (1811).</note> The fuller the Chronicle is in this
                    respect the better, and I would glean all the newspapers for it. The very follies and extravagences of the age are parts of its
                    History. The meeting of the four in hand club,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> An aristocratic club of 30&#8211;40 members,
                        which met 1808&#8211;1824.</note> the Grand Matches at Cricket even the fashions and the official account of the battles between
                    Gully &amp; Gregson<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. A prize-fighting match between John Gully (1783&#8211;1863;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Bob Gregson (d. 1824). On 10 May 1808 the two fought, watched by over a hundred members of
                        society. The vast crowd led to a scare that the French had invaded and the local volunteers were called out. After 27 rounds
                        Gregson was unable to continue and the fight was given to Gully. This event was not reported in <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1809</title>, 2.2 (1811).</note> all <del>lead</del> &lt;tend&gt; to characterise our times and in this view
                    would amuse and interest posterity. Burke was so sensible of this that in the first Volumes of the annual Register which he
                    planned for Dodsley<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Annual Register</title>, initiated in 1758 by the
                        bookseller and author Robert Dodsley (1704&#8211;1764; <title>DNB</title>). It provided a chronicle of the major events of the
                        previous year, and included poetry, reviews and essays on literary, historical and topographical subjects. From 1758 until
                        1764&#8211;1765 its editor and chief contributor was Edmund Burke (1729/30&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>). Southey possessed 8 volumes
                        from the period 1758&#8211;1790, no. 49 in the sale catalogue of his library. <title>Annual Register</title>, 1 (1758), 278&#8211;310, comprised a section of &#8216;Extraordinary Adventures&#8217;, including &#8216;The wonderful preservation of three persons buried above
                        five weeks in the snow&#8217;.</note> there was a separate department for remarkable adventures.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Dramatic article<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The section devoted to drama in <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.2 (1810), 253&#8211;325.</note> is too long and the criticism upon the performers might I
                    think well have been spared. This you say will be contracted in the second volume. Poetry would have been excluded from my
                        plan.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Original poetry was included in the second part of each year&#8217;s <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register</title>. Contributors to <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.2 (1810) included, Scott,
                        Baillie and Southey himself, with &#8216;The Alderman&#8217;s Funeral, an English Eclogue&#8217;, &#8216;King Ramiro&#8217; and &#8216;Queen Orraca&#8217; (i&#8211;xiii), and
                        a section from <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), Book 11, lines 27&#8211;112 (xlvi&#8211; xlviii). The first of these had not
                        been published before, but &#8216;King Ramiro&#8217; had appeared in <title>Morning Post</title>, 9 September 1803 and &#8216;Queen Orraca&#8217; in
                            <title>Morning Post</title>, 1 September 1803.</note> It crept originally into this work (I am well convinced) because
                    there was not historical matter enough to fill the volumes and therefore they were made Magazines as well as registers. &#8211; I will
                    send you what few verses I have unpublished. I have numberless subjects for poetry noted down and if I can rouse up inclination
                    enough, will endeavour to strike off some of them. If I had leisure I would do something also for your Biography.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ballantyne was proposing to add a section of biographies to the second part of each year&#8217;s
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>. This idea was not adopted in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.2
                        (1811).</note> The life of John Wesley is one which it has <del>long been desirous</del> &lt;long been interested&gt; to
                        write.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1820 Southey published a <title>Life</title> of John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791;
                            <title>DNB</title>), the founder of Methodism.</note> Cannot you get one of Toussaint?<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The hero of Haitian independence, Fran&#231;ois-Dominique Toussaint-Louverture (1743&#8211;1803).</note> This also I
                    could write con amore,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;with love&#8217;.</note> if like Kehama I could multiply myself upon
                        occasion.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> See <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), Book 24, where Kehama
                        &#8216;self-multiplies&#8217;.</note> But this yearly history is a long work. <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> looks to
                    me for the Quarterly &amp; if you could see the quantity of materials which I have written for my series of Portugueze
                        History,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) and Southey&#8217;s unfinished
                        &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> I think you would admire the patience with which I postpone their final arrangement till a more
                    convenient season, though it is chiefly upon this work &lt;that&gt; I rest my claims upon posterity. There is a life of that
                    diabolical woman Mary Bateman printed at Leeds which would make a very curious article in your Biography and which ought to find a
                    place there.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Extraordinary Life and Character of Mary Bateman, the Yorkshire Witch</title> (1809), an account of the thief,
                        fraudster and poisoner Mary Bateman (1768&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>). Playing on the popularity of the Southcottians, in 1806
                        Bateman claimed that one of her hens had laid three miraculous eggs inscribed with &#8216;Christ is coming&#8217;. Hundreds of people came
                        to see the eggs and were charged a penny each for the privilege. The &#8216;Chronicle&#8217; in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1808</title>, 1.2 (1810), 210&#8211;261, had included an account of her activities and execution.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Dramatic article, that upon the fine arts &amp; that upon Literature<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.2 (1810), 326&#8211;341 and 417&#8211;443.</note> look as if they came from the same
                    hand &amp; all of them seem to bear a family resemblance to the stile of the Prospectus.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), [v]&#8211;xii.</note> &#8211; I wrote the other day to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">W. Scott</ref> to tell him that a rascally attack <del>had been made</del> upon him which
                    appeared in the Courier with the signature S.T.C. did not proceed from <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> who I am very glad to say has written to the Courier requiring the Editor to acquaint himself if <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> was here lately.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Courier</title> (15 September 1810) had published an article entitled &#8216;Some Imitations of Scott&#8217;. This compared
                        extracts from <title>The Lay of the Last Minstrel</title> and <title>Marmion</title> with ones from Dryden, Baillie, Home,
                        Ossian, Pope, Spenser, and Southey (<title>Madoc</title>) in an attempt to prove that Scott had been &#8216;more particularly &#8230;
                        guilty of imitation&#8217;. A declaration, supplied by Coleridge, that the &#8216;S.T.C.&#8217; who had signed the piece on Scott was not the
                        same person as &#8216;Mr. S. T. Coleridge&#8217; appeared in the <title>Courier</title> on 20 September 1810; see Southey to Walter Scott,
                        17 September 1810, Letter 1806.</note> He has seen a good deal of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> and took a great deals of pain to persuade him that he passionately admired my poetry and <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref>. It is well I was not present when he delivered this opinion of me or
                    I should assuredly have been irresistably tempted to let him know my opinion of him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am glad you perceive an improvement in the debates. Be assured that no man can be more ready than myself to
                    acknowledge his own errors when they are pointed out nor more desirous to <del>correct</del> &lt;lessen&gt; them. &#8211;<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ballantyne adds his own postscript: &#8216;My Dr L: I send you this letter because I think it will give
                        you pleasure &#8211; what he says concerning the chronicle is I think well worth your attention. I have long despised the
                        squeamishness which would reject boxing matches &amp;c. If you paint a fair paint warts and all or it is no likeness. Yours
                        JB.&#8217;</note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>