<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2193</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3464</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 315&#8211;317.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2193" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2193" type="letter">
        <head>2193. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1812-12-30">30 December
                        1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey. R. N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helens/ Auckland<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 315&#8211;317.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Tom,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should know that midshipmans name if I saw it, &amp; the name we must have &#8211; so I have written to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> to learn what mids of the Victory fell in that action.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey wished to know the names of the midshipmen who shot the French sailor who killed Nelson
                        at the Battle of Trafalgar (1805). In Southey&#8217;s final account they were Francis Edward Collingwood (1785&#8211;1836) and John
                        Pollard (d. 1868). See <title>The Life of Nelson</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813), II, pp. 264&#8211;265.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You used to speak of the dead lying in shoal water at Copenhagen;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom was
                        providing Southey with information about the battle of Copenhagen, 2 April 1801, in which he had fought. For the build up to
                        the battle, the engagement and its aftermath, see <title>Life of Nelson</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813), II, pp. 95&#8211;153.</note>
                    there was the boatswains mate, or somebody, asked for, when he was lying face upward under the stern or somewhere, &#8211; tell me the
                    right particulars of this, &#8211; which is too striking a circumstance to be lost. I believe I <del>xxx</del> &lt;am&gt; making a most
                    impressive narrative of this battle by your help. Some thing I remembered from Quillian,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        John Quilliam (1771&#8211;1829), First Lieutenant on HMS <hi rend="ital">Amazon</hi> and later on HMS <hi rend="ital">Victory</hi>.</note> something from
                        Ponsonby<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lieutenant John Ponsonby (dates unknown), who was then living at
                        Ormathwaite, near Keswick.</note> &#8211; to whom I shall walk over, &amp; read this chapter in hope of <del>making</del> getting
                    some corrections &amp; additions. And a Danes account printed in English gives me some fine things.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andreas Andersen Feldborg (1782&#8211;1838), <title>A Tour in Zealand, the Year 1802; with an Historical Sketch of
                            the Battle of Copenhagen</title> (1805).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am such a sad lubber that I feel half-ashamed of myself for being persuaded ever <del>xx</del> even to review the
                    life of Nelson, much more to write one.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s biography grew out of his review of a
                        series of Nelsonian &#8216;lives&#8217; in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218&#8211;262.</note> Had I not been a thorough
                    lubber I should have remembered half a hundred things, worthy of remembrance, which have all been lost because tho I <del>xx
                        xxxxx</del> &lt;indeed&gt; know the binnacle from the <del>xxx xxxxx xxx</del> &lt;main mast, I know little more.&gt;
                        <del>xxx</del> tackle &amp; sheets, <del>xxxx</del> &amp; tally &amp; belay &lt;are alike to me, &amp; if you ask me about the
                    lee-clue garnets, I can only tell that they are <del>xxxxxx xxx</del> not the same kind of garnets as are worn in necklaces &amp;
                    bracelets&gt; They <del>xx</del> are all Aballeboogobanganorrobo<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A nonsense word much
                        favoured by Southey; used as a &#8216;mystic word&#8217; in &#8216;Interchapter II&#8217; of <title>The Doctor</title>, 7 vols (London, 1834&#8211;1847), I, pp. 91&#8211;94.</note> to me &amp;
                    so fine facts have been lost because I did not know where to stow them in the ship, or in my recollection-closet up stairs. There
                    is something ridiculous, &amp; something like quackery in writing thus about what I so little understand. I walk among sea terms
                    as a cat does in a china pantry, in bodily fear of doing mischief &amp; betraying myself. And yet there will come a good book of
                    it I verily believe!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have touched your old tyrant Sir Thomas, gently, but upon the sore place; imputing no blame, but stating every
                    circumstance which makes misconduct an (almost) unavoidable inference.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Thomas Boulden
                        Thompson, 1st Baronet (1766&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), Tom&#8217;s former commanding officer. During the battle of Copenhagen HMS
                            <hi rend="ital">Bellona</hi>, captained by Thompson, disobeyed orders and &#8216;kept too close on the starboard shoal, and
                        grounded abreast of the outer ship of the enemy: this was the more vexatious, inasmuch as the wind was fair, the room ample,
                        and three ships had led the way. The Russell, following the Bellona, grounded in like manner: both were within reach of shot;
                        but their absence from their intended stations was severely felt&#8217;. Only Nelson&#8217;s prompt action stopped his own and other ships
                        running aground and the battle being lost. See <title>Life of Nelson</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813), II, pp. 118&#8211;119.
                        Southey&#8217;s account ignored that fact that Thompson was wounded in the ensuing action and lost a leg.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What was your loss? Tell me all about your guns, &amp; what loss they occasioned. Were they not honey combed? Were
                    you not saying when you pulled the triggers, here goes the death of six? &#8211; this is a thing which would be felt.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did not Victor<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a dog on board Tom Southey&#8217;s ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Bellona</hi>.</note> distinguish himself that day. I must not mention poor &#8220;Sir Hyde&#8221; as Joe<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom&#8217;s dog Joe had been on board the <hi rend="ital">Bellona</hi> during the battle. He had
                        perhaps been scared and hidden, hence Joe&#8217;s renaming after the British admiral Sir Hyde Parker (1739&#8211;1807; <title>DNB</title>)
                        whose unwillingness to engage the enemy during the Copenhagen campaign led to the ruin of his reputation.</note> was called
                    for that days behaviour, for Sir Hyde had his merits. A jealous man, or a conceited one would not have let Nelson do anything,
                    &amp; I can perfectly well enter into Dometts feelings when he said Save what you can Sir H.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir William Domett (1752&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), commander of HMS <hi rend="ital">London</hi> during the
                        Copenhagen action. Southey later changed his account of the battle because of some new information sent to him by Domett via
                        Croker. This described how on Domett&#8217;s urging the fleet had entered the Baltic directly through the Sound rather than through
                        the Great Belt, as Parker had originally decided. As a result the fleet was more effectively positioned for the battle. See,
                            <title>The Life of Nelson</title>, 2nd edn, 2 vols (London, 1814), II, pp. 101&#8211;102; and Robert Southey to John May, 22
                        August 1814, Letter 2473.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not rightly understand you about the spare spars. &#8220;Many would have been saved that were destroyed lying on the
                    booms&#8221; you say. Do you refer to the mere value of the spars thus destroyed, &#8211; or to the damage also done by the splinters from
                    these spars?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am taking great pains with this chapter, &amp; great interest in it. Your letter was of main use.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What a miserable thing is this loss of a second frigate to the Americans!<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        On 25 October 1812 the USS <hi rend="ital">United States</hi>, commanded by Stephen Decatur (1779&#8211;1820), had dismasted and
                        captured HMS <hi rend="ital">Macedonian</hi>, captained by John Surnam Carden (1771&#8211;1858). This followed the capture of HMS
                            <hi rend="ital">Mandarin</hi> on 11 October 1812. Although the <hi rend="ital">United States</hi> was a large ship, Carden
                        was heavily criticised for the loss of the <hi rend="ital">Macedonian</hi> and never held an active command again. He remained
                        in the navy and continued to rise through the ranks, reaching full Admiral before his death.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> knew Decatur at Malta, &amp; has often spoken of him in the
                    highest terms. &#8211; It is a cruel stroke, &amp; tho their frigates are larger ships than ours, must be felt as disgrace &amp; in fact
                    is disgrace. It looks as if there was a dry rot in our wooden walls. Is it that the Captain also is a youngster hoisted up by
                    interest? or that the Americans were manned by Englishmen? or that our men do not fight heartily? or that their men are better
                    than ours?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The paragraph about <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> tragedy is correct. It is the
                    play which he wrote in 1797 &amp; which Sheridan<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The playwright, theatre proprietor and
                        politician Richard Brinsley Sheridan (1751&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>). He had rejected &#8216;Osorio&#8217; (later retitled
                            <title>Remorse</title>) in 1797.</note> then rejected. I think it will succeed.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Coleridge&#8217;s <title>Remorse</title> was staged at Drury Lane, London, 23 January-12 February 1813. This made it a moderate
                        success.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have written to Sister Anne,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Sister Anne&#8217; was an acquaintance who had
                        converted to Catholicism. She might have been Tom Southey&#8217;s sister-in-law; see Robert Southey to Thomas Southey, 24 December
                        1812, Letter 2192.</note> earnestly enough, but probably to little effect.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> has been reading the Pilgrims Progress,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Bunyan (1628&#8211;1688; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Pilgrim&#8217;s Progress</title> (1678).</note>
          <del>&amp;</del> &lt;taking infinite delight in the letter, but&gt; Sarah will think with no great <del>improvement</del> &lt;
                    edification from the spirit&gt; when she learns &lt;that&gt; his favourite amusement at present is to what he calls &#8220;play
                        Apollyon&#8221;<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;Destroyer&#8217;, an archdevil in <title>Pilgrim&#8217;s Progress</title>.</note>
                    with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref>. He goes about
                    the room or the passages, roaring towards them like a Lion seeking whom he may devour:<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> 1
                            <title>Peter</title>, 5: 8.</note> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">bluff Queen Henry</ref>, cry out don&#8217;t <hi rend="ital">pollyon</hi>, don&#8217;t <hi rend="ital">pollyon </hi>
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert"> Herby</ref>! &#8211; Tho when he has done they ask him to <hi rend="ital">pollyon</hi>
                    again.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Supposing the action<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Incidents at the battle of Copenhagen, presumably
                        after the <hi rend="ital">Bellona</hi> and <hi rend="ital">Russell</hi> ran aground. The <hi rend="ital">Desiree</hi> did not
                        run aground.</note> had not been suspended when it was were not you with the Russell &amp; the Desiree in danger? The great
                        Book<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>) and John McArthur
                        (1755&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of Admiral Lord Nelson, K.B. from his Lordship&#8217;s Manuscripts</title>
                        (1809).</note> here says that these three ships were not &#8211; but I think I remember otherwise from you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Robertson<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Robertson&#8217;s (1721&#8211;1793; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>History of America</title> (1777). Southey owned an edition of 1788, no. 2456 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note> &amp; Bryan Edward<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bryan Edwards (1743&#8211;1800; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The History, Civil and Commercial, of the British Colonies in the West Indies</title> (1793). Southey possessed a
                        later edition of 1807, no. 986 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> I knew must be in the Newcastle Library,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably a reference to the Thomlinson Library at St Nicholas Church, Newcastle.</note>
                    but it was better you should have them at hand, &#8211; the latter indeed you will want throughout the whole of your opus. I wish you
                    had the Naval Chronicle,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Naval Chronicle</title> was an annual account of
                        naval affairs. It had first appeared in 1759 and re-started in 1799.</note> but it is too expensive to be bought, &amp;
                    whenever you meet with a volume it may soon be gutted of all that is to your purpose. I shall look out for books for you when I go
                    to London: especially for Du Tertre.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> The missionary and botanist Jean-Baptiste du Tertre
                        (1610&#8211;1687), <title>Histoire Generale des Antiles habit&#233;es par les Fran&#231;ois</title> (1667). Southey later obtained a copy, no.
                        2828 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Many happy new years to you all!</p>
          <p rend="right">
            <del>Xxxx </del>
            <date when="1812-12-30"> Dec 30. 1812. </date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>