<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2498</idno><idno type="nines">rce3769</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Ramos, The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp.
                        137–139.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2498" type="letter"><head>2498. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1814-11-09">9 November 1814</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry<lb/>Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ 12NO12/ 1814’ and ‘10o’Clock/ NO.12/ 1814F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi><lb/>Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 177 1814/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> December<lb/>Watermark: J
                        Dickinson &amp; Co/ 1811<lb/>MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb/>Previously
                        published: Charles Ramos, <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp.
                        137–139.</note></head><epigraph><lg><l rend="indent3"> And therefore in his soul he felt that peace</l><l rend="indent3"> Which follows painful duty well perform’d</l><l rend="indent3"> Perfect &amp; heavenly peace – the peace of God.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> And therefore …
                                God: written in another hand. <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 7, lines 185–187.</note></l></lg></epigraph><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1814-11-09">9 Nov. 1814</date></dateline><salute>My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I ought ere this to have replied to your last letter. I was from home when it arrived, on a weeks visit to <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, &amp; there it followed me. You know my employments, – but not my
                    dissipations, which in a very natural process multiply to rob me of time as time becomes more valuable. From June to November this
                    place is any thing rather than a retirement. The task of tuition also, tho managed with as little fatigue as possible, occupies
                    daily an hour &amp; half, which, tho I read by snatches even then, is lost to regular employment.</p><p rend="indent1"> As soon as I returned from <ref target="places.html#RydalMount">Rydale</ref> I wrote to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeGeorge">G Coleridge</ref>, &amp; have received from him as satisfactory a reply as could be
                    expected or desired, tho much yet remains to be adjusted.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey to George Coleridge, 12
                        October 1814, Letter 2485.</note> He proposes to my consideration, two plans, – which indeed he would leave to my choice. 1.
                    That of obtaining for <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> the situation of Bible Clerk<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bible Clerks were students at Oxford University who received benefits such as reduced fees or
                        free meals in return for performing certain tasks, such as reading aloud chapters from the Bible at meals or in chapel. The
                        term had come into use in preference to that of Servitor, as the duties attached to this office had, in the past, included
                        acting as a servant to other students and wearing a distinctive plain black gown and round hat.</note> at one of the Oxford
                    Colleges, where the emoluments are very considerable: to this he states &amp; strongly feels two objections: that the person
                    holding such a situation is actually, tho not by any statute, disqualified from gaining a fellowship in the same college, custom,
                    &amp; probably the want of respectability of character in the Bible Clerks to rise above their situation, having established this
                    bar: – &amp; that tho there is no difference in the dress (as among the Servitors) still there is a practical degradation attached
                    to the office – men who hold it being rarely or difficultly admitted into the society of the commoners. This objection is
                    doubtless felt the more strongly because <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> has <del>in</del> so many
                    cousins who are so well known &amp; stand so high in the University, &amp; has undoubtedly on that account the more force. 2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi> He says that it might be preferable to send him as an independent member notwithstanding the additional
                    expence; &amp; at the expiration of two years, if the immediate college prospects were not promising, place him somewhere as an
                    Usher; where from the emoluments of his situation he might support himself, &amp; keep annually one or two terms, till he had
                    compleated the number requisite for his degree, &amp; for admission into Orders. To effect this he says that if <ref target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMary">Lady Beaumont</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#PooleThomas">Poole</ref> would
                    advance all that they offered for four years, in the space of two there would then be 80 £ per year, which the Ottery family would
                    double, making thus 160 £. – I incline to this latter plan, – because I have great hopes that <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> will make friends at College, as he has never failed to do every
                    where else, which will make his success certain there; – &amp; because if College Prospects fails, he cannot be made independent
                    too soon, nor subject to the discipline of self controul too early. But I wait to see <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> before I reply to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeGeorge">G Coleridge</ref>; &amp; <del>I</del> am in
                    daily expectation of him. Meantime my poor old friend <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> has offered an annual
                    five guineas toward this object: &amp; if it be necessary, <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> will
                    contribute 20 £. per year. Of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> himself all I can learn is from <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Cottle’s letter, 1 November 1814,
                        Lynda Pratt, ‘The “sad habits” of Samuel Taylor Coleridge: Unpublished Letters from Joseph Cottle to Robert Southey, 1813–17’,
                            <title>Review of English Studies</title>, n.s. 55 (2004), 85.</note> who tells me that a Bristol printer<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Matthew Gutch (1776–1861), Bristol printer. In 1817 he was closely involved in the
                        publication of Coleridge’s <title>Biographia Literaria</title>.</note> has bought the paper on which he expects to print a
                    work of S. T. C’s against the Unitarians.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> This is possibly connected to the magnum opus
                        Coleridge announced to Daniel Stuart on 12 September 1814: ‘my most important Work, which is printing at Bristol, two of my
                        friends having taken upon them the risk ... The Title is: Christianity the one true Philosophy - or 5 Treatises on the Logos,
                        or communicative Intelligence, Natural, Human, and Divine’, E. L. Griggs, <title>Collected Letters of Samuel Taylor
                            Coleridge</title>, 6 vols (Oxford, 1956–1971), III, p. 533 and n 2.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Now then for myself. And first I must once more thank you for taking care of me at the Insurance Office &amp;
                    supplying my deficits there. My great history<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Southey’s uncompleted ‘History of
                        Portugal’, or his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> when it appears will settle these accounts:
                    &amp; now the <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Chamberlains</ref> office may regularly be looked to.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. The regular payments Southey received as Poet Laureate.</note> If you will at any convenient time call on
                        W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Nicol,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Nicol (fl. 1800–1855), printer and bookseller.
                        Nicol was also Assistant Paymaster in the Lord Steward’s office and thus had some responsibility for part of Southey’s salary.
                        The Lord Steward, who has charge of the Royal Household’s domestic arrangements, had traditionally provided the Poet Laureate
                        with a tierce of canary wine, as a supplement to his salary. The wine had been converted into an annual sum of £27, but this
                        was still paid by the Lord Steward.</note> he will put you in the way of settling my accounts there; &amp; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> tells me the sooner this can be done the better as the Clerks want
                    to close their books. – <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">My youngest child</ref> has been dangerously ill since our return
                    from <ref target="places.html#RydalMount">Rydale</ref>, – &amp; we of course went thro that kind of suffering which I believe none
                    can truly comprehend but those who have experienced it – The effects have not yet so wholly left her, as to leave me entirely
                    without anxiety, – tho I know it is my nature to be anxious over-much in these cases. – I have begun with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Walpole,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was working on a memoir of Walpole (1736–1810), Envoy Extraordinary
                        and Minister Plenipotentiary to Portugal, 1771–1800. Southey had promised to write a Life of Walpole.</note> &amp; proceed
                    slowly from the great disappointment in the want of his Portugueze Correspondences: it cannot have been this which he sent to the
                    foreign office, – because the originals existed there before, &amp; these if they existed at all, would only have been duplicates.
                    I rather incline to think that he did not while at Lisbon preserve his correspondence as he had done in the commencement of his
                    diplomatic career. From his French papers<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prior to his time in Lisbon, Walpole had served
                        three years as secretary to the British Embassy in Paris.</note> I have collected a few interesting facts, – &amp; in the more
                    important part of his life must do what I can, by help of the Commercial Treaty which he negociated, – of the Wine Company, –
                    &amp; the attempt at introducing the Catholics into the Factory.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walpole was a central
                        figure in re-negotiating the trading relationship between Portugal and Britain in 1786–1787, after Britain’s Treaty with
                        France in 1786 threatened to upset the long-established export of Portuguese wine to Britain in exchange for textiles. British
                        merchants who were Catholics were not allowed to join the British Factory in Lisbon – a subject which caused some controversy
                        in the 1780s and 1790s.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My poem<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, The Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> will either have reached you, or be lying for you in town before
                    this letter can travel to Richmond. I have begun, &amp; barely begun another, of which the title is A Tale of Paraguay:<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> was published in 1825, and dedicated to Edith May Southey.</note> it is addressed to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">your God-daughter</ref> in a sort of Prologue &amp; Epilogue, or in old language Proem
                    &amp; L’Envoy. your name comes thus naturally &amp; properly to be introduced, – &amp; I trust you will allow me to repeat it in
                    some dedicatory lines. The subject of the poem is death, – &amp; you know in what strain of thought I shall present it.</p><p rend="indent1"> There shall be a long article of mine upon the English Poets in the next Quarterly,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander Chalmers (1759–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of the English Poets, from Chaucer to
                            Cowper</title> (1810), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 11 (July 1814), 480–504; and <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12
                        (October 1814), 60–90.</note> but some expressions in <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> letters
                    have put me in a <hi rend="ital">quandary</hi> lest the middle part should be lost, – which would be the loss of a weeks labour. I
                    have just begun a paper upon <del>the</del><hi rend="ital"> moral statistics</hi> as they may be called, to show what has been done toward real, practicable radical reform
                    in this country, – &amp; what remains to do.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a reference to Southey’s article on
                        ‘the Poor’ in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 187–235.</note> – Remember me to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> – &amp; God bless you</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs most affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>