<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1886</idno><idno type="nines">rce3157</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Beinecke Library,
                        Osborn C18th Bound MSS, Osborn fc 76, vol 2, item 152.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1886" type="letter"><head>1886. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MitfordJohn">John Mitford</ref>, <date when="1811-03-20">20 March
                        1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend John Mitford/ Benhall/ Saxmundham/
                        Suffolk<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Seal: Red wax; design illegible<lb/>Endorsement: R. Southey<lb/>MS: Beinecke Library,
                        Osborn C18th Bound MSS, Osborn fc 76, vol 2, item 152<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1811-03-20">March 20. 1811.</date></dateline><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Seeing your volume<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mitford’s <title>Agnes, the Indian Captive, a Poem in
                            Four Cantos, with other Poems</title> (1811).</note> &lt;advertised&gt; as on the point of publication I would not reply
                    to your letter till I &lt;could&gt; thank you for it, &amp; say something of the smaller poems which it contains. Last night I
                    received it. Both in the Indian Captive &amp; in the song of “those mighty Grecian peers”<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey quotes the first line of ‘Sonnet X’, <title>Agnes, the Indian Captive, a Poem in Four Cantos, with other Poems</title>
                        (London, 1811), p. 199. Mitford had included two classically-inspired ‘Odes’ in his volume, pp. 169–185; and ten sonnets, pp.
                        [189]–200.</note> there is great power &amp; great promise; yet high as the expectations were that these would lead me to form
                    of what you may produce hereafter, I draw still higher hopes from the sonnets. They give stronger indications of those habits of
                    thought &amp; feeling without which no man can become a true poet however expert he may be in all the mechanism of the art. I read
                    &amp; re-read them, &amp; <del>the xxxx they xxxxx xxxx xxxx</del> the conviction which they left upon my mind was that I had
                    never seen a first <del>volume</del> publication which augured so well. It gives me very sincere pleasure to add that <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, who happens at this time to be my guest, perfectly agrees with me in
                    this opinion, – there is no other man living whose opinion is worth so much.</p><p rend="indent1"> An edition of Grays work which should give us more of his correspondence, &amp; trace the imitations in his poetry
                    would be exceedingly valuable.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mitford became a distinguished editor of Thomas Gray
                        (1716–1771; <title>DNB</title>). His publications included, <title>Poems of Thomas Gray with Critical Notes, a Life of the
                            Author and an Essay on His Poetry</title> (1814), <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title> (1816) and contributions to the
                        Aldine edition of 1835–1843.</note> Surely his letters are still recoverable, they would naturally have been entrusted to
                        Mason<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Mason (1725–1797; <title>DNB</title>) had included bowdlerised and
                        censored version of Gray’s letters in his <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray, to which are Prefixed Memoirs of His Life and
                            Writings</title> (1775). Mason’s combination of ‘life and letters’ was highly influential on later biographers, including
                        Southey, who used a similar format in his edition of William Cowper (1731–1800; <title>DNB</title>).</note> by the persons to
                    whom they were addressed, &amp; returned by him when his work was done. If the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wharton<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gray’s friend and correspondent the physician Thomas Wharton (1717–1794), son of a prominent
                        Durham family.</note> who seems to have been the most frequent of his later correspondents be (as I suppose) father to,
                        <del>(</del>or at least of the family of the present Sec. of the Treasury,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard
                        Wharton (1764–1820), MP for Durham 1802–1804, 1806–1820, was the son of Grey’s friend, Thomas Wharton. He was Junior Secretary
                        at the Treasury 1809–1814.</note> I think I could make enquiry for you in that quarter. What became of Horace Walpoles<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The author, politician and patron of the arts, Horatio Walpole, 4th Earl of Orford
                        (1717–1797; <title>DNB</title>).</note> papers? – Upon all plans of this kind the first thing to consult is your own
                    inclination for the task, – the second the disposition of the booksellers. If there be any new materials forth coming they would
                    certainly find their advantage in such a work.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coleridge</ref> once expressed an opinion to me that the
                        Achilleid<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Publius Papinius Statius (c. AD 45–c. 96), whose unfinished epic the
                            <title>Achilleid</title> deals with the early life of the hero Achilles.</note> was not a fragment as is generally
                    supposd, but that Statius designed only to write the <hi rend="ital">Mocedades</hi><note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        ‘Youth’.</note> as the Spanish would say of Achilles. My recollections of the poem led me to a different conclusion. But it is
                        <del>xxx</del> now long since I have had leisure for classical studies. The age is over in which it was possible for a man to
                        <del>be</del> make himself an universal scholar, &amp; know all that was known in Europe. In our days there must be a division
                    of learning as well as of labour. There are many things which I <del>must be</del> &lt;am&gt; content never to learn, &amp;
                    classical learning is among those which I must be contented to forget. The most melancholy feeling which the lapse of time has
                    brought with it to me is that I have much to do, &amp; the day is short.</p><p rend="indent1"> You say you have no participator of your studies. – <del>look on</del> it is t[MS torn] peculiar blessing of
                    literary pursuits that they can be enjoyed without participation. By following them with ardour &amp; with perseverance I have
                    made myself far happier than any other circumstances could possibly have made me. – Go on as you have begun, – write always to
                    your own judgement whether it be <del>that</del> &lt;the taste&gt; of the day or not, &amp; content yourself with the approbation
                    of the few. The better your write, the fewer you will please at first; – but praise thus obtained <del>goes on</del>
                    &lt;increases&gt; in the ratio of compound interest, whereas they who are paid in present popularity <del>receive</del>
                        &lt;<del>exhaust</del> receive&gt; their whole capital at once.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> believe me</salute><salute rend="indent3"> Yrs truly &amp; with respect</salute><signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey. </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>