<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2406</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3677</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2406" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2406" type="letter">
        <head>2406. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1814-04-21">21 April 1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 25 AP 25/ 1814<lb />Endorsement:
                        April 21. 1814<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1814-04-21">Thursday April 21. 1814</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will see on the other leaf the fruit of your criticism, &amp; my mornings labour.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. corrections to <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 15, line 250&#8211;279, made in
                        response to Bedford&#8217;s criticism of the MS version. The new lines are at the end of the letter.</note> If you have any comments
                    to make upon these lines let it be speedily, for they will be in irrevocable printers ink in the course of next week. Tell me too
                    (&amp; this also requires a speedy resolution) whether or no I am exempted from the hair powder tax as one of the household, &#8211; for
                    my assessed taxes paper is in the house, &amp; there I see I am to state on what grounds I am exempted &#8211; if an exemption there be
                    for me.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Duty on Hair Powder Act (1795) stated that anyone wishing to use hair powder
                        must register with the Stamp Office and buy an annual certificate at a cost of one guinea. However, members of the Royal
                        Family and their servants were exempt. Southey is asking Bedford whether his post as Poet Laureate allowed him exemption from
                        this tax, as a member of the Royal Household.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your remark upon the ill-position of Strength to the weak &amp; to the wounded balm,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 14, line 4.</note> is perfectly just. I had felt it myself, &amp;
                    yet neither liked to strike out the line, nor change its position, &#8211; this latter however is now done, &amp; if it does not please
                    me <del>when</del> &lt;in&gt; the proof out it shall go.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the interview with Rusilla you seem to have overlooked what is expressly stated, that the presence of Florinda
                    prevents Roderick from making himself known, &amp; what follows also, (tho it is not expressed,) that the same cause would prevent
                    Rusilla from openly recognizing him, <del>xxxx</del> if she should discover him. With this in your mind, you will not feel that
                    the dog interrupts any expected discovery. The specific purpose of the scene is to prepare for what is to follow respecting
                    Julian. I totally dissent from your objection to Rodericks exclamation which concludes the book; &#8211; no reproach was intended in it,
                    &#8211; it is a speech of pure self-reflecting anguish, &#8211; <del>not</del> referring not to those who did not know him, but to himself who
                    was so changed as not to be known. Remember also that instinct is unerring.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 15, lines 241&#8211;279.</note> &#8211; In Ulysses any exclamation would have
                    been out of character &#8211; he sheds tears. Rodericks feelings must necessarily be much stronger. One might object to Homer that a dog
                    which was not full grown when his Master went away, would <hi rend="ital">not</hi> recognize him after twenty years. I certainly
                    believe he would not. That the death of Argus is overstrained. Dogs will die of grief beyond all doubt, &amp; cats also have been
                    known to pine after their <del>owne</del> owners; but to die of joy implies a <del>degree</del> &lt;kind&gt; of feeling above the
                    faculty of brutes. One might object also to the description of the dog as descending to loathsome objects, &amp; especially one
                    might object that Penelope Telemachus Eum&#230;us &amp; every body else who loved Ulysses should been so unmindful of the old proverb
                    Love me love my dog, &#8211; which Rusilla &amp; Siverian, as you will see, have religiously observed.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The parallels were with the faithful dog Argus in Homer&#8217;s <title>Odyssey</title>, Book 17, lines 290&#8211;327. The
                        elderly Argus recognises Odysseus on his return and then dies. In Southey&#8217;s poem (Book 15, lines 241&#8211;279) Theron sees through
                        Roderick&#8217;s disguise.</note> I have removed at your suggestion a great fault from the passage, &amp; thereby materially
                    improved it. It is very likely that both the versification &amp; the phraseology may be amended, &#8211; but the matter &amp; the
                    feeling satisfy me. &amp; both are in place.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> About pursual<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 14, line 115.</note> I can swear nothing farther than that it is a
                    word justifiable by analogy. but I rather think it is, like almost all my unusual words, good old standard English. I am
                    perpetually searching in the Tudor muses for ore of this kind.</p>
        <p rend="indent8"> _____</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">This house</ref> with the land belonging to it is to be sold, &amp; my Landlord<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Joseph Jackson (d. 1815), Rector of Lowick, and brother of William Jackson (1748&#8211;1809), the builder of Greta Hall.</note> makes me the first offer: whereat I smile in consideration of the capital at my disposal for such a purpose; &#8211;
                    &amp; do not sigh either upon that or any other consideration, tho I believe an advantageous purchase might be made of an
                    improving property. My first term will expire at Whitsuntide 1817. I begin to think of moving at that time if I can command the
                    means, <del>&amp; taking all my</del> &amp; going abroad with my family for two or three years, as the cheapest way of educating
                    them. &#8211; But this is looking far forward, &amp; God knows I have present occupations numerous enough &amp; <del>pressing x</del>
                    pressing enough to occupy my thoughts. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> is coming into power. As for doing any
                    thing for me I believe it would be very difficult, for I really do not myself know what could be done, &#8211; &amp; I dare say it would
                    be thought that the pension &amp; the laurel amply provide for me. But he might very truly serve &amp; very deeply oblige me by
                    doing something for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. Perhaps <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> can
                    let him know this. Where is his Honour? </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>The Bust???<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had sat for a bust in October 1813. The sculptor was James Smith
                            (1775&#8211;1815).</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> I have a card of invitation to dine at the Royal Academy<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Royal
                            Academy of Arts, London, founded in 1768.</note> on Saturday the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#8211; it is rather too far to go. I
                        suppose this is one of my PL<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Poet Laureate.</note> privileges. tant mieux<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> I have a card &#8230; mieux: written at top of fol 1 r; &#8216;so much the better&#8217;.</note>
          </p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent3"> A feeling uncommix&#8217;d with sense of guilt</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Or shame, yet painfullest, thrill&#8217;d thro the King;</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> But he to self-controul accustomed long (or &#8211; now long inured</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Represt his rising heart, nor other tears</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Full as his struggling bosom was, let fall</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Than seemed to follow on Florindas words.</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Looking toward her then, yet so that still</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> He shunnd the meeting of her eye, he said,</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Virtuous &amp; pious as thou art, &amp; ripe</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> For Heaven O Lady, I must think the man</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Hath not by his good Angel been cast off</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> For whom thy supplications rise. The Power</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Whose justice doth in its unerring course</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Visit the children for the <del>fathers sin</del> sires offence,</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Shall He not in his boundless mercy hear</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> The daughters prayer, &amp; for her sake restore</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> The sinful parent? My soul shall with thine</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> In earnest &amp; continual duty join, &#8211;</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> How deeply, &#8211; how devoutly, He will know</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> To whom the cry is rais&#8217;d!</l>
            <l rend="indent7"> Thus having said,</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Deliberately in self-possession still</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Himself from that most painful interview</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Dispeeding he withdrew. The watchful dog</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Followed his masters footsteps: He retired</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Into the thickest <del>covert from all eyes</del> &lt;grove&gt; there giving way</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Apart he cast himself upon the</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> To his oerburthened nature, from all eyes</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Apart, he cast himself upon the ground</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> And threw his arms around the dog &amp; cried</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> While tears streamed down, thou Theron thou hast known</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Thy poor lost master &#8211; Theron none but thou!</l>
          </lg>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>