<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1995</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3266</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1995" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1995" type="letter">
        <head>1995. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1811-12-07">7 December
                        1811</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Captain Southey. R.N./ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        Helens/ Auckland/ Durham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Taking it for granted that we shall see you soon, &#8211; your best way of coming will be to sleep at Bowes, &amp; take
                    the mail the next morning, which will set you down at Penrith early enough to reach this place by the time evening closes in.
                        <del>Should</del> &lt;Lest&gt; the weather &lt;should&gt; prove too bad for walking, you had better so time your movements
                    that the next morning may be the coach day to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, &#8211; either Monday, Wednesday or
                    Friday.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> will send you the two years Registers in the same parcel with
                        Vancouver.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810) and <title>1809</title> (1811), together with George Vancouver
                        (1757&#8211;1798; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Voyage of Discovery to the North Pacific Ocean</title> (1798).</note> I am
                    under-weigh with the third,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Southey&#8217;s contribution to the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1810</title> (1812).</note> &amp; shall in the course of a few days send off the first portion to the Press.
                    At present we are in the midst of a mighty operation, &#8211; cutting up the whole years newspapers, &amp; pasting the excerpts in blue
                    books, &#8211; to be bound up as &#8220;Newspaper Collections for the History of 1810.&#8221; &#8211; arranged under the various heads of Spain, &#8211; North
                    of Europe, &#8211; United States &amp;c &amp;c &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My progress in Dutch is a great joy, &amp; will I perceive soon put the German within my reach. &#8211; I met with a
                    ludicrous mistake the other day of the manner in which a metaphor strikes us in another language tho the same metaphor is
                    perfectly familiar in our own. We talk of a glass of spirits &#8211; &amp; perceive nothing remarkable in the term, &#8211; the Dutch call it
                    a glass of ghosts.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> General Hills<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rowland Hill, 1st Viscount Hill (1744&#8211;1833;
                            <title>DNB</title>), had recently pursued a successful campaign in Portugal against French forces led by General
                        Jean-Baptiste Girard (1775&#8211;1815).</note> is indeed a master stroke, &#8211; it is the first example of what we want so sorely,
                    enterprize &amp; celerity. I do not know whether I told you that <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> is
                    made Commissary General. I wrote to him about portable soup for the soldiers, in such cases as this where speed is required, &#8211;
                    &amp; shall communicate to him all the notions for bettering the condition of the soldiers which come into my head. &#8211; We must I
                    fear expect to hear that Valencia is fallen, &#8211; nevertheless things are going on well upon the whole in Spain. It is manifest by
                        Blakes<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish officer Joaquin Blake y Joyes (1759&#8211;1827). After a series of
                        defeats, Blake and his forces were trapped in Valencia, where they surrendered on 8 January 1812.</note> last defeat, &amp; by
                    all the movements of Ballasteros<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Ballesteros (1770&#8211;1832), one of the Spanish
                        commanders in the south of Spain.</note> that the Spaniards are improving in skill, &amp; if we do but learn enterprize,
                    nothing more is wanted. I wish to Heaven the affairs of S America looked as well as those of the mother country. Miranda<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sebastian Francisco de Miranda Ravelo y Rodriguez de Espinoza (1750&#8211;1816), Venezuelan
                        revolutionary who played a key part in his country&#8217;s struggle for independence in 1810&#8211;1812, until he was captured by the
                        Spanish. He had fought in the French army in 1791&#8211;1792 and was a friend of the leading Girondins. Southey&#8217;s account of events
                        and analysis of the &#8216;adventurer&#8217; Miranda&#8217;s character appeared in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1
                        (1813), 367&#8211;394. He accused Miranda of labouring &#8216;from the beginning to promote his own views of ambition&#8217; (386).</note> seems
                    to be as blood-thirsty as if he were still in the French service.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know probably that <ref target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> in the Edinburgh recommends the
                    Register to the notice of Parliament.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A long aside in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>,
                        18 (August 1811), 420&#8211;423n, had questioned whether the &#8216;virulent personal abuse &#8230; levelled at the most respectable members of
                        the Legislature&#8217; in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> was in breach of Parliamentary privilege and hinted that
                        action against the author and publishers might be taken. In the event, the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>&#8217;s suggestion was
                        not acted on.</note> Would not be amusing if I were to be summoned to the Bar of the House, &amp; delivered over to form an
                    acquaintance with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coleman the Sergeant at Arms?<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis John
                        Colman, serjeant-at-arms (i.e. the chief law enforcement office in the Houses of Parliament) 1805&#8211;1811, died in Portugal on 12
                        December 1811. His successor was John Clementson (1780&#8211;1856), who served in a temporary capacity from January-March 1812, when
                        the post went to Henry Seymour (1778&#8211;1844), who held it until 1835.</note> &#8211; As I am no speaker I should read my defence,
                    which would be very short &amp; very pithy &#8211; full of respect for the house, claiming the privileges of an historian living under a
                    free government, &amp; enjoying the freedom of the press, &#8211; &amp; appealing to the whole tenour of the book whether it were
                    contemptuous toward that House, or aimed at sowing disaffection, &amp; finally appealing to its justice, &#8211; this with a cut or two
                    at <ref target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Brougham</ref> &amp; the &#8220;friends of freedom&#8221; who want all
                    freedom for themselves &amp; none for any body else would read well in the next days papers, make the book in requisition &amp;
                    give me as much notoriety as any private gentleman need wish for. That I should keep my head upon my shoulders is pretty certain,
                    &#8211; but it is by no means so certain that I shall be able to keep it out of the shop windows. &#8211; Such an event would do more for my
                    books than all their intrinsic merit has done, &#8211; for I should have something said on my behalf by <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> &amp; perhaps <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref>, &#8211; which
                    would be worth all the praise of all the reviews that ever have been or will be written. Perhaps the fear of having an odium
                    brought upon themselves will deter the Whitbreadites<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Whigs as followers of Samuel
                        Whitbread (1758&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>).</note> from this wise measure. To me it would be attended with no other
                    inconvenience than a journey to London six months earlier than I intended with perhaps a few nights lodging in Newgate,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> London&#8217;s main prison, at the corner of Newgate Street and Old Bailey.</note> &#8211; that
                    however would be very doubtful, &#8211; a reprimand from <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">the Speaker</ref> might perhaps be thought enough. But I might
                    possibly come off with flying colours, N&#8217;importe, &#8211; with honour assuredly in any way.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for <ref target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> he is delivered into my hands in <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bells</ref> quarrel.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably
                        a reference to Southey&#8217;s <title>The Origin, Nature, and Object of the New System of Education</title> (1812), an expansion of
                        Southey&#8217;s appraisal of the educational systems advocated by Andrew Bell and Joseph Lancaster, <title>Quarterly Review</title>,
                        6 (October 1811), 264&#8211;304. Brougham was an advocate for Lancaster&#8217;s system and a member of the board of directors of the Royal
                        Lancastrian Institution (later the British and Foreign Schools Society). He had severely criticised Bell in &#8216;The Education of
                        the Poor&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 17 (November 1810), 58&#8211;88.</note> I have him on the hip, &amp; will give him such
                    a cross buttock as he has never had before. About that question I shall say no more than that what you have heard about <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is from one end to the other false.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge did support Andrew Bell and the Madras system.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="center">___</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are up to the knees in papers &#8211; cutting up the Times &amp; the Chronicle of the whole year &amp; arranging the
                    materials into my &#8220;Newspaper Collections for 1810 &#8211; a labour which is far greater than you would suppose. Perhaps you will come
                    before it is concluded. We are got on as far as June 23 to day.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If I knew what day to expect you I would walk out to meet you, but this you can hardly tell me, so much indeed does
                    it depend upon circumstances. Come however soon, &amp; stay as long as you can when you do come. I wish <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretdauTomandSarah">Miss Margery</ref>
                    could come with you, but I suppose they will not come till I go fetch them. My love to them. I shall find my way to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Helens some time in 1812.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This evening the first <del>xxx</del> batch goes off to <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref>.
                        <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love. The young ones have all a cold &#8211; was there ever such a succession of
                    stormy weather! &#8211; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="right">
            <date when="1811-12-07">December 7. 1811.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>