<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2199</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3470</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        30928.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2199" type="letter">
        <head>2199. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1813-01-05">5 January
                        1813</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol
                        <lb />Endorsement: 1813/ Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 5<lb />Postmark: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        30928<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick.</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-01-05">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 5. 1813.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Charles</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been waiting any time this last eight days to write to you, in expectation that poor unfortunate Mark
                    Anthony, who is no sooner out of one scrape about the fair sex than he runs his head into another, should make his appearance; but
                    where this unlucky hero of All-for-Love, or a Clerkship well Lost, may be, he knows best, for we have neither seen nor heard any
                    of him since I wrote to say he would be welcome.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> An oblique reference, but Southey may be
                        talking about his brother-in-law, <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George Fricker</ref>, who had just lost his job in
                        Bristol after falsely being accused of assaulting a young woman. Hence the references to Mark Anthony, the great lover of
                        Shakespeare&#8217;s <title>Antony and Cleopatra</title> and John Dryden's (1631&#8211;1700; DNB) <title>All for Love, or the World Well
                            Lost</title> (1678).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The box was long upon the road, &amp; most exceedingly pleased I am with its contents. Pray present my very sincere
                    thanks to Robert Hancock<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Hancock (1731&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>) had made a pencil
                        and chalk drawing of Southey in 1797. He had sent his portrait of Danvers to Southey, and the picture had just arrived.</note> he could not
                    possibly have gratified me more, &amp; he could not possibly have succeeded better. We all agree in thinking it as happy a
                    likeness as ever has been taken. <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">Your mothers</ref> picture is also admirably copied. It
                    brings her back perfectly to my recollection, &amp; I value it more than I shall express. It hangs in the parlour over the fire
                    place, in place of that ill-looking miniature which <del>xxx</del> made me look like a gentleman of fashion out of humour.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> It is not clear which painting Southey is referring to here.</note> I cannot provide a
                    frame for yours till I go to Whitehaven <del>xxxx</del> &amp; chuse one. We think of an expedition there when the spring comes on,
                    for the sake of looking in the neighbourhood for sea-bathing, &#8211; &amp; open a communication <del>with</del> which may supply me
                    with various articles not to be obtained at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have learnt from the newspapers that <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref>
                        tragedy<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Remorse</title> was staged at Drury Lane, London, 23 January-12 February 1813. This made it a moderate success and
                        Coleridge sent his family &#163;100.</note> which was rejected in 1798 by Sheridan<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        playwright, theatre proprietor and politician Richard Brinsley Sheridan (1751&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp;
                        Kemble<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Philip Kemble (1757&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), actor.</note> is about to
                    appear at New Drury Lane. I have little doubt of its success. The immediate profits in that case will pay his debts &amp; set him
                    afloat; &#8211; &amp; what is yet of greater consequence the spur of popular applause, to which no man is more sensible, may tempt him
                    to make <del>xxx xxx</del> use of the opening which he has gained &amp; exert himself in this which is the most lucrative of all
                    modes of writing &amp; to him one of the easiest. This is very desirable, &amp; I who as you know am not prone to be sanguine in
                    my expectations from <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> think it by no means unlikely.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Well might you speak of the ill-printing of the Omniana.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Omniana: or Horae Otiosiores</title>, a two volume compilation, including material by Coleridge, published in
                        1812.</note> I did not see the book till yesterday, &amp; it is another sample of the manner in which <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> has served me with his worn-out types! I suppose he has been an embarrassed man:
                    &#8211; nevertheless it is vexatious to have two books sent <del>out</del> into the world in so beggarly a manner.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The other book referred to is the third edition of <title>Madoc</title> (1812); see Southey to
                        Charles Danvers, 7 October 1812, Letter 2154.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Life of Nelson<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Nelson</title>, published by Murray in 1813.</note> will make a very different appearance. By some
                    miscalculation which lies between <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> &amp; the Printer,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Moyes (d. 1839), of Greville St, Hatton Garden, London.</note> &amp; of which I am altogether clear,
                    they have printed it in so open a page that it runs to two volumes instead of one, greatly I believe, to the injury, or certainly
                    to the <del>xxxx xxx</del> impediment of its sale. You will probably get it early in March. As far as all mechanical execution
                    goes it will be a very beautiful book. There will be a good portrait, at least no expense will be spared in procuring one, &amp;
                    plans of the three great battles, have been furnished me from the Admiralty by <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Crokers</ref>
                        interference.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813) contained a portrait
                        engraving by an unnamed artist. Its source was an 1800 pencil portrait of Nelson by Simon de Koster (1767&#8211;1831). The book also
                        contained a fold out plan of the Battle of the Nile (1798).</note> What is of more importance I am very well satisfied with my
                    own part, &#8211; tho the subject was one with which I should never have meddled had I not been <del>xxx</del> drawn or driven into it
                    by the review.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s biography of Nelson was an expansion of his article in
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218&#8211;262.</note> You will be pleased with the tone &amp; temper of the
                    book. <del>I have</del> There will be some original matter in it, &amp; a good deal of impressive <del>xxx</del> narratives. No
                    battles ever did so well upon paper as Nelsons.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the last Quarterly I reviewed <ref target="people.html#LandorRobertEyres">Landors</ref> Play,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Savage Landor, <title>Count Julian: A Tragedy</title> (1812), <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 8 (September 1812), 86&#8211;92.</note> &amp; the Calamities of Authors,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isaac D&#8217;Israeli (1766&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Calamities of Authors; Including some Inquiries Respecting their
                            Moral and Literary Characters</title> (1812), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (September 1812), 93&#8211;114.</note> &#8211; but as
                    the number has not reached me I cannot say whether these articles stand as they were written. The proofs of an essay on the state
                    of the poor or rather the populace are now upon my desk, &#8211; being part of an article for the next number.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Society for Bettering the Condition and Increasing the Comforts of the Poor. The first of a series of
                        Southeyan articles on the poor appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356.</note> It is an
                    attack upon Malthus,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The political economist Thomas Robert Malthus (1766&#8211;1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; upon the Manufacturing System, &amp; upon the <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbetts</ref> &amp; Hunts<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The radical Henry &#8216;Orator&#8217; Hunt (1773&#8211;1835;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> who have produced this Luddite<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Luddite movement
                        smashed textile machinery that was seen as threatening employment. It was based in the East Midlands, Yorkshire and
                        Lancashire.</note> feeling in the mob. I go to the conclusion as soon as this letter is folded up. It is to recommend modes of
                    employment for those who want work, &#8211; public education upon a national establishment, &#8211; military &amp; naval schools to receive as
                    many children as may be offered, &#8211; extensive colonization, &#8211; &amp; those means of improving our own state at home, &amp; advancing
                    the human race, of which the operation would be without contingent evil or inconvenience, &amp; the effect certain.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Buonaparte&#8217;s escape is vexatious.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Napoleon had abandoned his defeated Army
                        that was retreating through Russia in November 1812 and was organizing the defence of his central European empire.</note>
                    General Maitlands<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frederick Maitland (1763&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>). British soldier. He
                        commanded an army from Sicily, which had landed at Alicante in Spain in August 1812. However, he resigned his command in
                        November 1812 having accomplished little. Wellington&#8217;s troops had captured Madrid in August 1812, but then retreated to
                        Portugal to avoid encirclement.</note> &amp; <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellingtons</ref>
                    blunders more so. But I verily hope that the <del>Russian</del> destruction of Moscow has delivered Europe.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> As French troops entered Moscow on 14 September 1812 the city caught fire (probably accidentally)
                        and this prevented the French Army gaining any benefit from occupying the Russian capital. In October, the French were forced
                        to retreat.</note> Nothing can be finer than the whole conduct of the Russians. It is fitting that this Monster <del>xx</del>
                    should drink the cup of humiliation to its <del>xxx</del> dregs before he dies, &amp; nothing can prevent this, unless the Whigs
                    betray this country to as abominable a peace now, as the Tories did in the days of Marlborough.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough (1650&#8211;1722; <title>DNB</title>). Southey is referring to the Treaty of
                        Utrecht (1713), at the conclusion of the War of the Spanish Succession, which was widely-criticised for being too lenient to
                        the French.</note> Give me that man for minister, be he who he may, whose principle it shall be that there must never be peace
                    with Buonparte. If that principle were solemnly avowed by the Government &amp; recognised by the public, he could not maintain
                    himself upon his throne for three months after it <del>xxx</del> was known in France.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are going on well &amp; our weather is delightful. The <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhora</ref> is as
                    you may suppose a great acquisition to us. &#8211; Which is become of <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">Sam Reid</ref>? Remember me
                    to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> &amp; believe me dear <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles</ref>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> R Southey </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>