<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2549</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3820</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Art
                        Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 28.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 100&#8211;102 [misdated 3 February
                    1815].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2549" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2549" type="letter">
        <head>2549. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1815-02-05">5
                        February 1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Tours/ France.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; ANGLETERRE<lb />Postmark: [partial] 8 FE 8/ 1815<lb />MS: National Art
                        Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 28<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 100&#8211;102 [misdated 3 February
                    1815].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1815-02-05">5 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1815</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter gives me great pleasure. Doubt not but that you will be able to keep your promise, &amp; be the happier
                    for keeping it.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor had quarrelled with his wife and separated from her. In Landor to
                        Southey, 23 January 1815 (John Foster, <title>Walter Savage Landor: a Biography</title>, 2 vols (London, 1869), I, pp.
                        415&#8211;417), he indicated there might be a reconciliation and described his hope that he could keep his promise to forget his
                        wife&#8217;s &#8216;humiliating and insulting language&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Where shall I send Roderick<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814). The second, duodecimo, edition was printed in 1815.</note> to meet you
                    when you cross the channel, or shall I direct it to <ref target="people.html#LandorJulia">Mrs Landor </ref>
          <del> x</del> &amp; where? <del>Xx xx x</del> Before she sets out, if you wait for spring weather, it will be reprinted in a more
                    portable form than its present cumbrous quarto.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In one of the first books which I published a crazy compositor took into his head to correct the proofs after me;
                    &amp; this he did so assiduously that it cost me no fewer than sixteen cancels to get rid of the most intolerable of
                        blunders.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a reference to Southey&#8217;s troubles when publishing <title>Letters
                            Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797), when he claimed the printer had &#8216;compleatly
                        disgraced himself by the blunders he has made. I was obliged to cancel sixteen leaves.&#8217; (Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford,
                        30 January &#8211; [2 February] 1797, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 198).</note> One of
                    his principles was that in printing verse, wherever the lines were so indented that two in succession did not begin in the same
                    perpendicular, there was to be a full stop at the end of the former; &#8211; &amp; upon this principle he punctuated my verses. I
                    discovered it at last in the printing office upon enquiring how it happened that the very faults for which a leaf was cancelled
                    appeared most perseveringly in the reprint: the man then came forward, quite in a fit of madness, told me I should have made a
                    pretty book of it if he had not corrected it for me, &#8211; &amp; it was as much as the master of the office could do to pacify
                        him.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797) was printed in Bristol by William Bulgin
                        (fl. 1790s-1830s) and Robert Rosser (d. 1802).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have I think at Tours the grave of Ronsard,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French poet Pierre de
                        Ronsard (1524&#8211;1585). Southey possessed a 1592 edition of Ronsard&#8217;s <title>Oeuvres</title>, no. 2467 in the sale catalogue of
                        his library.</note> &#8211; who would have been a great poet if he had not been a Frenchman. I have read his works in those odds
                    &amp; ends of time which can be afforded to such reading, &amp; have so much respect for him, Frenchman as he was, that I shall
                    not visit Tours without enquiring for his grave. Never did man more boldly promise immortality to himself; never did man more
                    ardently aspire after it: &amp; no Frenchman has ever impressed me with an equal sense of power. But poetry of the higher order is
                    as impossible in that curst language as it is in Chinese. &#8211; And this reminds me of a certain M. Le Mierre,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Auguste-Jacques Le Mierre d&#8217;Argy (1762&#8211;1815); see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 16 January
                        1815.</note> Interprete &#8211; Traducteur &amp;c &#8211; who has written to tell me that many of my compatriotes distingu&#233;s par leur gout
                    et leurs connoissances<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;My countrymen, distinguished for their taste and their
                        knowledge&#8217;.</note> have spoken to him with great eulogies of my poem of Roderick, &#8211; whereupon he, not having seen the poem has
                    resolved to translate it, &amp; found a bookseller who will undertake to print the translation. &#8211; I wrote him as courtesy required
                    a civil reply, but expressed my doubts whether such a poem would accord with the taste of a French public, &amp; recommended him,
                    if he should persist in his intention when he had read the book, to render it in prose rather &lt;than&gt; in verse.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have begun my Quaker poem,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;, left incomplete at Southey&#8217;s
                        death.</note> &amp; written the first book in irregular rhyme, a measure which allows of a lower key than any structure of
                    rhymeless verse; &amp; may be laid aside where the passion requires it for dialogue. The principal character is rather a Seeker
                    (in the language of that day) than a Quaker, &#8211; a son of Goffe the Kings Judge,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> William
                        Goffe (d. 1679?; <title>DNB</title>), Puritan, regicide and major general, who fled to New England in 1660 after he was
                        excluded from the Act of Indemnity after the Restoration. In Southey&#8217;s poem, he was the father of Oliver Newman.</note> a
                    godson of Cromwell,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Oliver Cromwell (1599&#8211;1658; <title>DNB</title>), parliamentary
                        general and Lord Protector of England, Scotland and Ireland 1653&#8211;1658.</note> &#8211; a friend of Milton, &#8211; a companion of William
                        Penn.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Quaker leader and founder of Pennsylvania, William Penn (1644&#8211;1718;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> The plan is sufficiently made out, &#8211; but I have no longer that ardour of execution which I
                    possessed twenty years ago. I have the disheartening conviction that my best is done, &amp; that to add to the bulk of my works
                    will not be to add to their estimation. Doubtless I shall <del>fini</del> go on with the poem, &amp; compleat it if I live, but it
                    will be to please others, not myself; &amp; will be so long in progress that in all likelihood I shall never begin another. &#8211; You
                    see I am not without those autumnal feelings which your stanza expresses; &amp; yet the decline of life has <del>joys of</del>
                    delights of its own, &#8211; its autumnal odours &amp; its sunset [MS torn] <del>&amp; hues</del> hues. My disposition is invincibly
                    chearful &amp; this alone would make me a happy man, if I were not so from the tenour of my life: yet I doubt whether the
                    strictest Carthusian has the thought of death more habitually in his mind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope to see you in the autumn; &amp; will, if it be possible.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>