<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2010</idno><idno type="nines">rce3281</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6
                        vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 320–321 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2010" type="letter"><head>2010. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1811-12-31">31 December
                        1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/
                        Surry<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb/>Postmark: E/ 3 JAN 3/ 1812; [partial] 10o’Clock/ 1812<lb/>MS: Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery<lb/>Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6
                        vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 320–321 [in part].</note></head><p rend="indent1"> The hint which I threw out concerning our English martyrs in writing upon the Evangelical Sects is likely to mature
                    into something of importance.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Southey’s review of <title>Hints to the Public and the
                            Legislature, on the Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title> (1809), in <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 480–514.</note> I conceived a plan which <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> &amp; the Bp. of Meath<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Lewis O’Beirne
                        (1747–1823; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Meath 1798–1823. The son of a County Longford farmer, he had been educated for the
                        Catholic priesthood, but converted to Protestantism and became a Church of Ireland clergyman. He had been a well-known Whig,
                        but by 1811 he was increasingly conservative and a defender of the Church of Ireland.</note> took up <del>xxx</del> warmly,
                    &amp; the former has in some degree bound me to execute it by sending down Fox’s Book of Martyrs<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Foxe (1517–1587; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Actes and Mounuments</title> (1563). Southey possessed an
                        edition of 1684, no. 975 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> as soon as he reached London. The projected outline is
                    briefly this. Under the title of the Book of the Church<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s projected <title>Book of
                            the Church</title> was eventually published in 1824.</note> to give what should at once be the philosophy &amp; the
                    anthology of our Church History, so written as to be addressed to the hearts of the young, &amp; the understandings of the old, –
                    for it will be placed upon the Establishment of the National Schools.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anglican schools
                        founded by the National Society for the Education of the Poor in the Principles of the Christian Church, set up by Bell in
                        November 1811.</note> It begins with an account of the <del>xx</del> various false religions of our different ancestors,
                    British, Roman &amp; Saxon, – with the mischievous temporal consequences of those superstitions, being the evils from which the
                    country was delivered by its conversion to Xtianity. 2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>. a picture of Popery &amp; of the evils from which
                    the Reformation delivered us. 3 Puritanism rampant – from which the restoration of the Church rescued us, lastly Methodism from
                    which the Establishment preserves us. These parts to be connected by an historical thread, containing whatever is most impressive
                    in the Acts &amp; Monuments of the English church. How beautiful a work may be composed upon such a plan, (which from its very
                    nature excludes whatever is uninviting or tedious) you will at once perceive. The civil history would form a companion work upon a
                    similar plan called the Book of the Constitution,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The ‘Book of the Constitution’ was never
                        written.</note> showing the gradual <del>x xx</del> but uniform amelioration of society; – &amp; the direct object of both
                    would be to make the rising generation feel &amp; understand the blessings of their inheritance.</p><p rend="indent1"> Each of these works would extend to about as much as would fill from 80 to 100 pages of the Quarterly. For the two,
                        <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> offers me 500£. His letter came to night, – I had written yesterday to <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> to consult with him as to the terms which ought to be made,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The letter to Turner appears not to have survived.</note> &amp; shall wait his advice, – for the
                    advantages which these books would enjoy thro <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> are such as
                    to afford a probability of greater emolument than I should be justified in foregoing even for such a price as this.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am well stored with materials, having all the republished Chronicles,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Chronicles of England, Scotland and Ireland</title> (1807–1812), no. 654 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                        library.</note> &amp; Hooker, – the only controversial work which it will be at all necessary to consult.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Hooker (1554–1600; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Lawes of Ecclesiastical
                            Politie</title> (1594–1597), which argued for Anglicanism as a middle way between Puritanism and Catholicism, the role of
                        reason in religion and a historical understanding of the Bible – all approaches that appealed to Southey. The book was no.
                        1427 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> The <del>only</del> other books which I want I have orderd – they are
                    Burnett, &amp; the Ch. Histories of Fuller &amp; of the stiff old Non juror Jeremy Collier.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gilbert Burnet (1643–1715; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of the Reformation of the Church of
                            England</title> (1679–1714); Thomas Fuller (1607/8–1661; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Church History of Britain</title>
                        (1655); and Jeremy Collier (1650–1726; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Ecclesiastical History of Great Britain</title> (1708–1714).
                        Collier was a bishop in the non-juring church which refused to accept the Glorious Revolution of 1688. Southey had ordered
                        these books from Murray.</note> – I will send the manuscript to you before it goes to the press, for it will require an
                    inspecting eye, – meantime if any thing occur to you which would correct or improve the plan, such as you here see it, do not omit
                    to communicate your advice &amp; opinion. I have a strong persuasion that both these works may be made of great, extensive &amp;
                    permanent usefulness.</p><p rend="indent1"> The enlarged article on the New System is in the press,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s
                            <title>The Origin, Nature and Object, of the New System of Education</title> (1812) was an expansion of his advocacy of
                        Andrew Bell in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (August 1811), 264–304. At Bell’s request, Southey’s attacks on Brougham,
                        Jeffrey and others were moderated before publication; see Southey to Andrew Bell, 30 December 1811, (Letter 2008)
                        and Southey to John Murray [c. 30 December 1811] (Letter 2009).</note> – but the teeth of the argument are likely once more to
                    be extracted, – an operation to which I submit with exemplary patience. Questions of prudence, such as this must be, I leave
                    willingly to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>. Both he &amp; <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffard</ref> urge me to a deadly attack upon the Edinburghers, to be brought forth <del>xxxx</del> in perfect secresy under
                    some &lt;such&gt; title as the Beauties of the E. Rev.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> This project was not
                        realised.</note> I neither want power nor provocation for this, – but unless somebody will turn mud-lark for me, &amp; rake in
                    the Flowers of Edinburgh to make the collection, – the thing must remain undone – my stomach could never be brought to the
                    task.</p><closer><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1811-12-31">Dec. 31. 1811</date></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has not got at the precise meaning of the phrase concerning which he applied to
                        you. – el segundo quadrante<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. ‘the second quadrant’.</note> &amp;c – he takes the
                        quadrantes to be the cardinal points. <del>x xx but if xxx how many</del> in that case el segundo quadrante would be East.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>