<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2384</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3655</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Don.
                        d. 3.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2384" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2384" type="letter">
        <head>2384. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1814-03-02">2
                        March 1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey./ Queen Anne
                        Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 5 MA 5/ 1814<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don.
                        d. 3<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is fortunate that the Dutchmen proved beyond the skill of the bookbinder, for the set turns out to be
                        imperfect.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified books, probably on Dutch colonial history; see Southey to
                        Henry Herbert Southey, 28 December 1813, Letter 2357.</note> Will you the next time you go to <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch&#8217;s</ref> call at Lackingtons<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The London
                        booksellers and publishers Lackington, Allen and Co, at this time headed by George Lackington (1777&#8211;1844;
                        <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; say this. The case is this, there are the number of volumes which the Catalogue specified
                    viz. 29. But the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> vol. is wanting, &amp; the thirteenth being in two parts (or what <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref> would call a double-volume) makes up the number. &#8211; I make no doubt but that the
                    bookseller will readily exchange it. Tell the circumstances &amp; remind them when &amp; by whom the book was bought, &amp; when
                    they promise to exchange it &#8211; I will send it back by waggon, <del>&amp; of course</del> the carriage &lt;of course&gt; must be at
                    my loss &#8211; &amp; I will chuse from their catalogue, as soon as I can get it other books to the same &#8211; or a greater amount.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I desired <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> to give you the 12 &amp; 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> book of Rodericks,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814); see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 18 February 1814, Letter
                        2379.</note> &#8211; two more will very shortly be ready, &#8211; the printer keeps spurring me on, &#8211; I have corrected nine sheets.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> One of our servants has a cough which I am certain must be the <hi rend="ital">tussis ferina</hi>, or second
                    hooping cough. For she has had the hooping cough; this certainly is not infectious, &amp; she hoops with it so as to disturb the
                    whole house. Have you ever met with a case of this most rightly &#8211; named disorder? <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry
                        Bedford</ref> has had it. And do you know any remedy for it, besides the slow one of patience, or the, in this case,
                    impracticable one of change of air? It is curious that the disease should be undistinguishable from hooping cough by any other
                    circumstances than its not being infectious, &#8211; which means I suppose in other words that <del>xxx</del> the hooping cough in the
                    very rare instances of its recurrence is always mitigated in this degree, &#8211; <del>not to the patient, but to</del> &#8211; the more
                    remarkable because the patient seems to suffer as much.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very ill pleased at the aspect of public affairs. A moving mind is equally wanted at home &amp; abroad. It is
                    disheartening to see that the experience not only of former times, but &lt;even&gt; of their own is lost upon our statesmen. They
                    themselves made the peace of Amiens, &amp; they have the execrable example of the peace of Utrecht before them, &amp; yet we are
                    likely to have the folly of the one &amp; the sin of the other united in a third peace which will be more injurious to Europe than
                    any before it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Treaty of Utrecht (1713) ended the War of the Spanish Succession and
                        was widely regarded as too lenient towards France; the Treaty of Amiens (1802) provided a temporary respite in the war with
                        France, which was resumed the following year.</note> &#8211; Did you see my ode in the Courier?<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Ode Written During the Negotiations with Bonaparte&#8217;, published in the <title>Courier</title>, 3 February
                        1814.</note> They must go to somebody else to write odes upon peace for them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#StandertHughChudleigh">Standert</ref> has never answered the letter in which I asked him for his
                        case.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was collecting information for Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Observations on Pulmonary Consumption</title> (1814), and had promised to write to Standert for information on
                        consumptive cases; see Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 28 December 1813 (Letter 2357) and Southey to Hugh Chudleigh
                        Standert, 21 December 1813 (Letter 2353).</note> &#8211; Have you among your memoranda that John Wesley in his Primitive Physic (it
                    is a book worth buying) mentions human milk as a remedy for consumption, &amp; <del>xxx I</del> if I remember rightly states that
                    his father was recovered by its use.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Primitive Physic</title>, 20th edn (London, 1781), p. 45, which noted &#8216;In the last stage [of pulmonary
                        consumption], suck an healthy woman daily. Tried by my father [Samuel Wesley (1662&#8211;1735; <title>DNB</title>]&#8217;.</note> A case
                    not less memorable is that of <del>the</del> Alva, the famous &amp; bloody Alva; &#8211; the last remedy to which he had recourse in a
                    decline induced more by vexation than any other cause was a womans breast.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The governor of
                        the Spanish Netherlands, Fernando &#193;lvarez de Toledo y Pimentel, 3rd Duke of Alba (1507&#8211;1582).</note> When his cruelties are
                    remembered, the fact becomes one of the most striking in history. Should you have occasion to mention it, I dare say I can hunt
                    out the authority for you; &#8211; it is either Conestaggio<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was probably thinking of
                        Jeronimo de Franchi Conestaggio (c. 1530&#8211;1618), <title>Delle Guerre della Germania Inferiore</title> (1614).</note> or
                    Linschoten,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Huyghen van Linschoten (1563&#8211;1611), <title>Discours of Voyages into y
                        Easte and West Indies</title> (London, 1598), p. 3: &#8216;the Duke of Alva died in Lisbon, in the King&#8217;s palace &#8230; who, during his sickness, for fourteen days, received no sustenance but only women&#8217;s milk&#8217;.</note> but I believe the
                    latter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SayersFrank">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sayers</ref> should review the Synonimes,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Taylor&#8217;s <title>English Synonimes Discriminated</title> (1813). Sayers did not review it for the
                            <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> if he is well enough to do it. He writes in the Quarterly, &amp; the subject is not out
                    of his way. I would do it if I could, but it is out of my reach, except for that sort of general praise, laudatory extract &amp;
                        <del>g</del> desultory comment which would do for other reviews but does not accord with the plan of the Quarterly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How is <ref target="people.html#GonneWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gonne</ref> going on? &#8211; Has the <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Marquis</ref> had his Wedding Cake<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Gooch
                        had married for the second time in January 1814.</note> from <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Doctor <hi rend="ital">D</hi>ooch</ref> &#8211;? I owe that said Doct[MS torn] a letter &#8211; &amp; it will not be long the debt will be discharged.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am getting on with my Brazil<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second and third volumes of <title>The
                            History of Brazil</title> appeared in 1817 and 1819.</note> at present, &amp; hesitating among many <del>subjects on</del>
                    projected poems on which to begin when Roderic<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> is finished. Perhaps a Persian or a Manich&#230;an Romance in
                    Thalaban <del>metre</del> verse.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. in the metre of <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801). Neither romance was written.</note> &#8211; the latter more likely of the two, Mani having more
                    imagination than Zoroaster.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mani (216&#8211;276) was the founder of the dualistic Manichean
                        religion; Zoroaster (11th/10th century BC) was the prophet of Zoroastrianism.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1814-03-02">March 2. 1814. </date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>