<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2039</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3310</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42550.  Previously 
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
                        28&#8211;30.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2039" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2039" type="letter">
        <head>2039. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1812-02-15">15 February
                        1812</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Murray/ Fleet Street/
                        London.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb />Postmark: E/ 18 FE 18/ 1812 <lb />Watermark: shield/ 1806<lb />Endorsement: 1812 15 Feb/
                            Rob<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42550<lb />Previously
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
                        28&#8211;30.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-02-15">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 15. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Respecting <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Charles Lamb</ref> nothing can be done but to expunge the allusion
                    when the number is reprinted; &#8211; this will prove that it was unintended, &amp; I will let him know that it has given you &amp; the
                    writer more pain than it can possibly have given him.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gifford had described Lamb, in a
                        review of John Ford (bap. 1586&#8211;1639x53?; <title>DNB</title>), as &#8216;a poor maniac&#8217; for whom &#8216;every feeling mind will find an
                        apology in his calamitous situation&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (December 1811), 485. Gifford expressed both regret
                        and ignorance of Lamb&#8217;s personal history; see his letter to Southey, 13 February 1813, Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, p. 151 n. *.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have read the Letter<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor&#8217;s <title>Commentary on Memoirs of Mr
                            Fox</title>, which was printed by Murray in 1812, but suppressed.</note> which is here returned, with some sorrow. The
                    evening that the Commentary reached me I wrote<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Walter Savage Landor, 12
                        February 1811, Letter 1870.</note> to <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">L.</ref> (being certain that he was the
                    author) telling him I could not lay my head in peace upon the pillow if I did not urge him to strike out <del>some</del> certain
                    passages, &#8211; &amp; by the next post I pointed out, not all which were objectionable to my own feelings, but those which appeared to
                    me most likely to wound others, or to produce <del>any</del> inconvenience to himself. The actionable parts as I imagine are p.
                    iii about withholding supplies,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> In <title>Charles James Fox. A Commentary on His Life and
                            Character</title>, ed. Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), p.7, Landor suggested that the British people could force their
                        government to change its policies by refusing to pay taxes.</note> &#8211; the language applied to Lord Chatham,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pitt, 2nd Earl of Chatham (1756&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), army officer and elder brother of
                        the former prime minister William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>). The <title>Commentary</title> criticised his role in
                        the ill-fated Walcheren expedition of 1809, <title>Charles James Fox. A Commentary on His Life and Character</title>, ed.
                        Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), p. 23.</note> &amp; to Fellowes.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In a tirade against
                        &#8216;Reviewers and magazine-men, the linkboys and scavengers of literature&#8217; Landor singled out Robert Fellowes (1770&#8211;1847;
                            <title>DNB</title>): &#8216;Of late years, if any one had paid any attention to such people [reviewers] &#8230; one would imagine &#8230;
                        that Aristotle only kept a box for Mr. Fellowes.// This reverent gentleman having settled religion to his mind, but unhappily
                        &#8230; driven out from the poets, is retaliating on them as their judge. He writes, or did write, for I know not whether the work
                        survives his hand, in <title>The Critical Review</title>; strange successor to the gentle, but high-minded Southey&#8217;, Landor,
                            <title>Charles James Fox. A Commentary on His Life and Character</title>, ed. Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), p. 146.
                        Landor&#8217;s dislike of Fellowes had undoubtedly been fuelled by learning (from Southey) of the latter&#8217;s views on his poetry.
                        Fellowes had observed in a letter to Seward of 1803 that: &#8216;The author of Gebir &#8230; has lately made another attempt to convey the
                        waters of Helicon by leaden pipes, and many dark subterranean ways &#8230; having trod the dark profound of Gebir, I feel no
                        inclination to begin another journey, which promises so little pleasure, and probably where only a few occasional flashes will
                        enlighten the road&#8217;, <title>Letters of Anna Seward: Written Between the Years 1784 and 1807</title>, 6 vols (Edinburgh, 1811),
                        V, p. 77 n. *.</note> I objected to what was said of Croker as in every respect wrong,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Landor seems to have removed his comments on Croker.</note> &#8211; to the mention of Lord Riversdale,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Tonson, 2nd Lord Riversdale (1775&#8211;1848). His father, William Tonson, 1st Lord Riversdale (1724&#8211;1787),
                        was born William Hull and was probably the illegitimate son of the substantial Irish landowner, Robert Tonson (1695&#8211;1773).
                        Landor had referred to the 1st Lord Riversdale as &#8216;the bastard of a scullion&#8217;; <title>Charles James Fox. A Commentary on His
                            Life and Character</title>, ed. Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), p. 90.</note> &amp; the story of Kett.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Kett (1761&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), Fellow of Trinity College, Oxford, and writer on
                        education. Landor had encountered him during his time at Oxford. Kett features regularly in Landor&#8217;s satirical writings and
                        the <title>Commentary</title> related an anecdote about his unprofessional, self-serving conduct; <title>Charles James Fox. A
                            Commentary on His Life and Character</title>, ed. Stephen Wheeler (London, 1907), pp. 220&#8211;222.</note> It would not
                    surprize me if he should resolve in anger to suppress the whole. Had he given me a hint of this intended publication I would have
                    begged him to let me see the manuscript; any comments upon it in that state would have availed more, because there would have been
                    no inconvenience in attending to them. Now they will vex &amp; perhaps for that reason irritate him, &#8211; because anger is the
                    easiest way of throwing off vexation, or at least of disguising it. Yet I have too good an opinion of him, &amp; believe that he
                    has too good a one of me, &#8211; to expect that this will be the case. <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">L.</ref> is a man
                    of most ungoverned mind, with an excellent heart, classical attainments which are not to be surpassed, &amp; a strength of genius
                    to which Count Julian<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor, <title>Count Julian: A Tragedy</title> (1812). It deals
                        with similar subject-matter to Southey&#8217;s <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> bears witness: &#8211; but in
                    his life as in his Commentary there is a want of self-government; &#8211; do not understand this as implying that he is a
                        <del>vicious</del> debauched man &#8211; far from it, &#8211; it is that sort of imprudence which the Commentary so strikingly displays, &#8211;
                    feeling strongly, acting upon light grounds, &amp; speaking with a fearless sincerity, which becomes very dangerous when it is not
                    sufficiently influenced by fore thought. I thought him greatly sobered when I saw him in August last, &#8211; but this is a proof to the
                    contrary. <del>He is one of the men</del> As soon as the reviewal of the Iceland-travels<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Sir George Steuart Mackenzie (1780&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in the Island of Iceland, in the Summer of the
                            Year 1810</title> (1811); reviewed by Southey alongside Sir William Jackson Hooker (1785&#8211;1865; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Journal of a Tour in Iceland, in the Summer of 1809</title> (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (March
                        1812), 48&#8211;92.</note> is compleated I shall begin upon his Tragedy, many parts of which are above the pitch of any other living
                        writer.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Count Julian</title> appeared in <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 8 (September 1812), 86&#8211;92.</note> I feel this, who never effect to undervalue myself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for Rodds book.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Rodd (1763&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>),
                        bookseller, poet and translator. His <title>History of Charles the Great and Orlando, and Other Spanish Ballads</title> was
                        published in 1812.</note> it will furnish a very amusing article, especially if we can get Balbue&#241;as poem of Bernado del
                        Carpio.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manuel Jos&#233; Quintana (1772&#8211;1857), Spanish poet and man of letters had, in
                        1808, republished <title>El Bernardo</title> (1624), Bernardo de Balbuena&#8217;s (1564&#8211;1627) epic on the legendary Spanish hero
                        Bernardo del Carpio, whose exploits included slaying the French paladin Roland at the battle of Roncesvaux (778). Southey did
                        acquire a copy &#8211; it was no. 3175 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is expected tomorrow. I shall endeavour to get from him a reviewal
                    of Chalmerss Poets,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander Chalmers (1759&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works
                            of the English Poets, from Chaucer to Cowper</title> (1810). It was reviewed not by Coleridge, but by Southey in
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 11 (July 1814), 480&#8211;504; and <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (October 1814),
                        60&#8211;90.</note> &#8211; in such criticism you must know, if you have heard him lecture, that he is unequalled; &amp; the thing will be
                    far better in his hands than mine, &#8211; tho better I believe in mine than in those of any third person. &#8211; I am promised an article
                    upon <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">Miss Seward</ref> (as I mentioned to you in town) from D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Lister,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Lister (c. 1773&#8211;1828), of Armitage Park, Staffordshire. He was a
                        lawyer and landowner, who, in his younger days, was a miscellaneous writer and prot&#233;g&#233;e of Anna Seward. No article on Seward
                        was published in the <title>Quarterly Review</title> at this time.</note> who means to send it here, before it is offered,
                    &amp; <del>xxx</del> &lt;if&gt; I understand him right, rather to offer me his materials, than to submit them in a finished form
                    himself. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> is a very able man, &#8211; one of the most promising <del>xxx</del> of
                    my friends; &#8211; &amp; capable of being a useful assistant in the Quarterly.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gooch did
                        become a very occasional contributor to the <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> No man is more likely to distinguish himself in
                    literature as well as in his own profession.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have a very water-gruel sort of article upon the Bible Society in a former number.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (August 1810), 68&#8211;80. Its author was John Ireland (1761&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>).</note> I
                    believe we had better let it rest. Marsh is strong enough to break the bones of all his antagonists; I have been reading his
                    pamphlett this very afternoon &amp; Clarkes most disgraceful reply to it,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Herbert Marsh
                        (1757&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), cleric and biblical critic. He had preached a sermon at St Paul&#8217;s on 13 June 1811 that was
                        critical of the interdenominational British and Foreign Bible Society (founded 1804) and urged that Anglicans should found
                        their own Bible society. Southey had been reading the pamphlet form of the sermon, <title>The National Religion the Foundation
                            of National Education: A Sermon Preached in the Cathedral Church of St. Paul, London</title> (1811). Its arguments were
                        rebutted by Edward Daniel Clarke (1769&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to Herbert Marsh, D.D., F.R.S. &#8230; in Reply to
                            Certain Observations Contained in His Pamphlet Relative to the British and Foreign Bible Society</title> (1812).</note> &#8211;
                    that man must be as great a blockhead as his brother James Stanier of ponderous memory.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The historian James Stanier Clarke (1765?-1834; <title>DNB</title>), of &#8216;ponderous memory&#8217; because of his co-authorship of a
                        biography of Lord Nelson (1758&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>) that weighed, so Southey estimated, some twenty pounds.</note> This
                    is Marshs position, &#8211; all sects ought to associate for distributing the Bible in <hi rend="ital">foreign</hi> countries; &#8211; but at
                    home it is the <hi rend="ital">duty</hi> of the <hi rend="ital">Church</hi> to accompany it with the Liturgy. Churchmen therefore
                    ought to join a <hi rend="ital">foreign</hi> Bible society, &#8211; <del>but at home</del> i.e. this very Society if it would confine
                    itself to foreign distribution, &#8211; but if they act with it at home, they make a concession of principle, &amp; what they yield the
                    dissenters gain. This is very clear, &#8211; Marsh is a logical writer, &amp; all his antagonists are mere children to him. But it would
                    have been better not to have agitated the question, &#8211; &amp; to have effected the proposed object in a quieter way by proposing a
                    vote that the Church Members of the Society should <del>add</del> &lt;have&gt; the prayer book added to the Bible which they
                    distribute. A little management might have effected this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you go on as in your last number you will run the Ed. down tho it should call in a dozen Mackintoshes<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> On his return to Britain from India in 1811, the writer and politician Sir James
                        Mackintosh (1765&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>) had been courted by the Tories, but he was elected to Parliament in 1813 as MP for
                        Nairn and became a leading spokesman for the Whigs. At the same time he began contributing to the Whig quarterly, the
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title>.</note> to its help.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>