<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2662</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3933</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research
                        Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos, The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                            1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 148&#8211;150; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 137&#8211;140 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2662" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2662" type="letter">
        <head>2662. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1815-10-20">20 October 1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ 4. Tavistock Street/ Bedford
                        Square/ London<lb />Stamped: P.94P/BRUXELLES <lb />Postmark: [partial] FORE[ILLEGIBLE]GN/ OC/ 27/ 1815<lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 183 1815/ Robert Southey/ Brussels 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. personally<lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research
                        Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos, <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                            1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 148&#8211;150; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 137&#8211;140 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>Brussels.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1815-10-20">Friday 20 Oct. 1815.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wrote to you from <del>Lige</del> Liege, up to which time all had gone on well with us. Thank God it is well with
                    us at present, but <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">your god-daughter</ref> has been so unwell, that we were detained six
                    days at Aix la Chapelle, in a state of anxiety which you may well imagine, &amp; at an Hotel where the Devil himself seemed to
                    possess the mistress &amp; the greater part of the domestics. Happily I found a physician who had graduated at Edinburgh,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gerhard Reumont (1765&#8211;1828), eminent Belgian doctor, who had studied at Edinburgh
                        University in 1792&#8211;1793. Reumont visited Edward Jenner (1749&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), the pioneer of vaccination against
                        smallpox, in 1800 and introduced Jenner&#8217;s discoveries to the Continent. He also enjoyed literary pursuits, and when Southey
                        visited Aix-La-Chapelle in 1817, he took with him, at Reumont&#8217;s request, a copy of Thomas Percy&#8217;s (1729&#8211;1811;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Reliques of Ancient English Poetry</title> (1765); see Southey to Edith Southey, 1 August
                        1817.</note> who spoke English, &amp; pursued a rational system, &#8211; &amp; happily also by this painful &amp; expensive delay I
                    was thrown into such society, that now the evil is over, I am fully sensible of the good to which it has conduced.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The day after my letter was written we reached Spa, &amp; remained there Sunday &amp; Monday, a pleasant &amp;
                    necessary pause, &#8211; tho the pleasure was somewhat interrupted by the state of my own health, which was somewhat disordered there, &#8211;
                    perhaps the effect of the thin Rhenish wines &amp; the grapes. Tuesday we would have slept at Verviers (the great clothing town)
                    if we could have found beds, &#8211; an English party had preoccupied them, &amp; we proceeded to Herve, a little town half-way between
                    Liege &amp; Aix la Chapelle, in the old principality of Limbourg. There, for the only time during our journey <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref> was put to sleep in a different from mine, for it was not possible to
                    arrange things otherwise. She slept with the servant of the <ref target="people.html#VardonMr">Vardons</ref>, &#8211; a young woman whom
                    they have bred up.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary (surname and dates unknown).</note> When we rose in the morning
                    we found that she had not slept <del>xxxxx</del> any part of the night owing to a sore throat: &#8211; she had gone to bed apparently in
                    high health &amp; spirits. Being accustomed to see her tonsils swoln to a degree which might have alarmed a person not used to
                        <del>such</del> see it, I was not uneasy; &amp; having bought some hartshorn to rub it with, we proceeded to Aix la Chapelle &#8211;
                    about 16 miles. &#8211; there was indeed no alternative, for any medical advice which could have been found in Herve, would have been
                    worse than nothing. But the journey over a paved road, was the worst thing which could have <del>been</del> befallen a patient in
                    an incipient fever, &amp; when we arrived the child was so ill, that after seeing her laid to bed (about one o clock
                        <del>&amp;</del> in the afternoon) I thought it necessary to go to the Bankers &amp; request them to recommend me to a
                    physician. You may imagine how painful a time we past. It was necessary for her to gargle every hour, even if we waked her for it,
                    &#8211; but she never slept an hour continuously for the three first nights. Thank God however she seems thoroughly recovered now, we
                    are at Brussels, &amp; can estimate the good with calmness.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> While I was acting as nurse &amp; cook (for we were obliged to do every thing ourselves) our party dined at the
                    Table d&#8217;Hote, &amp; there as the child grew better I found myself in the company of some highly-distinguished Prussian officers.
                    One of them a Major Dresky,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ferdinand Augustus Leopold Francis von Dresky (dates unknown),
                        led the 2nd Regiment of Silesian infantry at the Battle of Ligny on 16 June 1815.</note> is the very man who was with Blucher
                    at Ligny when he was ridden over by the French:<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gebhard von Blucher (1742&#8211;1819), commander
                        of the defeated Prussian forces at the battle of Ligny, 16 June 1815. His horse was shot from underneath him. He was carried
                        from the field semi-conscious by an aide.</note> the other Major Petry<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> is said by his brother officer to have won the battle of Donowitz for
                        Blucher.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Battle of Dennewitz, 6 September 1813, in which a French force was defeated
                        by a combined army from Prussia, Russia and Sweden. It was an important turning point in the war in north Germany.</note> Two
                    more extraordinary men I never met with. You would have been delighted to hear how they spoke of the English, &amp; <del>how</del>
                    to see how they treated us as representatives of our country. Among the toasts which were given, I put this into French &#8211; the
                    Belle Alliance between Prussia &amp; England, &#8211; may it endure as long as the memory of the battle: I cannot describe to you the
                    huzzaing &#8211; &amp; hob-nobbing &amp; handshaking with which it was received: But the chief benefit which I have derived was from
                    meeting with a certain Henry de Forster, a Major in our German Legion,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The King&#8217;s German
                        Legion (1803&#8211;1816), a unit in the British army made up of expatriate German personnel.</note> a Pole by birth whose father
                    held one of the highest offices in Poland.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Constantine Charles Henry Ernest Frederick
                        Augustus Gustav Adolph de Forster (dates unknown).</note> Forster, one of the most interesting men I ever met with, has
                    been marked for misfortune from his birth. Since the age of 13 he has supported himself, &amp; now supports a poor brother of 18,
                    a youth of high principles &amp; genius, who has for two years suffered with an abscess of the spleen. Forster entered the
                    Prussian service when a boy; was taken prisoner, &amp; cruelly used in France, &amp; escaped almost miraculously on foot into
                    Poland. In 1809 he joined the D of Brunswick,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frederick William, Duke of
                        Brunswick-Wolfenbuttel (1771&#8211;1815), leader of the German volunteer force, the Black Brunswickers, against French troops. He
                        died at the battle of Quartre Bras, 16 June 1815.</note> &amp; was one of those men who proved true to him thro all danger,
                    &amp; embarked with him &#8211; The Duke was a true German in patriotism, but without conduct, without principles &amp; without
                    gratitude. Forster entered our German Legion, &amp; was in all the hot work in the peninsula from the lines of T Vedras<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lines of forts built to defend Lisbon during the Peninsular War.</note> till the end of
                    the war. The severe duty of an infantry officer proved too much for his constitution, &amp; a fall of some 80 feet down a
                    precipice in the Pyrenees brought on a hemorrhage of the liver, for which he obtained unlimited leave of absence &amp; came to Aix
                    la Chapelle, I grieve to say that he had a relapse on the very day that we left him. I never saw a man whose feelings &amp;
                    opinions seemed to coincide more with my own. When we had become a little acquainted he shook hands with me in a manner so unlike
                    an ordinary greeting, that I immediately understood it to be (as really it was) a trial whether I were a free mason. This gave
                    occasion to the following sonnet, which I put into his hands at parting.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> The ties of secret brotherhood made known</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> By secret signs, &amp; pressure of linkd hand</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Significant, I neither understand</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Nor censure. There are countries where the throne</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And altar, singly or with force combined,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Against the welfare of poor humankind</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Direct their power perverse: in such a land</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Such leagues may have their purpose: in my own,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Being needless, they are needs but mockery</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> But to the wise &amp; good there doth belong,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Ordained by God himself, a surer tie;</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> A sacred &amp; unerring sympathy,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Which bindeth them in bonds of union strong</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> As time, &amp; lasting as eternity.</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent5"> ________</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> He has promised me to employ this winter in writing his Memoirs &#8211; a task which he had once performed, but the
                    papers were lost in a shipwreck off Santora; he has promised also to come with the MSS (if he lives) to England next summer &#8211;
                    where I hope &amp; expect that the publication will be as beneficial to his immediate interests, as it will be honourable to his
                    memory. &#8211; We left Aix on Tuesday for Maestricht, slept the next night at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Trond, Thursday at Louvaine, &amp;
                    arrived here to day. Tomorrow I go again with <ref target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> to Waterloo, for the purpose of
                    procuring drawings of Hougoumont.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nash illustrated the <title>Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to
                            Waterloo</title> (1816). His drawing &#8216;Entrance to Hougoumont&#8217; is between pp. 58&#8211;9 and &#8216;Interior View of the Ruins of
                        Hougoumont&#8217; between pp. 70&#8211;1.</note> On Sunday we go for Antwerp, rejoin the <ref target="people.html#VardonMr">Vardons</ref>
                    on Monday night at Ghent, &amp; then make the best of our way to Calais &amp; London. &#8211; The delay at Aix with its added expences
                    has cost me a good deal, &#8211; I draw on you therefore without scruple for 30 &#163; for this place, &amp; Englebert Werth<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Engelbert Werth (dates unknown), a German-born merchant and acquaintance of Vardon. Werth drew a
                        plan of the battle of Waterloo for Southey.</note> (a merchant here) will cash the bill. I have bought a good many books,
                    &amp; seen &amp; heard enough to leave a little volume behind me, if I should not think proper to publish it now. In ten or eleven
                    days I hope to see you. It is as much as I can do, to keep pace in my journal with the business of the day. &#8211; On the whole I
                    believe that I have never passed a month of my life to greater advantage.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear friend</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> your most affectionate</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">
            <del>R South</del> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>