<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2513</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3784</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        25.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2513" type="letter">
        <head>2513. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1814-12-11">11 December
                            1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 9. Stafford Row/ Buckingham
                        Gate<lb />Endorsement: 11 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1814/ Route of
                        Roderick<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        25<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Ready as I should be to repent of any unjust severity, or even of
                    just severity if exercised without adequate occasion, I have no compunctions
                    respecting Alexander Chalmers.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Alexander Chalmers (1759&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of the
                            English Poets, from Chaucer to Cowper</title> (1810), reviewed by
                        Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 11 (July 1814), 480&#8211;504; and
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (October 1814), 60&#8211;90.</note> He may
                    be the best natured man in the world, &amp; the most inoffensive, &#8211; but he has
                    approached the Ark with irreverent hands, &amp; I as one of the servants of the
                    Altar, am bound to resent the pollution. It is not to be borne that a man who is
                    ignorant of the very nomenclature of poetry, &amp; the commonest principles of
                    versification should undertake to form a Collection of the English Poets, reject
                    &amp; insert writers with no other rule than his own caprice, &amp; pass
                    sentence upon them with oracular solemnity. At <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> desire I expunged some
                    passages of personal severity, which were well deserved; &#8211; &amp; having done
                    this, &amp; read the article with <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, he as well as myself felt satisfied that nothing more was
                    said than what was due to <del>t</del> our predecessors. Perhaps you have heard
                        <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> speak of his complaints,
                    for <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> knows him. I cannot
                    repent. By the bye I am to have double pay for the article, &#8211; a thing equally
                    unexpected &amp; convenient at this juncture, when the Constable is lagging
                    sadly astern.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. a time when
                        Southey was short of cash. To &#8216;outrun the Constable&#8217; was an old phrase
                        signifying money worries.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The battle in which Roderick<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Roderick (d. 711/ 712), last Visigothic ruler of
                        Hispania and the subject of Southey&#8217;s <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814).</note> was defeated was fought near Xeres, (&#8211;
                    between Seville &amp; Cadiz.)<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        location of his defeat against the Moors is uncertain. It was possibly near
                        the mouth of the river Guadalete, hence the name popularly given to it, the
                        Battle of Guadelete.</note> He goes from thence due north till he comes to
                    the Caulian schools which are on the Guadiana, near Merida. Then his journey
                    lies West, or W N W. He crosses the Tagus about Abrantes, then the Zezere, &amp;
                    so by the site of Alcoba&#231;a to the sea at Nazareth which you will find in the
                    maps. When he sets off again he goes to Leyria, the Pombal (which is on the
                    Arunca,) Condeixa which is the old Conimbrica, &#8211; Coimbra, Guimareus (the cradle
                    of that famous monarchy<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Portuguese Monarchy. Guimaraes was the first capital of the County of
                        Portugal in the 11th century.</note>) &#8211; Braga &#8211; (Bracara Augusta) &amp;
                    Orense (Auria.) You have him next at a monastery in the Bierzo, from whence he
                    travels to Cordoba, &amp; from Cordoba across the country to Cangas in Asturias,
                    passing near Leon &lt;(the city)&gt; on the way. Gegio is the present Gijon.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The MSS<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. A MS of
                            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>. This was probably the
                        final, fair copy, from which the poem was printed: now Beinecke Library,
                        Yale University, Gen. MS 298.</note> in no very clean condition &amp;
                    improper disorder, is here for you &#8211; I shall send a coach parcel to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> early in the week &amp; will
                    inclose it; &amp; at the same time I will inclose my own original mss. that you
                    may get it either bound for me, or a case made for it; the latter I think will
                    be better, as preserving them compleatly in their original form: in which I
                    think those who come after me would like to have them best. This is a curious
                    mss inasmuch as there is probably no other such extant, the place where I began
                    to write being dated day by day throughout, so as to shew the hot &amp; the cold
                    fits, the long intervals, &amp; the hard gallops at last. I think I should like
                    a Russia case resembling a book in its appearance, &amp; lettered &#8220;Roderick the
                    original MSS.&#8221; You &amp; the workman may determine in what manner it should open
                    &amp;c.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> leads me into temptation by
                    saying he has a fancy to go on <hi rend="ital">with</hi> the Register<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Murray was proposing either to take
                        over or continue the failing <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> or to
                        establish a new annual publication. He was sounding out Southey, who had
                        written for the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> from 1810&#8211;1813, as
                        a possible lead contributor. In the end, nothing came of the idea.</note>
                    himself &amp; asking me if I should like it. Now I find it so difficult to go on
                        <hi rend="ital">without</hi> it, that I know not how to answer. For tho, God
                    knows, I am willing enough to be at work, I require sometimes the prospect of a
                    direct remuneration to make me progress working upon a given subject. To express
                    myself more plainly I <del>xx</del> am so much inclination to sacrifice work of
                    profit, to work of reputation which is in other words work of pleasure, that it
                    sometimes useful to have the profit full in sight. On the other hand I am not
                    made of iron, &amp; having but one head &amp; one pair of hands if I take the
                    yoke of a yearly volume again upon my neck there will be very little
                        <del>leis</del> time left for other &amp; <del>greater</del> worthier
                    things. This edition of Roderick will give me from 100 to 120 &#163;: a second
                    edition will produce about as much more, &amp; may probably sell <del>in
                        the</del> in this the first twelvemonths; the book will then settle into a
                    slow &amp; steady sale, &amp; may bring me in regularly some 20 or 30 &#163; &#8211; per
                    year. And this is the extent of the possible profits. I am not discontented at
                    this, believing it <del>is</del> not possible that the same work should produce
                    great immediate profit, &amp; permanent fame. It cannot become popular if it be
                        <del>about the</del> above the pitch of the &#963;&#953;
                        &#964;&#953;&#959;&#955;&#955;&#959;&#953;,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;hoi polloi&#8217;.</note> &#8211; &amp; if it be not, &#8211; it must
                    find its way at last to the family vault.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will write a few lines to <ref target="people.html#RobertsEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                    Roberts</ref>. The book is, to me, very interesting &#8211;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Grosvenor Bedford&#8217;s <title>Letters and
                            Miscellaneous Papers &#8230; With a Memoir of His Life</title> (1814) of his
                        cousin Barr&#233; Charles Roberts, who had died in 1810 aged 21. For Southey&#8217;s
                        review see <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (January 1815),
                        509&#8211;519.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">your Mother &amp; Miss Page</ref> &amp; the <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Mag: Rot:</ref>
          </salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> &amp; God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent6"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> I hope <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>
                        will exhibit the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Docstor</ref> in his next number<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> No review of Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s
                                <title>Observations on Pulmonary Consumption</title> (1814) appeared
                            in the <title>Quarterly</title>.</note>
          </p>
          <p>
            <date when="1814-12-11">11 Dec. 1814.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>