<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2179</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3450</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously  published:
                        John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                        303&#8211;306.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2179" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2179" type="letter">
        <head>2179. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1812-11-18">18 November
                        1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey/ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Helens/ Auckland <lb />Stamped: [partial] KESWICK<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Previously published:
                        John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp.
                        303&#8211;306.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-11-18">Nov. 18. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I give you joy of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHannah">your daughter</ref>, &#8211; but have no joy to give her of
                    her names, which tho both good in themselves made an abominable compound. If my advice were to be taken it would be to toss up for
                    one, &amp; reserve the other for next time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are going on well upon the whole. <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">The Imperial</ref>
                    departed yesterday; today I look to my leathern jerkin, &amp; am now fairly set-to for keeping-house &amp; hard work during the
                    winter. My hair has escaped cutting for the last month, or six weeks, &amp; if I have power enough to save it, shall be reserved
                    for a glib till the spring, <del>Xxx xxx xxx xxx xxxx xxx xxx</del> We never shear sheep in cold weather &amp; why should we shear
                    ourselves?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am writing upon the state of the poor, or rather the populace, for the Quarterly &amp; the first thing to be done
                    is to make an exposure of Malthus.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The political economist Thomas Robert Malthus
                        (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>). His <title>Essay on the Principle of Population</title>, first published in 1798, had gone
                        into four editions by 1807. Southey used a review of Patrick Colquhoun (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Propositions for
                            ameliorating the Condition of the Poor: and For Improving the Moral Habits, and Increasing the Comforts of the Labouring
                            People</title> (1812), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356, as &#8216;an attack upon Malthus&#8217;, amongst
                        others; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 5 January 1813, Letter 2199.</note> Thro this part I shall probably get to night, if
                    the post (which is unusually late) does not bring anything to prevent me. The main object of this article is to probe the wounds
                    of the body politic. We shall soon hear of scarcity again; <del>xx</del> the Luddite system<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Luddites smashed textile machinery that they saw as a threat to their livelihoods. The movement was based in the East
                        Midlands, Lancashire and Yorkshire. Southey expressed his fears in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), esp.
                        348&#8211;349.</note> will then be renewed, &#8211; &amp; these things will become more &amp; more dangerous till some means are adopting
                    for curing the evil, not merely for palliating it. I have a good deal to say upon this subject, &amp; could not have a better
                    place to say it in. Associations for soup-shops &amp;c are mere palliatives, &amp; tho they have their good have their evil also.
                    The immediate desideratum is to supply employment to those who want it, &#8211; national education is the alternative medicine slow in
                    its operation but sure if time can be found for it. Schemes of extensive &amp; liberal colonization are of the same character, but
                    will not be adopted so soon: an extended military establishment might be connected with these, &amp; so connected as to render the
                    country equally secure from within &amp; from without. But there will be no time for any thing, unless that license of the
                    newspaper press is checked, which in its <del>tendency</del> &lt;consequences&gt; is inevitably destructive to the liberty of the
                    press &amp; to every thing also that is valuable in society. Spring will be a trying season. It is now plain that the harvest is
                    rather below the average &amp; ordinary years. There will be no supplies from America, none from the Baltic. Barbary &amp; the
                    Black sea remain, from the latter I think we <del>might</del> ought to expect little or nothing, for Russia will want all its
                    produce for herself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There seems indeed ground of hope in the state of the war. If Russia continue to hold out, &amp; preserves her
                    armies unbroken, she must necessarily triumph at last: &amp; of this event I should have no doubt if Russia were not like the
                    statue in Nebuchadnezzars dream,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Daniel</title> 2: 31&#8211;35. The statue was made up of gold, silver, bronze, iron and clay.</note> made up of such
                    heterogeneous &amp; easily divisible materials. I know not what principle the Cossacks have which should make them fight on one
                    side rather than on the other. They love fighting, &#8211; but if travellers may be trusted, they hate the Russians. However, tho I am
                    not so easily elated with Lord Cathcarts<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Schaw Cathcart (1755&#8211;1843;
                            <title>DNB</title>), army officer and politician. He had taken up the post of Ambassador to the Russian court in July
                        1812. He was actively involved in Russian attempts to resist Bonaparte and sent regular dispatches to the British
                        government.</note> wretched dispatches as the Courier is,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Cathcart&#8217;s dispatches were
                        regularly reported and praised in the <title>Courier</title>; see, for example, <title>Courier</title>, 26 October
                        1812.</note> &amp; as Government appears to be, &#8211; I certainly do think, there is blue sky enough in the North to make a pair
                    of trousers, &amp; there is blue sky in the West, &amp; there is a tempest brooding in France which is also a cause of hope,
                    because till there has been a defeat in that quarter than can be no fair weather.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the Register I am writing the chapter about Ireland, of which the Catholic committee forms the main
                        business.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 115&#8211;139.
                        The Catholic Board was set up in 1811 to campaign for Catholic Emancipation.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The post is just arrived. Two thumping double letters very properly post-paid &amp; containing the Evangelical
                    Application of Thalaba<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The interpretation of <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801)
                        proposed by Southey&#8217;s correspondent <ref target="people.html#LongmireJohnMartyn">Longmire</ref>.</note> &#8211; they may rest
                    quietly with the seal unbroken till I have finished my letter. I like the last Bulletin,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>London Gazette</title>, 11 November 1812 carried a despatch from Cathcart dated 27 October 1812, detailing the French
                        army&#8217;s retreat through Russia.</note> &amp; infer from it that Buonaparte means to retreat to Poland, a movement which must be
                    attended with certain life of reputation, &#8211; &amp; probable loss of half his army. Fine sport for the Cossacks. The Atamans Platows
                    daughter seems <del>xxx</del> to have a fair chance of a husband.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Matvei Ivanovitch
                        Platov (1757&#8211;1818), Ataman (Commander) of the Don Cossacks. He became a Count of the Russian Empire as a reward for harrying
                        the French forces on their retreat from Moscow in late 1812. He had reputedly promised his daughter that he would bring
                        Napoleon Bonaparte back alive.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Times (in Wellesley<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">Marquis Wellesley</ref> and his younger brother <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Wellington</ref>.</note> pay) underrates most grossly the Portugueze force;
                    &amp; lays as much blame as possible to Government &#8211; (blameable enough no doubt as to the state of the engineer department) &#8211;
                    taking especial care to impute no blame to <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">M. Wellington</ref>;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> See the report in <title>The Times</title> , 6 November 1812, which criticised the lack of
                        &#8216;experienced sappers and miners&#8217; at the siege of Burgos, but noted that no blame for this or the conduct of the siege could be
                        laid at the feet of the &#8216;illustrious Hero&#8217; Wellington.</note> whom I &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> all severally blamed (before the event was known)
                    for losing precious time at Burgos.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wellington and his allies had besieged the Spanish
                        city of Burgos from 19 September&#8211;21 October 1812, but failed to capture it. There was no decisive battle in Spain in 1812
                        after the siege was lifted.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> His business should have been to drive the enemy out of the field wherever they were to be found. &#8211; <del>xxx</del>
                    A battle, if he can bring one on, will set all to rights.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretdauTomandSarah">my niece</ref> &amp; God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>