<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2094</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3365</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS
                        Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 334&#8211;338 [in part]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2094" type="letter">
        <head>2094. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1812-05-14">14[&#8211;15] May 1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: [illegible]<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS
                        Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 334&#8211;338 [in part]. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-05-14">May 14. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> In spite of myself I have been weeping, &#8211; this has relieved the throbbings of my head, &#8211; but my mind is overcharged
                    &amp; must pour itself out. I am going to write something upon the state of popular feeling, which <del>must</del> &lt;will
                    probably&gt; appear in the Courier<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s proposed article did not appear in the
                            <title>Courier</title>.</note>
          <del>as the</del> where it will obtain the readiest &amp; widest circulation. Enough to alarm the people I shall be able to say
                        <del>xxxx</del>, but I would fain alarm the Government, &amp; if this were done in public they would think it imprudent, &amp;
                    indeed it would be so. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall probably begin with what you say of the sensation occasioned by this most fatal event,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Prime Minister <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Spencer Perceval</ref> had been shot
                        dead in the lobby of the House of Commons on 11 May 1812. His assassin was John Bellingham (1770&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), a
                        merchant with a grudge against the government.</note> &#8211; &amp; then give the reverse of your account as I have received it from
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>: &#8211; what he <hi rend="ital">heard</hi> in a pot house into
                    which he went on the night of the murder, not more to quench his thirst, than for the purpose of hearing what the <del>xx</del>
                    populace would say. &#8211; Did I not speak to you with ominous truth upon this subject in one of my last hasty <del>xxxxxx</del>
                    letters? This country is upon the brink of the most dreadful of all conceivable states, &#8211; an insurrection of the poor against the
                    rich: &amp; if by some providential infatuation the <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdettites</ref> had not continued to <hi rend="ital">insult</hi> the soldiers, the existing Government would not be worth a weeks purchase, nor any throat which
                        <del>could be</del> could be supposed to be worth cutting, safe for a month longer.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know Grosvenor I am no agueish politician, nor is this a sudden apprehension which has seized me. Look to what
                    I have said of the effect of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Clarkes business upon the public in the last years Register,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1809, Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>) had been
                        forced to resign as commander-in-chief of the British army in the wake of allegations that he had profited from office
                        trafficking. After a lengthy investigation, the charges were found to be unproven. It had, however, become apparent that his
                        former mistress Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) had received money from individuals keen for her to use
                        her influence with the Duke, and that the Duke himself had known of her actions. For Southey&#8217;s account, <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 109&#8211;301.</note> &amp; look to the remarks upon the tendency of manufactures
                    to this state, in Espriella, written five years ago.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Do I then think that England is in
                        danger of revolution? If the manufacturing system continues to be extended, increasing as it necessarily does increase the
                        number, the misery, and the depravity of the poor, I believe that revolution inevitably must come, and in its most fearful
                        shape&#8217;, <title>Letters from England</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), III, p. 133.</note> Things are in that state at this time
                    that nothing but the army preserves us. &#8211; it is the single plank between us &amp; the red sea of an English Jacquerie, &#8211; a Bellum
                        Servile,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. a slave war.</note> not provoked as both those convulsions were by
                    grievous oppression, but prepared by the inevitable tendency of the manufacturing system, &amp; hastened on by <del>a f</del> the
                    folly of a besotted faction, &amp; the wickedness of a few individuals. &#8211; The end of these things is full of evil even upon the
                    happiest termination, &#8211; for the loss of liberty is the penalty which has always been paid for the abuse of it. But we must not now
                    employ our thought upon the danger of our own victory, &#8211; there is but too much yet to be done to render the victory certain.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The first step should be the immediate renewal of associations for the protection of our lives &amp; properties,
                    &amp; of the British Constitution: with the reestablishment to the utmost possible extent of the volunteers,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Part-time home defence forces that had been greatly expanded in 1803 when invasion from France
                        seemed a real possibility.</note> &#8211; as effective a force against a mob of United Englishmen<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> An underground revolutionary society that existed 1796&#8211;1802.</note> &#8211; as they would be inefficient in the
                    first shock of an invasion. This may be safely said &amp; prest upon the <del>people</del> government &amp; the people, what I
                    dare not say publicly is that there is yet danger from the army, &#8211; that cursed flogging for the <del>repeal</del> abolition<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Burdett had consistently pressed for the abolition of flogging in the army since
                        1808.</note> of which <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdett</ref> has been suffered to appear as the advocate! Oh that
                        <ref target="people.html#PercevalSpencer">Perceval</ref> had prevented this popularity, by coming forward himself as the
                    soldiers friend. He has good works enough for his good name, as well as for his soul&#8217;s rest, &#8211; but this would have remained for
                    his colleagues &amp; for the country.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This of course can not be touched upon immediately, for it would be too obviously an act of fear, &#8211; but if I knew
                    the ministers I would urgently press upon them the wisdom of granting some boon to the soldiers, &#8211; something which at little cost
                    to the nation would yet come home to the feelings of every individual in the army. The mere institution of honorary rewards would
                    do this, &#8211; fifty pounds in copper medals would go farther than as many thousands in bounties towards recruiting it hereafter. But
                    I would couple it with something more &#8211; for instance ten or twenty of the oldest men, <del>in</del> or oldest soldiers, in every
                    regiment which <del>xxxx</del> distinguished itself in the two late assaults<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The capture
                        of the towns of Ciudad Rodrigo on 19 January 1812 and Badajoz on 6 April 1812.</note> should have their discharge with full
                    pay for life, &#8211; or an increase of pay if they chose to serve on. Do not think that these things are inefficacious or beneath the
                    notice of statesmen. Why is it that poets move the hearts of men, but because they understand the feelings of men, &amp; it is by
                    their feelings that they may best be governed. Look at the agitators, they address themselves to the passions of the mob; &amp;
                    who does not perceive with what tremendous effect!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wish you would read this to <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> &amp; to <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>, because I am sure that these cheap &amp; easy measures would go far
                    toward winning the affection of the soldiers at these perilous times. Other topics I shall speak of elsewhere. &#8211; the establishment
                    of a <del>paro</del> system of parochial education, &amp; the necessity of colonial schemes as opening an issue in the distempered
                    body politic. This <del>is</del> &lt;will be&gt; for the Quarterly.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Issues covered in
                        Southey&#8217;s review of Patrick Colquhoun (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Propositions for Ameliorating the Condition of
                            the Poor: and For Improving the Moral Habits, and Increasing the Comforts of the Labouring People</title> (1812), in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356.</note> Vigorous measures I trust in God will be taken while
                    the feelings of the sound class are <del>alive</del> in a state to favour them. Were I minister I would prosecute Lord Ossulston
                    for his speech at the dinner,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Augustus Bennet, Lord Ossulston (1776&#8211;1859), Whig
                        politician and heir to the Earldom of Tankerville. At this time he was MP for Knaresborough (1806&#8211;1818). Southey was exercised
                        by his speech at a City of London dinner in favour of parliamentary reform on 9 May 1812.</note> &amp; teach him &amp; his
                    friends that the privilege of exciting rebellion does not extend beyond the walls of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Stephens.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> St Stephen&#8217;s Chapel, in the Palace of Westminster, was the meeting-place of the House of
                        Commons.</note> In this state of feeling any jury nor decidedly Jacobinical, would find <del>agai</del> him guilty. And were I
                    a member of Parliament whenever <ref target="people.html#Burdett">Burdett</ref> rose I would clear the gallery. He should not <hi rend="ital">speak</hi> to the people, &amp; if he <hi rend="ital">wrote</hi> to them it would be at his peril. To this pitch
                    in my judgement things are come. This murder, tho <del>xx</del> committed probably by a madman, has been made the act &amp; deed
                    of the populace. Shocking as this appears, so it is! &amp; so it must be considered. With timely vigour, the innocent blood which
                    has been shed may prove an <del>xx</del> accepted sacrifice &amp; save us, &#8211; otherwise it is but the opening of the flood
                    gates.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thought of poor <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> as soon as I could think of any thing.
                    &#8211; The loss which the country has sustained I <del>xxx</del> scarcely dare to contemplate. There seems nothing to look to but the
                        Wellesleys,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">Marquis Wellesley</ref> and his brother the <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Duke of Wellington</ref>.</note> with <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref>, Huskisson for Chanc. of the Exc.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The politician William Huskisson (1770&#8211;1830; <title>DNB</title>) did not become Chancellor of the Exchequer. He had been
                        Secretary to the Treasury 1807&#8211;1809 but was at this time out of office.</note> &#8211; &amp; in all likelihood Sir James Mackintosh,
                    who is sure to take the strongest side, &#8211; tho <del>xxxx</del> he may now afford to be honest, &amp; his talents will make him a
                    powerful supporter to any party.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> On his return to Britain from India in 1811, the writer
                        and politician Sir James Mackintosh (1765&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>) had been courted by Perceval and the Tories. He was
                        elected to Parliament in 1813 as MP for Nairn and became a leading spokesman for the Whigs.</note> Yet in this train there
                    seems to follow a long catalogue of dangers. Catholic concessions, &amp; next by aid of all the admitted enemies of the Church,
                    the sale of tythes, to supply the necessities of the Government, &#8211; a measure which will be as certainly popular as it will be
                    ultimately ruinous to the Church &amp; most fatal to the country. There will be a glorious war to console us, &#8211; but under such
                    circumstances I shall look to that war with the painful thought that <del>its success</del> &lt;we&gt; may be repaid for our
                    service to the Spaniards by finding <del>a refu</del> an asylum in Spain when England will have lost all that our fathers
                    purchased for us so dearly!</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> Tell <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">G.</ref> I shall be ready for him with the French Biography &#8211;
                        which will be a sketch of the Revolution <del>with</del> &lt;introducing&gt; an examination of our own state as tending toward
                        the same gulph.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> A review of <title>Biographie Moderne: Lives of Remarkable Characters
                                who have Distinguished themselves from the Commencement of the French Revolution to the Present Time</title> (1811),
                                <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (June 1812), 412&#8211;438.</note> &#8211; Would to God it were not so well timed! &#8211; What has
                        past seems like a dream to me &#8211; a sort of night mare that overlays &amp; oppresses my <del>faculties</del> thoughts &amp;
                        feelings. </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Friday. The Courier speaks of <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Abbot</ref> as Ch. of the Exchequer.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had misread an item in the <title>Courier</title>, 14 May 1812. This had noted
                            that there was &#8216;no foundation&#8217; for the report that Abbot had been offered the post of Chancellor of the Exchequer.</note>
                        If the ministry do not feel themselves so weak as to call in the Wellesleys I should think Vansittart<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicholas Vansittart, 1st Baron Bexley (1766&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), Chancellor of the Exchequer
                            1812&#8211;1823.</note> a more likely man. Would the Grand Parleur<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Abbot, the
                            &#8216;Great Speaker&#8217;.</note> take the situation? has he <hi rend="ital">tongue</hi> enough? &#8211; if he has I know where he may
                        find head.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tell G. &#8230; head: written at top of fol 1 r.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>