<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1904</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3175</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian
                        Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1904" type="letter">
        <head>1904. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1811-04-15">15 April 1811</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 18 APR 18/ 1811<lb />MS: Bodleian
                        Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1811-04-15">April 15. 1811</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It surprizes me that Blake<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish general Joaqu&#237;n Blake y Joyes
                        (1759&#8211;1827). He was a member of the 5-man Supreme Council of Regency appointed on 28 October 1810 and was creating a General
                        Staff for the Spanish armies.</note> who must know so well from his own inexperience the wretched state of the Spanish armies
                    should oppose so sure a plan of reestablishing them as that of <del>xxxxxxx xxxxxx</del> &lt;training men&gt; under British
                    officers. This prejudice cannot possibly last long, the Spaniards themselves will cry out against it, &amp; remove him from the
                    Regency. There is one thing which I could wish to see done in Portugal &amp; that is, that as fast as possible, native officers
                    should be made from the ranks, &amp; honours even showered upon those who are of deserving of them. Silveira<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Portuguese general Francisco da Silviera (1763&#8211;1821). He was ennobled as the Count of
                        Amarante in 1811.</note> for instance ought to be ennobled.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I want to hear of more troops going out that <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord
                        Wellington</ref> may not have to wait upon the frontier till Massena<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French
                        Marshal Andr&#233; Massena (1758&#8211;1817), one of the commanders of the invasion of Portugal in 1810.</note> receives reinforcements
                    sufficient for all this to be acted over again. I would have him enabled to continue on the offensive, <del>&amp;</del> recover
                    Almeida &amp; Cuidad Rodrigo,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish cities of Almeida and Ciudad Rodrigo had been
                        captured by the French in summer 1810. Ciudad Rodrigo was recaptured by the allies in January 1812.</note> &amp; put this army
                    at least whose <hi rend="ital">morals</hi> are in such a shatterd state completely <hi rend="ital">hors de combat</hi>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. &#8216;out of action&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have not seen the <hi rend="ital">Goggery</hi> upon Kehama, &#8211; nothing that comes from that Micromegas is to be
                    called criticism, so there you have a new word for it fresh from the mint.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Francis Jeffrey&#8217;s</ref> appraisal of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810),
                            <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 17 (February 1811), 429&#8211;465. Gog and Micromegas are swipes at Jeffrey&#8217;s lack of
                        height.</note> As for <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> he will never do any thing that he ought to do, either for himself or for any body else.
                    Perfectly unoccupied as he is, &amp; with a daily paper<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The London newspaper the
                            <title>Courier</title>, for which Coleridge was working.</note> completely at his command, he might have extinguished <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Gog</ref> long ago, &amp; ought to have done it. If you think <del>thi</del> Goggery is
                    worth answering, I would not wish it in better hands than yours, &#8211; but I doubt whether any answer would be useful, &#8211; those who can
                    listen to such doctrines as the Ed. Review promulgates upon points of taste, are in a state of moral &amp; intellectual blindness
                    &lt;of which&gt; no operator can cure them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When you speak of the existing Spanish armies you do not include those in Catalonia &amp; Valencia. The Catalans
                    have done their duty most nobly. It is unaccountable why we should so totally have neglected them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> About the flower seeds you need do no more than walk into a seedsmans &amp; ask for what you want, &#8211; adding if you
                    please the Persicaria to the list, &#8211; they may come in <del>edi</del> eodem franko<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;in the
                        same place, franked&#8217;.</note> with the other half-notes,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. half-banknotes &#8211; a secure
                        way of sending money in the post, by tearing banknotes in half and sending the two halves separately.</note> &#8211; for the season
                    for sowing is passing by. I doubt the possibility of bringing the blue thistle to town, it has a large tap root, &#8211; &amp; we shall
                    a week on the road if we make first for London, &#8211; three if we go round by Bristol instead of returning by it, &#8211; points as yet
                    undecided.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The stags-horn nap I have not forgotten, as yet it has hardly shown its nose I believe. The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Moon</ref> &amp; the Moons Father will ascend Latrigg &amp; see. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 400 pages of the Register<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title> (1811).</note> are printed, &amp; I send off as much copy to night as will
                    carry it on to 500. Hei mihi<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Woe is me&#8217;.</note> there yet remains a world of work to do!
                    &#8211; I am only sorry for this because it confines me longer here than is convenient for my intended movements. We cannot start before
                    the last week in May.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You are often enquired for here by your town acquaintance, the <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Doctor</ref>,
                    the Crosthwaites<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly the family of Peter Crosthwaite (1735&#8211;1808), a retired naval
                        commander, publisher of maps and inventor of the aeolian harp. In the 1780s he established the first museum in Keswick. Its
                        treasures included a set of musical stones, a stuffed albatross and a pig with no legs. By 1811 the Museum was run by his son
                        Daniel (c. 1776&#8211;1847), a portrait painter.</note> &amp; John Cockbaine,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Cockbain
                        (dates unknown), a tailor in Keswick.</note> &#8211; who &#8211; be it known to you, has this day received orders for the pantaloons in
                    which I am to travel to town.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211; I must go to work upon a whole pile of Spanish papers. &#8211; You will wonder to see what a chapter I
                    have made upon Turkey, Slavonic politics &amp; Czerni George.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Karageorge Petrovitch
                        [Czerni George; Black George] (1768&#8211;1817), one of the leaders of the first Serbian uprising against Ottoman rule; see the
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 446&#8211;469.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Continue to send me good accounts of yourself, &amp; to defy all prophets of ill. I rejoice to hear of the claret,
                    &#8211; &amp; should rejoice still more to partake of it. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Vive vale que<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Live and be well&#8217;.</note>
          </salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>