<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2196</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3467</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2196" type="letter">
        <head>2196. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1813-01-03">3 January 1813</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 6 JA 6/ 1813<lb />Endorsement: 3
                            Jan<hi rend="sup">ry</hi> 1813<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> When you have some charr sent how many will you please to have? one dozen, a dozen &amp;
                    half, or two dozen?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi> When you send me some money, quod quanto citius, tanto acceptius,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;so much and as speedily as is agreeable to you.&#8217;</note> &#8211; it will be very convenient to have as much of it as
                    may be sent in bills of five pounds &amp; under; &#8211; for we are in bodily fear of this vile country currency, &amp; grievously
                    inconvenienced by the last failure, which leaves this place without any thing in the character of a banker.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 3<hi rend="sup">dly</hi> Can you vi&#226; Primi Domini,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;First Lord&#8217; i.e.
                        via the First Lord of the Admiralty, at this time, Robert Saunders Dundas, 2nd Viscount Melville (1771&#8211;1851;
                            <title>DNB</title>), First Lord of the Admiralty 1812&#8211;1827.</note> procure for <del>the</del> me the names of the
                    Midshipmen who fell on board Nelsons ship in the battle of Trafalgar. There is a curious fact connected with one of them, about
                    the man who killed Nelson; &amp; neither <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> nor I can recollect his name, but we
                    should recognize it.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Frenchman who shot Horatio Nelson, 1st Viscount Nelson
                        (1758&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>) during the battle of Trafalgar. For Southey&#8217;s account of Nelson&#8217;s fatal wound, see<title> The
                            Life of Nelson</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813), II, pp. 257&#8211;258. Southey recounted that the French sniper was in turn shot
                        dead by two midshipmen in HMS <hi rend="ital">Victory</hi>, Francis Edward Collingwood (1785&#8211;1835) and John Pollard (d. 1868);
                        see <title>The Life of Nelson</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813), II, pp. 264&#8211;265.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By some strange miscalculation which lies between <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> &amp; the
                        Printer,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Moyes (d. 1839), of Greville St, Hatton Garden, London.</note> my life
                    of Nelson makes two volumes instead of one, &#8211; a blunder which will be very detrimental to its success, &amp; may very probably
                    ruin it. For speculating upon one volume I dare say <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has struck off a much larger
                    edition than is likely to go off at a double price, as a library book, instead of a midshipmans manual. It <del>costs</del> will
                    cost me about a weeks additional work to ballast the volumes. I am just now finishing the battle of Copenhagen, which by help of
                    the Danish account<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andreas Andersen Feldborg (1782&#8211;1838), <title>A Tour in Zealand, the
                            Year 1802; with an Historical Sketch of the Battle of Copenhagen</title> (1805).</note> &amp; of some valuable
                    circumstances gleaned from original sources, (<ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom had served in HMS <hi rend="ital">Bellona</hi> at Copenhagen. Amongst the information he supplied was the
                        fact that seventy-five of his fellow crew had been killed when their elderly cannon burst; see <title>The Life of
                            Nelson</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813), II, p. 126.</note> Ponsonby,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lieutenant
                        John Ponsonby (dates unknown), who was in 1813 living at Ormathwaite, near Keswick.</note> &amp; Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        Quilliam,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Quilliam (1771&#8211;1829), First Lieutenant on HMS <hi rend="ital">Amazon</hi> and later on HMS <hi rend="ital">Victory</hi>.</note> who was Rious<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Edward Riou (1762&#8211;1801; <title>DNB</title>), Captain of HMS <hi rend="ital">Amazon</hi>. He was killed at the Battle of
                        Copenhagen.</note> Lieutenant that day) is made an impressive narrative. I have also some original Trafalgariana.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Material relating to the Battle of Trafalgar (1805).</note> The blunder about the form of the
                    book is exceedingly unlucky, as under favourable circumstances I really think it would have answerd <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> expectations. I have taken infinite pains with it, &amp; made a much better book
                    than he had any reason to look for.</p>
        <p rend="indent3"> _____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A happy new year to you, &amp; plenty of them!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I spent two days of the Xmas week under the Doctors hands, which is not the pleasantest way of spending them. At
                    dinner one day I was without the slightest previous ailment, seized with so sudden a sickness that I could scarcely make my way
                    upstairs before half my dinner which I had made was unmade. There was no nausea or sense of sickness of any kind, &#8211; nor can I in
                    any way account for it. It began with an unusual sensation in the abdomen which if you can understand such a phrase, was as it
                    were reflected by another in the head; this latter however was what I have been accustomed to for years, &#8211; a <del>sudden</del>
                    sense of sudden apprehension, such as a person feels when startled <del>from</del> as he is falling to sleep, <del>&amp; x</del>
                    it began with me <del>in my xx</del> in 1799: &amp; before I went to Lisbon alarmed me much. But since that time tho it has never
                    entirely left me <del>I have</del> it has been unfrequent, &amp; when it does recur, more easily by a mental effort represt, for
                    it is no doubt nervous.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was very unwell the remainder of the day, &amp; annoyed with a sense of fullness in the abdomen. Some swinging
                    doses of rhubarb I hope have set me to rights, &amp; as soon as this part of the process is over, I shall delight the great <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Doctoress</ref> by going thro a course of her tonics.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tell <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> that I have been thus indisposed, &#8211; as the reason why
                    he has not had the conclusion of my article on the poor.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of Patrick
                        Colquhoun (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Propositions for ameliorating the Condition of the Poor: and For Improving
                            the Moral Habits, and Increasing the Comforts of the Labouring People</title> (1812), appeared in the <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will look over your MS.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The MS of Bedford&#8217;s <title>Letters and
                            Miscellaneous Papers by Barr&#233; Charles Roberts</title> (1814).</note> with all due care whenever it arrives. But even
                    before I see them my advice would be not to <del>publish</del> publish the book; &#8211; because if it were to be received with neglect
                        <ref target="people.html#RobertsBarreCharles">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Roberts</ref> would probably feel <del>a kind</del>
                    &lt;some degree&gt; of pain, <del>which</del> &amp; that it would be so received is most likely, not so much from the reason which
                    you so well state, <del>but</del> as from the doctrine of chances in the lottery of publication, &#8211; for a lottery it is. Had <ref target="people.html#RobertsBarreCharles">Barr&#233;</ref> been a Methodist the book would have been sure of popularity. As it is,
                    private circulation by ensuring a certain value to the book ensures it also a certain reputation. It will be more <del>xxx</del>
                    sought after, ten to one, &amp; more talked of than if it were published. &#8211; &amp; no disappointment is risqued. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1813-01-03">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 3. 1813.</date>
          </dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>