<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2442</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3713</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS
                        226.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 78&#8211;80 [in part; dated 16 June 1814].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2442" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2442" type="letter">
        <head>2442. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1814-06-15">15 June
                        1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: RS./ 15 June 1814<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS
                        226<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 78&#8211;80 [in part; dated 16 June 1814].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-06-15">
              <del>July</del> &lt;June&gt; 15. 1814</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It came into my head that it might peradventure be a fit thing for the P. L. to write certain verses upon the Peace
                    &amp; the Personages who are now dragging all London after their horses heels. I was very well inclined to put this thought out of
                    my head, if some of the very few persons whom I see here had not shown me by their enquiries that it would come into other heads
                    as well as mine. The subjects for their kind were the best possible, &#8211; so I fell to in good earnest, &amp; have written three odes
                    in Thalaban verse.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. in the verse form used in <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>
                        (1801). The three odes were to George, Prince Regent (1762&#8211;1830; Prince Regent 1811&#8211;1820; King of the United Kingdom
                        1820&#8211;1830; <title>DNB</title>); Alexander I (1777&#8211;1825; Emperor of Russia 1801&#8211;1825); Frederick William III (1770&#8211;1840; King
                        of Prussia 1797&#8211;1840). They were published in book form as <title>Congratulatory Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness The Prince
                            Regent, His Imperial Majesty The Emperor of Russia, and His Majesty the King of Prussia</title> (1814).</note> The
                        Carmen<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (1814).</note> was an oration in rhyme. These are odes without rhyme, &#8211; but in manner &amp;
                    matter altogether lyric. I shall have no time even to correct the press: &#8211; this packet for Bedford contains an insertion of a few
                    lines for one of them, which I hope will not be too late.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford, 15 June [1814], Letter 2441.</note> On Monday or Tuesday, a copy I hope will be duly delivered at your door. &#8211; I have
                    written to Croker<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to John Wilson Croker, 14 June 1814, Letter 2440.</note>
                    saying that it may be proper to present copies to the persons be&#246;ded (you will remember analogous verbs <del>ap</del> as applied
                    to Ditton &amp; wicked Will Whiston<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jonathan Swift (1667&#8211;1745; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;Ode
                        for Musick&#8217; (1715), lines 5&#8211;8: &#8216;So Ditton and Whiston/ May both be be-pst on; / And Whiston and Ditton/ May both be besh-t
                        on&#8217;; referring to Humphry Ditton (1675&#8211;1715; <title>DNB</title>) and William Whiston (1667&#8211;1752; <title>DNB</title>),
                        mathematicians who produced an impractical solution to the problem of determining longitude at sea.</note>) &#8211; or that such a
                    presentation might be improper, &amp; that in my ignorance of such things I requested him to act for me. Copies should be sent to
                    him, &amp; I relied upon him to dispose of them as he should judge fitting. This was said in proper phrase, &amp; I dare say he
                    will have no objection to the commission.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am in some trouble about my good correspondent <ref target="people.html#AbellaManuel">D Manuel Abella</ref>. A
                    man of letters, &amp; a staunch friend of the old Cortes, tho no admirer of the head-over-heels activity of the new ones,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. of the old form of Cortes that had existed in Castile, Aragon, Catalonia, Valencia and
                        Navarre, consisting of three estates of clergy, nobles and cities; rather than the new Cortes elected in 1810, which
                        represented all of Spain (and some of the colonies) and sat as one chamber.</note> I think he is in some danger of coming
                    under a proscription which seems to make little distinction of persons. That Ferdinand &amp; the Constitution could long coexist
                    was not possible; &#8211; the King was a mere log, &amp; must soon have been treated as such.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain, 1808, 1813&#8211;1833) abolished the liberal Constitution of 1812 on 4 May 1814 and
                        imprisoned leading liberals on 10 May. He promised to call a traditional Cortes of three estates, but never did so and ruled
                        absolutely.</note> But he has gone vilely to work, &amp; tho I will not condemn him in toto till it be seen what sort of
                    constitution he means to give to the people (<hi rend="ital">encore un constitution!</hi>) I very much fear that the old system of
                    favouritism will return, &amp; that abominations of every kind will be restored as well as the Inquisition;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ferdinand VII also restored the Inquisition in 1814. It was permanently abolished in 1834.</note>
                    &#8211; which blessed Office you see has been reestablished in compliance with the popular cry as a boon! Was it not old Frederic who
                    upon some theological dispute about Purgatory &amp; Hell, said he gave free liberty to all his subjects to be damned eternally who
                    liked it?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frederick II, &#8216;the Great&#8217; (1712&#8211;1786; King of Prussia 1740&#8211;1786). On receiving a
                        plea to suspend a clergyman who did not believe in the eternal damnation of souls, he was said to have replied, &#8216;I have
                        considered the petition, and do hereby give my royal permission to all my loyal subjects to be damned to all eternity, if they
                        choose it; but I do positively forbid their quarrelling with their neighbours, who are not willing to keep their company so
                        long.&#8217;</note> This gracious permission could do no harm, &#8211; but a nation cannot quite <del>xx</del> so innocently be indulged
                    with a Holy Office.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> An officer of Suchets army, who served at the siege of Tarragona,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        siege of Tarragona, 5 May-29 June 1811, after which a large French force finally captured the port from a Spanish Army.</note>
                    &amp; was afterwards taken by Eroles,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joaquin Cuevas Ibanez y de Valonga, Baron de Eroles
                        (1784&#8211;1825), leader of a guerrilla army called &#8216;the Army of the Faithful&#8217; in Catalonia.</note> was brought here last week by
                        <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, to whom he had letters of recommendation from France. A young
                    man, &amp; apparently one of the best of the Frenchmen.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French officer was Eustace
                        Baudouin (b. c. 1792). He served in the army of Louis Gabriel Suchet, 1st Duc d&#8217;Albufera (1770&#8211;1826), Marshal of France, saw
                        action at the first siege of Tarragona, 1811 and in the same year was captured by Eroles. Baudouin spent time in Britain as a
                        prisoner of war, and at one point was held at Oswestry, in Shropshire. On his release, he visited the Wordsworths before
                        returning to France. Baudouin had made contact with Wordsworth in 1812 via mutual acquaintances: his brother was engaged to
                        Caroline (1792&#8211;1862), daughter of Wordsworth and Annette Vallon (1766&#8211;1841). Caroline and Jean Baptiste Baudouin (b. c. 1780)
                        married in February 1816. Southey travelled to France and visited them and their infant daughter in 1817, when he also renewed
                        his acquaintance with Eustace Baudouin; see Southey to Edith Southey, 17 May 1817.</note> He had grace enough to acknowledge
                    that the Spanish business was an unjust war &#8211; which he said all the officers knew, &amp; he amused me by complaining that the
                    Spaniards were very hard-hearted: to which I replied that they had not invited him &amp; his countrymen. He said &#8220;they did make
                    beautiful defence&#8221; &#8211; &amp; I gathered from him some information upon points of consequence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Two or three weeks will compleat my long poem,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> &amp; I am longing then to have my Brazil in the press<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second volume of the <title>History of Brazil</title>, published in 1817.</note> &#8211; the
                    next main work. &#8211; What will you &lt;do&gt; with this mischievous Princess?<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Either a
                        reference to the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince Regent&#8217;s</ref> only child Charlotte Augusta (1796&#8211;1817;
                            <title>DNB</title>), who had broken off her engagement to the Hereditary Prince of Orange, William (1792&#8211;1849; King of the
                        Netherlands 1840&#8211;1849), the husband selected for her by her father and his advisers. In his official capacity as Poet
                        Laureate, Southey had been planning a poem on the marriage; or, to Charlotte&#8217;s mother, Princess Caroline of
                        Brunswick-Wolfenbuttel (1768&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have sent to the Courier a doggrel march to Moscow<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The &#8216;March to Moscow&#8217;
                        appeared in the <title>Courier</title>, 23 June 1814.</note> written months ago to amuse the children, &amp; chiefly upon the
                    provocation of one irresistible rhyme, &#8211; which is <hi rend="ital">not</hi> to be printed. I give you the supprest stanza, for I am
                    sure if you happen to see the song, you will <del>cry</del> wonder how such a hit should have been mist</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="center"> The Emperor Nap he talked so loud</l>
          <l rend="center"> That he frightened <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Roscoe</ref>, &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="center"> John Bull he cries, if you&#8217;ll be wise</l>
          <l rend="center"> Ask the Emperor Nap if he will please</l>
          <l rend="center"> To grant you peace upon your knees,</l>
          <l rend="center"> Because he&#8217;s going to Moscow!</l>
          <l rend="center"> He&#8217;ll make all the Poles come out of their holes.</l>
          <l rend="center"> And eat the Prussians &amp; beat the Russians &#8211; </l>
          <l rend="center"> The fields are green, &amp; the sky is blue</l>
          <l rend="center"> Morbleu! Parbleu!</l>
          <l rend="center"> He&#8217;ll certainly get to Moscow!</l>
        </lg>
        <p>There is some &lt;good&gt; doggrel in the rest, &amp; Morbleu &amp;c &#8211; is the <del>choru</del> burthen of the song.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs most truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> Is there no chance of your visiting your &#8216;roads &amp; bridges&#8217;<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rickman
                            was Secretary to the Parliamentary Commission, set up in 1803, on the making of roads and bridges in Scotland.</note> this
                        summer, &amp; leaving <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref> here on your way?</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>