<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1894</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3165</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1894" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1894" type="letter">
        <head>1894. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1811-03-31">31 March
                        1811</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ Durham<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1811-03-31">March 31. 1811.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I begin to wonder at not hearing from you. The first three or four pages of the Basque Roads business came here
                    last week &amp; I kept it some days expecting your comments, till I concluded that you had found nothing to correct.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Battle of the Basque Roads, April 1809, had generated considerable public controversy.
                        Although they achieved some success, the British fleet failed to destroy the French navy completely. Captain Thomas Cochrane,
                        later 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), who had led a highly effective fireship attack at the start of
                        the battle, accused his commanding officer, the evangelical Admiral James Gambier, Baron Gambier (1756&#8211;1833;
                            <title>DNB</title>), of being reluctant to pursue the attack and thus achieve a complete victory. Cochrane was also an MP
                        with a reputation for exposing abuses of office, and, in the weeks after the battle, he pursued his campaign against Gambier
                        via parliamentary speeches. Gambier demanded a court-martial at which he was exonerated and, by implication, Cochrane was
                        convicted of libelling a superior officer. Whilst Gambier received public thanks from parliament for his actions in the
                        battle, Cochrane was not permitted to rejoin his ship for a few months. When he received new orders to serve in the
                        Meditteranean, Cochrane refused and went on half-pay, devoting his time to exposing abuses in the Admiralty. For Southey&#8217;s
                        account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 364&#8211;379. Southey had requested that the proofs of his
                        discussion of the Battle of the Basque Roads be sent to Tom Southey; see Southey to John Rickman, 4 March 1811, Letter
                        1879.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Still we have a sick house. All the last week <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> was suffering
                    from a somewhat severe attack of bile. Yesterday she began to amend, &#8211; &amp; yesterday <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> sickened with a sore throat &amp; fever, for which he is now being gargled, &amp; dosed with bark &amp; port
                    wine. It is the worst throat we have ever had among us in any of these attacks, &#8211; tho he seems to suffer nothing in his feelings
                    except loss of appetite. The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">young one</ref> had just recovered from a long &amp; wearying
                    ailment when <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> was taken ill, &amp; so we have been going on with little
                    intermission, ever since you left us. Thank God without any serious evil thus far, &amp; so I hope it will prove at last, &#8211; but
                    with a great deal if disquietude, which is to me the most expensive of all things, because it keeps me idle. Let me know when I
                    shall draw upon <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn ">Ballantyne</ref>, &#8211; merely because I do not wish to do it sooner than it
                    is wanted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wanted something to exhilerate me last week, &amp; the newspapers brought it. What a fine thing was that of
                        Graham&#8217;s!<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Major-General Thomas Graham (1748&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), had played a
                        crucial part in the victory of an Anglo-Spanish force at Barrosa on 5 March 1811.</note> Lapena&#8217;s misconduct<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> General Manuel La Pena (fl. 1808&#8211;1811), commander of the Spanish forces, notably failed to
                        support Graham at the battle of Barrosa.</note> will put the Spaniards upon their mettle &amp; from the spirit which
                        Zayas<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish commander Jos&#233; Pascual de Zayas y Chac&#243;n (1772 &#8211; 1827), famed for
                        his skill and daring.</note> has shown, &amp; Blake&#8217;s<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish general Joaquin
                        Blake y Joyes (1759&#8211;1827).</note> well known talents I have great hopes of great news from that quarter. It will do good too
                    in <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Wellingtons</ref> army, &amp; if he can but bring Massena<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andr&#233; Massena (1758&#8211;1817), French general. His retreat from Portugal into Spain began on 13 March
                        1811.</note> to action we are as sure of a thumping thumping victory as the devil is of Sir James Mackintosh.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The writer and politician Sir James Mackintosh (1765&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>).</note> That is to
                    say cock sure. There has never before been such strong reason for hope. A victory now <del>xx</del> will have the effect of
                    clearing the south of Spain, &amp; once more <del>xxxxxx x</del> driving the French to the Ebro. Oh Tom when Grahams boys began to
                    administer the bayonet what parbleuing &amp; morbleuing &amp; sacrebleuing &amp; ventrebleuing &lt;there must have been!&gt;, to
                    say nothing of diabling &amp; those <del>xxxxxx</del> other exclamations which ought to make the <hi rend="ital">ninth</hi>
                    unclean part of speech in a Frenchmans grammar. When Major Gough<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> At the Battle of Barrosa
                        on 5 March 1811, Hugh Gough, 1st Viscount Gough (1779&#8211;1869; <title>DNB</title>), Lieutenant-Colonel of the Prince of Wales&#8217;s
                        87th Irish Regiment, led a famous charge of the French 8th Light Infantry. It produced the first capture of a French Imperial
                        Eagle during the Peninsular War.</note> swept the Colonels head off at one stroke it must have been a fine sight to have seen
                    the grimaces of all the Frenchman near, &#8211; it might then have been ascertained to a nicety how <del>xxx</del> far the eyebrows can
                    fly up, &amp; to what dimensions a mouth is capable of being opened.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> has my <del>xxxx</del> permission to chide me as much as she pleases for this
                    bloody-mindedness, provided she holds herself ready to make me the amende honorable after she shall have read the Register for
                        1809.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title> (1811).</note> if upon reading it she becomes &lt;as&gt; bloody minded
                    herself &#8211; which I fully expect her to do.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am behind hand with this &amp; begin to fear that my visit to London must be postponed till autumn. Here is March
                    at an end &amp; I have not less than 150 pages yet to <del>xx</del> write! Such is the unmerciful business of the year. Had it
                    been no longer than the last &#8211; my work would have been ended a month ago.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">Mary</ref> &#8211; tell us how the young one comes on. &#8211; I have
                    some little reason to hope that something may be done for you thro <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, &#8211; at least you
                    have friends at work in that direction.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent4"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent6"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>