<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2066</idno><idno type="nines">rce3337</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Beinecke Library, GEN MSS 298, Series I, Box 1, folder 21.  Previously 
                        published: John Holland and James Everett, Memoirs of the Life and Writings of James Montgomery, 7 vols
                        (London, 1854–1856), II, pp. 332–335 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2066" type="letter"><head>2066. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">James Montgomery</ref>, <date when="1812-03-26">26 March
                        1812</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> James Montgomery/
                        Sheffield.<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>MS: Beinecke Library, GEN MSS 298, Series I, Box 1, folder 21<lb/>Previously
                        published: John Holland and James Everett, <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of James Montgomery</title>, 7 vols
                        (London, 1854–1856), II, pp. 332–335 [in part].</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Montgomery</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> So we have lost Vanderkemp.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Dutch missionary Johannes Theodorus van der
                        Kemp (1747–1811; <title>DNB</title>). In 1799 he had led the first mission of the London Missionary Society to South Africa,
                        and worked extensively with indigenous populations, including the Khosa, who nicknamed him Jank’hanna (‘the bald man’). A
                        controversial activist, he argued that native African converts (not their white peers) were the true Christians. He died in
                        Cape Town of a fever on 18 December 1811.</note> I am far from sympathizing with the Directors of the Missionary Society in
                    all their opinions &amp; feelings, – but I feel the whole heroism of such a man as much as they can do, – &amp; would to God that
                    statesmen could see the importance of such men as clearly as I do. That souls which have never heard of redemption may
                    nevertheless be saved I certainly believe, &amp; God forbid that I should ever blaspheme him by thinking otherwise, but I am
                    equally certain that savage &amp; barbarous nations can be reclaimed by nothing but Christianity. In thinking of the merits of a
                    missionary therefore I never consider his creed, – a martyr in Japan is to me not less an object of admiration than a martyr in
                        Smithfield,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Japan was the site of a widespread persecution of Catholics in the late
                        sixteenth and early seventeenth centuries; Smithfield market in London was the execution site of many Protestant martyrs under
                        Mary I (1516–1558; Queen of England 1553–1558).</note> tho I do not owe him the same gratitude; – I could kiss the ground upon
                    which Xavier<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis Xavier (1506–1552), missionary and co-founder of the Society of
                        Jesus. He was an important figure in the spread of Catholicism in India, Japan, Borneo and the Moluccas.</note> or
                        Nobrega<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manuel de Nóbrega (1517–1579), Portuguese missionary and first Provincial of
                        the Society of Jesus in Brazil. He was a key figure in the history of early colonial Brazil.</note> have trod as zealously as
                    the most bigotted Jesuit; I hold Egede<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hans Egede (1686–1758), Danish-Norwegian missionary
                        to the Inuit of Greenland. He was a Lutheran and the first Bishop of Greenland 1741–1758, but co-operated with Moravian
                        missionaries who founded a settlement in Greenland in 1733.</note> in as much veneration as if I were a Moravian, &amp; could
                    not take a deeper interest in the proceedings of the society at Serampore<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Baptist
                        mission at Serampore, India. Co-founded by William Carey (1761–1834; <title>DNB</title>), Joshua Marshman (1768–1837) and
                        William Ward (1769–1823).</note> if I <hi rend="ital">had</hi> been dipped in Andrew Fullers baptistery.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Baptist minister and theologian Andrew Fuller (1754–1815; <title>DNB</title>). In 1792 he
                        became secretary to the newly-founded Baptist Missionary Society. His writings included <title>Apology for the Late Christian
                            Missions to India</title> (1807).</note> This is not from indifferentism, – it is because one principle is common to all
                    these men &amp; that principle is the light &amp; life of the world. God knows I am no indifferentist<del>e</del>. I am for tests
                    &amp; establishments, &amp; would rather see our own Church revoke some of <del>its</del> &lt;her&gt; concessions than yield a
                    foot more, either to Popery over which she has triumphed, or to Puritanism which by a coalition as monstrous as any of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fox’s,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The politician Charles James Fox (1749–1806;
                            <title>DNB</title>) who was Foreign Secretary in the coalition governments of 1783 and 1806–1807.</note> is at this time
                    leagued with Popery &lt;Infidelity&gt; &amp; misbelief of every kind, in the hope of pulling her down.</p><p rend="indent1"> Vanderkemp was in many respects the most interesting character among all the Missionaries. The state of his mind
                    before his conversion shows a heart <del>xx</del> perpetually <del>against</del> struggling against the doubts which perplexed his
                    faith, &amp; the sophisms in which he had bewildered his understanding. His conversion manifestly took place in a moment of
                    delirium, produced by the dreadful calamity which had befallen him, – but never was there a happier delusion. It led him to the
                    only source of comfort, &amp; the impression continued thro life. I am not surprized at finding him venture to use his interest
                    with Heaven to procure rain for the Caffirs, – it rather surprizes &lt;me&gt; that under such an impression he did not attempt to
                    work more miracles, &amp; as the Catholic Missionaries in many instances undoubtedly have done, – actually work them.</p><p rend="indent1"> This leads me to ask you if it be possible to purchase the two first old volumes of the Moravian Periodical
                        Accounts<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Periodical Accounts</title> of Moravian missionary activity,
                        published quarterly from 1790.</note> in your part of the country, where they have their headquarters, – for I am very
                    desirous of possessing them. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> La Trobes<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Moravian minister and
                        composer Christian Ignatius Latrobe (1758–1836; <title>DNB</title>). Born into the Moravian community at Fulneck, Yorkshire,
                        he was educated in Germany and returned to England in 1784. From 1787–1834 he was secretary to the Moravian Brethren’s Society
                        for the Furtherance of the Gospel to the Heathen. In 1790 he initiated the influential <title>Periodical Accounts</title> of
                        Moravian missions and in 1795 became secretary of the international Moravian church in Britain. He moved in
                        interdenominational evangelical circles and was much sought after by founders of new missionary societies.</note> copy was
                    borrowed for me once, but it is a book which I want to have at hand. Whenever time will permit me I purpose giving a view of all
                    the existing Missions in the Quarterly, showing the policy as well as duty of these efforts.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> This was not written.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Thank you for your comments on Kehama.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Hindu romance <title>The Curse
                            of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> The best reply I can make to what you say of the line Never should she behold her father
                    more, – is to say that it is altered upon your suggestion. You say Kailyal <hi rend="ital">is</hi> a Xtian, – is it not because
                    the poem, supposing the truth of the mythology on which it is built, requires from her faith &amp; resignation? – I know not how
                    it was that in my youth the mythologies &amp; superstitions of various nations laid strong hold on my imagination &amp; struck
                    deep in it, so that before I was twenty one of my numerous plans was that of exhibiting the most striking features of each in a
                    long poem. Thalaba<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Islamic romance <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>
                        (1801).</note> &amp; Kehama are the fruits of that early plan, – Madoc<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Madoc</title> (1805), which dealt with, amongst other things, Aztecan civilisation.</note> partakes of it, but only
                    incidentally. If I had gained money as well as reputation by these poems, the whole series would ere this have been compleated. Do
                    not misunderstand me, when I talk of gaining money, nothing more is meant than supporting myself by my labours, – &amp; the
                    literal truth &lt;is&gt; that for many years I did not write a line of poetry <del>bef</del> because I could not afford it. Kehama
                    was written before breakfast in hours borrowed from sleep, &amp; so is Pelayo<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The early
                        name for <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> as far as it has yet proceeded: The world is
                    brightening upon me now. I get well paid for prose, &amp; yet even <del>the</del> in this the capricious humour of the times is
                    apparent. Some of the best years of my life have been devoted to the history of Portugal &amp; its dependencies, in a series of
                    works, of which only one volume is as yet before the public,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first volume of the
                            <title>History of Brazil</title>, published in 1810. Southey’s long-planned ‘History of Portugal’ was never
                        completed.</note> but upon which as much laborious &amp; scrupulous research has been bestowed as ever was, or will be, given
                    to any historical compilation. These works will scarcely while I live, pay for their own materials, – whereas I might be employed
                    if I chose from morning till night in reviewing the <del>p</del> productions of Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Tag, Rag &amp; Bobtail,
                    at ten guineas per sheet.</p><p rend="indent1"> From the age of eight my heart was <del>fixed</del> &lt;set&gt; upon poetry, – a passion owing in the first
                    instance to Shakespere, &amp; which would have taken a dramatic turn, if it had not soon been diverted by our execrable modern
                    versions of Tasso &amp; Ariosto,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Hoole (1727–1803; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Jerusalem Delivered</title> (1763) and <title>Orlando Furioso</title> (1783); versions of Torquato Tasso
                        (1544–1595), <title>La Gerusalemme Liberata</title> (1580) and Ludovico Ariosto (1474–1533), <title>Orlando Furioso</title>
                        (1516).</note> &amp; then fixt by Spenser,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund Spenser (1552?-1599;
                            <title>DNB</title>), whose <title>Faerie Queene</title> (1590–1596) was a particular influence on Southey.</note> for whom
                    I have as entire a love as you can have, – &amp; if you had not loved him as I do, you would not have spoken of Una. No writer has
                    ever given me such hours &amp; days of intense delight as Spenser. Before I was fifteen I had resolved to finish the Faery Queen,
                    – three cantos of the intended continuation was part of a huge pile which some years ago I committed to the flames. I rather
                    regret that the memoranda for this notable undertaking were destroyed also, for young as I was, they were a good deal in the
                    spirit of Spenser, &amp; I had in the course of repeated perusals gathered together every hint which can be found throughout the
                    whole six books, that affords the least intimation of what the author designed to do in the other half. Nothing which I have done
                    ever gave me so much delight as the dream of what I intended to do. I lived in Faery Land with Timias, &amp; Belphœbe, &amp;
                    Prince Arthur, &amp; the Salvage Man, &amp; young Tristram, &amp; Sir Sophy, &amp; Arthegal who won Achilles’ arms. Time has
                    produced little change in my feelings of poetry, – but it has left me little feeling to spare for it. I have learnt to prefer that
                    calmer pleasure which is to be found in historical pursuits, – which seldom excites any passion, but when it does excites it with
                    all the impressiveness of truth. My expectations are as ardent respecting the History of Portugal as ever they were about Joan of
                        Arc,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s controversial epic <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796).</note> &amp;
                    upon better grounds. Then the creatures of my own imagination delighted &amp; deceived me; as an historian I may be deceived
                    concerning my <del>p</del> own powers, but knowing what the duties of an historian are those duties I know that I have
                    performed.</p><p rend="indent1"> Dear Montgomery you say you write of nothing but yourself, – only look back upon the great <del>xx</del> I’s which
                    I have sent you in return! – I have always said that we English are the honestest people in the world, because we are the only
                    people who <del>always</del> write that important word always with a capital letter, <del>xxxxxx</del> as if to show every mans
                    sense of its consequences. – I long to see your antediluvian world.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Montgomery’s
                            <title>The World Before the Flood</title> (1813).</note> Do not talk to me of Alfred,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> A poem on the subject of Alfred the Great (848/9–899; <title>DNB</title>).</note> – for I am engaged three
                    subjects deep after Pelayo, &amp; heaven knows when that will be compleated. The next in order is Philips war in New England, with
                    a primitive Quaker for the Hero.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> King Philip’s War, or Metacom’s Rebellion, 1675–1676. An
                        armed conflict between English colonists and the native American inhabitants of New England. Southey’s poem was ‘Oliver
                        Newman’, left incomplete at his death.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> farewell, yrs most truly</salute><signed rend="indent4"> R Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1812-03-26">March 26. 1812.</date></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#ConderJosiah">Josiah Conder</ref> gave me some verses of yours addressed to his friends the
                            Minstrels<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Montgomery’s ‘Verses, Written on a Blank Leaf in the “Hymns for Infant
                            Minds”’, which praised (line 19) the ‘fair Minstrels’ Ann (1782–1829; <title>DNB</title>) and Jane Taylor (1783–1824;
                                <title>DNB</title>); see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812), pp. xcii–xciii. The Taylors
                            were minstrel friends of Conder’s because they had contributed to his <title>The Associate Minstrels</title>
                            (1810).</note> – for the Edinburgh Annual Register, – to which you may perhaps know that I perform the office of Annalist.
                        If you have any thing else which you could spare for such a purpose, I am sure the <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Editor</ref> would feel himself both flattered &amp; obliged by such a communication. Ballantyne is the Editor, &amp; if
                        he had <del>had</del> not <del>taste</del> had taste to appreciate you as he ought himself, <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> would have taught him to do so. – Have you seen Count Julian?<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Count Julian: A Tragedy</title> (1812), which covered similar territory to that in Southey’s <title>Roderick, the
                                Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> It is by <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> the author
                        of Gebir.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> Josiah Conder … Gebir: Inserted at top of fol. 1 r. Landor’s
                                <title>Gebir</title> had been published in 1798.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>