<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1745</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3016</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Department of Rare Books, Special
                        Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers
                        A.S727.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1745" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1745" type="letter">
        <head>1745. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref>, <date when="1810-02-10">10 February
                        1810</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Humphrey Senhouse Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Maryport<lb />Seal: Red Wax, &#8216;S&#8217; with motto &#8216;In Labore Quies&#8217;<lb />MS: Department of Rare Books, Special
                        Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers
                        A.S727<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Senhouse</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your Note has been consigned to <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> as
                    Receiver General for <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">her husband</ref> in this District. The obscurity of the
                    Friend appears to me to arise from a want of arrangement rather than from any other cause.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Coleridge&#8217;s <title>The Friend</title>, published in 26 weekly instalments, 1 June 1809&#8211;15 March 1810.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> loves talking, &#8211; it is his disease, he has literally a diabetes of
                    the tongue. He multiplies words in conversation for the mere pleasure of articulating them, &amp; if he begins at Dan rambles on
                    till he gets to Beersheba.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> From the furthest north to the southernmost part of the Kingdom
                        of Israel, <title>Judges</title>, 20: 1.</note> This rambling manner has now extended itself to his style of writing. Let him
                    start what subject he will he loses sight of it, &amp; like a young dog which has not yet been broke in, runs after every thing.
                    Instead of going straight as an arrow to the mark, he turns &amp; winds &amp; doubles, nosing his way, &amp; changing the scent
                    for whatever comes in his track. Just as it was with Burke,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund Burke (1729/30&#8211;1797;
                            <title>DNB</title>). Originally an opposition Whig, Burke became increasingly conservative and attempted to persuade his
                        friends to follow him, as in his <title>Appeal from the New to the Old Whigs</title> (1791).</note> he is continually evolving
                    the causes of things &amp; involving their consequences, so that like one in a maze you neither see how you got in, nor how you
                    are to get out. This it was which made Burke so inefficient a writer &amp; speaker with all his mighty mind &amp; surpassing
                    eloquence. He never persuaded any body. Many were the persons who sheltered themselves under his name, &#8211; but it was only when they
                    wanted an excuse for abandoning their former party. Till Burke became an Anti-Jacobine no person ever pretended to be converted to
                    any of his opinions.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have said something of Robertson in a note to the Brazilian History pointing out two remarkable instances of his
                        faithlessness.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The historian and Church of Scotland minister William Robertson
                        (1721&#8211;1793; <title>DNB</title>), author of a <title>History of America</title> (1777). Southey owned an edition of 1788, no. 2456 in the sale
                        catalogue of his library. Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), I, pp. 639, 644, attacked
                        Robertson for not realising that many forms of metal currency were used in pre-Columban America and for his silence about the Maya
                        civilization in Yucatan.</note> I have a very bad opinion of that Scotchman. When he was once asked to communicate an Essay to
                    some Edinburgh Society (I forget what) his answer was that he never wrote anything for which he did not get copy-right.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robertson was a staunch defender of copyright and also skilled at negotiating excellent terms for
                        his writings. He received, for example, a record &#163;3,500 for his <title>The History of the Reign of Charles V</title>
                        (1769).</note> I believe
                    that precisely upon the same system he never read anything which would not pay him for reading it, in the gross pound shilling
                    &amp; pence meaning of the phrase. Of the list of books which he has prefixed to that vile history of America one half have no
                    reference to the work itself.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robertson&#8217;s <title>History of America</title> (1777) was
                        accompanied by copious references.</note> And with respect to the prime documents for the subjects on which he wrote, I have
                        <hi rend="ital">proved</hi> that he either did not read them thro, or that he supprest some of their most important facts. I
                    have read most of the books which he ought to have read, all that he did read, &amp; a great many more, &amp; I find him as
                    deficient in all parts of his American history as Bernal Diaz<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bernal Diaz del Castillo
                        (1492&#8211;1585), conquistador and author of an eyewitness account of the Spanish conquest of Mexico, <title>Historia Verdadera de
                            la Conquista de la Nueva Espana</title> (1632), no. 3370 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> proves him to
                    be in the affairs of Mexico.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The conquest of Mexico appears to me the most splendid event that ever was atchieved, &amp; Cortes<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hern&#225;n Cort&#233;s (1485&#8211;1547), conqueror of the Aztec empire.</note> the greatest of all military
                    adventurers. Did you ever see his portrait as engraved by Vertue<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The engraver and
                        antiquary George Vertue (1684&#8211;1756; <title>DNB</title>).</note> from Titian?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Italian painter Tiziano Vecelli (c. 1488/1490&#8211;1576).</note> It is prefixed to a translation of Solis&#8217;s turgid history, &amp;
                    is I think the very finest countenance I ever remember to have seen.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The History of the Conquest of Mexico by the Spaniards. Done into English from the Original Spanish of Don Antonio de
                            Solis</title> (London, [1724]), Frontispiece; no. 721 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. It was a translation of
                        Antonio de Solis y Ribandeneyra (1610&#8211;1686), <title>Historia de la Conquista de Mexico</title> (1684).</note> It is the
                    countenance of a man made to govern the world, &amp; not less beautiful than it is majestic &amp; commanding. &#8211; American history
                    is very little known in England, &amp; is indeed only to be learnt from the original authors. To think as Robertson did of
                    including all America in one work was preposterous. The different parts have not the slightest connection with each other. Mexico
                    is less connected with Brazil, &amp; Peru with New England, than this country is with Russia. Hayti with the other Spanish
                    Islands, Mexico, Peru, the Nuevo Reyno<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Modern Colombia and parts of Venezuela.</note>
                    &amp; Brazil all require seperate works of considerable extent, &#8211; &amp; then the French &amp; English colonies still remain.
                    Neither my life or leisure will admit of my doing more in American history, than that part which relates to the Portugueze. The
                    first volume<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title>, published in 1810.</note>
                    will appear, I trust, early in the ensuing month, a most faithful, &amp; sufficiently laborious work. It brings it own reward in
                    the pleasure which it has given me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Edinburgh Annual Register is about half-printed.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810).</note> &#8211; The Columbiad<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Joel Barlow (1754&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Columbiad</title> (1807); Southey owned an edition of 1809, no. 114 in
                        the sale catalogue of his library.</note> in its present state has not reached me &#8211; It was to have been sent here for the
                    Quarterly, &amp; I know not why it[MS torn] arrived. Originally it was called the Vision of Columbus, &amp; in that form [MS torn]
                    have it.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Barlow&#8217;s <title>The Vision of Columbus</title> (1787). Southey&#8217;s copy was no.
                        114 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> Barlow had not corrupted his taste by the study of Darwin<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Erasmus Darwin (1731&#8211;1802; <title>DNB</title>), whose poetry Southey actively disliked.</note>
          <del>xx</del> when he began his career as a poet, &amp; the poem in its first state, tho tedious because written in couplets &amp;
                    upon a wretched plan, yet bore marks of a vigorous mind. In the days of Jacobinism he published a book which fell under the law
                    here in England, &#8211; it was one of the best written that appeared.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Barlow&#8217;s <title>Advice
                            to the Privileged Orders</title> (1792&#8211;1795). In 1792, faced with the prospect of prosecution, Barlow moved from England
                        to France.</note> Some years ago he was employed in a diplomatic capacity to settle some disputes between the United States
                    &amp; Algiers,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joel Barlow was United States consul at Algiers 1795&#8211;1797 and negotiated
                        the Treaty of Tripoli (1796). Article 11 contained the words &#8216;the Government of the United States is not, in any sense,
                        founded on the Christian religion&#8217;.</note> &amp; the main arguments by which he succeeded in persuading the Dey to a treaty
                    were these, that America was not to be considered as a Christian Government, all religions being equally tolerated there &amp;
                    none established, &#8211; &amp; that there were was a natural connection between the half moon of Algiers, &amp; the thirteen stars of
                    the United States. <del>Th</del> I heard this from Smith the American Envoy at Lisbon.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        William Loughton Smith (1758&#8211;1812), United States Minister Plenipotentiary to Portugal 1797&#8211;1801.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Our youngest</ref> got rather severely burnt two or three weeks ago by an explosion from
                    the fire. These explosions are so frequent in the coal which we get here, &amp; sometimes so violent, that it would not surprize
                    me to hear of some serious accident from them. Excepting this, we have all been tolerably well this winter. My non-descript
                        poem<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> is just in the press, &amp; I have begun another in a soberer strain upon
                        Pelayo.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> An early version of what became <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814). Pelayo [Pelagius] (d. 737; reigned 718&#8211;737) was the founder of the Kingdom of Asturias. He is
                        credited with beginning the Christian reconquest of the Iberian peninsula.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; her sisters<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sarah Coleridge</ref> and <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary
                        Lovell</ref>.</note> beg to be remembered to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Senhouse. We meditate a journey to Durham in April, &amp;
                    have some expectation of seeing <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my sea-faring brother</ref> before that time.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey</signed>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick.</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1810-02-10">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 10. 1810.</date>
          </dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>