<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1972</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3243</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                    30928.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1972" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1972" type="letter">
        <head>1972. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1811-10-24">24 October
                        1811</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Bristol<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: 1811/ 24 Oct<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                    30928<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1811-10-24">Oct 24. 1811</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Danvers,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope I have heard of something which will take the Boy<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Danvers&#8217;s nephew,
                        John Danvers, son of his brother, John Danvers (d. 1812), a surgeon and apothecary in Woolwich, who had been made bankrupt in
                        1808.</note> off your hands. It is the Royal Military Asylum at Chelsea, an establishment for 1000 boys, the children of
                    soldiers, &amp; about to be increased to 1500.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Royal Military Asylum had been founded
                        in 1801 to educate the children of soliders in the regular army who had died in the service of their country. It was also
                        known as The Duke of York&#8217;s School, after its patron.</note> They are educated upon <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bells</ref> plan, &amp; at fourteen chuse for themselves their way of life, being apprenticed to what
                    trade they like best, if they prefer trade to the army or navy. This is an institution in which no interest can be of any use, &#8211;
                    you have only to cause application to be made at the proper office which may easily be found out, &#8211; if the child be admissable
                    (which from all I can learn I suppose him to be) he will be admitted if there is a vacancy, &#8211; &amp; if there be none will take his
                    turn for one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our journey home was remarkably fortunate. We had neither rain nor accident nor hindrance of any kind either then,
                    or indeed during our whole <del>xxxxx</del> journey, which considering that we travelled 800 miles &amp; I 100 besides may be
                    regarded as <del>xxxx xx xxxx</del> a rare instance of good fortune. We past two days with <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>, &amp; slept in one of the towers of the ruin. The house which he is
                    building is about a quarter of a mile, or rather more, from the Abbey, on the ascent of the hill, &amp; on the bank of a
                        dingle.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Landor was attempting to improve his estate on the English&#8211;Welsh borders. It
                        centred upon the ruins of the Augustinian priory of Llanthony. His new house was never completed.</note> It will be a very
                    good sensible house but the situation from its utter seclusion has so many inconveniences necessarily attached to it, that I wish
                    he had never begun <del>xxx</del> to build there. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We past a few days also very pleasantly at Ludlow, &#8211; which is so beautiful a town that I earnestly advise you to
                    make it in your way when next you travel northwards. I forget whether you saw the <ref target="people.html#BrowneWade">Brownes</ref> at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>: &#8211; they are settled there. the Castle is one of the most
                    impressive ruins I ever saw. We went also to Croft,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Croft Castle, near Ludlow.</note> &#8211; to
                    me an interesting place because my mothers grandmother<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Margaret Croft (dates
                        unknown).</note> was born there &#8211; &amp; to Downton<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Downton Castle, near Ludlow, the
                        gothic revival house built in c. 1774&#8211;1778 by Richard Payne Knight (1751&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>).</note> a place of more
                    celebrity, tho I think undeservedly so. Downton reminded me of finer things than itself in the country. From thence we made for
                        <ref target="places.html#Teddesley">Teddesley</ref>, where <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward
                        Littleton</ref> is literally kept alive by the incessant watchfulness of <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss
                        Barker</ref>; &#8211; he is well enough to enjoy life, &#8211; but without the utmost care, so weak is he from age, he would drop like a
                    leaf from a tree.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In our next visit we were less fortunate. <ref target="people.html#WynnMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wynn</ref>
                    having gone to pay a visit some eight miles from home, had miscarried there in consequence of the jolting on the way, &amp; then
                    she was confined while we were at Llangedwin. A friend of hers was sent for to receive <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> that there might be a female in the house. We were invited to take <ref target="people.html#WynnSirWatkinWilliams">Sir Watkins</ref> in our way, but this I declined. On the road we halted at
                    Llangollen &amp; dined with <ref target="people.html#LlangollenLadies">the Ladies</ref>, &#8211; a visit which was not the least
                    interesting event of our long journey.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Since my return I have been very much interrupted with visitors, to the grievous consumption of good time. <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Col. Peachy</ref> was here, &amp; is daily expected here again from Scotland. That hideous
                    house opposite us, is tenanted at present by the Bishop of Meath, &#8211; a sensible man, &amp; with a pleasant household of
                        females.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Lewis O&#8217;Beirne (1747&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Meath
                        1798&#8211;1823. The son of a County Longford farmer, he had been educated for the Catholic priesthood, but converted to
                        Protestantism and became a Church of Ireland clergyman. He had been a well-known Whig, but by 1811 he was increasingly
                        conservative and a defender of the Church of Ireland. His wife was Jane (n&#233;e Stuart) (1755&#8211;1837) and he had two unmarried
                        daughters, Jane Ormsby O&#8217;Beirne (1784&#8211;?) and Jean O&#8217;Beirne (d. 1838).</note>
          <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> is also now at <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. I have been fighting his battles in the Quarterly, &amp; had not my work been mutilated even more unmercifully
                    than usual, this affray would have been the severest blow that the Edinburgh Review ever received.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey advocated the educational system of Andrew Bell over that of Joseph Lancaster in his review of Joseph
                        Fox (1775&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Comparative View of the Plans of Education as detailed in the Publications of
                            Dr. Bell and Mr. Lancaster, and Remarks on Dr. Bell&#8217;s Madras School, and Hints to the Managers and Committees of Charity
                            and Sunday Schools, on the Practicability of extending such Institutions upon Mr. Lancaster&#8217;s Plan</title>, 3rd edn
                        (1811); Herbert Marsh (1757&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Sermon, Preached in the Cathedral Church of St. Paul, London,
                            on Thursday, June 13, 1811. To which is Added, a Collection of Notes and Illustrations</title> (1811); Reynold Gideon
                        Bouyer (1741&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Comparative View of the two New Systems of Education of the Infant Poor, in a
                            Charge delivered to the Clergy of the Officialty of the Dean and Chapter of Durham, at Berwick-upon-Tweed, on Tuesday, May
                            12, 1811</title> (1811), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (August 1811), 264&#8211;304. (This number of the
                            <title>Quarterly</title> was published in October 1811.) The article was heavily censored by Gifford prior to publication
                        and personal attacks on the <title>Edinburgh Review</title> were removed; see the account in <ref type="l" target="/reference/qr/index/11.html">Jonathan Cutmore, <title>The
                            Quarterly Review Archive</title>
            </ref>.</note> for never have they
                    committed more flagrant injustice nor more wilful &amp; mischievous falshood, than upon this subject. I shall not however let the
                    matter rest here. The Philistines are delivered into my hands, &amp; I will [MS obscured] them just as much mercy as they deserve.
                    I look upon <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> as the man to whom, next to <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref>, the human race is more deeply indebted than to any other of this
                    generation, &amp; never has any man been more infamously treated.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Nothing has been heard of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> since our return. &#8211; When
                    you write let me know the amount of my debt to you. Remember me to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> &#8211; Hort<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Jillard Hort (1764&#8211;1849), Unitarian minister at Frenchay Chapel in Bristol 1803&#8211;1815 and
                        later in Cork. He taught in the school run by John Prior Estlin and was the addressee of Coleridge&#8217;s &#8216;To the Rev. W. J. H.&#8217;,
                            <title>Poems on Various Subjects</title> (London and Bristol, 1796), pp. [12]&#8211;14.</note> &amp; <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Estlin</ref>. how is he? <del>Xxxxx</del> Joseph&#8217;s death<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Prior Estlin (1777&#8211;1811), eldest son of John Prior Estlin.</note> must have been a
                    shock to him, &#8211; which I fear his health is not in a state to support. Remember me also to <ref target="people.html#JardineDavid">David</ref> if he be not returned to the land where <del>xxxx xxxx xx xxx xxx fiddle</del> you can never be balked of a dance
                    for want of a fiddle.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Yrs affectionately RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>