<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1741</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3012</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d.110
                        .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1741" type="letter">
        <head>1741. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1810-02-05">5 February
                        1810</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: 1810<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d.110
                        <lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1810-02-05">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 5. 1810.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Lightfoot</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have more than once been thinking of addressing a letter to Crediton for the sake of ascertaining whether you
                    were in this world or the next, &amp; had not my occupations been so numerous &amp; so constant that every hour brings with it its
                    business, you would long ere this have been troubled with a question to that effect. &#8211; The history of my unfortunate brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> I can carry on as far as last summer. &#8211; Having obtained the Ensigncy to which
                    you allude he wrote to inform me of it, <del>to which</del> &lt;&amp;&gt; I replied by a letter of exhortation. Some months
                    afterwards he acquainted me with his promotion to the rank of Lieutenant, &#8211; &amp; I wrote to him again in a manner which implied
                    more hopes of his reformation than I really felt. In July last there came a letter to me from a Major Chamberlayne<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Thomas Chamberlain (d. 1828), Major in the 24th Foot Regiment.</note> with the army in
                    Portugal, stating that he had discovered a brother of mine in the ranks, &#8211; that he had taken him by the hand, &#8211; &amp; obtained him
                    a commission in a Portugueze regiment which he was then raising, &#8211; &amp; that Lord J Fitzroy<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lord John Fitzroy (1785&#8211;1857), attach&#233; at the British Embassy in Lisbon and son of Augustus, 3rd Duke of
                        Grafton (1735&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1768&#8211;1770.</note> had insisted upon fitting him out for this new
                    appointment. I replied to Major Chamberlayne as such conduct from one who was a perfect stranger to me deserved, &#8211; &amp; expressed
                    an ominous apprehension that even this fresh opportunity of retrieving himself would be lost upon poor <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref>; &#8211; an apprehension <del>xxxx</del> founded not merely upon my thorough
                    knowledge of his nature, but also upon the melancholy symptoms shown in a letter from himself, which arrived by the same post as
                    Chamberlaynes, &#8211; in which he imputed this change in his fortunes wholly to his own good conduct, &amp; never mentioned one of the
                    persons who had so generously befriended him. My fears were soon verified &#8211; &amp; the last I heard of him by a circuitous channel
                    was that he was taking up money, <del>xxx</del> drafts upon <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Tyler</ref>, &#8211; had left the regiment, &amp; sold his mule, &#8211; in short was become a vagabond again. By what means he lost his
                    Militia Commission &amp; was reduced into the ranks of the regulars I have never learnt. &#8211; You see how <del>th</del> hopeless it
                    is, &#8211; it is a case of moral insanity, &#8211; perfectly incurable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Since last you heard &lt;from&gt; me I have had two daughters born, &#8211; &amp; laid <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">one of them</ref> to rest, &#8211; a sweet child of 15 months, &#8211; cut off in a few hours by an
                    attack of cholera morbus as we suppose it to have been. I have <del>x</del> now three living, &amp; God be praised doing &amp;
                    promising well. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">the eldest</ref> in her sixth year, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">the youngest</ref> not <del>quite</del> having completed her first. As my expences increase
                    my means increase with them. I hold the pen of a ready writer, &amp; find time to raise <del>my</del> ways &amp; means, as well as
                    to produce works for which however great the reward may be which they will entail upon my name, I expect no remuneration. I bear a
                    part in the Quarterly Review, &#8211; in the first number there is a defence of the Missionaries in India with which I think you would
                    be pleased.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Account of the Baptist Missionary Society&#8217;, <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193&#8211;226.</note> &#8211; I am at present engaged in writing the historical part of a new
                    Edinburgh Annual Register,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810).</note> the first volume of which will appear next spring. These are
                    anonymous labours, which obtain me immediate reputation with the booksellers &amp; being written bon&#226; fide &amp; with hearty good
                    will bear upon them a stamp which any person who knows me will recognize as the mark of Robert Southey, &#8211; a man who never let
                    &lt;any&gt; one mistake his principles &#8211; <del>what</del>&lt;how&gt;ever they might mistake his character.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The first vol of my Hist of Brazil<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                            Brazil</title>, published in 3 volumes 1810&#8211;1819.</note> will be published in a few weeks &amp; I have just sent a
                        Poem<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> to press, which every body will stare at. &amp; most people will abuse. You
                    will be surprized at hearing that I dedicate it to <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> of Trinity, a man of
                    such marvellous genius that I regret to think we should have been so near neighbours without knowing each other in the days of our
                        youth.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been a student at Balliol College, Oxford, which is next door to
                        Trinity College, Oxford, and the two had overlapped at the university in 1793&#8211;1794.</note> Have you seen Espriellas
                        Letters?<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England</title> (1807), narrated by the fictitious Don Manuel Alavarez Espriella.</note> if so you would
                    probably father them upon me. &#8211; The Remains of <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">H K White</ref>
          <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White</title> (1807)</note>. which I published for <del>th</del> his family have been in an
                    extraordinary degree succesful. It will amuse you to hear that this work procured me a letter from &#8211; <ref target="people.html#CampbellHenry">Horse Campbell</ref>; &#8211; who is a Methodist of the first order, having been expelled the
                    Diocese of Oxford for field preaching.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Campbell had married Anne Rose of Shrewsbury
                        in 1805 and was presumably living in that town. Southey had last seen him in 1801 when was on his way to become Rector of St
                        Johns, Antigua.</note> He began by recalling himself to my recollection &#8211; as if any body could possibly have forgotten him! &#8211;
                    told me he had skipt all the poems, having no taste for any poetry above the pitch of a Tabernacle Hymn, &#8211; &amp; that the object
                    of his writing was to learn whether I might not have supprest some papers as too pious, &#8211; which would have been in a high degree
                    consolatory to such Xtians as himself, &#8211; if so he should he happy to subscribe to their publication. He then proceded to express
                    the concern he was under for the state of my soul. &amp; concluded by inviting me &amp; all my family (if I had any) to Shrewsbury
                    &#8211; where I suppose I was to put my soul under his care. &#8211; I would as willingly trust my body to him upon the strength of the
                    anatomical knowledge which he picked up from <ref target="people.html#PeggeChristopher">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pegge</ref>
          <note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pegge&#8217;s anatomy lectures were very popular with Oxford students in the 1790s.</note> &amp;
                    his aide de camp M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> West.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mr West (first name and dates unknown) was
                        Pegge&#8217;s assistant in his anatomy demonstrations.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> is my most constant correspondent. In worldly circumstances he
                    &lt;is&gt; well off having an official situation of nearly 1000&#163; a year,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bedford was
                        Clerk of Registers and Issues at the Exchequer 1806&#8211;1822.</note> &#8211; but his lot has been a heavy one. Family misfortunes press
                    upon him, <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">his brother Horace</ref> lost his senses &amp; died a few years ago, &#8211;
                    &amp; worst of all he is in &lt;such&gt; a state of health himself, that I very very much fear he will soon follow him. It will be
                    a heavy blow to me whenever that happens, &#8211; there has scarcely elapsed a month during 18 years in which we have not interchanged
                    letters, &#8211; &amp; tho it would be unjust to others to say that he is the dearest of my friends, &#8211; he is the most <hi rend="ital">familiar</hi> of them, &#8211; a word which in this sense implies so much affection, that it brings tears into my eyes when I use
                    it. <del>xxxx</del>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> past a few days with me in the autumn. I wish Crediton were nearer that I might
                    the sooner hope to be introduced to your wife,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bridget Prideaux (dates unknown), whom
                        Lightfoot had married in 1801.</note> &#8211; make acquaintance with my God-daughter,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Frances Jane (Fanny) Lightfoot (1806&#8211;1882).</note> &amp; see whether you look like a schoolmaster.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you have not seen Espriella I will send a copy with the new edition of Thalaba.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England</title> (1807), and the second edition of <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>, published in
                        1809.</note> &#8211; <del>xxx xxxx xxxxxxx xxx xxxxx xxxx xxxxx xx xxxxx xxxxxx xxxxxxxx xxxxxx xxxx xx xxxx xxxxx xxx
                        xxxxxxxxxxxx</del>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you my old friend</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> sense implies &#8230; Southey: written at top of fol 1
                            r.</note>
          </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>