<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2139</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3410</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry
                        Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos, The Letters of
                            Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 124&#8211;126.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2139" type="letter">
        <head>2139. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1812-08-28">28 August 1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry<lb />Postmark:
                        E/1SE1/1812&#8217; and&#8216;10o&#8217;Clock/ SP.1/ 1812F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Watermark: crown and anchor/ 1806<lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 162 1812/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> August/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> September/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.<lb />MS: Harry
                        Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos, <title>The Letters of
                            Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 124&#8211;126.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-08-28">Aug 28. 1812</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter led me to expect M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpoles papers<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert
                        Walpole (1736&#8211;1810), Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Portugal, 1771&#8211;1800.</note> almost soon as itself,
                    &amp; therefore I delayed replying to it till I could <del>announce</del> acknowledge the receipt of these documents. They arrived
                    last night, safe &amp; uninjured.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It would be needless I trust, my dear friend, for me to express the concern which I feel at the information which
                    you communicate respecting your concerns in Brazil, &#8211; even if I could tell how to express it. Something of this kind you imparted
                    to me when we saw each other at Richmond last year, but one of your letters led me to believe that that business had been settled
                    to your wishes. Is this then a new evil, or were you deceived when you expected that the affair was terminated? And is there &#8211; for
                    I cannot help referring to selfish considerations, &#8211; is there any reason for your friends to apprehend that the mismanagement of
                    your concerns at Rio Janeiro may make it necessary for you to go there yourself? &#8211; This you would probably regard as the worst
                    consequence, &#8211; the loss of property may be repaired, &amp; the success of one year make amends for the <del>xxx</del> reverses of
                    another, but time past in a foreign country &#8211; away from our nearest &amp; dearest ties, is an irretrievable loss of comfort &amp;
                    happiness.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Privilegios<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a copy of the <title>Cartas dos Privilegios de
                            Nacam Britannica em Portugal</title> (1746). In 1808 Britain had been extended similar trading privileges in
                        Brazil.</note> shall be sent up in a few days, &#8211; they will serve as ballast to a portion of manuscript on its way to the
                    Press, &amp; I will request <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to send it to <del>Tavistock Street</del>. Broad
                    Street. I did not make use of this book as had been my intention in the Register for 1810, for a reason which you will find partly
                    expressed in a note to P. 497.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.1 (1812), 497.</note> The want of that volume of the Proceedings of the
                        Cortes<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey later acquired the <title>Diario de las Discusiones y Actas de las
                            Cortes, 1810&#8211;1813</title>, 19 vols (Cadiz, 1811&#8211;13), as it was no. 3288 in the Sale catalogue of his Library.</note> gave
                    me a good reason for not entering upon the affairs of Spanish America, &#8211; &amp; the size of the volume rendered it highly expedient
                    that I should avail myself of that plea for deferring a subject which requires a long &amp; elaborate chapter. In the natural
                    order of my arrangement Brazil would follow B Ayres &amp; therefore I postponed both together.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s account of recent revolutions in Spanish America, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 367&#8211;421.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The last Quarterly has only one article of mine.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A review of
                            <title>Biographie Moderne: Lives of Remarkable Characters who have Distinguished themselves from the Commencement of the
                            French Revolution to the Present Time</title> (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (June 1812), 412&#8211;438.</note> I
                    wish it were in my power to restore it to its original state, &#8211; but what <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>
                    expunges is lost for ever. It is, as you may suppose, only of particular parts that I make a second copy, most of my articles are
                    sent off as they are written.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the purchase of Muratori.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lodovico Antonio Muratori
                        (1672&#8211;1750). Southey hoped that May could buy <title>Rerum Italicarum Scriptores, Ab. Anno 500 Ad Annum 1500</title>, 36 vols
                        (1723&#8211;70). In fact, May purchased Muratori&#8217;s <title>Annali d&#8217;Italia dal Principio dell&#8217;era Volgare sino all&#8217;anno 1750</title>
                        (1786); no. 1894 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, though this lacked the first volume; see Southey to John May, 16
                        September 1812, Letter 2145. Southey later did manage to obtain a copy of <title>Rerum Italicarum Scriptores</title>, no. 1922
                        in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> By the price I guess that there is a much longer deficit at the end of the
                    collection than at the beginning, &#8211; but if it be only half the set it is cheaply purchased for the intrinsic value of each volume
                    is altogether independent of every other.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> From <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> I have not heard for some time, &#8211;
                    tho it is since the losses of which you speak had fallen upon him. When first I heard of them I wrote to him, &amp; his reply was
                    in such a tone as to distress me very much. In consequence I took counsel with a friend of his &amp; mine, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gooch</ref> of Aldermanbury a man whom I wish you knew &#8211; &amp; we
                    were about to have raised among his friends an annuity &#8211; <del>such</del> which might have prevented him from ever feeling any
                    thing like the apprehension of want. But upon enquiring from those who were ne[MS torn] him &amp; intimate with his concerns it
                    was found that no necessity for this existed, &amp; my last letter from <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> T</ref> himself was in a more chearful strain, &amp; spoke of offers of assistance which had <del>only</del> been
                    not accepted only because they were not wanted. Since this his mother<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sarah Taylor, n&#233;e
                        Wright (1735/6&#8211;1812) had died on 27 April 1812.</note> is dead, &amp; this event which in the course of nature has been long
                    to be expected, removes his main cause of anxiety.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your godchild</ref> has had a slight attack of bilious fever, from which she seems this
                    evening, I hope &amp; believe, thoroughly recovered. I regret very much that you should be one of the very few friends who
                        <del>have</del> in the course of nine years have not looked in upon me &amp; seen the comforts with which I am surrounded. You
                    would have been well pleased with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref>; who has as good disposition of every
                    kind as I could possibly wish for her.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Remember us to <ref target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &amp; believe me </salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> yours very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>