<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2627</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3898</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42551 .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2627" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2627" type="letter">
        <head>2627. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1815-06-30">30 June 1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London
                        <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb />Postmark: E/ 3 JY 3/ 1815<lb /> Watermark: J DICKINSON &amp; Co/ 1811<lb />Endorsement: 1815
                        June 30 Keswick/ Southey &#8211; Rob<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
            <lb />MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42551 <lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1815-06-30">30 June 1815. </date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Among the Books which you last sent me is a French account of Massenas Campaign in Portugal,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andre Massena (1758&#8211;1817), commander of the invasion of Portugal in 1810.</note> a master-piece
                    of impudence. I think this may serve for our text,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Eustache-Auguste Carel (1788&#8211;1836),
                            <title>Pr&#233;cis Historique de la Guerre d&#8217;Espagne et de Portugal, de 1808 &#224; 1814</title> (1815); one of a series of books on
                        Wellington&#8217;s campaigns reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (July 1815), 448&#8211;526. For examples of his
                        swipes at Carel, see <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (July 1815), 461, 463, 472, 475.</note> &amp; introduce naturally
                    &amp; strikingly enough to <del>xxx</del> narrative, which we may take up from the battle of Vittoria.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The allied defeat of the French at Vittoria, 21 June 1813. It paved the way for eventual victory in the
                        Peninsular war.</note> &#8211; There is a grievous scarcity of materials from that time, &#8211; except Col Jones&#8217;s account<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Thomas Jones (1783&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal of Sieges Carried on by the
                            Allies in Spain in 1810, 1811, and 1812</title> (1814). This was highly critical of the tactics and mechanics of sieges
                        conducted by the British and their allies in the Peninsular campaign, in which Jones had served.</note> of the siege of S
                        Sebastian<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Allied forces successfully besieged San Sebastian, 7 July-8 September
                        1813.</note> &amp; the little that is to be found in Broughtons Letters,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The military
                        surgeon Samuel Daniel Broughton (1787&#8211;1837; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Letters from Portugal, Spain and France, Written
                            During the Campaigns of 1812, 1813, and 1814</title> (1815). Broughton had witnessed the campaign in the Peninsula and
                        been present at Waterloo.</note> not a book has reached me which relates to <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Ld Wellingtons</ref> army after the retreat from Burgos.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The siege of Burgos, 19 September-21 October 1812, saw an allied army fail to capture the castle
                        from a French garrison.</note> The Military Chronicle<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Royal Military Chronicle, or, The British Officer&#8217;s Monthly Register, Chronicle, and Military Mentor</title>
                        (1811&#8211;1817).</note> which began so well became about that time a mere catchpenny republication, without a particle of original
                    matter, &#8211; &amp; for all the subsequent battles I have as yet literally nothing but the gazette accounts, &#8211; except some private
                    correspondence the writer of which unfortunately was wounded at the storming of the Camp before Bayonne.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a reference to Captain William Lewis Herries (d. 1857), Deputy-Assistant Quarter-Master-General, who
                        was reported as &#8216;severely wounded&#8217; at the Battle of Bayonne, 14 April 1814. He had lost a leg and been made prisoner, but
                        survived and continued in the army until 1854, rising to be a Commissioner of the Board of Audit. He was the brother of John
                        Charles Herries and Southey may have obtained his letters through this source.</note> You sent me the Military Panorama to the
                    end of 1813: if that has been continued there may perhaps be something there.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Military Panorama</title> (1812&#8211;1817), nos. 1847&#8211;1848 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; I shall
                    stand in need here of all that historical &amp; local knowledge can do for me, &amp; in these points I am well provided. Send me
                    Pinckneys Travels,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ninian Pinkney (1776&#8211;1825), <title>Travels through the South of
                            France, and the Interior of the Provinces of Provence and Languedoc, 1807&#8211;8</title> (1809). A second edition appeared in
                        1814.</note> &#8211; from which perhaps something may be gleaned. The latter part is indeed a splendid subject, <del>xx</del> &amp;
                    we do not yet know what the conclusion may be; &#8211; for if Paris should resist the Prussians will not be restrained a second time.
                    The more likely termination seems to be that Macdonald,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Marshal Jacques MacDonald
                        (1765&#8211;1840) was one of Napoleon&#8217;s Marshals who remained loyal to the Bourbons in 1815.</note> acting as if he has acknowledged
                    Buonaparte for the purpose of more effectually serving the Bourbons, will take advantage of the situation in which he is placed; &#8211;
                    proclaim them at the head of the National Guard<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The National Guard in Paris was a
                        part-time militia, originally set up in 1791, and mainly consisting of fairly wealthy citizens. In 1814&#8211;1815 it had shown
                        liberal sympathies and some hostility to the Bourbon regime.</note> &amp; open the gates to <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Ld Wellington</ref>. But it is very idle thus to offer conjectures upon what
                    may probably be known in London before this letter arrives there. &#8211; Of course it must be the concluding article to allow as much
                    time as possible for collecting details.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It was for <hi rend="ital">space</hi> that I was straitened in the last paper, &amp; not for <hi rend="ital">time</hi>.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s earlier article on Wellington had appeared in <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 215&#8211;275.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Egyptian story had the great advantage of picturesque accompaniments, &amp; my canvass allowed room for
                        them.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of Jacques Fran&#231;ois Miot (1779&#8211;1858), <title>M&#233;moires pour
                            servir &#224; l&#8217;Histoire des Exp&#233;ditions en Egypte et en Syrie</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April
                        1815), 1&#8211;55.</note> There ought to be a second paper, taking up the subject after Buonapartes flight, &amp; finishing with the
                    close of our Expedition.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Although Napoleon left Egypt in August 1799, the French Army
                        there did not capitulate to a British force until August 1801.</note> I have not sent back the <del>books</del> documents, &#8211;
                    because if you like this thought as well as I do, this use may be made of them; &amp; the whole might very well be recast into a
                    regular historical form, &amp; make one little volume, &#8211; as a history entire in itself of the most memorable <hi rend="ital">expedition</hi> of modern times.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey wrote neither a &#8216;second paper&#8217; nor expanded
                        his materials into a book.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have no wish to write the life of Buonaparte. In the Egyptian Expedition &amp; in the War of the Peninsula<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> I shall have
                    fully detailed two important acts of his life. And there will be a general view of the whole if I ever <del>write</del> compose
                    &#8220;the Age of George 3d&#8221;<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of the United Kingdom 1760&#8211;1820;
                            <title>DNB</title>). For Southey&#8217;s proposals; see Southey to John Murray, 31 March 1813, Letter 2238. The project never
                        came to fruition.</note> &#8211; which it is certainly my intention <del>xxx</del> to do, if it please God to grant me sufficient
                    length of life. My other historical works<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Primarily Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                            Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) and his unfinished &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> will be works of detail, &#8211; this will be a
                    specimen of general &amp; philosophical history. The materials are magnificent, &amp; I have full confidence in my own
                    architectural skill.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Salt<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Henry Salt (1780&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Voyage to
                            Abyssinia</title> (1814). Southey did not review it for the <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> I think must stand over till
                    a paper upon E. Africa be compleated which is now publishing in the Investigador Portuguez, &amp; the continuation or conclusion
                    of which was provokingly postponed in the last number.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first two parts of &#8216;Descrip&#231;&#227;o
                        do estado em que ficava&#245; os negocios de Mozambique em 1789&#8217; appeared in <title>O Investigador Portuguez</title>, 12 (1815),
                        184&#8211;195, 375&#8211;384. No further instalments seem to have appeared.</note> I shall have however another article for your next, &#8211;
                    the Egypt if you like it, or Gregoires Sects.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henri Gregoire (1750&#8211;1831), <title>Histoire
                            des Sectes Religieuses</title> (1810), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822),
                        1&#8211;46.</note> &#8211; And for the one after I shall have something to say upon our good friend <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref>, &amp; his Ludus Literarius.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andrew Bell,
                            <title>Elements of Tuition, Part III: Ludus Literarius, the Classical and Grammar School</title> (1815), a Madras system
                        (i.e. one in which advanced students were used to instruct more junior pupils) for teaching the classical languages,
                        originally formulated by Bell in 1808. Southey did not write the projected article for the <title>Quarterly</title>.</note>
                    The subject of modern systems of Education is by no means a barren one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When you send to me do not forget the two last numbers, &#8211; nor the second edition of the Missionary, &#8211; on which I
                    believe <ref target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles</ref> will expect a letter from me, as he told me to expect the
                        book.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Lisle Bowles&#8217; anonymously published <title>The Missionary; A
                            Poem</title> (1813), set in the Andes. A second edition appeared in 1815. Southey did not review it for the
                            <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> Would you like to afford it four or five pages? You may remember that I asked this
                    question upon its first appearance; when (stupidly enough) I had no suspicion of the author. I have all the Spanish books which
                    are necessary for a full knowledge of Chilese history &amp;c.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Penroses Journal has amused me &amp; delighted my children.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Journal of Llewellin Penrose, a Seaman</title>, a fiction (but possibly with some autobiographical basis) now
                        attributed to the American painter William Williams (c. 1710-c. 1790).</note> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Eagle dreamt over that
                    book for the last twenty years of his life, &amp; spent a great deal of time in making drawings for it.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors"> The merchant, classical scholar and amateur artist Thomas Eagles (bap. 1746, d. 1812; <title>DNB</title>) had
                        known William Williams, and possibly planned to publish the <title>Journal</title>. In the event, his son, John Eagles
                        (1783&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>), edited the 4 volume edition published in 1815.</note> I wish the portrait of the author had
                    been prefixed, for the countenance was very striking. How any person can believe that the story has even a foundation of truth is
                    to me wonderful. It is however a very amusing fiction, &amp; likely to prove a popular one, if it be printed in a cheap form for
                    boys, like Robinson Crusoe.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors"> Daniel Defoe (1659/1661&#8211;1731; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Robinson Crusoe</title> (1719).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>