<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2156</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3427</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2156" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2156" type="letter">
        <head>2156. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1812-10-09">9 October 1812</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 12 OC 12/ 1812<lb />Endorsement: 9
                        Octr 1812<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for your news, &#8211; its substance tho not in the Bulletin form, is in the Courier,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The battle of Borodino, or Mojaisk, was reported in the <title>Courier</title>, 7 October 1812. The issue of
                        the newspaper, probably that for 8 or 9 October 1812, that dealt with Wellington&#8217;s entry into Madrid does not survive.</note>
                    &#8211; but I am afraid that Bulletin &amp; all will not quite justify three chears, &#8211; like <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Ld W.s</ref> entrance into Madrid.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Wellington had entered Madrid on 12 August 1812.</note> The great battle is manifestly the battle of Mojaisk,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The battle of Mojaisk, also known as the battle of Borodino, 7 September 1812, saw massive
                        casualties on both sides. Although it was a French tactical victory, in the longer-term Napoleon&#8217;s failure to destroy the
                        Russian army marked a turning point in his campaign in Russia.</note> &#8211; tho the circumstances are <del>xxxxxxx</del>
                    &lt;much&gt; at variance with the French accounts, unhappily <del>xx</del> Buonaparte dates from Mojaisk, &#8211; so that he has
                    evidently not been beaten back. Nevertheless I am satisfied that he has little to boast, &amp; that he may say with Pyrrhus<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> King Pyrrhus of Epirus (319/318&#8211;272 BC), whose army suffered massive casualties in
                        defeating the Romans in the battle of Heraclea, 280 BC. Hence, the phrase, a pyrrhic victory.</note> another such victory will
                    be his ruin: the Russians must ultimately be victorious, if they are neither betrayed not frightened into a peace; <hi rend="ital">till</hi> they are victorious, I confess myself apprehensive of such a result.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Certes, &amp; Certissime,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Certainly, and very certainly&#8217;.</note>
                    Grosvenor, there is nothing which I should like better than to write the history of the Peninsular war,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> was published between 1823&#8211;1832.</note> &#8211; so in
                    whatever you may say to <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford </ref>
          <del> upon the subject</del>, my disposition to the subject must be taken into the account.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The first proof of the Register is on my table.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title> (1812).</note>
          <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">John Ballantyne</ref> is a thorough shuffler. I asked him to make his arrangements so
                    that my drafts might be payable in London instead of Edinburgh: &amp; this he said should be done; &#8211; yet he did not at the same
                    time tell me <hi rend="ital">where</hi> I was to draw upon him, &amp; delays writing I suspect for the purpose of procrastinating
                    my bills. Not that the man is or can be embarrassed, &#8211; but that every delay is so much interest saved. Meantime he has about 110&#163;
                    of mine in his hands, &amp; while he is shuffling I am in want of money. Can you lend me thirty pounds, till I get this fellows
                    address? As soon as it comes I will draw upon him <del>to the full</del> &amp; send you the draft. And most assuredly if he
                    attempts to play me any trick I will have done with him at the end of the volume.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did you receive the Common-Place-Book?<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey might have lent Bedford one
                        of his own common place books; or he could be returning one of Bedford&#8217;s own books; see Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford, 29 September 1812, Letter 2152.</note> &#8211; Your note was duly delivered to Sally Crosthwaite<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Peter Crosthwaite (1735&#8211;1808), was a retired naval commander, publisher of maps and inventor of the aeolian
                        harp. In the 1780s he established the first museum in Keswick. Its treasures included a set of musical stones, a stuffed
                        albatross and a pig with no legs. By 1811 the Museum was run by his son Daniel (c. 1776&#8211;1847), a portrait painter. Sally
                        Crosthwaite might be his sister, Sarah Crosthwaite (1771&#8211;1817).</note> by the hands of <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref>. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Downmans<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Downman (1750&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>), who in autumn 1812
                        painted two portraits of Southey (one commissioned by Murray) and one of Edith.</note> price is ten guineas. He is gone to
                    Newcastle, &amp; did not talk of going to London, &#8211; otherwise he could <del>xxx</del> of course have no objection to copying from
                    a picture.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Concerning <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Marquis Wellington</ref>. I suspect some want of
                    conduct in Clinton<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British officer Henry Clinton (1771&#8211;1829;
                        <title>DNB</title>).</note> who was &lt;left&gt; at Cuellar when <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord
                        W.</ref> went to Madrid, &amp; who let the French advance to Astorga, &amp; bring off their garrison from Toro &amp; Zamora. &#8211;
                    We are clumsy at sieges &amp; do that by lavishing brave blood which ought to be done by sciences: generals who act thus, ought
                        <del>to</del> when they storm a place to put the garrison to the sword. Every Frenchman who might have been thus sacrificed at
                    C Rodrigo would have saved five English at Badajoz.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British took Ciudad Rodrigo on 19
                        January 1812 and Badajoz on 6 April 1812.</note> It seems to me that 2500 men would not have been left by the French at
                    Burgos, unless Massena<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French Marshal Andr&#233; Massena (1758&#8211;1817).</note> meant to make
                    an effort to relieve them: if so there will be another battle, &amp; sans doubt another victory, &#8211; at less expence probably than
                    the Fort itself will cost our <del>xxxxxxx</del> bungling engineers. A<del>n</del> second victory would enable <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord W.</ref> to push on part of his army to Vitoria &amp; seize the stores;
                    the Spaniards might &lt;then&gt; blockade Pamplona, &amp; be these things as they may, I think he will; as soon as he has crippled
                    Massena, march upon Zaragoza,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French had finally taken Zaragoza on 20 February 1809
                        after two lengthy sieges.</note> &#8211; where I think I would give one of my eyes to see his entrance with the other.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should dearly like to write the history of this war, &amp; to make it as compleat as views, portraits, plans
                    &amp; human industry could make it. What fine materials the Countess would procure concerning Zaragoza!<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Countess of Bureta, Mar&#237;a de la Consolaci&#243;n Azlor y Villavicencio (1775&#8211;1814), a Spanish aristocrat who
                        took an active role in the two sieges of Zaragoza in 1808&#8211;1809.</note> But this is a dream &amp; the sooner I wake from it the
                    better. You may &lt;be&gt; sure his Majesty&#8217;s Historiographer<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Stanier Clarke (c. 1765&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), who
                        earlier in 1812 had been appointed Historiographer Royal, a post Southey had coveted.</note> will deal by <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> as he has dealt by Nelson,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Stanier Clarke and John McArthur (1755&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Life of Admiral Lord Nelson, K.B. from his Lordship&#8217;s Manuscripts</title> (1809).</note> &amp; disgrace our
                    military hero as he has done our naval one by a clumsy compilation.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-10-09">Oct 9. 1812.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> I am sorry that <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> stands for Liverpool.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Canning was elected an MP for Liverpool in the general election of 1812. This was a
                            constituency with a large electorate (c. 4,000), compared to the handful of voters at the pocket borough of Old
                            Sarum.</note> A contest with <ref target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> seems to be letting himself
                            down.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Brougham was the Whig candidate for Liverpool. He was not elected.</note>
                        What respectability can he derive from being Member for Liverpool, or what weight in the House? If he sat for Old Sarum he
                        would be <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> still, &amp; Middlesex, Westminster or Yorkshire<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> All popular constituencies with relatively large electorates.</note> could make him nothing
                        more!</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>