<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1872</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3143</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS
                        166.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 305&#8211;306 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1872" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1872" type="letter">
        <head>1872. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1811-02-20">[20 February
                        1811]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsements: RS/ Febry 1811; Circ<hi rend="sup">a</hi> 20: Feby 1811<lb />MS: Huntington Library, RS
                        166<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 305&#8211;306 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have sent me a copious supply &#8211; but <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> as you
                        <del>all</del> ought to allow Pasley<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Charles William Pasley (1780&#8211;1861;
                            <title>DNB</title>), whose <title>Essay on the Military Policy and Institutions of the British Empire</title> (1810) had
                        been sent to Southey for review. His article was deemed by <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> to be
                        &#8216;perfectly incorrect and dangerous&#8217; with the result that the version published in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5 (May
                        1811), 403&#8211;457, was much altered by <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, in consultation with Gifford and <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>; see <ref type="l" target="/reference/qr/index/10.html">Jonathan Cutmore, <title>The Quarterly Review Archive</title>
            </ref>. Southey did not just prescribe Pasley to Wynn, but also to the
                        readers of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>, who were informed: the <title>Essay</title> was &#8216;a book which ought
                        to be in the hand and the heart of every Englishman&#8217;, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 345
                        n*.</note> as much room as Pitt.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801,
                        1804&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>).</note> By the bye that book was written by the other Giffard &#8211; John the Pamphleteer,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The newspaper editor and politician John Giffard (1745&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
                    not William of the Baviad.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Gifford&#8217;s satire <title>The Baviad</title>, first
                        published in 1791.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have it under the hand of <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> that any new Ministry <hi rend="ital">must</hi> recall our troops from Spain &amp; Portugal, &#8211; to which I replied by praying he might stay out of place
                    as long as he thought so, &amp; prescribing Pasley.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pasley had served in Spain and
                        therefore had much to say in his <title>Essay</title> on the conduct of the war in the Iberian peninsular.</note> &#8211; Your
                    account of Frank Moore running with news from the War office to the Chronicle<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francis
                        Moore (1767&#8211;1854), Deputy Secretary at War and brother of the general Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
                    was also told me by <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>, who very properly gave him the appellation of
                    &#8216;half-traitor.&#8221;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When I read L Goldsmiths<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lewis Goldsmith (c. 1763/4&#8211;1846;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Secret History of the Cabinet of Bonaparte</title> (1810).</note> book about France the
                    impression it made upon me was that he was sent over by Buonaparte to further his purpose here God knows by what other means, but
                    specially by publishing such outrageous &amp; absurd stories <hi rend="ital">against</hi> him, as should give his good friends a
                    plea for disbelieving any thing against a man who <del>had</del> was so palpably calumniated. For instance that B. when at the
                    military college poisoned a woman who was with child by him;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Secret History of the Cabinet of Bonaparte</title> (London, 1810), p. 74.</note> &#8211; that &lt;this&gt; <hi rend="ital">is</hi> a lie <hi rend="ital">I</hi> know, because I <del>know</del> happen to have a person resident in the same
                    town,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mrs Keenan, n&#233;e McKinnon (dates unknown), the wife of John Keenan (fl.
                        1780&#8211;1819), portrait painter, whom Southey had met in Exeter in 1799.</note> at whose house B. was in the habit of visiting,
                    &amp; from whom I learnt that his character was exactly what you would suppose, very studious, &amp; very correct. That it <hi rend="ital">must</hi> be a lie is obvious, because such things <del>could x</del> could not be done with more impunity in
                    France than in England, wheels being in use there, &amp; to say that it might have been concealed, leads to the obvious question,
                    if so &lt;then&gt; how came L Goldsmith to know it? &#8211; A still grosser &amp; more ridiculous story is that B. makes his poison by
                    giving arsenic to a pig, <del>&amp;</del> tying the pig up by the hind legs, &amp; collecting what runs from his mouth,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Secret History of the Cabinet of Bonaparte</title> (1810), p. 173 n.*.</note> which is his agua
                        porco-<del>topi</del> tofana.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. the porcine version of aqua tofana, a strong
                        poison reputedly widely used in Naples and Rome in the late seventeenth century.</note> Now the man is no fool, &amp; it is
                    not possible that he can believe this himself, or that he can suppose it can be believed by any person of common sense. For what
                    purpose then can he publish such lies?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If he be the rascal which I take him to be, his newspaper<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Goldsmith had
                        launched a Sunday newspaper, the <title>Anti-Gallican Monitor</title>, earlier in 1811. His backers were rumoured to include
                        supporters of the exiled French monarchy and the British government.</note> I think <del>has</del> already shows what the main
                    purpose is for which he has been sent over. &#8211; To put the Bourbons into Buonapartes hands. He recommends a Bourbon to be
                        <del>sat</del> at the head of the army in Spain, &#8211; a Bourbon to land in France. Now there can be no doubt that this is what B.
                    would above all things desire, &amp; I verily believe this is what this double-died renegade<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Goldsmith had previously produced pro-French, pro-Napoleonic propaganda.</note> is aiming at.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have Leckies book,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gould Francis Leckie (1760&#8211;1850), <title>An
                            Historical Survey of the Foreign Affairs of Great Britain, For the Years 1808, 1809, 1810: With a View to Explain the
                            Causes of the Disasters of the Late and Present War</title> (1810). Leckie had run a farm in Sicily in 1800&#8211;1807 and
                        advocated Anglicizing Sicily and similar islands in order to increase British trade.</note> &#8211; excellent matter put together in
                    so provoking a form that you are tempted at first to throw the volume down. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> knows well, &amp; <hi rend="ital">ought</hi> to have brought forward the main matter of his book immediately
                    on his return from Malta. By the bye <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> knows Pasley too, &amp; might
                    introduce you to him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Should the reviewal<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Of Pasley&#8217;s <title>Essay</title>.</note> prove longer
                    than <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford </ref>
          <hi rend="ital"> can</hi> admit, &#8211; (he will go to the utmost limits for me sans doubt) &#8211; I think the best plan will be to curtail
                    the commercial &amp; financial details, &amp; keep them for a second <del>xxxxx</del> sermon, (a text may easily be found) in
                    which again to preach up a Crusade, according to the true Pasleyan faith. This faith should be preached in all places on every
                    opportunity. If <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> ever did what he ought to do, he would set the
                    Courier to trumpet it. My Register is as much to the same tune as could be expected, &amp; I shall take care to make it perfectly
                    orthodox as it proceeds. The D of York &amp; the plaguey proceedings which grow out of the enquiry,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1809, Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), had been forced to resign
                        as commander-in-chief of the British army in the wake of allegations that he had profited from office trafficking. After a
                        lengthy investigation, the charges were found to be unproven. It had, however, become apparent that his former mistress Mary
                        Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) had received money from individuals keen for her to use her influence with the
                        Duke, and that the Duke himself had known of her actions. For Southey&#8217;s account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 109&#8211;301.</note> Christian Curwen<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1809 the MP for
                        Carlisle, John Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), had introduced a Bill for &#8216;&#8220;better securing the independence
                        and purity of Parliament, by preventing the procuring or obtaining seats by corrupt practices, and likewise more effectually
                        to prevent bribery&#8221;&#8217;. Southey&#8217;s account is in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 249&#8211;281.</note>
                    &amp;c &#8211; <del>have hung</del> hang like a mill stone about the neck of the volume, tho I have done my best to relieve it. These
                    things will swell it to &lt;about&gt; two hundred page beyond the extent of the former <del>year</del> &lt;volume&gt;,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> was concerned enough about the length of the historical section
                        to insist that Southey explained himself to the readers in a prefatory note; see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1809</title> 2.1 (1811), [v]&#8211;vi.</note> &#8211; taking in also the Austrian war<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> See
                        chapters 24&#8211;27 of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 575&#8211;659, on the defeat of Austria by
                        France in 1809.</note> among the extraordinaries of the year. But it will be better than the last, &amp; will I doubt not,
                    establish the work in such a sale, as to make it produce considerable effect upon <del>the</del> public opinion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A name is waiting for the <hi rend="ital">Gr.</hi> &amp; <hi rend="ital">G</hi>r. party,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Whigs, led by Charles Grey, 2nd Earl Grey (1764&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1830&#8211;1834; and
                        the followers of <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William Grenville</ref>, Foreign Secretary 1791&#8211;1801, Prime Minister
                        1806&#8211;1807. &#8216;Gregres&#8217; were idols of wood and clay in West Africa.</note> &#8211; &amp; I think, as they are two wooden idols we might
                    borrow one sufficiently apt from the <hi rend="ital">Gre-gres</hi> of the <del>xxx</del> Negroes. If this were &lt;set&gt; afloat
                    in the Courier it might take.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am glad that the discovery of <del>xxxx</del> Binghams roguery<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        offences for which Bingham was arraigned were summed up in the title of a pamphlet: <title>The Trials of the Rev. Robert
                            Bingham, Curate of Maresfield in Sussex, On a Charge of Sending an Incendiary Letter, and of Setting Fire to His
                            Dwelling-House</title> (1811). Southey&#8217;s conviction of Bingham&#8217;s &#8216;roguery&#8217; could be in response to the report of the case
                        in <title>The Times</title> (5 February 1811), which claimed to provide firm evidence of the clergyman&#8217;s guilt. (Southey could
                        also have been concerned by Bingham&#8217;s involvement in the enclosure of tracts of Ashdown forest in Sussex.) The Bingham case
                        attracted great publicity and, as reported in the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 31 (April 1811), 395, it was claimed that:
                        &#8216;The means taken to influence the public against him by the most scandalous falsehoods, and the treatment he met with in
                        prison, render this one of the most diabolical conspiracies on record&#8217;. For condemnation of <title>The Times</title>&#8217;
                        reporting see the <title>Political Register</title> (4 May 1811), cols 1104&#8211;1110. Bingham was, however, acquitted on both
                        counts.</note> has redeemed Sussex from the imputation of something <del>too</del> &lt;so&gt; much like Irish <del>xxxx</del>
                    barbarity, as to make me feel very uncomfortable when I saw the first story &#8211; here is an impromptu on the clearing up of the
                    mystery &#8211;</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> The <hi rend="ital">i</hi> &amp; the <hi rend="ital">a</hi> should be read <hi rend="ital">a</hi> &amp; <hi rend="ital">i</hi>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent3"> In that Gentlemans name, &#8211; &amp; I&#8217;ll tell you for why; &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Because as for B<hi rend="ital">i</hi>ngh<hi rend="ital">a</hi>m we then should read B<hi rend="ital">a</hi>ngh<hi rend="ital">i</hi>m</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The name will go glibly in rhyme when they hang him.</l>
        </lg>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> farewell</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>