<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2243</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3514</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42551 .  Previously  published: Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 55&#8211;57.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2243" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2243" type="letter">
        <head>2243. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1813-04-09">9 April 1813</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle Street/
                        London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 12 AP 12/ 1813 <lb />Seal: black wax &#8216;S&#8217; and motto<lb />Watermark: C WILMOTT/
                        1807<lb />Endorsement: 1813 July/ Southey R<lb />MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42551 <lb />Previously published: Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 55&#8211;57.</p>
        <epigraph>
          <p>
            <del>To J W C &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c these volumes are respectfully inscribed, as one whose offical situation &lt;knowledge&gt;
                            enables him &lt;rightly&gt; to appreciate their &lt;historical&gt; accuracy, &amp; who as a man &lt;member of the
                            republic&gt; of letters &lt;(himself)&gt; is competent &lt;qualified&gt; to decide upon their &lt;literary&gt; merits or
                            defects, &amp; who as an individual will be disposed to &#8220;weigh errors in the balance of good will.&#8221;</del>
          </p>
          <p>To J. W. C. &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c, who <del>from</del> &lt;by&gt; the official situation which he <del>fills</del> so ably
                        &lt;fills&gt; is qualified to appreciate their historical accuracy, &amp; who as a member of the republic of letters is
                        equally qualified to decide upon their literary merits, these volumes are respectfully inscribed.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A draft of the dedication (to Croker) of Southey&#8217;s <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You can have no conception of the difficulty which it has cost me to lick this clumsy compliment into shape, &#8211;
                    &amp; after all &lt;see&gt; what a bears birth it is!<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> In popular mythology bear cubs were an unformed
                        mass at birth and were licked into shape by their mothers.</note> &#8211; In this respect my nature is an unlucky one, that from a
                    fear of being thought to express more than I feel, I am perpetually expressing less. &#8211; What is written above is equally sincere
                    &amp; awkward; but no time &amp; no dogged labour would avail to mend it. &#8211; If you like it better than the former, &#8211; send it to
                    the printer,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">James Moyes (d. 1839), of Greville St, Hatton Garden, London.</note> &amp; let
                    it be struck off; &#8211; without <del>stop</del> delaying the publication for the sake of sending the proof here. I am perfectly
                    conscious that <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> C.</ref> has a claim upon me for any mark of respect which
                    it is in my power to offer. I must rely upon your kindness to see that the <hi rend="ital">proper form</hi> of address is
                    preserved, &#8211; for of this I am entirely ignorant, &amp; have put the <hi rend="ital">&amp;cs</hi> because I know no better.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been thinking to better purpose about the Cosmography,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> An
                        alternative name for the &#8216;View of the World&#8217; Murray had proposed to Southey; see Robert Southey to John Murray, 31 March 1813,
                        Letter 2238. This project never came to fruition.</note> (a name merely used till a good one is found.) &amp; with the map
                    before me have traced out the line of march. Egypt is clearly the point from where to set out, then the Scripture-Country, &amp;
                    the countries connected with Scripture history &amp; earliest civilization. Here the account should come in of the Jews, who tho
                    they have no local habitation, must have a place somewhere in the work, &amp; this will be the best. And here, I think, it would
                    be desirable to give a sketch of the various eastern systems of &lt;ancient&gt; mythology, which have more or less, leavened
                        <del>xx</del> still-existing superstitions; the system of Zerdusht or Zoroaster, &amp; Manes<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manes (AD 216&#8211;276) founded the dualist religion known as Manicheanism.</note> would form delightful chapters,
                    &amp; with the Rabbinical matter contained in the chapter upon the Jews fitly introduce the general account of the all-swallowing
                    system of <del>xx xx xx</del> Mahommed<del>xxx</del>. &#8211; You will observe that the system is what is here spoken of, the varieties
                    of belief, with the rites &amp; ceremonies will come in in their geographical place. Then come Arabia, Persia, Hindostan, the
                    Burman Empire &#8211; Thibit &#8211; China &#8211; Japan; back by the Philippines &amp; the larger islands to the Maldives &#8211; then to the East
                    African Islands &#8211; Madagascar &#8211; the African shore of the Red Sea. Abyssinia &amp; the surrounding nations barbarous &amp; savage.
                    Round by E Africa to the Cape &amp; on to Senegal. Then the interior &#8211; lastly Morocco &amp; the Piratical states.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Turkey next. Greece &#8211; Albania. Italy. Spain &#8211; France. England. &amp; so up to the remotest North, then Sweden
                    Germany, the Slavonic countries. Russia tho barbarous some Xtians between the Suxine &amp; Caspian. Tartary. Lastly the New World,
                    &amp; the Austral Countries.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Smollets book<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tobias Smollett (1721&#8211;1771; <title>DNB</title>), probably his
                            <title>Compendium of Voyages</title> (1756).</note> never fell in my way. &#8211; You know I am insatiable in my desire of
                    materials, &#8211; thinking indeed that nothing is done while any thing remains undone in the way of research; &amp; much of the first
                    repute of the work must depend on its bearing with it the proofs &lt;of this&gt; as well as the reality <del>xxx xxxx</del> Most
                    of the books being required only for single chapters, may be borrowed as they are wanted &amp; soon returned; but there are some
                    collections which would be in constant requisition. I have &lt;Grynaeus&gt;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Simon Grynaeus
                        (1493&#8211;1541), <title>Novis Orbis Regionum ac Insularum Veteribus Incognitarum</title> (1532), no. 1204 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Hakluyt,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Hakluyt (1552?-1616; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Principall Navigations, Voyages, and Discoveries of the English Nation</title> (1598&#8211;1600), no. 1212 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Churchill,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Awnsham (d. 1728) and John (fl.
                        1695) Churchill, <title>A Collection of Voyages and Travels in Various Parts of the World</title> (1704). Southey owned an
                        edition of 1744&#8211;1745, no. 2675 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; Pinkerton,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pinkerton (1758&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A General Collection of the Best and Most Interesting
                            Voyages and Travels in all Parts of the World</title>, published in 18 volumes between 1808&#8211;1814. Southey&#8217;s copy was no.
                        2335 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> Ramusio,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Giovanni Battista Ramusio
                        (1485&#8211;1557), <title>Navigationi et Viaggi</title> (1550&#8211;1559). Southey owned an early edition (3 vols, 1588, 1583 and 1556),
                        no. 2382 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> Purchas<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Purchas (c.
                            1577&#8211;1626; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Hakluytus Posthumus, or Purchas his Pilgimes</title> (1625).</note> &amp; Thevenot<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean de Th&#233;venot (1633&#8211;1667), <title>Relation de
                            Divers Voyages Curieux qui n&#8217;ont point este Publices, ou qui ont este traduites d&#8217;Hakluyt, de Purchas, et autres</title>
                        (1663&#8211;1672); no. 2675 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> would be wanted; perhaps Harris.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Harris (1666&#8211;1719; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Navigantium atque Itinerarium Bibliotheca, or
                            Complete Collection of Voyages and Travels</title> (1705).</note> I have two volumes of De Bry.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Theodore de Bry&#8217;s (1528&#8211;1598). Southey had copies of his: <title>Peregrinationes</title> (1590),
                            <title>Indorum Floridam</title> (1591), <title>Brasiliae Historia</title> (1691&#8211;1692), <title>Navigatio in Brasiliam
                            Americae</title> (1592) &#8211; bound together as one volume; and <title>Collectiones Perigrinationum in Regnos Africani et
                            Indiae Orientalis</title> (1598&#8211;1601), nos 717&#8211;718 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s Library.</note> The others, with
                        Thevet<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andre de Thevet (1516&#8211;1590), <title>La Cosmographie Universelle</title>
                        (1575), no. 2677 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; some of the rarer &amp; otherwise unattainable
                    books, might be consulted at the Museum. Purchas&#8217;s <hi rend="ital">Pilgrimage</hi> I have, &#8211; not his Pilgrims.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel Purchas, <title>Purchas. His Pilgrimage</title>, n.d., no. 2179 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey's library. None of his works were reprinted until 1905&#8211;1907, though a new edition was advertised as &#8216;in the press&#8217; in 1810.</note> Is the republication of his great work
                    abandoned?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Should this plan take effect, I will not begin seriously upon it, till the B of the Church,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> &amp; the hist. of Brazil<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> are finished; To both of which I shall <del>put in</del> apply tooth
                    &amp; nail, as soon as the Register<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was working on the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1811</title> (1813). This was the last year in which he wrote the historical section of the
                            <title>Register</title>.</note> gives me breathing time. But I would make notes, &amp; begin to collect &amp; sort
                    materials without delay, &#8211; so that every thing would go on rapidly when it was time to weigh anchor &amp; hoist sail.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As the publication of Nelson<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> will not now be long delayed I will take this opportunity of giving
                    directions <del>for</del> concerning the presentation copies. They are so many debts of friendship, or civility. &#8211; Our friend <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>, <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref>, <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Williams Wynn</ref> (Duke Street
                    Westminster) <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>, <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Burney</ref>, <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref>, Lord Radstock,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The naval officer William
                        Waldegrave, 1st Baron Radstock (1753&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> (71 Berners Street) <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John
                        May</ref> (Stert &amp; May 2. New Burlington Street). <ref target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref> 8. Wood
                    Street Cheapside. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Herries</ref>, the Commissary General, &#8211;
                        <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gifford</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Croker</ref>. <ref target="people.html#AbellaManuel">D. Manuel Abella</ref> &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c Cadiz
                    to the care of the Spanish Consul General D Juan Alonso Ortiz 7 Salisbury Street. My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey</ref> 28 <ref target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Queen
                        Anne Street</ref>, Cavendish Square, &amp; <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle the Rev. H. Hill</ref>, <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BrowneWade">Wade Browne Esqr</ref> Ludlow. <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers E</ref> &#8211; Corn Street, Bristol (2 copies) &#8211; <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
          </ref> Norwich. <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> S</ref>, &#8211; &amp; please to send with his copy the volumes of the Quarterly subsequent to those which were sent him
                    a year ago &#8211; I forget to what number they went down, &#8211; but it may be seen by referring to my account. &#8211; Finally six copies here,
                    by coach, &#8211; &amp; the last review may come with them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; I am rejoiced to find that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother</ref> can discover no blunder in the
                    book of sufficient consequence to require notice in an erratum.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A critical account of the best books of Travels would be a proper appendix to the Cosmography. &#8211; I expect to carry
                    the B. of the Church thro the Press in the course of the autumn, &amp; to get Brazil into it <del>xxx</del> in six weeks after the
                    Register is concluded. Once in the press, &#8211; &amp; it never stops for me. &#8211; Whatever form you decide upon for the work, you will
                    probably rather publish a volume at a time, than wait till the whole is compleated. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-04-09">April 9. 1813</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>