<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1783</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3054</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Mitchell Library, Glasgow.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1783" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1783" type="letter">
        <head>1783. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ElliottEbenezer">Ebenezer Elliott</ref>, <date when="1810-06-05">5 June
                        1810</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> E Elliott Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./
                        Rotherham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Mitchell Library, Glasgow<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1810-06-05"> June 5. 1810</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter of Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> ought not to have been so long unacknowledged.
                    The truth is that my time is very much occupied, &amp; I have but little leisure for correspondence, &#8211; nevertheless I ought to have
                    replied to your last, on account of the <del>xxxxxxx</del> bill which it contained, because my silence may perhaps have led you to
                    suppose that I was in some degree offended. Certainly it was by no means my intention in sending you a copy of Madoc<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> that you should pay me for it, &#8211; nor should you have done so. To have sent back the note
                    would have hurt you, &amp; implied <del>xx</del> a displeasure which I did not feel, &#8211; as however you have overpaid by seven
                    shillings that which was intended as a mark of respect to a man of genius, &#8211; you must allow me to send you the poem which I have
                    in the press &amp; which will appear in the course of two or three months.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> You will find something unlike any poem which you have never seen before, &#8211;
                    by examining its structure &amp; versification you may derive some advantage in your own compositions, by learning what faults you
                    have to avoid. That spirit of criticism which looks only for faults, &amp; delights in exaggerating &amp; ridiculing them, is more
                    mischievous to the critic who employs it, than to the author on whom it is employed: &#8211; the man who suffers himself to be actuated
                    by such a spirit, if he does not begin with an incapacity of feeling what is good, is sure to render himself incapable as he
                    proceeds. But if you read other poems in the same temper with which you scrutinized Madoc, every great work which you peruse will
                    render you more equal to the task which you have projected for yourself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>&amp;</del> I have not, I fear, made myself quite intelligible as to what I consider the laws of blank verse. <del>It is of
                        no consequence</del> whatever be the number of syllables they must not be more than ten to the ear, or <del>x</del> eleven if
                    the line ends with a trochee, <del>xx</del> which is very frequent in our dramatic blank verse, &amp; makes its main difference
                    from that of the epic. Thus in the often quoted instance</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">And many an amorous, many a humorous lay<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> An example widely quoted in
                            eighteenth century manuals of prosody.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>there are fourteen syllables, but they run into each other so as not to take up more time than ten. A line with fewer than ten
                        <del>xxxxxxx</del> is inadmissable, &#8211; your<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Elliott had presumably sent Southey some of
                        his verse. The lines quoted in this letter were not published.</note>
        </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">In prospect, There too serpents strayd</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <del>That which foll</del>
        </p>
        <p>is defective, that which follows it is redundant</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">And vast, &amp; dreadly-lovely hissing wove i&#8217;the sun</l>
        </lg>
        <p>remove the two syllables which begin the line &#8211; to the end of the former &amp; both are then legitimate. Some of your lines in this
                    specimen are not reducible to any laws of metre, nor is it possible so to read them as to make them harmonious.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> Climes unexplord. Mountains gloomy as night</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Mountains enormous immeasurable, frownd</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <del>The first of</del> &lt;Both&gt; these <del>is</del> &lt;lines are&gt; so unmusical that I should not venture them
                        <del>to</del> But there need no rules upon this subject, &#8211; your own ear &amp; the study of good poets must lead you right.
                    Read them for yourself, &amp; never take the opinion of a critic, whether dead or living, <del>x</del> upon their merits, as
                    valid, till you <del>xxx xxxx</del> see that the passage to which he refers when examined in its place will bear him out.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall be glad to hear that you are thinking seriously of the American poem,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Elliott&#8217;s unrealised plan for a poem on the British conquest of Canada in 1759&#8211;1763; see Southey to Ebenezer
                        Elliott, 1 August 1810, Letter 1796.</note> &#8211; that you have conceived its characters, &#8211; sketchd the outline, &#8211; &amp; are at
                    work upon it. Have you seen the Lady of the Lake?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>Lady of the Lake</title>
                        (1810).</note> &#8211; It pleases me on the whole better than either of <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scotts</ref> former
                        poems,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Lay of the Last Minstrel</title> (1805) and <title>Marmion</title> (1808).</note> the situations are more
                        <del>forc</del> striking, &amp; there is a worthier interest excited. Its metre seems to me less happy, &#8211; the regularity seems
                    to have tempted him to throw off many incorrect expressions &amp; feeble lines. There is one lesson <del>xxx</del> which you
                    should especially learn from our great poets, &#8211; that of purity of style, &#8211; &amp; the charm of giving not only a meaning, but its
                    own <del>mean</del> peculiar meaning to every word, &#8211; in which almost all your contemporaries are grievously, most grievously
                    deficient. Campbell&#8217;s Gertrude<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Campbell (1777&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Gertrude of Wyoming</title> (1809).</note> has scarcely a sentence of good English in it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have begun a poem in blank verse upon Pelayo,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pelayo (c. 685&#8211;737),
                        founder of the Kingdom of Asturias, who is credited with beginning the Christian reconquest of the Iberian peninsula from the
                        Moors. The poem eventually mutated into <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> the founder of the
                    Spanish Kingdom, a noble subject, &#8211; a single canto is all that is yet written. I never allow myself any other time for poetry than
                    what is fairly won from sleep in the morning, &#8211; so that my progress is necessarily slow. History is my favourite employment, &#8211; the
                    quiet interest which it excites is more congenial to me now than any thing which affects &amp; agitates me. This sort of feeling
                    comes with the first grey hairs.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> farewell</salute>
          <salute rend="indent4"> yours very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>