<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2370</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3641</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d.110 .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2370" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2370" type="letter">
        <head>2370. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1814-01-25">25 January
                        1814</date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand] Rhuabon January Twenty
                            <del>eight</del> &lt;nine&gt;/ 1814/ The Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. N. Lightfoot/ Crediton/ C W Williams Wynn<lb />Stamped:
                        RHUABON<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d.110<lb /> Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-01-25">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 25. 1814.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Lightfoot</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was in London when your letter was written, &amp; since my return have delayed answering it too long. Thank you
                    for your congratulations, &#8211; the emoluments of the Laureateship are very trifling, they were raised for Ben Jonson<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ben Jonson (1572&#8211;1637; <title>DNB</title>), who held the Laureateship 1616&#8211;1637.</note> from 100
                    marks to 100 pounds &amp; a tierce of Spanish Canary Wine: they have been diminished since by a commutation which allows &#163;26
                    instead of the wine. This commutation, like the salary, is subject to property tax, <hi rend="ital">land-tax</hi>,
                    shilling-in-the-pound, sixpence-in-the-pound, &amp; heaven knows what taxes beside, which reduce the whole to a net income of 90&#163;.
                    I have vested it in a life-policy &amp; thus converted it into a <del>legacy</del> post-obit for my children. The newspaper
                    accounts of my appointment were partly true, but for the greater part mere falsehoods. Upon Pyes<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The politician and poet Henry James Pye (1745&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), Poet Laureate from 1790&#8211;1813. He died
                        on 11 August 1813.</note> death the succession, unknown to me, was asked for me by <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Croker</ref>, &amp; given by the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref>. Meantime
                        <ref target="people.html#HertfordLord">Lord Hertford</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lord Liverpool</ref>
                    had consulted together &amp; offered it to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>. Scott &amp; I have long been
                    friends: he declined it, urging that it might be conferred on me, &amp; writing at the same time to me to urge that I would accept
                    it. The long delay which intervened before the appointment was gazetted arose from a long series of punctilios of office, &amp;
                    the customary management of <del>persons</del> &lt;men&gt; in power who contrive when any thing, however trifling, is to be given
                    away, that as many persons as possible may take credit to themselves for disposing of it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you knew my dear <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> what pleasure it gives me to hear
                    from you, you would <del>let me</del> make our communication more frequent. Of the men with whom I became intimate at Oxford, you
                    only are left, &#8211; &amp; as I believe <del>xxx</del> our regard for each other continued to increase as long as we lived together, I
                    am well assured that since we separated it has undergone no diminution. I long to see you, your wife,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bridget Prideaux (dates unknown).</note> &amp; your children, &amp; to become acquainted with my
                    god-daughter.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Frances Jane (Fanny) Lightfoot (1806&#8211;1882).</note> I also have
                    five children,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate Southey</ref>.</note> the only <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">boy</ref>
                    among them is in his eighth year. And I also am a schoolmaster, for I teach him Greek, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">his eldest sister</ref> Latin &amp; Spanish. You ask me my opinion of public schools. As
                    far as relates to morals, <del>I can xxxxxxx</del> &amp; as far as my experience of both went, they were rather better than worse
                    than private ones. Indeed nothing could be worse than the only private one at which I ever was a boarder.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The school at Corston that Southey attended in 1781&#8211;1782 and which he commemorated in &#8216;The Retrospect&#8217;. He was
                        removed when his family discovered his head had become infested with lice.</note> And I think that at Westminster there was a
                    certain openness of character, a certain manliness of feeling &amp; a boyish <del>spirit</del> sense of honour communicated, which
                    private schools can hardly give. But in your case I should finish a sons education myself. I can see but one valid reason for
                    sending him from home &#8211; which is lest he should <del>xxx</del> think of you more as a schoolmaster than a father, &#8211; &amp; of this
                    there can be little danger, unless you are woefully changed since you began to wield the birchen sceptre. So far indeed as other
                    schools may have exhibitions, scholarships &amp;c <del>xxxxxxxxx</del> to bestow, they may hold out some inducement. &#8211; But I have
                    ever regarded Tiverton<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Blundell&#8217;s School in Tiverton, Devon, founded in 1604. Old boys
                        could proceed to Balliol College, Oxford or Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge through &#8216;closed&#8217; scholarships provided by the
                        school&#8217;s founder.</note> with horror from the specimens which it sent to Balliol in our time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Douglas spent a day with me about three years ago, with a wife whom he had just married.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr James Douglas (1775&#8211;1846) of Kelso, an old friend of Southey&#8217;s from Balliol College, Oxford. He had married Frances, daughter of James Robson of Samieston, in
                        Edinburgh, on 10 December 1810.</note> He was settled at Kelso on his paternal property, &amp; practising as a Physician. The
                    elder Moncrieffe<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Wellwood Moncrieff (c. 1775&#8211;1813) had died on 5 September 1813. He was a contemporary of Southey&#8217;s at Balliol College, Oxford. The eldest son
                        of Sir Henry Wellwood Moncrieff, 8th Baronet (1750&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), he had been His Majesty&#8217;s Advocate in the
                        Admiralty Court at Malta.</note> died a few months ago &#8211; He <del>was</del> held some official situation at Malta, &amp; wore
                    out his constitution by habitual excesses: he came to England in hope of amendment, &amp; when he arrived found that the ship had
                    to perform quarantine. In his state of debility this proved fatal to him. Could he have landed his life might certainly have been
                    prolonged, if not preserved. His brother<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir James Wellwood Moncrieff, 9th Baronet
                        (1776&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), younger brother of William Wellwood Moncrieff and later a Judge of the Court of Session. He, too, was a contemporary of Southey&#8217;s at Balliol College, Oxford.</note> has probably by this time followed him. When I was in town I heard that he was going out to Madeira,
                    far gone in consumption.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wish I could persuade you to give me your next holydays. It is a long way, &#8211; &amp; yet &lt;<del>xxxx xx xxx
                        xxxx</del>&gt; persons come every year as far to see the Lakes, who have nothing but the scenery to tempt them. When I have
                    travelled hither from Bristol I have gone two nights successively in the mail, &amp; arrived here in 45 hours: but there are day
                    coaches which would bring you (from Bristol) in three days &amp; a half. You would find me less changed than most men in the
                    course of twenty years, &#8211; &amp; more changed in any thing than in manners, &#8211; for I am as noisy a fellow as ever, &amp; if I had a
                    neighbour with such a tempting round hole opposite his chamber door, as that in Old C&#230;sar,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> A building in the grounds of Balliol College, Oxford. It derived its name from the fact that it was opposite another college
                        building known as &#8216;Pompey&#8217;.</note> I should enjoy throwing stones thro it as heartily as in old times. I can ask you with a
                    safe conscience to come &amp; see me, because the sight of this country would alone repay the journey. Come <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> &amp; see what effects the good &amp; the evil of twenty years have
                    wrought upon one whom you knew in the stirring season of his life, &#8211; <del>xxx</del> who, God be praised, is not the worse for the
                    fermentation which he went thro. &amp; who feels himself better &amp; happier for all the difficulties he has undergone,
                        <del>&amp; will with xxxxxx xxxxx xxxxx xxxx xxxxxxx xxxxx xxxx</del> Remember me to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L with whom some
                    day or other I trust to be better acquainted, &amp; believe me my dear friend</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs with sincere affection</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> [signature cut off]</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>