<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2057</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3328</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2057" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2057" type="letter">
        <head>2057. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1812-03-10">10 March
                        1812</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry
                        <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmarks: [partial] 10 o&#8217;Clock/ MR 13/ 1812; E/ 13 MR 13/ 1812<lb />Seal: Partial, red
                        wax.<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-03-10">March 10. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been called from home for three days by poor <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref>, who was
                    miserably ill with a nervous disease, little short of derangement, &amp; fancied it would do him good to see me. <ref target="people.html#PembertonSophia">His wife</ref> was in hourly expectation of being brought to bed, &#8211; he had within six
                    weeks lost two brothers &amp; a sister,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Lloyd (1779&#8211;1811), a merchant in
                        Birmingham; Robert Lloyd (1778&#8211;1811), partner in the high quality booksellers, printers and publishers, Knott &amp; Lloyd; and
                        Caroline Lloyd (1790&#8211;1811). All died of typhus in September-October 1811.</note> &amp; the surviving branches of his family
                    were not in a state to go to him. &#8211; This was neither a seasonable nor a pleasant interruption.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 5 March 1812, Letter 2053.</note> However I left him materially
                    better, when I was relieved by a friend of <ref target="people.html#PembertonSophia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Ll.</ref> from
                        Warwickshire.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Miss Hawkes of Birmingham.</note> Letters &amp; proofs accumulated
                    during my absence &amp; I have had no leisure till now for making my norabuena<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        &#8216;Felicitation&#8217;.</note>. to my new cousin. Oliver is a good name, &amp; the reason for it very much to my liking. Wither is not
                    a good one, <del>xxxx</del> you cannot vociferate it conveniently, &amp; it does not suit with Hill. If you will have a family
                    name you must go back to Bradford,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Herbert Hill&#8217;s maternal grandfather (and thus Southey&#8217;s
                        great-grandfather) had the surname Bradford. John Foxe (1517&#8211;1587; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Actes and Monuments</title>
                        (1563) recounted the sufferings of the evangelical preacher and martyr John Bradford (c. 1510&#8211;1555;
                        <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; which the Book of Martyrs has made respectable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To night I send back the concluding sheets of my Book of <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">Bell</ref> &amp; the
                        <ref target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Dragon</ref> which a few days will bring forth.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>The Origin, Nature and Object, of the New System of Education</title> (1812), an expansion of
                        his advocacy of <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">Bell</ref> in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 6 (August 1811),
                        264&#8211;304.</note> I have desired <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to send you four copies, &#8211; one of them you
                    may give to your neighbour M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Davies.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Reynold Davies (c. 1750&#8211;1820),
                        Curate of Streatham. He kept a school for young boys which he called his &#8216;University&#8217;.</note> It is the paper from the
                    Quarterly, altered in some points, &amp; extended in others, so as to be about doubled in length.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Book of the Church<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> This project finally became the <title>Book of the
                            Church</title> (1824).</note> is not likely to make much progress till the Register<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title> (1812).</note> is off my hands. I have a very distinct perception of its
                    parts &amp; proportions, &amp; see no difficulty any where. The object is not to convince the reader of the Church articles, but
                    to interest him in the Church History, &#8211; to show what the benefits of the Establishment are, how dearly &amp; hardly they were
                    purchased, &amp; how zealously they ought to be upheld. This I shall do with perfect sincerity: &amp; where it may be necessary to
                    speak of points of doctrine it certainly will not be necessary to make it appear that the writer is one who does not find the
                    Church doors wide enough for himself. &#8211; Unless I <del>am</del> greatly deceive myself it will be a very useful as well as an
                    interesting book.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has got the Peruvian book<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Descripcion
                        de las Provincias Pertenecientes al Arzobispado di Lima&#8217;; no. 3645 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, inscribed in
                        his hand: &#8216;This book of which perhaps a duplicate is nowhere to be found, was given me by Mr Murray; it contains the fullest
                        account which has yet been published on the old Vice-royalty of Peru, province by province. The information was obtained from
                        the respective Corregidores, and printed for many successive years in the Lima Almanack, from whence some curioso cut out the
                        whole collection, and formed them into this <hi rend="ital">most valuable volume</hi>&#8217;.</note> from its owner &amp; given it
                    me. I mean to give him a series of articles in the Q. upon Spanish America beginning with Humboldt,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Alexander von Humboldt (1769&#8211;1859), especially his <title>Essai Politique sur la Nouvelle Espagne</title>
                        (1811), published with accompanying <title>Atlas Geographique et Physique</title> (1811). Southey did not review these for the
                            <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> &#8211; Mexico, Venezuela, Peru, Chile, &amp; the Plata provinces furnishing each a separate
                    paper, &#8211; reserving the Plata for the last that it may have the overflowings of my History.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> The politics of these colonies I leave to Blanco who is preparing an
                    article upon that subject for the next number,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Blanco White&#8217;s review of William Walton
                        (1783/4&#8211;1857; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Present State of the Spanish Colonies; Including a Particular Report of Hispanola,
                            or the Spanish Part of Santo Domingo</title> (1810), appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (June 1812),
                        235&#8211;264.</note> &#8211; what I can say about it must be said in the Register.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813), 367&#8211;421.</note> &#8211; I have sent off the first part of a reviewal of
                    the Iceland travellers for the next number, &amp; shall also review Count Julian.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir
                        George Steuart Mackenzie (1780&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in the Island of Iceland, in the Summer of the Year
                            1810</title> (1811); reviewed by Southey alongside Sir William Jackson Hooker (1785&#8211;1865; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Journal of a Tour in Iceland, in the Summer of 1809</title> (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (March
                        1812), 48&#8211;92. Southey&#8217;s review of Walter Savage Landor&#8217;s <title>Count Julian</title> (1812) appeared in <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 8 (September 1812), 86&#8211;92.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#GoodenJames">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Goodens</ref> books are upon the road &amp; ought to have arrived if
                    punctuality could be calculated upon from the carriers.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Robert Southey to Herbert
                        Hill, 1 February 1812 (Letter 2027; where the books are detailed) and Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, [early May 1812] (Letter
                        2089; written following their arrival).</note> This &#8211; by a round about association leads me to <del>xxx</del> tell you that
                    the reason why <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> people did not send Mr Withers<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> A relative of Herbert Hill by marriage. Probably Herbert Hill&#8217;s father-in-law, Lovelace Bigg-Wither (c.
                        1742&#8211;1813), or his son, Harris Bigg-Wither (1781&#8211;1833). One of them had ordered the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1809</title> (1811).</note> Register according to order is explained, &#8211; they either never received my letter, or mislaid
                    &amp; forgot it, &#8211; for it contained other orders which in like manner were never executed, &amp; which they say they never
                    received.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I expect to finish the Register in April. You will find in it some good remarks furnished by <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> upon the Parliamentary Economists Bankes &amp; Co &#8211; .<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Bankes (1757&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Corfe Castle 1780&#8211;1826. Southey expressed his disapproval
                        of Bankes&#8217;s campaign to abolish sinecures and the granting of reversion to state offices in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register,
                            for 1810</title>, 3.1 (1812), 207&#8211;218.</note> I have just got thro the Madras business,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> A mutiny by European officers in the East India Company&#8217;s Madras Army in 1809. <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register, for 1810</title>, 3.1 (1812), 260&#8211;281, for Southey&#8217;s account.</note> &#8211; which ought to have been terminated by
                    shooting some of the officers, &amp; displacing Sir G Barlowe,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir George Hilaro Barlow
                        (1763&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>), Governor of Madras 1807&#8211;1813. He was recalled in 1812 and there was much controversy about
                        his actions during the mutiny of 1809.</note> for the misconduct of one party is no excuse for the other. <ref target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blancos</ref> Journal<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Blanco edited
                            <title>Seminario Patriotico</title> in Seville 1808&#8211;1810.</note> has enabled me to give a <del>xxx</del> satisfactory view
                    of the proceedings of the Central Junta,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The supreme authority in those parts of Spain
                        not under French control in September 1808-January 1810.</note> &amp; I am well provided with documents for all the events of
                    the year in Spain &amp; Portugal. &#8211; As for my poem<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> it proceeds as slowly as if a Spaniard were the author instead
                    of the hero. I am only in the fifth book: it will advance more rapidly as the days lengthen.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your information concerning Windhams papers came too late. I have never seen <ref target="people.html#AmyotThomas">Amyot</ref> but he was the means of procuring me some valuable material last
                    year respecting Romanas<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish general Pedro Caro y Sureda, 3rd Marquis of la Romana
                        (1761&#8211;1811).</note> movements, &amp; sent me several letters of Carrols<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> William
                        Parker Carrol (1776&#8211;1842), liaison officer between the British and Spanish forces. Later promoted to Major-General and Field
                        Marshal in the Spanish Army.</note> in answer to certain queries.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember us to <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &#8211; I hope <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">the man</ref> &amp; the <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">young man</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#HillErrol">the infant</ref> are as well as my young ones &#8211; better they cannot be.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>