<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2112</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3383</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary
                        Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), 405&#8211;408.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 278&#8211;80.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2112" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2112" type="letter">
        <head>2112. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1812-06-09">9 June 1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Barker/ Teddesley/ Penkridge/ Staffordshire<lb />Postmark:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary
                        Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), 405&#8211;408<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 278&#8211;80.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-06-09">June 9. 1812</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Senhora,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The first frank is carefully deposited in my desk till you come for it. I am sincerely glad of <ref target="people.html#Hatherton">the young knight&#8217;s</ref> election<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward John Littleton
                        (later Lord Hatherton) had been elected unopposed as Tory MP for Staffordshire in a by-election in May 1812. His Whig
                        opponent, Sir John Wrottesley (1771&#8211;1841), MP for Lichfield 1799&#8211;1806, Staffordshire 1823&#8211;1832, Staffordshire South 1832&#8211;1837,
                        declined to go to the poll after a lengthy canvas of his support among the voters (owners of freehold land worth 40<hi rend="ital">s</hi>. per annum).</note> &amp; had I been a Staffordshire freeholder would have given him a vote, in spite
                    of his youth, &#8212; an objection, weighty as it is, of less moment than the political principles of his opponent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward&#8217;s</ref> will seems to have been in all its provisions, perfectly
                    conformable to his life, &#8212; that is, all that it ought to have been.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Sir Edward
                        Littleton&#8217;s will Mary Barker was bequeathed &#163;500, an annuity of &#163;200 and all the gifts and furniture that Sir Edward had
                        bought for her use. His main heir was Edward John Littleton (later Lord Hatherton).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My wicked summer cold has taken up its quarters with me, &amp; will no doubt torment me for many weeks. It brings
                    with it much discomfort, but, thank God does not disable me, &amp; is less accompanied by any general indisposition than one would
                    suppose possible from so violent a local affection. Last year I escaped it by setting out on a long journey just as it was
                    beginning.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have my eye upon that ugly house opposite, &#8212; which ugly as it is without, would become a pleasant object if it
                    can ever be got for you. <ref target="people.html#SunderlinLord">Lord Sunderlin</ref> (a brother of Malone)<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund Malone (1741&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), the editor of Shakespeare and friend of Johnson,
                        Boswell and Burke.</note> has it for three years, one of which is expired, &#8212; he took it for the sole purpose of resting a few
                    weeks every year on his way from Ireland, &#8212; but he is a very old man &amp; may very likely drop his lease, &#8212; or drop himself. He
                    left it in August last year, &amp; lent it to the Bp of Meath:<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Lewis O&#8217;Beirne
                        (1749&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Meath from 1798 until his death. Originally a Whig, he was by this time more
                        conservative and a noted defender of the Church of Ireland.</note> very likely he may be disposed to let it this autumn. It
                    would suit you well, &#8212; There is land belonging to it, which may probably be had, &amp; the communication by land would be easy,
                    &amp; better still by lake.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do not send off anything but what is wanted for your own use, for this House tho rather of larger dimensions than a
                    nutshell, is almost as full as one. <ref target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Martha</ref> is coming next week, &amp; <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref>, &#8212; &amp; what is worse the boys holidays begin. &#8212; I shall march off with
                        <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> early in July for Durham, &#8212; &amp; the holydays luckily have an end as
                    well as a beginning. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> is grown a great fellow, all beard &amp; eyes,
                    &#8212; as odd &amp; as extraordinary as ever he was, with very good disposition, but with ways &amp; tendencies which will neither be
                    to his own happiness, nor to the comfort of any body connected with him. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref>
                    contrary to all former appearances, is much weaker in body, &#8212; he is very tractable, may be made anything, &#8212; whereas <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> is of such unmalleable materials that what he may make of himself God
                    knows, but I suspect, nobody will be able to mould or manage him. &#8212; You will be much pleased with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> , who may best be characterised by calling him a sweet boy. &#8212; You can hardly
                    conceive anything more gentle &amp; more docile. He has just learnt his Greek alphabet &amp; is so desirous of learning, so
                    attentive, &amp; so quick of comprehension, that if it please God he should live, there is little doubt but that something will
                    come out of him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have long had many day dreams of what was to be done when you came to reside among us. One has been of a poem or
                    series of poems about this country, for which you were to make drawings, &#8212; so as to make a splendid book.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> This project was never completed.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you get off as soon as you expect &#8212; we may look for you early next week. &#8212; I had nearly forgotten what you say
                    about the Island. &#8212; it does not seem to me the kind of thing that could be asked.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Miss
                        Barker apparently asked about the possibility of using <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General Peachy&#8217;s</ref> house
                        on Derwent Island.</note> God bless you. Come speedily, &amp; cure me of my cold, &#8212; for you know you have undertaken to cure
                    every body. &#8212; I must go to work upon this endless Register,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title> (1812).</note> &#8212; hoping &amp; trusting to finish the third volume this
                    week, &#8212; after which the first letter from Edinburgh will be to press me to lose no time in beginning the fourth.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813).</note> There is the difference between my labour &amp; that of a
                    millers horse, that he goes round &amp; round, &amp; that I go straight forward, &#8212; but both of us are likely to be kept working as
                    long as our strength lasts. Well! &amp; if the horse likes it as well as I do, he has no reason to complain.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent6"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent8"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> We are afraid Neddy<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> William White&#8217;s (d. 1811) former mistress and
                            heiress, and Southey&#8217;s neighbour.</note> will marry before she goes to London, in which case it is to be feared marriage
                        will not rid us of our neighbours. I want Mr White to come for her a-la-Lenora:<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In
                            Gottfried August B&#252;rger (1747&#8211;1794). <title>Leonore</title> (1773), Lenore&#8217;s lover returns from the grave to claim
                            her.</note> if he came belly &amp; all<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8220;Belly-gerant&#8221;, Southey&#8217;s nickname for the
                            late William White (d. 1811).</note> he *** make such a Ghost as was never seen before.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>