<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1927</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3198</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1927" type="letter">
        <head>1927. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1811-05-29">29 May
                        1811</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ St Helens/ Bishops Auckland/
                        Durham.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1811-05-29">May 29. 1811</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am still hard at work, &#8211; but I believe it may now be said confidently that (if nothing unforeseen should occur)
                    we shall start on Monday June 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> that is &lt;next&gt; Monday week. We mean on the way up to stage it as far
                    as we can, &amp; go by way of Kendal &amp; Leeds to Nottingham where we shall &lt;stay&gt; four &amp; twenty hours for the sake of
                    seeing <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">K Whites</ref> family, &#8211; so that I suppose, we shall not reach <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> before the Saturday.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This will be a very good volume of the Register, &amp; so it ought to be by the length of time which it has cost.
                    544 pages printed, &amp; I believe it will run hard upon 800!<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was right, the
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811) ran to 797 pages plus a 24-page appendix.</note> to the
                    great dismay of the publishers. Even then I am compelled to put off till next year the disturbances in the E Indies, &#8211; a chapter
                    upon our infatuated conduct in Sicily, &#8211; the rise &amp; progress of the Guerrilla system in Spain, &#8211; &amp; a view of the conduct
                    of the Supreme Junta,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.1 (1812), 260&#8211;281, dealt with the Madras &#8216;mutiny&#8217; by British troops in
                        1809; 472&#8211;481, with the guerrilla forces in Spain; and 353&#8211;380, reviewed the conduct of the Supreme Junta. British policy
                        towards the Bourbon regime in Sicily was only mentioned in passing and had to wait until <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 422&#8211;437.</note> &#8211; all subjects which <hi rend="ital">may</hi> stand over without any manifest
                    impropriety, but which, had I been writing leisurely, would have made part of this years annals.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I differ from you about the Bullion Question.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Whether Britain&#8217;s paper
                        currency should be convertible into gold. For Southey&#8217;s later account, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1
                        (1813), 89&#8211;114.</note> &amp; in nothing are you more wrong than in supposing it to be wholly decided as a party
                        <del>question</del> &lt;matter&gt; in the House. &#8211; Vansittart<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Nicolas Vansittart, 1st
                        Baron Bexley (1766&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), who became Chancellor of the Exchequer on 20 May 1812. He was opposed to an
                        early return to convertability.</note> the main speaker <del>upon</del> on the side of the practical men, being not a
                    ministerialist, but of Lord Sidmouths<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The former Prime Minister, Henry Addington, 1st
                        Viscount Sidmouth (1757&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>), who became Home Secretary in 1812.</note> party, &#8211; &amp; the question being
                    one upon which political oeconomists are now driven to confess themselves very much in the dark. <ref target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">Koster</ref> has given me the only light I have yet found upon the subject, he I think
                    has demonstrated that the ideal pound must be the true standard of value, &amp; that the price of gold, like that of every thing
                    else, varies according to the proportion between the demand &amp; the supply.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Theodore Koster, <title>A Short Statement of the Trade in Gold Bullion: Shewing the True Causes of the General Scarcity and
                            Consequent High Price on that Precious Metal: Also Demonstrating that the Notes of the Bank of England are Not
                            Depreciated</title> (1810). It went into a second edition in 1811, and Koster followed this with <title>Further
                            Observations on Bullion and Bank Notes</title> (1811).</note> Now the consumption has increased, probably 500 fold, within
                    the last <del>xxx</del> 20 or 30 years, &#8211; &amp; the supply has stopt, almost wholly. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> About the D of York I entirely agree with you as to the impropriety &amp; indecency of his reappointment, &#8211; but
                    with respect to Parliament the remedy which you would apply is worse than the disease. The voice of the people is heard there, &#8211;
                    witness his forced resignation.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827;
                            <title>DNB</title>), had been reappointed as commander-in-chief of the British army in May 1811. He had previously held
                        the post from 1798&#8211;1809, but had been forced to resign in the wake of allegations that he had profited from office
                        trafficking. After a lengthy investigation, the charges were found to be unproven. It had, however, become apparent that his
                        former mistress Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) had received money from individuals keen for her to use
                        her influence with the Duke, and that the Duke himself had known of her actions. For Southey&#8217;s account of this earlier
                        scandal, see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 109&#8211;301.</note> Make all elections popular &amp;
                    public opinion would instantly become despotic, &#8211; a despotism of all others the most cruel. At present public opinion has just the
                    sway which it ought to have; the evil it does by crippling the executive in its foreign transaction is more than counterbalanced
                    by the public morality it enforces.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Very likely the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> has an object in view in this appointment
                    which the ministers are from suspecting. The King<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of the
                        United Kingdom 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>). He had been incapable of conducting public business since October 1810.</note>
                    is not likely to recover (so <ref target="people.html#BunburySirHenryEdward">Col. Bunbury</ref> told me) &#8211; &amp; the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref>, as soon as that point is established looks on to bringing his own party
                    into power. It <del>will</del> &lt;is&gt; not <del>be</del> inconsistent with his character to suspect that he gladly makes these
                    present men take upon themselves the odium of a measure which reconcile the country to seeing them turned out.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">Aunt Mary</ref> tells me to enquire about the money (between 2 &amp; 300&#163;) arising from the
                    sale of the plate &amp; furniture at Fitzhead,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> An estate belonging to Southey&#8217;s distant
                        cousin, Cannon Southey (d. 1768). His exceptionally complex will led to much litigation.</note> which according to her account
                    was by order of Chancery placed in the funds &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> T. S.</ref>
                    enjoying the interest during his life, &amp; then the principal to be claimed by <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John&#8217;s</ref> heir at law.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I mean when in town to get acquainted with <ref target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco</ref> the editor of
                    El Espa&#241;ol,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>El Espa&#241;ol</title>, the Spanish-language political journal established by Blanco White, with the discrete encouragement
                        of the British Foreign Office. Published in London, the first number had appeared in May 1810; it ran until 1814.</note> &#8211;
                    &amp; likewise if possible to get at the correspondence of the Guerrilla chiefs with our Government. They are doing great things.
                        Mina<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Francisco Espoz y Mina (1781&#8211;1836), since 1810 he had been commander of the
                        guerrilleros of Navarre against French troops.</note> has not less than 6000 men in Navarre, with whom he almost commands the
                    province, the Empecinado<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Juan Martin Diez (1775&#8211;1825) (&#8216;El Empecinado&#8217;, &#8216;the Undaunted&#8217;),
                        guerilla leader who by 1811 commanded some 3000 men and attacked French communications between Madrid and Burgos.</note> also
                    is very strong. <ref target="people.html#AbellaManuel">Abella</ref> tells me he had just cut off 400 French in Guadalaxara, &#8211;
                    which is only one short step from Madrid. I got a letter from <hi rend="ital">mi buen amigo</hi>
          <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;My good friend&#8217;.</note> a day or two ago, &#8211; with little more than the news of his safe arrival &amp; that
                    every thing was going on most prosperously. I am writing to him for more documents &amp;c.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Mark the extract from Hutchinson.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a passage in the work of
                        William Hutchinson (1732&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), topographer and writer on Durham and the Lake District.</note> I fancy
                        Amadis<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s 1803 translation of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>. It was not
                        reprinted.</note> is out of print, but not likely to be reprinted, till I make a collection of my operas, &#8211; if I ever live to
                    make one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> has sent me a print of Manuella Sanchez &#8211; one of the Zaragozan heroines, who
                    fell in the second siege.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manuella Sanchez (d. 1809), one of many Spanish women who
                        distinguished themselves in the defence of Zaragoza. She was shot through the heart. For Southey&#8217;s account, <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 521.</note> Of course we have given it an honourable place &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All well. God bless you, love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref> &#8211; I wish I could see <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretdauTomandSarah">my niece</ref> &#8211; &amp; I wish you could see <ref target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha Bruin</ref>, what a fine creature she is without her cap. O she is capital
                    kissing!</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>