<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1985</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3256</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.81.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 242&#8211;244.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1985" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1985" type="letter">
        <head>1985. Robert Southey to [<ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>], <date when="1811-11-18">18
                        November 1811</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/
                        Durham<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.81<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 242&#8211;244.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Von Troil<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Uno Von Troil (1746&#8211;1803), <title>Letters on Iceland</title>
                        (1780). Southey&#8217;s copy was no. 2834 in the sale catalogue of his library. Southey was at this time reviewing two more recent
                        works on Iceland, Sir George Steuart Mackenzie (1780&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in the Island of Iceland, in
                            the Summer of the Year 1810</title> (1811) and Sir William Jackson Hooker (1785&#8211;1865; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Journal
                            of a Tour in Iceland, in the Summer of 1809</title> (1811); see <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (March 1812),
                        48&#8211;92.</note> does not enumerate consumption among the diseases of Iceland, &#8211; which is remarkable, because Horrebow (who wrote
                    before him) does. He says &#8220;it is usual with the men about the age of fifty to fall into a decay, by reason of the various
                    disorders that come upon them &amp; at last put an end to their lives. Consumption &amp; asthmas, <hi rend="ital">the reigning
                        disorders among them</hi>, are occasioned chiefly by the many hardships they endure at sea in fishing, &amp; their
                    carelessness of preserving their health. They do not mind jumping into the sea to save their boat from running aground, or
                    receiving damage against the rocks, &amp; frequently keep on their wet cloaths, even in frost &amp; snow, without changing any
                    thing. &#8211; Coughs &amp; consumption so afflict them that none hardly ever wear as well, or have such florid complexions as the
                    people of Denmark.&#8221;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Niels Horrebow (1712&#8211;1760), <title>The Natural History of
                            Iceland</title> (London, 1758), p. 103. Southey&#8217;s copy was no. 1428 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Olafsen &amp; Povelsen give the same account &#8211; about the age of fifty, they say the <del>people</del> Icelanders
                    begin to lose their strength. catarrhal fevers are very prevalent, but more so in the interior than along the shore, probably from
                    the circumstance that the inhabitants throw of their clothes during &amp; after the hay season, &amp; thereby expose themselves to
                    colds. The fevers are accompanied with a cough &amp; expectoration, &amp; it has been observed that this expectoration is not the
                    same with young as with old people; the former only throw up phlegm while the latter expectorate a more viscid substance.&#8221;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Travels in Iceland, by Messrs Olafsen and Povelsen</title> (London, 1805), p. 12. Southey&#8217;s copy was no. 3468 in the
                        sale catalogue of his library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="center">______</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just stumbled upon a passage which shows how strongly the Spaniards are impressed with a belief that
                    consumption is contagious. It appears that when a woman died of consumption leaving a child at the breast, &#8211; other women were
                    afraid to suckle it. &#8211; una <del>carxi</del> caritativa muger, is spoken of, que se encarg&#243; de criar un ni&#241;o de pecho, cuya madre
                    muri&#243; etica, y por tanto no se atrevian &#224; darle de mamar otras mugeres.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Espana Sagrada. T. 17. P. 214.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Enrique Florez (1702&#8211;1773), <title>Espana
                            Sagrada, Theatro Geographico-Historico de la Inglesia de Espana</title>, 42 vols (1754&#8211;1801), XVII, p. 214; Southey&#8217;s copy
                    was no. 3468 in the sale catalogue of his library. The Spanish translates as: &#8216;A charitable woman [...] who took it upon herself to breastfeed a child, whose mother died consumptive, for which reason other women refused to feed him.&#8217;</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="center">______</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here is a fact entirely to your purpose.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Herbert Southey was working
                        on <title>Observations on Pulmonary Consumption</title>, published in 1814.</note> Lord Molesworth (p. 91) says few or none of
                    the Danes are troubled with coughs, catarrahs, consumptions, or such like diseases of the lungs. I am persuaded, he adds, their
                    warm stoves, with the plenty &amp; pureness of their firing (which is beech wood) contributes as much to their freedom from these
                    kinds of maladies, as the grossness &amp; unwholesomeness of our coals in London doth to our being so universally troubled with
                        them.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert, 1st Viscount Molesworth (1656&#8211;1725; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An
                            Account of Denmark, as it was in the Year 1692</title>, 3rd edn (London, 1694), p. 84.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="center">______</p>
        <p>Lapland.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;Coughs are of very rare occurrence, notwithstanding the constant practice of drinking snow &amp; ice water, even
                    after swallowing pure grease or fat, which perhaps may prevent its bad consequences. However this may be the Laplanders seldom die
                    from catching cold. Cases of phthisis, or consumption, do indeed now &amp; then occur among them &#8211; &amp; pleurisies are very
                    common especially in spring &amp; autumn &#8211; &lt;some elderly people are afflicted with asthma, &amp; hoarsenesses now &amp; then
                    occur in the winter &amp; spring.&gt;</p>
        <p>Linn&#230;us&#8217;s Tour in Lapland. 1. 34.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Carl von Linnaeus (1707&#8211;1778), <title>Lachesis Lapponica:
                            or A Tour in Lapland</title>, 2 vols (London, 1811), I, p. 34. Southey&#8217;s copy was no. 1730 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="center">______</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Consumption is very prevalent in North America, among the Indians as well as the Anglo-Americans. If you want
                    chapter &amp; verse for this I can send you abundant authorities.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You are acquainted with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Whartons sister.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably a
                        reference to one of the three living sisters of Richard Wharton (1764&#8211;1820), MP for Durham 1802&#8211;1804, 1806&#8211;1820. He was Junior
                        Secretary at the Treasury 1809&#8211;1814. Southey may be referring to Margaret Wharton (dates unknown); Elizabeth Wharton (dates
                        unknown); or Deborah Wharton (dates unknown), who had married Thomas Brand (1750&#8211;1814), Rector of Wath and Chancellor of
                        Lincoln Cathedral 1808&#8211;1814.</note> Is she not related to the D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wharton who was Grays<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poet and literary scholar Thomas Gray (1716&#8211;1771; <title>DNB</title>), whose friends and
                        correspondents included the physician Thomas Wharton (1717&#8211;1794), member of a prominent Durham family. Richard Wharton, MP for
                        Durham, and his sister, mentioned in footnote 8, were among the eight children of Thomas Wharton.</note> correspondent? I wish
                    you would ascertain for me whether Grays letters, after Mason had made his selections from them,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Mason (1725&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>) had included bowdlerised and censored version of Gray&#8217;s letters
                        in his <title>The Poems of Mr. Gray, to which are Prefixed Memoirs of His Life and Writings</title> (1775). Mason&#8217;s
                        combination of &#8216;life and letters&#8217; was highly influential on later biographers, including Southey, who used a similar format in
                        his edition of William Cowper (1731&#8211;1800; <title>DNB</title>).</note> were returned to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wharton, as I
                        <del>pres</del> suppose they were, &#8211; if they are still in being, &#8211; &amp; if they would be communicated to a Gentleman &amp; a
                    Scholar, who <del>x x</del> designs to publish an edition of the Poets works, with such a commentary as his own classical
                    attainments will qualify him to produce. It is believed that Mason suppressed almost every thing in the letters which related to
                    Grays individual concerns; &#8211; there exists no motive of delicacy now for such suppression. The person for whom I make these
                    enquiries is a clergyman, a young man, who distinguished himself very much at Oxford, &amp; who seems to me very likely to make a
                    distinguished figure in literature. His name is <ref target="people.html#MitfordJohn">Mitford</ref>.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mitford became a distinguished editor of Gray. His publications included, <title>Poems of Thomas Gray with
                            Critical Notes, a Life of the Author and an Essay on His Poetry</title> (1814), <title>The Works of Thomas Gray</title>
                        (1816) and contributions to the Aldine edition of 1835&#8211;1843. Southey offered to help Mitford locate Gray&#8217;s surviving
                        correspondence; see Southey to John Mitford, 20 March 1811, Letter 1886.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of course we shall see you before you go to London. Arrange your plans so as to give yourself a holy day here
                        <del>on</del> upon the way. <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> did not stay here long enough. I am glad he
                    has set you to work &#8211; but do not give up the Crusades.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Herbert Southey had been
                        conducting research on the crusades.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1811-11-18">Nov. 18. 1811.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>