<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2428</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3699</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2428" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2428" type="letter">
        <head>2428. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1814-05-27">27 May
                        1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Postmarks: 10 o&#8217;Clock/ MY 30/ 1814; E/ 30 MY 30/ 1814<lb />Watermark: 1807<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art
                        Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-05-27">May 27. 1814.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Sir Ch. S. has proposed a very unfit sort of payment: &#8211; this however will be easily settled by paying him the sum
                        expended.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles Stuart, Baron Stuart de Rothesay (1779&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>),
                        envoy at Lisbon 1810&#8211;1814 had offered to provide Southey with a Portuguese book, from the context a Cancioneiro, or collection
                        of songs. Stuart was particularly interested in the Portuguese playwright and poet, Gil Vicente (c. 1465-c. 1536), and
                        probably wished to establish if any of his works were in the book; see Southey to Herbert Hill, [started before and continued
                        on] 8 March 1814, Letter 2386.</note> &#8211; If you should like to compare this cancioneiro with Resende,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey suggests Hill compare Stuart&#8217;s book with the <title>Cancioneiro Geral</title> (1516), collected by
                        Garcia de Resende (1470&#8211;1536).</note> which I should wish to do, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> can procure you access to the Kings Library<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The library of over 65,000
                        volumes assembled by George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of the United Kingdom 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>). It was given to the
                        nation in 1823.</note> thro Nicol<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The bookseller and publisher George Nicol
                        (1740?-1828; <title>DNB</title>), who was Bookseller to the King, 1781&#8211;1820.</note> who holds some office thereunto belonging.
                    There is a copy <del>xxx xxx</del> there, among a choice collection of the rarest Port: books presented many years ago by
                        Pinto,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luis Pinto de Sousa Coutinho, Viscount of Balsemao (1735&#8211;1804), Ambassador to
                        Great Britain 1774&#8211;1788, Prime Minister of Portugal 1788&#8211;1801, 1803.</note> &amp; there it is not unlikely that Gil
                        Vicente<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Portuguese playwright and poet Gil Vicente (c. 1465&#8211;c. 1536).</note> might
                    be found. I am especially curious to see this author; &#8211; he may turn out to be good for nothing, &#8211; or to be the father of the
                    Spanish drama, &#8211; &amp; the latter chance is the more likely of the two.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your neighbour&#8217;s inclosure was of the usual kind, &#8211; a paper perfectly useless. I have been several times on the
                    point of writing to request that you would acknowledge its receipt for me, &amp; have as often postponed the intention till a more
                    convenient season. A good deal of his restlessness will be removed now, &#8211; &amp; when there is an end of all suspence, which there
                    soon will be when the matter is brought before parliament, I hope he will sit down contented with the right of complaining of ill
                    usage as long as he lives. Government will give the Chief a quietus, &amp; probably nothing more. But of this they may be assured
                    that neither friends nor enemies can possibly interest the public upon the subject.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        William Barlow (1759&#8211;1839), a neighbour of Herbert Hill&#8217;s in Streatham. In 1813 Southey was commissioned by the Barlows to
                        write a defence of the conduct of William Barlow&#8217;s brother, Sir George Hilaro Barlow (1763&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>), Governor
                        of Madras 1807&#8211;1813. The result was the anonymously published pamphlet <title>An Exposure of the Misrepresentations and
                            Calumnies in Mr Marsh&#8217;s Review of Sir George Barlow&#8217;s Administration at Madras. By the Relatives of Sir George
                            Barlow</title> (1813). This was a response to the barrister and MP, Charles Marsh&#8217;s, (c. 1774&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Review of Some Important Passages in the Late Administration of Sir G. H. Barlow, Bart., at Madras</title> (1813).
                        Marsh stated in the Commons on 27 July 1814 that he would move for an enquiry into Sir George Barlow&#8217;s conduct in the next
                        session of Parliament.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James Ballantyne</ref> prints Roderic,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> &#8211; a portion of the notes are in his hand to expedite the
                    publication, &#8211; as they may be seperately paged without inconvenience. Another month will probably deliver me of it. I have just
                    begun the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> section, &#8211; &amp; according to my present view of the subject, 22 will compleat it. My brother
                    Bards are laudably labouring to put me in better humour with the Carmen Triumphale<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s first production as Poet Laureate; published in a quarto of 30 pages on 1 January 1814.</note> by <del>sending</del> &lt;giving me&gt; productions of their own to compare with it. I have a cargo
                    of such things from Murray.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have tidings of the bust for you at last.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had sat for a bust in
                        October 1813. The sculptor was James Smith (1775&#8211;1815).</note>
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> tells me the artist wishes to keep them ten days longer, &#8211;
                    according to which account you will receive yours in about a week.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The corn laws<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> A House of Commons committee in 1813 recommended that no
                        corn should be imported into Britain until domestic corn reached a price of &#163;4 per quarter. This idea proved the basis of the
                        Corn Law passed in 1815. It was greatly resented by many urban consumers, who feared it would increase food prices.</note>
                    have not taken up much of my consideration, for <del>if</del> when I take the trouble to understand a question of this kind, it is
                    like writing in sand, &#8211; my mind <del>has some xxx</del> seems to <del>have</del> be actually incapable of retaining it. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> (who is here at present) is very deep in the argument, &amp; attacks <del>xxx</del>
                    all the landholders whom he meets. Upon that common sense view of the matter which a mere statement enables every man to form, I
                    should think it very mischievous, &#8211; &amp; rather incline to think that the out of door opposition will put a stop to it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have bought Gage cheaply. I have the folio edition which cost me 10/6. His historical matter is a transcript
                    from the old translation of Gomara, &#8211; but this does not detract from the authority of the rest of the book.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Dominican friar and writer Thomas Gage&#8217;s (1603?-1656; <title>DNB</title>) <title>A New Survey
                            of the West Indias</title> (1648); Southey owned an edition of 1655, no. 1191 in the sale catalogue of his library. Gage&#8217;s
                        account of the conquest of Mexico drew on Francisco Lopez de Gomara (c. 1511&#8211;1566?), <title>Hispania Victrix</title>
                        (1552).</note> His own character perhaps does. But it is easy to see when there is any malicious colouring laid on. We owe
                    Jamaica to this man, &amp; he lost his life in taking it.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gage had acted as an informer
                        on fellow Catholics, and his testimony had sent some to the gallows. A servant and defender of the Cromwellian commonwealth,
                        Gage was a member of the English force that seized Jamaica in 1655. He died there the following year during an epidemic of
                        dysentery and malaria.</note> I am about to review Lewis &amp; Clarkes <del>voya</del> journal, &amp; shall bring together a
                    good deal of curious matter concerning that part of America.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey review of
                        Meriweather Lewis (1774&#8211;1809) and William Clarke (1770&#8211;1838), <title>Travels to the Source of the Missouri River, and Across
                            the American Continent to the Pacific Ocean</title> (1814), published in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (January
                        1815), 317&#8211;368.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Two of the new titles have been bestowed undeservedly &#8211; Sir John Hopes,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Sir John Hope (1765&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), was created Baron Niddry on 17 May 1814, before succeeding his half-brother as
                        4th Earl of Hopetoun in 1816. Though he was a very successful soldier in the Peninsular War, Southey probably disliked his
                        role in the Convention of Cintra (1808) and the evacuation of British troops from Corunna (1809).</note> &amp; Sir S.
                        Cottons.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Stapleton Cotton (1773&#8211;1865; <title>DNB</title>), was created Baron
                        Combermere on 17 May 1814. Primarily a cavalry commander, he, too, had been involved in the actions at Corunna.</note>
                        Picton<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Thomas Picton (1758&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), was another prominent
                        commander in the Peninsular War. His reputation was overshadowed by his controversial term as Governor of Trinidad 1797&#8211;1803,
                        which led to accusations of sanctioning torture. He was killed at Waterloo.</note> had a better claim than either, tho he had
                    certainly fairer claims to a halter than to the peerage. &#8211; This question of the slave trade is easily settled with France.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Treaty of Paris, signed on 30 May 1814, ended the war between France and the Sixth
                        Coalition. One of the terms was that France should abolish the slave trade over a five-year period.</note> But <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Ld Grenville</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Mr Canning</ref> must know
                    little of the state of Brazil if they would press it upon Portugal. Were the Prince<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        VI (1767&#8211;1826; King of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826), Prince Regent of Portugal 1799&#8211;1816.</note> to attempt an abolition he would lose
                    Brazil, &#8211; whether he will keep it or not after his return, without such an experiment, is perhaps doubtful enough. Ucalegons house
                    is on fire,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ucalegon was an elder of Troy, whose house was set on fire by the Greeks,
                            <title>Aeneid</title>, Book 2, lines 311&#8211;312. The term became a common way of referring to a neighbour whose house was on
                        fire &#8211; in this case Portugal&#8217;s neighbour, Spain.</note> &amp; his own is of combustible materials. I should think it good
                    policy on the part of Portugal to give us Rio Grande do Sul,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> The southernmost area of
                        Brazil, which had long been in dispute between Spain and Portugal.</note> if it were only to interpose a barrier between
                    herself &amp; Buenos Ayres. As for Madeira<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> The British had occupied Madeira 1807&#8211;1814 to
                        prevent French encroachment. The island was returned to Portugal.</note> I do not see why we should ask it, or why they should
                    grant.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been obliged to return my Dutchmen to Lackington the set being imperfect.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors"> The London booksellers and publishers Lackington, Allen and Co, at this time headed by George Lackington
                        (1777&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>); Southey had purchased some imperfect Dutch books from him, see Southey to Henry Herbert
                        Southey, 2 March 1814, Letter 2384.</note>
          <del>Xxx</del> You can get at his catalogue more easily than I so you had better take out books to the amount, &#8211; I forget whether
                    it was three guineas, or three &amp; a half. This will be the only the deduction of back-carriage.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">My house</ref> is about to be sold over my head, &#8211; <del>a xxxxxx</del> an event which is not
                    unlikely in its consequence to set me upon moving at the expiration of my first term. For it seems to me more than likely that
                    whoever purchases it will build upon part of the ground in such a manner as to build me out of some of my prospect, &amp; more of
                    my comfort.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tell the <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Marquis</ref> I am glad to hear of his good beginnings, &amp; tell
                    the <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Duke</ref> I hope he can say look at the lamb &amp; the lark. The <ref target="people.html#HillErrol">Earl</ref> I suppose is now beginning to talk. And how go on the goats? &#8211; &amp; the refractory
                    gardiner? the season is coming on when tithe in kind will pinch him. &#8211; Have you heard that Evangelical from Penryn is going to
                    distribute bibles &amp; <hi rend="ital">tracks</hi> from S Sebastiano to Lisbon.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        minister was a Mr Smith of Penryn. His journey was reported in the <title>Evangelical Magazine</title>, 22 (February 1814),
                        155, which asked readers to donate money and to pray for the success of his endeavours: &#8216;Here new channels of benevolence may
                        be opened; and if the smiles of Heaven descend on the undertaking, Bigotry may receive a more fatal wound&#8217;.</note> I wish him
                    a pleasant journey. If he lives to get back we may perhaps have some account from him of the underground apartments in the
                        Rocio.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Rocio, Lisbon, a prison used by the Inquisition.</note> Love to <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref>. God bless you</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>