<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2152</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3423</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                        c. 24.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2152" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2152" type="letter">
        <head>2152. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1812-09-29">29 September
                            1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Postmark: E/ 2 OC 2/ 1812s<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                        c. 24<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-09-29">Sept. 29. 1812</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have stolen away from an evening party at the <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhora&#8217;s</ref> to write to
                    you. &amp; the first thing to be said is that I have given M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Downman<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Downman
                        (1750&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>), who in autumn 1812 painted two portraits of
                        Southey (one commissioned by Murray) and one of Edith.</note> a draft
                        <del>x</del> upon your worship at three days sight, for &#163;16&#8211;10/ &#8211; three days
                    sight I said, because the presentation being duly announced, there can be no
                    inconvenience in not finding you at home &amp;c&#8211;. Every body seemed so pleased
                    with his portrait that I have had another &lt;taken&gt; (which might
                        <del>p</del> almost pass for a fac-simile of it, if the position of the arms
                    &amp; body were not different) This I had done for <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> who was reasonably
                    enough dissatisfied with the two ill-looking miniatures.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> It is not clear which portraits Southey is referring to
                        here.</note> Downman has given me a companion to it, in her portrait, every
                    body exclaims at the happiness of the likeness. I see it less than any
                        <del>xx</del> body, &#8211; still I see it, &amp; it is a very pleasant picture.
                    The draft is for my own portrait &amp; the two frames, which he will provide for
                    me according to his own taste.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Common place book<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey might have lent Bedford one of his own common place books; or he
                        could be returning one of Bedford&#8217;s own books.</note> shall go tomorrow, I
                    will send with a book<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly a copy
                        of the <title>Cartas dos Privilegios de Nacam Britannica em Portugal</title>
                        (1746), which Southey had borrowed from John May.</note> of <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John Mays</ref> which I wanted an opportunity
                    of sending to London. You will have the goodness to get it conveyed to him,
                    according to its direction.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I received <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> letter with the draft, &amp; must tell you (tho he desired
                    it might be between <del>x</del> ourselves) that he in a very friendly manner
                    desired me at any time when I might be out of cash to draw upon him at sight,
                    &amp; pay him at leisure; &#8211; an offer for which I am as sincerely obliged to him
                    as if I could accept of it. But in the first place I am almost a stranger to
                        <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">G.</ref> &amp; in the
                    second, according to the present state of my affairs, &amp; the probable
                    prospect, I am not likely to feel any other want than what <del>will</del> may
                    be supplied by requesting you to send me a quarter pension a few weeks before it
                    is due, &#8211; &amp; that perhaps may not occur again, for every year is now
                    bettering my worldly condition. &#8211; I have an answer from that shuffling fellow
                        <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">John Ballantyne</ref> to
                        <del>my</del> &lt;that&gt; <del>xx</del> letter which you saw. He was in
                    London &amp; <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames ">his
                    brother</ref> who had opened <del>his</del> mine, sent him notice of
                    its contents. so he writes to say he hopes his brother has explained &amp;
                    apologized to me about the Chronicle, &#8211; that he hopes I will resume it, &#8211; &amp;
                    that about the other points he will reply as soon as he gets back to
                        Edinburgh.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was already
                        having trouble extracting money from the Ballantynes. The <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813) was to be his last.</note> &#8211;
                    Reply how he may, he has shuffled with me, &amp; I am perfectly aware that
                    nothing but a sense of his own interest will make him behave either with
                    civility or <del>xx</del> honesty. As soon as I can get his account &amp; his
                    address I shall draw upon him for every farthing which is due to me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> I hear is in town, but whether at this time he is with
                        <ref target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gooch</ref>
                    in Aldermanbury, or at <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> I do
                    not know.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tell <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">G.</ref> I
                    am writing <hi rend="ital">for</hi> him, &amp; therefore will not subduct
                        <del>time</del> precious time for the purpose of writing <hi rend="ital">to</hi> him. &#8211; Since you left us some little progress has been made with
                    Pelayo, or Roderick as we must call it for the future,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                        (1814).</note> &#8211; &amp; what is of more importance the main difficulty in the
                    management of the story seems to be removed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Dawe,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The history and
                        portrait painter George Dawe (1781&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>).</note> whose
                    genius soars as Eagles flight, has removed his easel to day into my room, where
                    Kate &amp; Bertha lay by turns for about an hour to be made Eagles prey for him,
                    &#8211; much to the Painters contentment.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Dawe&#8217;s residence at Greta Hall whilst he worked on the 9 foot by 8 foot
                        canvas &#8216;Mother Rescuing her Child from an Eagle&#8217;s Nest&#8217; was not without
                        controversy. The picture was based on William Hayley&#8217;s (1745&#8211;1820;
                            <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;The Eagle&#8217;, first published in <title>Designs to a
                            Series of Ballads</title> (1802).</note> &#8211; The <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhora</ref> has been highly
                    flattered to day by an application from <ref target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edmondson</ref>, who requested that he purchase
                    a pound of her Epsom salts, &#8211; because he despaired of getting any so good. She
                    gave him about half-a pound, &amp; told him she hoped that would answer any
                    present want, but she could part with no more. He seems to look upon her house
                    as a second Apothecaries Hall.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know Downman is about to publish a series of portraits of the
                    English Reformers.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Downman did not
                        complete this project. In his retirement he arranged his preliminary
                        sketches for portraits of &#8216;Distinguished Persons&#8217; into a series of
                        albums.</note> he meant to accompany each head with a page of brief
                    biographical notices. I have offered to write an inscription for each, this I
                    could do con amore,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;With
                        love&#8217;.</note> whether it will be done depends upon <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not write the inscriptions.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">your
                        father &amp; mother</ref>. the <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Mag: Rut:</ref>  &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref> &#8211;
                    How did the chair arrive? &#8211; Remember also that you half promised me a picture of
                    yourself.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref>
                        arrived to day to occupy your lodgings, before he goes to Rose Castle<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The home of the Bishop of
                            Carlisle, in 1812 Samuel Goodenough (1743&#8211;1827;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> on his way Eastward.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>