<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2456</idno><idno type="nines">rce3727</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                        c. 25.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2456" type="letter"><head>2456. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1814-07-06">6 July
                            1814</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9 Stafford Row/ Buckingham Gate/
                        London<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: E/ 9 JY 9/
                        1814<lb/>Endorsement: 6. July. 1814<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                        c. 25<lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1814-07-06">6 July 1814</date></dateline><salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> If your arm is not better, ask some of your medical advisers if
                    the vapour bath may not be tried for it. In Lewis &amp; Clarkes Travels there
                    are two most extraordinary cases of its efficacy, – both in point, – one being
                    of violent rheumatism, another of paralysis.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meriweather Lewis (1774–1809) and William Clark
                        (1770–1838), <title>Travels to the Source of the Missouri River, and Across
                            the American Continent to the Pacific Ocean</title>, 3 vols (1814), II,
                        pp. 234–236 (rheumatism); III, pp. 210–211 (paralysis). Southey reviewed the
                        book in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 12 (January 1815),
                    317–368.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Do’nt abuse the poor <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmen</ref>. The vulgarity &amp; familiarity of the proposed title were
                    mine, who supposed all Imperials &amp; Majesties were as needless at the head of
                    an ode as Graces &amp; Most Nobles on the superscription of a letter.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bedford had objected to Southey’s original
                        titles for the poems published as <title>Congratulatory Odes. Odes to His
                            Royal Highness The Prince Regent, His Imperial Majesty The Emperor of
                            Russia, and His Majesty the King of Prussia</title> (1814).</note> My
                    letter to <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> was perfectly explicit,
                    – that is as explicit as it could be when it was matter of doubt whether the
                    Odes would be published or not. It stated that I did not know whether it would
                    be proper or improper to present them to the beöded, – that he did; – &amp; that
                    copies should be sent him to be thus disposed of, at his discretion.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to [John Wilson Croker], 14
                        June 1814, Letter 2440.</note> Longman was of course directed to send him 4
                    copies (the one being for himself) – &amp; <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, – who I fancy has been taken with some fit of the sulks
                    towards me, God knows why or wherefore – had nothing to do with the
                    business.</p><p rend="indent1"> As to presenting one to the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> I suppose it is
                    one of those cases in which there is no choice. Learn of <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> whether there will be a
                    second edition, for only 250 were struck off, on account of haste.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Congratulatory Odes</title> did
                        not go into a second edition in 1814.</note> If they be reprinted the
                    insertion which I sent you will be made,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> A new section for ‘Ode to His Royal Highness the Prince Regent, of the
                        United Kingdom of Great Britain &amp; Ireland’, III; <title>Congratulatory
                            Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness The Prince Regent, His Imperial Majesty
                            The Emperor of Russia, and His Majesty the King of Prussia</title>
                        (London, 1814), p. 8; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 15 June
                        [1814], Letter 2441.</note> &amp; the errors corrected, – there were two of
                    material consequence – sea – instead of sun, – &amp; breach instead of
                        beach.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘Ode to His Royal Highness
                        the Prince Regent, of the United Kingdom of Great Britain &amp; Ireland’,
                        III and IV; <title>Congratulatory Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness The
                            Prince Regent, His Imperial Majesty The Emperor of Russia, and His
                            Majesty the King of Prussia</title> (London, 1814), pp. 7 and 18.</note>
                    In this case the improved copy should be that which should be presented: – tho
                    it is of very little importance, – &amp; indeed it is very likely that 250
                    should have been sold. So get one bound &amp; put it into <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Crokers</ref> hands; certainly no other copy
                    will ever be bound separately, &amp; therefore this will be so far curious. But
                    I shall make no more presents of this kind, &amp; having done my devoir in
                        <del>xxxxx</del> odifying the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref>, feel neither<del> xxx the</del> &lt;the&gt; propriety nor
                    &lt;the&gt; inclination of dedicating Roderick to him.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had considered dedicating <title>Roderick, the
                            Last of the Goths</title> (1814) to the Prince Regent, and sent Bedford
                        a draft dedication; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, [30 April-1
                        May 1814], Letter 2412. In the end, the poem was dedicated to Grosvenor
                        Bedford.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I am very near the end of this long labour. The 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> section is transcribed for you, – the 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi> in
                    course of transcription, – &amp; I shall perhaps finish the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> this evening. The 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> will be the last. Pray
                    send me those in your hands as soon as possible – not to delay the
                        publication.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been
                        sending Bedford MS drafts of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                        (1814).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> As soon as this is compleated I shall begin “A Tale of Paraguay”
                    – the story (a true one) is very simple but very sweet – the <del>x</del> extent
                    from 1000 to 1500 lines.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A
                            Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825). Southey’s source was Martin
                        Dobrizhoffer (1717–1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus</title>
                        (1783–1784).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I suppose <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>
                    wisely abstained from farther advertisement as being too late. Are you aware
                    that the regular expence of advertising each of my books <del>is</del> amounts
                    to £30? – &amp; that the profit of these Odes will not be thirty shillings.
                        <del>Verily pr</del> Very probably they will not pay their expences. As for
                    them being better known at <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref>
                    than in the Row, – they could of course be at <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref>. – They do me credit however
                    &amp; that is enough.</p><p rend="indent1"> Thank the <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Magrot</ref> for his official. Remember me most kindly to him
                    &amp; to <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">your mother &amp; Miss
                        Page</ref>. Here we are all well. <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">The Ancient (M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        C)</ref> is <del>with Sara</del> at <ref target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref> trying what the sea will do
                    for <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref>. – I had been anxiously looking to hear from you for some days.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1"> If I were upon the spot I should dearly like to have a tool
                        cut <del>for the side of the binding</del>, representing bag, sword &amp;
                        ruffles, – fit ornaments for a full dress court binding.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>