<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2175</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3446</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4812D.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2175" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2175" type="letter">
        <head>2175. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1812-11-05">5
                        November 1812</date>
          </head><p>Address: [readdressed in another hand] To/ C W Williams
                        Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.P./ <del>Llangedwin</del> &lt;Norton Priory&gt;/ <del>Oswestry</del>
                        &lt;Warrington&gt;<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: [illegible]<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4812D<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-11-05">Nov 5. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Wynn,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have another <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">daughter</ref>, &#8211; being like you it seems, in the girl-line.
                    Five children are a tolerable allowance in these long&#232;-post-diluvian times;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. a long
                        time after the Flood, before which Biblical patriarchs had lived to a great age, <title>Genesis</title> 5.</note> but the more
                    the merrier, &amp; the more there are of a family, the better in general do they make their way in the world.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have probably been warmly engaged in the Chester contest.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the
                        General Election of 1812 at Chester the sitting MPs, the Independent, John Grey Egerton, 8th Baronet (1766&#8211;1825), MP for
                        Chester 1807&#8211;1818 and the Whig, General Thomas Grosvenor (1764&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Chester 1795&#8211;1826, were
                        returned on 20 October 1812, receiving 602 and 637 votes respectively. The defeated candidates were the Whig Sir Richard
                        Brooke, 6th Baronet, of Norton Priory (1785&#8211;1865), who received 575 votes, and the Independent Edward Venables Townshend of
                        Wincham (1774&#8211;1845), who received 537 votes. Elections at Chester were bitterly contested between the Grosvenors and their
                        &#8216;Independent&#8217; opponents and that of 1812 saw the usual bribery, intimidation and drunkenness during a prolonged poll of the
                        Chester freemen.</note> I am glad it was not for your own seat.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wynn had been one of
                        the members for Montgomeryshire since 1799.</note> There is a piece of secret history about Curwen&#8217;s<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> At the 1812 general election, the wealthy colliery owner John Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>)
                        had allegedly refused to stand for the Carlisle seat he had held for 21 years because of rumours concerning his seduction of
                        Dorothy Watson (1777&#8211;1837), eldest daughter of Richard Watson, Bishop of Llandaff, who owned an estate at Calgarth on Lake
                        Windermere.</note> ejectment which perhaps you may not have heard. He must have won his election if he could have ventured to
                    stand it, &#8211; but he could not face the scandalous stories which would have risen in judgement against him, &amp; has literally paid
                    the penalty to public decency. He exceeds any man that I ever heard of in this country in profligacy with respect to women. The
                    particular scandal which would most have shamed him relates to a sort of sentimental intrigue with the Bp of Llandaffs eldest
                    daughter, concerning which he writes exculpatory letters to his friends, confessing imprudence &amp; protesting innocence as to
                    any thing farther.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will find the Omniana<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Omniana, or Horae Otiosiores</title> (1812).</note> in Duke Street, whither I suppose you will soon migrate. My own
                    movement will not take place till April, &amp; meantime I have a long winters work to perform. The life of Nelson<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813). The biography, commissioned by John Murray, was a
                        development of an article in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218&#8211;262.</note> will be ready by Xmas. I have
                    corrected seven sheets &amp; am better pleased with it than I had <del>anti</del> expected, for it was not a subject which I
                    should have chosen originally for the review, &#8211; neither should I ever have thought of enlarging what was there printed into a
                    compleat life. &#8211; My poem<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> What became <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                        (1813).</note> is now in rapid progress, &#8211; the plan is now matured &amp; the difficulties disappear. It must not take its name
                    from Pelayo, &#8211; because Roderick is the more conspicuous personage. I <del>xxxx</del> cannot yet determine whether to call it
                    Roderick, the Last of the Goths, &#8211; or Spain Restored. The former is the better title, but I should be very sorry to <del>give it
                        a</del> use one which could possibly seem as if it were intended to remind the <del>pub</del> reader of <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scotts</ref> poem<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>Vision of Don
                            Roderick</title> (1811).</note> &amp; thereby invite an unfair comparison. I am making a transcript which is ultimately
                    intended for the press, but goes to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> now, &amp; to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother Henry</ref>, when he has done with it. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> will show it you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A few days ago I received a letter from an <ref target="people.html#LongmireJohnMartyn">Evangelical Parson</ref> to
                    thank me for the benefit he had derived from &#8211; Thalaba. It has strengthened his faith, he says, &#8211; &amp; he proposes to send me &#8220;a
                    sketch of the instruction to be derived from it&#8221;.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Longmire had read <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801) as an allegory of the powers and virtues of Faith, and drawn parallels between events and
                        characters in Southey&#8217;s poem and the bible; see Southey to John Martyn Longmire, 4 November 1812, Letter 2172.</note> &#8211; I dare
                    say this will be almost as good as some of Croxalls morals to Esops fables.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Samuel
                        Croxall (1688/9&#8211;1752; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Fables of Aesop and Others</title> (1722), which fused morality with Whig
                        politics.</note> &#8211; He read the book upon the recommendation of the Xtian Observer.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        This had praised Southey for being &#8216;unequalled&#8217; in &#8216;sublimity of conception, eloquence, and depth of feeling&#8217; and cited
                            <title>Thalaba</title> as &#8216;by far the best&#8217; of his &#8216;performances&#8217;, <title>Christian Observer</title>, 9 (June 1810),
                        389.</note> If the Evangelicals should take me in good earnest into favour as a poet, it would be what the Portugueze call a
                    fat fortune, as well as a comical one. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">My brother</ref> the Doctor is removed to town &amp; has taken a house in <ref target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Queen Anne Street</ref>, Cavendish Square: &#8211; according to the opinion of all who know him,
                    with good prospect of success.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have now good hope from the Russian war.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French had invaded Russia
                    on 24 June 1812. Although they won a tactical victory at Borodino (7 September), in the longer-term the French&#8217;s failure to
                        destroy the Russian army marked a turning point in the campaign. Their numbers decimated by appalling weather, lack of
                        supplies and guerilla attacks, the last French troops left Russia on 14 December 1812.</note> The Bear is made of good stuff.
                    He loves his country &amp; his beard &amp; St Nicholas,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> St Nicholas (270&#8211;343), a popular
                        saint in Russian culture, particularly in times of trouble.</note> &amp; he does not understand parlezvous. This insurrection
                    at Paris<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The attempted Parisian coup of 23 October 1812 led by Claude Fran&#231;ois Malet
                        (1754&#8211;1812). This planned to announce the death of Bonaparte and establish a provisional republican government. It failed and
                        the leaders were executed on 31 October.</note> is a daybreak of hope also <del>even</del> in that quarter. I am deeply
                    convinced that from the beginning of the Spanish contest we ought to have published to the world the terms upon which we were
                    ready to make peace, <del>&amp; to have</del> declaring &lt;at the same time&gt; our determination never to negociate with
                    Buonaparte. I would do it now, &amp; offer at once to France all the cessions which would ever be made <del>by xx xx xx</del> by
                    treaty. But alas &#8211; I wish you could see the picture of the English Government which is given in the last number of the
                    Investigador Portuguez.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The periodical <title>O Investigador Portuguez em Inglaterra; ou,
                            Jornal Liter&#225;rio, Politico, &amp;c</title> (1811&#8211;1819), no. 3409 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; I
                    could not read it without shame &amp; humiliation.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>