<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2685</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3956</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25.  Previously 
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
                        128&#8211;130.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2685" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2685" type="letter">
        <head>2685. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1815-12-19">19 December 1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9 Stafford Row/ Buckingham Gate/ London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 22 DEC 22/
                        1815<lb />Endorsement: 19 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1815<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25<lb />Previously
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
                        128&#8211;130.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1815-12-19">19 Dec. 1815</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am in some discomfort about the fiddlers &amp; that unmannerly fellow <ref target="people.html#ParsonsWilliam">Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Parsons</ref>, &#8211; fellows who have still a claim upon me, notwithstanding the implied condition
                    upon which I first acceded to the situation, &amp; Ally <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Crokers</ref>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A nickname given by Southey to Croker because of the latter&#8217;s use of an accentuated &#8216;all&#375;&#8217; in his
                            <title>The Battles of Talavera</title> (1809); see Southey to John Rickman, 1 May 1811, Letter 1914. Southey was also
                        probably recalling the title of the popular Irish song &#8216;Ally Croker&#8217; (1725).</note> promise that he would take an opportunity
                    of speaking to the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref>, &amp; hinting to him how proper a thing it would be
                    to exempt an office of honour from a service which could only tend to bring it into disrepute. This he has never done, &amp; I
                    shall have my exercise to do as long as I hold the office, or till the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Deus Lunus</ref>
                    is old enough to do it, by way of exercise, for me.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was concerned that he was
                        going to once again have to fulfil the Poet Laureate&#8217;s traditional duty of writing a New Year&#8217;s ode, which would be performed
                        at court. He had expressed the wish, when taking the office, that the custom would be discontinued; see Southey to John Wilson
                        Croker, [4 September 1813], Letter 2298.</note> What I want to know now is, whether the verses must be ready for the New Years
                    day, or if I have as long grace this year as there was in the last; &amp; this I pray you learn for me with as little delay as
                    possible: that is tell me by what time I must send &lt;them&gt; up. Ever since my return I have been close at work, for the most
                    part upon this poem, the title of which will be The Poets Pilgrimage to La Belle Alliance.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The original title for <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> Hitherto it proceeds much to my liking,
                    &#8211; it is in the six lined stanza, like the unfinished marriage-poem<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> In 1814 Southey, as
                        Poet Laureate, had started a poem celebrating the forthcoming marriage of the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince Regent&#8217;s</ref> only child Charlotte Augusta (1796&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>) to the Hereditary Prince of Orange,
                        William (1792&#8211;1849; King of the Netherlands 1840&#8211;1849). The poem had not been published because the royal engagement was
                        broken off in June 1814. Southey reworked the 1814 poem into <title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen Nuptiale</title> (1816) to
                        celebrate Charlotte&#8217;s marriage to Leopold of Saxe-Coburg (1790&#8211;1865; <title>DNB</title>).</note> which you have seen, &amp;
                    pitched in the same Spenserian<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e after the manner of Edmund Spenser (c. 1552&#8211;1599;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> key. There is a Proem, beginning with an address to <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>, passing to a picture of my return home, &amp; so introducing the subject. Then follows the Journey, this part
                    I may possibly finish to night, &amp; these two parts will be about 400 lines. The Field of Battle is to come next. Then the
                    Meditation or Lamentation; (for I have not fixed the title of this part), &#8211; the Reproof, or the Hopes of Man afterwards, &amp;
                    finally the Hymn of Victory, from this last the Fiddlers must be supplied;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        followed this general plan in the <title>Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title>, but he omitted the &#8216;Hymn of Victory&#8217; and
                        concluded with the &#8216;Hope of Man&#8217;.</note> &#8211; but I should rather come to it in the regular course of composition, than lay the
                    rest aside to get that ready like a schoolboys task.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This poem has grown under my hands, perhaps had I been aware of its extent <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> would have chosen to give it a quarto form: &#8211; for it will most probably exceed 1000 <del>or</del> lines, making
                    from <hi rend="ital">six</hi>ty to 70 pages,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The final poem ran to 193 pages.</note> &#8211;
                    &amp; the notes as many more. However this is of little consequence &amp; I have written to <ref target="people.html#NashEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nash</ref> about the drawings, giving him dimensions for the small size. As soon as I hear of his
                    arrival in London, where he is now expected, I will give you an introduction to him, &amp; appoint you <del>xxxxxxxxx</del> Agent
                    in this matter between him &amp; the <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Long men</ref>. &#8211; The subjects which I think of
                    having engraved are Waterloo Church, an outer view of Hogoumont, an inner one, &amp; a view of Ligny;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> These engravings appeared in the <title>Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> at: frontispiece [unpaginated];
                        between pp. 58&#8211;59; between pp. 70&#8211;71; and between pp. 90&#8211;91.</note> &#8211; these are all sufficiently picturesque, but I rather
                    think Charles Bell of the Middlesex Hospital has made a better view of Hogoumont on the outside, &amp; if it prove to be so he
                    will give it me,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The physiologist and surgeon Charles Bell (1774&#8211;1842;
                        <title>DNB</title>). He had been appointed surgeon at the Middlesex Hospital in 1814 and in the following year travelled to
                        Brussels to treat casualties from the battle of Waterloo. Southey probably received this information about his sketches from
                        Henry Herbert Southey, who also held an appointment at the Middlesex Hospital.</note> &#8211; <del>the x</del>
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert"> Sirius</ref> will manage this. There is another inner view of the ruins which will
                    make a good etching, &amp; to which we may allow double length, &amp; I would have etched or wooden vignettes of La Belle
                    Alliance, La Haye Saint, &amp; Les Quatre Bras,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> These engravings appeared in the
                            <title>Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> at: between pp. 68&#8211;69 (though not double length); between pp. 56&#8211;57; between
                        pp. 62&#8211;63; and between pp. 88&#8211;89.</note> places which have no beauty whatever, but <del>which</del> of which faithful
                    representation will give an interest to the book. Of La Haye Saint we have no sketch, but we may take that from the panoramic
                    print, unless another should offer from any private sketchbook. &#8211; I am very full of this poem at present, being quite in tune for
                    it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I gave <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> as a title to announce it by, merely La Belle
                    Alliance, &#8211; there is a necessity for enlarging it as you have seen, &amp; the new title is both more suitable &amp; more
                        <del>excit</del> likely to excite curiosity. Tell him therefore of the alteration when you see him, or if you think it worth
                    while inform him of it by a note. &#8211; Part of my books are arrived in the Row, &amp; I believe the Acta Sanctorum<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey met with mixed success on his book-buying expedition in Belgium and France. For a while,
                        he hoped he had bought the complete set of the rare, 53 volume <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (Brussels, 1643&#8211;1794), no. 207 in
                        the sale catalogue of his library. In fact he received from the bookseller a 6 volume edition of 1783&#8211;1794, no. 152 in the
                        sale catalogue of his library.</note> among them. <ref target="people.html#VardonMr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Vardon</ref> gives
                    them a passage for me to Newcastle.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has sent me Sir J Malcolms book to review, &amp; I have read it for that
                    purpose. It is just that kind of book which would <del>enable me</del> lead me to put more matter into a reviewal than the work
                    itself contains, &#8211; but at a great expence of time &amp; labour &#8211; <note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John Malcolm
                        (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of Persia</title> (1815); no. 1661 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library. The review of Malcolm in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 236&#8211;292, was by Reginald Heber, not
                        Southey.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have done something to Brazil<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The History of Brazil</title>, the two final volumes appeared in 1817 and 1819 respectively.</note> since my return,
                    &amp; something also to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dove,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr Daniel Dove; the hero of
                        Southey&#8217;s novel <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847).</note> &#8211; a secret which we must keep as much as possible, &#8211; for a half
                    years secret I think would be very probably worth half a dozen editions. There is so much of Tristram Shandy about it, that I
                    think it will be proper to take the name of Stephen Yorickson Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> in the title page, &#8211; this is a notion only
                    half a day old.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Doctor</title>&#8217;s unstructured narrative bore some resemblance to Laurence Sterne (1713&#8211;1768; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Life and Opinions of Tristram Shandy, Gentleman</title> (1759&#8211;1767), which contained the character of Parson
                        Yorick (sometimes seen as a self-portrait by Sterne).</note> I would give one of my ears, if I could have both yours just now
                    to try some of this book upon them. So much of it is done, that I shall very probably put it to press in the spring. It is very
                    doubtful <del>at this time</del> whether I do not lose more than I gain by giving up so much time to reviewing; &#8211; &amp; whenever
                    that ceases to be doubtful, huzza for a joyful emancipation!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to all at home. We are going on well &#8211; the <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Venerable</ref>
                    speaks of you as ungratefully as ever, &#8211; I have had a visit from a young American physician of New York.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> He tells me that my note in the Courier respecting the attack made upon me in that city,
                    was copied into the American papers.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been attacked in James Kirke Paulding
                        (1778&#8211;1860), <title>The United States and England: Being a Reply to the Criticism on Inchiquin&#8217;s Letters, contained in The
                            Quarterly Review, for January, 1814</title> (1815). Paulding was mistaken. Southey had not written the review of Charles
                        Jared Ingersoll (1782&#8211;1862), <title>Inchiquen, the Jesuit&#8217;s Letters, during a Late Residence in the United States of America;
                            being a Fragment of a Private Correspondence, accidentally discovered in Europe, containing a favourable View of the
                            Manners, Literature, and State of Society, of the United States; and a Refutation of many of the Aspersions cast upon this
                            Country, by former Residents and Tourists. By some Unknown Foreigner</title> (1810), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>,
                        10 (January 1814), 494&#8211;530. The author of the offending article, which was highly critical of the United States, was John
                        Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>). In response, Southey had defended himself publicly; see Southey to the Editor of the
                            <title>Courier</title>, 16 June 1815, Letter 2616. For the appearance of this letter in American newspapers, see
                            <title>The North-American Review and Miscellaneous Journal</title>, 1 (September 1815), 442&#8211;443.</note> I think (&amp; the
                    intention arose from this knowledge) of exposing M Beauchamps theft of my Brazil thro the same channel, as the surest method of
                    widely &amp; effectually exposing him, &#8211; &amp; an excellent advertisement to boot.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey was considering writing a letter to the <title>Courier</title> to expose the plagiarism of his <title>History of
                            Brazil</title> in Alphonse de Beauchamp (1769&#8211;1832), <title>Histoire du Br&#233;sil</title> (1815); see Southey to Grosvenor
                        Charles Bedford, 3 October 1815, Letter 2659. The letter was not written.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>