<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2174</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3445</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47891.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 299&#8211;301 [in
                    part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2174" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2174" type="letter">
        <head>2174. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BrowneWade">Wade Browne</ref>, <date when="1812-11-05">5 November
                        1812</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Wade Browne Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Ludlow<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47891<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II, pp. 299&#8211;301 [in
                    part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-11-05">November 5. 1812.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Guy Faux<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Guy Fawkes (1570&#8211;1606; <title>DNB</title>), traditionally burned
                        in effigy on the night of 5 November to celebrate the discovery of the Catholic plot to blow up Parliament in 1605.</note> is
                    receiving his usual honours of bonfire &amp; uproar in the market-place: the two girls<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara
                            Coleridge</ref>.</note> are exhibiting themselves at the dancing-masters ball as happy as innocent hearts &amp;
                    &lt;apple-green&gt; kid-shoes can make them; good old nurse is twirling the spinning wheel in the room where <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey</ref> is in bed with her new-born daughter <ref target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref>, &amp; I, who like the last Duke of Cumberland<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The king&#8217;s younger brother Henry Frederick, Duke of Cumberland (1745&#8211;1790; <title>DNB</title>). After a court
                        case in 1770 concerning his affair with a married woman, Harriet Grosvenor (d. 1828), his love letters were published, to much
                        ridicule, as they displayed his uncertain grasp of written English, including the tautology &#8216;all alone by myself&#8217;.</note> am
                    all alone by myself, take pen &amp; paper to inform you of this daughters safe arrival.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have desired <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> to send you a book of shreds &amp;
                        patches,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Omniana, or Horae Otiosiores</title> (1812).</note> the work of many hours of that sort of laborious idleness, which is
                    to me the most delightful of all dissipation. You will find some things to smile at, &amp; some curious facts affording matter for
                    speculation, from which it is not impossible that scientific men may draw <del>important</del> conclusions of some importance. I
                    inserted some <del>things</del> &lt;articles&gt; of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> in the book,
                    merely in the hope of getting some thing from him in this way, &#8211; he had literally only to cut them out of his commonplace books.
                        <del>Xx xxxxx xx</del> it was my intention to make four volumes instead of two in this manner; &#8211; but he kept the press waiting
                    fifteen months for an unfinished article, so that at last I ordered the sheet in which it was begun to be cancelled in despair. I
                    have marked whatever is his, &amp; you will wish that it were more.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My intended journey to London is postponed till spring, because it is expedient that the Register<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813).</note> for 1811 should be published in April, &amp; this therefore
                    allows me no time to stir from home. I am busily employed upon it, &amp; have this day got over in as summary a manner as possible
                    the Bullion business, &#8211; a part to which I looked on with as much horror as ever Christian did to the Slough of Despond, or the
                    Hill of Difficulty.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 89&#8211;114. Southey compares his troubles writing this section
                        with incidents in John Bunyan (1628&#8211;1688; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Pilgrim&#8217;s Progress</title> (1678&#8211;1684).</note> This
                    is a very laborious work; it does not weary me, &#8211; nevertheless as it commenced with the usurpation of Spain,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810), which dealt with the French invasion of Spain in 1808.</note> the
                    first instance in which Buonaparte unequivocally displayed himself in his true character of pure Devil, I should be well pleased
                    to bring my part in it to a conclusion in his fall: an event which I verily hope is not far distant. This murderous war in Russia,
                    since it has become not a political game at war for territory, but a national cause, in which men fight <del>for</del> to save
                    their wives &amp; children, or to revenge them, &#8211; promises to become as fatal to France as the Spanish contest has been;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French had invaded Russia on 24 June 1812. Although they won a tactical victory at
                        Borodino (7 September), in the longer-term Napoleon&#8217;s failure to destroy the Russian army marked a turning point in the
                        campaign. Their numbers decimated by appalling weather, lack of supplies and guerilla attacks, the last French troops left
                        Russia on 14 December 1812.</note> &amp; a daybreak of hope has appeared even in Paris itself.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The attempted Parisian coup of 23 October 1812 led by Claude Fran&#231;ois Malet (1754&#8211;1812). This planned to
                        announce the death of Bonaparte and establish a provisional republican government. It failed and the leaders were executed on
                        31 October.</note> Should he leave his army <del>xx</del> to prevent the danger of another insurrection. I hardly think,
                    composed as it is of so many different people, all forced to serve, &amp; hating him for whom they are sacrificed that it can be
                    kept together: &amp; should he continue with it, there is good hope that a winter at Moscow may involve him &amp; his army in the
                    same destruction, &#8211; or that a more succesful attempt at deliverance may be made in France, &amp; that she may refuse any longer to
                    supply so wicked &amp; so wanton a waste of life. Oh that there were but energy enough in our Government to publish the terms upon
                    which it is ready to make peace with France. &#8211; at the same time pledging itself never to make peace with this frantic tyrant! What
                    an instrument would such a declaration have been in the hands of these Generals at Paris!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Curwen has been thrown out at Carlisle merely by the infamy of his private character.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> At the 1812 general election, the wealthy colliery owner John Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>)
                        had allegedly refused to stand for the Carlisle seat he had held for 21 years because of rumours concerning his seduction of
                        Dorothy Watson (1777&#8211;1837), eldest daughter of Richard Watson, Bishop of Llandaff, who owned
                        an estate at Calgarth on Lake Windermere.</note> His election would have been certain, if he could have dared to face the
                    stories which would have risen in judgement against him. This is at least a triumph of public decency. He has got into a sort of
                    sentimental intrigue with the eldest Miss Watson, concerning which he has written a letter of exculpation to <ref target="people.html#SpeddingJohn">Spedding</ref>, &#8211; confessing imprudence, &amp; protesting &lt;his&gt; innocence. The country
                    rings with this<hi rend="ital"> scandalum magnatum</hi>,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Scandal of magnates&#8217;; in
                        (obsolete) English law a defamatory speech or writing that injures a peer of the realm.</note> the common people see a sort of
                    sacrilege in intriguing with a Bishops daughter &#8211; others half lose the feeling<del>s</del> which his intimacy with the old Bishop
                    have occasioned, in astonishment at his folly; &#8211; for that grossest &amp; most outrageous imprudencies have take place is beyond
                    all doubt.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So much for Cumberland scandal. Of other news the best is that our friend <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss
                        Barker</ref> is settled in the next house. White-Widow,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The unnamed mistress and
                        heiress of William White (d. 1811).</note> as she was called, having married the first man who asked her, &#8211; a good riddance
                    for us. The wet October which we have had, has spoilt <ref target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calverts</ref> corn upon the top of Lattrig, which would else have been <del>an abund</del>
                    a most profitable crop. The floating island<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Floating Island is a mass of vegetation
                        in Lake Derwentwater that is sometimes raised to the surface by marsh gas.</note> attempted to rise about six weeks ago, but
                    did not reach the surface. You heard of the failure of the Workington bank,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Workington Bank had failed earlier in 1812, causing much local inconvenience.</note> &#8211; I have five &amp; twenty of their
                    notes, but am better off than many of my neighbours. Spence<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Spence (dates unknown)
                        had built &#8216;Pigmy Hall&#8217;, near Keswick.</note> has left the country &amp; sold his house to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Morsehead<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably Sir Frederick Treise Morshead, 2nd Baronet (1783&#8211;1828), rather
                        than his younger brother, John Morshead (d. 1831), a Lieutenant in the 10th Hussars.</note> (son of Sir John M.)<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John Morshead, 1st Baronet (1747&#8211;1812), landowner and MP for Bodmin (1790&#8211;1801). In 1809 he
                        lost much of his fortune, allegedly at the gaming table, and retired to the Isle of Man.</note> &#8211; who keeps a mistress in it,
                    in more open scandal than his predecessor. Lord William has bought Marshalls house,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lord
                        William Gordon (1744&#8211;1823), son of Cosmo George Gordon, 3rd Duke of Gordon (1720&#8211;1752). He owned the Waterend estate on the
                        west side of Derwentwater. Mr Marshall is unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> &amp; I hope will improve
                        <del>his</del> &lt;its&gt; appearance. His property will be prodigiously increased by an inclosure which is about to take
                    place of all the fells between Derwent &amp; Buttermere. Methinks this is a tolerably good <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> Gazette.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now let me ask you whether little Mary<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Browne (dates unknown) was
                        Wade Browne&#8217;s only child from his second marriage.</note> is yet provided with a play-fellow? &amp; how you &amp; <ref target="people.html#BrowneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> B.</ref> &amp; your daughters<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Wade Browne&#8217;s daughters from his first marriage: Lydia (c. 1789&#8211;1864); Elizabeth (dates unknown); and Sarah
                        (1793/1794&#8211;1860s).</note> have been during the long interval which (by our own fault) has elapsed since we have heard of you.
                    Is Wade<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wade Browne (1796&#8211;1851), only son of Wade Browne. He later became a country
                        gentleman at Monkton Farleigh in Somerset.</note> at his new school? And does he not sometimes wistfully remember not the
                    fleshpots of <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, but the great fish of Keswick Lake?</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> joins in the kindest remembrances with</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs most truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> Lucien Buonaparte<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lucien Bonaparte (1775&#8211;1840), brother of Napoleon
                            and author of <title>Charlemagne, ou l&#8217;Eglise D&#233;livr&#233;e</title> (1814). Southey refused a request to translate it into
                            English. Southey did not review it but did insert a critical aside in his review of accounts of Wellington and Waterloo,
                                <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (July 1815), 448&#8211;526: &#8216;The publication of Charlemagne, so ostentatiously
                            announced, was fatal to his [Bonaparte&#8217;s] literary character &#8230; his poem &#8230; proved him to be a sorry Homer&#8217; (489).</note>
                        has made his arrangements for publication with <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, &amp; no doubt his poem will
                        be consigned to my critical care. This has long been settled. My own poem<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> of which I had the pleasure of showing you the commencement,
                        is rapidly proceeding. I had a curious letter last week from an <ref target="people.html#LongmireJohnMartyn">Evangelical
                            Clergyman</ref>, requesting that he might send me the moral of Thalaba, &amp; telling me that it had strengthened his
                            faith.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors"> Longmire had read <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801) as an
                            allegory of the powers and virtues of Faith, and drawn parallels between events and characters in Southey&#8217;s poem and the
                            bible; see Southey to John Martyn Longmire, 4 November 1812, Letter 2172.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>