<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2401</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3672</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2401" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2401" type="letter">
        <head>2401. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, [<date when="1814-04-13">13 April 1814</date>]</head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9. Stafford Row/ Buckingham Gate/ London.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ 16 AP 16/ 1814
                        <lb />Endorsement: 13 April 1814<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Shipt by the grace of God in good condition on board the good stage coach <del>the Defian</del> Good Intent a Pike
                    weighing 27lb. <del>thi</del> to be this present day April 13. 1814 conveyed to Penrith, &amp; from thence forwarded by the Mail
                    Coach, directed to G. C. B. <ref target="places.html#StaffordRow">Stafford Row</ref>. And so God send the good pike to its desired
                    table in safety.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So large a fish at this early season had not been caught for fifty years in Basenthwaite Lake. This is the best
                    season, &amp; no person here makes any doubt of its arriving in good condition, for pike will keep five or six days, <hi rend="ital">six </hi>
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary"> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref> desires me to say; a little salt does not injure them.
                    A fish of this size is better cut &amp; boiled like salmon. Thus they dress them <del>in</del> at Geneva, &#8211; &amp; thus we always
                    do;</p>
        <p rend="indent3"> _____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had imagined three likely catastrophes for Buonaparte; that he would fight till the last &amp; die game, &#8211; that
                    he would (like Lope de Aguirre<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The conquistador Lope de Aguirre (c. 1510&#8211;1561), notorious
                        for his final expedition down the Amazon in search of El Dorado. Southey had published a &#8216;Life&#8217; of Aguirre in the
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812), [i]-l; republished as <title>The Expedition of Orsua; and
                            the Crimes of Aguirre</title> (1821).</note>) be forsaken by every body, &amp; kill himself; &#8211; or that he would abscond
                    &amp; be lost. Another might have been added which is still probable enough, &#8211; that his own soldiers would take revenge upon him.
                    Neither of these would be so humiliating to him as thus <del>present</del> to be pensioned off!<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Paris had been captured by allied forces on 30 March 1814, but Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821) did not abdicate
                        until 6 April 1814. Under the terms of the Treaty of Fontainebleau, he was exiled to Elba, given sovereignty over the island,
                        and permitted to retain the title Emperor.</note> Not that I would have assented to any such arrangement; he ought to have
                    been hunted down, &amp; exhibited upon a gibbet dead or alive. Austria has prevented this, &amp; I dare say the Parisians are even
                    more disappointed than I am. That amiable people would have delighted in seeing him on the wheel. He will suffer more in living to
                    hear the execrations of mankind, which will perpetually <del>x</del> keep him in mind of the damnation in store for him. As for
                    the French people &#8211; they have acted up to their <del>xxxxxxx</del> character. <del>Folly</del> Frivolity, baseness &amp; unfeeling
                    folly were never more beautifully exemplified than in the first effusions of the Bourbonized Monsteur.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles X (1757&#8211;1836; King of France 1824&#8211;1830). As the King&#8217;s eldest brother he held the title &#8216;Monsieur&#8217;
                        (which Southey lampoons as &#8216;Monsteur&#8217;) and acted as Lieutenant-General of the Kingdom until Louis XVIII (1755&#8211;1824; King of
                        France 1814&#8211;1824) could arrive in Paris.</note> They have found out that B. is a Corsican! They have found out that no
                    Frenchman presumed to sit upon the throne of the Bourbons, &#8211; good people so delicate towards the crown, &#8211; &amp; so tender towards
                    the head that wore it! &#8211; And I dare say that those Senators who <del>before the King of Romes backside</del> paid their
                    appropriate reverence to the King of Rome<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Napoleon&#8217;s son and heir, Napoleon II
                        (1811&#8211;1832), whose title was King of Rome. Napoleon had attempted to abdicate in his favour on 4 April 1814, but when the
                        allies would not accept this proposal, Napoleon abdicated on his own and his son&#8217;s behalf on 6 April 1814.</note> are ready to
                    exclaim what have we kissed his nasty dirty backside &amp; all for nothing!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Well Grosvenor this Tragedy of five &amp; twenty years is over. I shall never forget the sensation which the fall
                    of the curtain gave me. But I will not dwell upon this subject.</p>
        <p rend="indent3"> ____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Praise me for good will at least, if not for good works. I have laid down the timbers of another ode,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly Southey&#8217;s proposed &#8211; but unexecuted &#8211; ode celebrating the peace of 1814.</note> &amp;
                    written the first stanza this morning. This &amp; the Epithalamium,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince Regent&#8217;s</ref> only child Charlotte Augusta (1796&#8211;1817;
                        <title>DNB</title>), had been engaged since December 1813 to the Hereditary Prince of Orange, William (1792&#8211;1849; King of the
                        Netherlands 1840&#8211;1849), the husband selected for her by her father and his advisers. As Poet Laureate, Southey was required to
                        write on the occasion. He started the required poem (<title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen Nuptiale</title>) but in the
                        event it was not needed as the engagement was broken off in June 1814. The <title>Lay</title> was recycled in 1816 to
                        celebrate Charlotte&#8217;s marriage to Leopold of Saxe-Coburg (1790&#8211;1865; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; the Inscriptions<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Inscriptions Triumphal and Sepulchral, recording the acts of the British army in
                        the Peninsula&#8217; had been recently advertised as &#8216;nearly ready for publication&#8217; (e.g. in <title>European Magazine</title>, 65
                        (January 1814), 77). However, the promised volume did not appear and only 18 of the proposed 30 inscriptions were written.
                        They were not collected together until 1837&#8211;1838 when they appeared in the last-lifetime edition of Southey&#8217;s <title>Poetical
                            Works</title>.</note> ought to intitle me to a discharge in full from all future official compositions, &#8211; the death of the
                        <del>King or</del> Sovereign<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of the United Kingdom
                        1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>). His death led to Southey&#8217;s <title>A Vision of Judgment</title> (1821).</note> excepted. &#8211; The
                    Times was sent me one day last week with that article in it concerning the Carmen &amp; <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s feud with Jeffrey continued unabated. The notes to
                            <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> had attacked the personalities and politics of the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>. The
                        review of <title>Carmen</title> in <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 22 (January 1814), 447&#8211;454, retorted: &#8216;For our own parts,
                        when we are seriously occupied with the destinies of Europe, or of mankind, we should think very contemptibly of ourselves, if
                        we could permit the recollection of our differences with Mr Southey to intrude either into our writings or our thoughts&#8217;
                        (452), before going on to criticise his support of the Spanish and acceptance of the Laureateship. An article in <title>The
                            Times</title>, 7 April 1814 attacked these comments. Finally, <title>The Times</title>, 21 April 1814 reprinted the &#8216;Ode
                        Written During the Negotiations with Bonaparte&#8217;, in a corrected version and retitled &#8216;Ode; Written in January, 1814&#8217;. A short
                        headnote again defended Southey from the criticism levelled against him in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>.</note> The
                    review which called forth this attack I have not seen, &#8211; but from the excessive soreness which <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> expressed upon my notes,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> For Southey&#8217;s
                        reply to Wynn&#8217;s criticisms, see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 15 January 1814, Letter 2364.</note> I was perfectly
                    certain they would produce their full &amp; proper effect. On the next occasion I shall serve up a second course, &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Master Jeffrey</ref> will find before I have done with him that he could not have laid
                    hold of an <hi rend="ital">uglier customer</hi>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very much obliged to Courtenay<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Peregrine Courtenay (1782&#8211;1841;
                            <title>DNB</title>), MP for Totnes 1811&#8211;1832 and Secretary of the Board of Control 1812&#8211;1828. He had previously been a
                        civil servant at the Exchequer, where he probably encountered Grosvenor Bedford.</note> for having frequently of late sent me
                        <del>news</del> later news than the evening paper would have communicated.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211; Let me have the books of Roderick<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> MS drafts of
                            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> as soon as you can. I have as yet made but little way in the
                        17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#8211; but the spirit is come, &amp; it will now be in good progress.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do&#8217;nt be in a-hurry to go to Paris, &#8211; &amp; perhaps I will run over with you <del>wh</del> for a few weeks when
                    next I visit London. <hi rend="ital">Entre nous</hi> if I ever go there it must be before my history<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> is published, as I shall most certainly speak in very
                    plain terms of certain Marshals &amp; Dukes who have hitherto escaped a halter.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Vale &#8211;</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Wednesday evening.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>