<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2571</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3842</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47553.  Previously  published: W.
                        Braekman, &#8216;Letters by Robert Southey to Sir John Taylor Coleridge&#8217;, Studia Germanica Gandensia, 6 (1964), 110&#8211;112.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2571" type="letter">
        <head>2571. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1815-03-14">14 March 1815</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Coleridge Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 44. Southampton Buildings/ Chancery Lane/ London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/
                        298<lb />Postmark: E/ 17 MR 17/ 1815<lb />Endorsement: R. Southey Keswick March 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1815<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47553<lb />Previously published: W.
                        Braekman, &#8216;Letters by Robert Southey to Sir John Taylor Coleridge&#8217;, <title>Studia Germanica Gandensia</title>, 6 (1964), 110&#8211;112.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1815-03-14">14 March. 1815</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I received your letter yesterday, &amp; allowed myself four &amp; twenty hours to chew the cud upon it. This evening a letter has arrived from <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeWilliamHart">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Coleridge</ref>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Hart Coleridge was
                        well-suited to give advice about the University of Oxford as he had graduated from Christ Church in 1811.</note> in answer to one which <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S. Coleridge</ref> had written inquiring when it would be necessary for <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> to be at Oxford. In this letter an opinion is expressed of the value of <hi rend="ital">time</hi> at <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley&#8217;s</ref> age which comes in aid of my own judgement. &#8211; He is now in his nineteenth year.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I feel all the objections which you have stated to Merton,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hartley Coleridge enrolled at Merton College, Oxford in 1815,
                        largely because he was awarded a scholarship or &#8216;Postmastership&#8217;.</note> &#8211; perhaps even more forcibly than you do, because I am thoroughly acquainted with <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref>. There is no young man to whom it could be of so much importance to be under a tutor whom he <del>xxxx</del>
                    &lt;might&gt; respect. Such a tutor <del>xxxx</del> would find in &lt;him&gt; all the docility he could desire, &amp; would soon become attached to him. But a man who should be
                    incapable of seeing farther than the outside might excite in him a contempt for the course of University Studies, which <del>xx</del> of all things is most to be deprecated in his
                    case.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Let me tell you as well as I can, what kind of youth this cousin of yours, &amp; nephew of mine, is. Without being an ugly fellow, he is a marvellously odd one; &#8211; he
                    is very short, with remarkably strong features, some of the thickest &amp; blackest eyebrows you ever saw, &amp; a beard which a Turk might envy. His manners are almost as peculiar
                    as his appearance, &amp; having discovered that he is awkward by nature, he has formed an unhappy conclusion that art will never make him otherwise, &amp; so resigns himself to his
                    fate. My endeavours have not been wanting to remedy or rather palliate this, &#8211; but it is bred in the bone, &#8211; &amp; you know the remainder of the proverb.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. &#8216;What&#8217;s bred in the bone will come out in the flesh.&#8217;</note> I have <del>xxxx</del> even habitually quizzed him for the purpose of teaching him to bear
                    such things with good humour, &#8211; knowing how much he <del>will</del> must be exposed to it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thus much for the outward man. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley&#8217;s</ref> intellect will soon overcome all disadvantages that his exterior may
                    incur, if it do but <hi rend="ital">keep the course</hi>. And here indeed I feel how fortunate it is that he has a <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeWilliamHart">kinsman</ref> upon the spot so willing &amp; able to direct him, &amp; whom he is so well prepared to respect. The great lesson which <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; myself have endeavoured to impress upon him is that he goes to Oxford to devote himself to the studies of
                    the place; &amp; that no degree of general ability, or general knowledge, can, or ought to, atone for any deficiency in the attainments which the University requires; that to these
                    he must apply himself <hi rend="ital">totis viribus</hi>
          <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;With all his might&#8217;.</note> while he is there; &amp; when he has attained by
                    these that establishment for which we look, life will be before him to cultivate his intellect in whatever manner he may then please. His disposition is excellent: his principles
                    thoroughly good; &amp; he has instinctively a devotional feeling which I hope will keep them so. An overweening confidence in his own <del>xxxx</del> talents, &amp; a perilous
                    habit of finding out reasons for whatever he likes to do, are the dangerous parts of his character. &#8211; To extravagance he has not the slightest propensity, &#8211; but he knows as little
                    of frugality; &amp; it is well that he has a friend at hand who may question him concerning his ways &amp; means, &#8211; for in these things he is, &amp; I believe always will be a mere
                    child.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will see from this faithful statement how especially desirable it is that he should be under good discipline. I should not therefore for a moment hesitate in
                    preferring Corpus, were it not on the score of his age. [MS torn]ting till after Xmas, <del>xxxx</del> three terms would be lost &#8211; &amp; I could not say that the time would
                    certainly be as well employed as it might be. Emulation is wanting here, &amp; mathematics are evidently against the grain. <del>xxxx xxx xxxx xxxx xxx xxxx xxxxx xxxxxx</del> All
                    things considered I incline to think that he had better taken the Merton situation, &amp; be removed from thence whenever it is practicable to Corpus. But I would better refer this
                    to your judgement &amp; your cousin&#8217;s, than my own, for you need not be told that Oxford in my days was not what it is now. Do you therefore decide, &#8211; &amp; let us know your
                    determination.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must not forget to say that when he shall be fairly at college, there is a prospect of getting some <hi rend="ital">city exhibitions</hi> for him, &#8211; things perhaps
                    of which you never heard. They come from the different companies,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. the City of London Livery Companies.</note> &amp; are of 8 to 10&#163;
                    each, &#8211; but a man may hold as many of them as he can get: they are obtained by interest, &amp; I have a friend<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, with whom Southey had been corresponding about Hartley&#8217;s future.</note> upon the watch in his behalf, with good hope of
                    success. But the recipient must actually be keeping terms, before he can be named to them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now my dear Sir farewell. I hope it is needless to add how glad we should be if in one of your summer holydays, you would direct your course toward the Lakes; &#8211;
                        <del>x xxxxxxxx</del> you will find a bed, a sincere welcome, &#8211; &amp; an experienced guide.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>I ought to say that <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> has Greek enough for a whole College.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>