<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2391</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3662</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        34046.  Previously  published: Letters from the Lake Poets, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, William Wordsworth, Robert
                            Southey, to Daniel Stuart (London, 1889), pp. 416&#8211;420. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2391" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2391" type="letter">
        <head>2391. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Daniel Stuart</ref>, <date when="1814-03-14">14 March
                        1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Daniel Stuart Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Kilburne
                        House/ near London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: 10o&#8217;Clock/ MR.18/ 1814 F.N<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Endorsements:
                        Southey 1814/ Irregularity of Courier/ Spain/ Wordsworths Recluse; Southey March/ 1814<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        34046<lb />Previously published: <title>Letters from the Lake Poets, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, William Wordsworth, Robert
                            Southey, to Daniel Stuart</title> (London, 1889), pp. 416&#8211;420. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-03-14">March 14. 1814.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is one of the Miseries of Human Life in times like these to be disappointed of one&#8217;s newspaper, &#8211; &amp; for the
                    last three or four weeks the Courier has fallen into such a course of irregularity that I think the cause cannot lie in the
                    Post-Office. To day we have the paper which ought to have arrived on Sunday, &#8211; &amp; indeed the right paper seldom arrives on the
                    right day, &#8211; for one whole week we were sometimes one, sometimes two days behind hand, &#8211; I am sure you will excuse me for
                    informing you of this misery.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I cannot but assent to all you say about the Bourbons.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> It was becoming
                        increasingly likely that the Bourbon dynasty would be restored to power in France, especially once Napoleon rejected the terms
                        of the Treaty of Chaumont of 1 March 1814, which offered France a ceasefire in return for accepting the country&#8217;s borders of
                        1791.</note> Most certainly it is a desirable event that they should be restored; &amp; if I have any feelings which would
                    allay the joy that such an event ought to excite, they would arise not so much from a remembrance of the early days of the
                    Revolution, as from the history of the family, &#8211; for the policy of Louis 13, 14 &amp; 15<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Louis XIII (1601&#8211;1643; King of France 1610&#8211;1643); Louis XIV (1638&#8211;1715; King of France 1643&#8211;1715); Louis XV (1710&#8211;1774; King
                        of France 1715&#8211;1774).</note> was little less flagitious than that of Buonaparte, tho not upon so wide a scale. They have been
                    bitter &amp; treacherous enemies to England: &#8211; this however was natural, &amp; the Government of France is always likely to be
                    actuated by the same spirit.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At present I look at the contest with more apprehension than hope. The readiness of our ministry to make peace
                    against the opinion both of the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> &amp; the people, must tend greatly to
                    dishearten such of the allies as are hearty in the cause, which no doubt Russia &amp; Prussia are, &amp; the Germans also in
                    general, &#8211; but I distrust some of their courts. And if peace be made, in the course of a year or two when <del>he is</del>
                    &lt;Buonaparte is&gt; strong enough to break it I fear we should see him fighting on German ground in alliance with Austria. <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> thinks that Austria is playing false, &amp; wilfully exposing Blucher
                    &amp; the Russians to be cut up.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gebhard Leberecht von Blucher (1742&#8211;1819), Prussian Field
                        Marshal and commander of the Army of Silesia, a joint Prussian and Russian force. Blucher was defeated by Napoleon at
                        Champaubert (10 February 1814), Montmirail (11 February 1814) and Vauchamps (14 February 1814), but still managed to win a
                        decisive victory at Laon (9&#8211;10 March 1814). Meanwhile, the Austrian Army of Bohemia was notably inactive.</note> If any thing
                    were to be got by it I should think so too, &#8211; for the Austrian Government is capable of any baseness. Did I tell you that Hofer
                    took shelter in a prison at Vienna, getting himself arrested under a false name, &#8211; &amp; that he was actually turned out?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Tyrolean patriot Andreas Hofer (1767&#8211;1810), executed for his leadership of a failed
                        rebellion against France&#8217;s ally, Bavaria.</note> Adair assured me that this is a fact!<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The politician and diplomat Sir Robert Adair (1763&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>), who had been posted to Vienna from
                        1806&#8211;1809.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The campaign in France puts Spain out of sight, &#8211; the affairs of that country would otherwise excite, &amp;
                    probably baffle, all our political sagacity. Will Ferdinand or the New Constitution go to the Wall &#8211; or is it possible that they
                    can long hold together?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813&#8211;1833). He had
                        been a prisoner in France since 1808, but his release was agreed in the Treaty of Valencay on 11 December 1813. He was finally
                        liberated on 24 March 1814 and lost little time in abolishing the liberal Constitution of 1812, on 4 May 1814.</note>
                    Ferdinand was at first a mere stalking-horse, &amp; after his arrest an excellent <hi rend="ital">nom de guerre</hi>, but in the
                    course of the war, the people may have <del>been taught</del> learnt to believe that they were fighting for him &amp; his rights,
                    &#8211; <del>xx</del> in that case any able minister will find little difficulty in sweeping away all the sweeping reforms of the
                    Cortes, &amp; the New Constitution will go to the family vault. A Spanish Officer<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably
                        a Colonel Stenor; see Southey to Mary Barker, [c. 9 November 1813], Letter 2325.</note> told me that if the Duke del
                        Infantado<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro de Alc&#225;ntara &#193;lvarez de Toledo, 13th Duke of the Infantado
                        (1768&#8211;1841). He had attended the conference of Spanish leaders called by Napoleon at Bayonne in March-April 1808 and had been
                        the leader of those participants who rejected the idea of passing the throne to Napoleon&#8217;s elder brother, Joseph I (1768&#8211;1844;
                        King of Spain 1808&#8211;1813).</note> on his escape from Bayonne had had the spirit of a mouse (those were his words) he would have
                    been King of Spain. The officer was in Romanas<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish general Pedro Caro y Sureda,
                        3rd Marquis of la Romana (1761&#8211;1811).</note> army &amp; spoke his own feelings &amp; those of his comrades. I know not which
                    is most probable. &#8211; that he should be deposed, &#8211; or that he should be reestablished in all the despotic power of his forefathers:
                    &#8211; but either is more likely than that the Constitution should be permanent. For the Cortes have done many things prematurely, many
                    things unjustly: &#8211; on the one hand this facilitates to the Crown <del>xx</del> what must needs be its darling object, &#8211; <del>that
                        it rec</del> the recovery of its uncontrolled authority, &#8211; on the other the same spirit which has produced these measures is
                    ready to go farther, &#8211; perhaps &amp; probably the whole length of Republicanism.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Why does the Courier attack Madam Sta&#235;l so often?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anne Louise Germaine de
                        Sta&#235;l-Holstein (1766&#8211;1817), Swiss writer and hostess of a famous salon, whom Southey had met in London in 1813.</note> There
                    is no person who abhors Buonaparte more heartily than she does, &#8211; or who would more zealously maintain the necessity of carrying
                    on the war against him as long as he is at the head of the French Government. The picture which I heard her draw of France, when
                    talking upon the subject to Mackintosh<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The writer and politician Sir James Mackintosh
                        (1765&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref>, would have figured as a
                    leading article in the Courier or the Times. I am sorry to see her attacked. The Opposition flatter her, &amp; tho she is fairly
                    astonished at their political blunders in the ordinary course of human nature she will learn to think well of those who speak well
                    of her.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> is about to put his great poem (the Recluse) to the press, &#8211; which
                    has been the great work of his life.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Excursion</title> (1814); it was the second part of Wordsworth&#8217;s long-projected, but never completed three-part
                        &#8216;The Recluse&#8217;.</note> Sooner or later it will no doubt place him in his proper rank among the English Poets, &#8211; &amp; if I were
                    to supply him with a motto for it, it should be <hi rend="ital">Parturiunt montes</hi>, &#8211; without any fear that the remainder of
                    the line could be added, &#8211; &amp; in defiance of it.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. only the first part of the
                        quotation from Horace, <title>Ars Poetica</title>, line 139: &#8216;Paturient montes, nascetus ridiculus mus&#8217; (&#8216;The mountains are in
                        labour, and a ridiculous mouse is born&#8217;) applied to Wordsworth.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> &amp; her sisters<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sarah Coleridge</ref> and <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary
                        Lovell</ref>.</note> beg to be remembered to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Stuart.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary
                        Napier Schalch (dates unknown), whom Stuart had married in 1813. She was the daughter of Major Schalch of the Royal
                        Artillery.</note> Present my respects to her also &amp; believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>