<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2338</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3609</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        25.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2338" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2338" type="letter">
        <head>2338. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1813-11-30">30 November 1813</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer<lb />Endorsement: 30 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1813<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        25<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1813-11-30">Nov 30. 1813</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Roderic<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> must go to press for this reason among others, that when it is
                    in the printers hands I shall feel that my first &amp; most urgent business must be to finish it. You wish to preserve the copy. &#8211;
                    I will direct the printer to preserve it &amp; keep it as clean as he can, &#8211; the dirt which it may contract in his hands will
                    rather increase than lessen its value as a curiosity. &#8211; So send it me I pray you as soon as you can under favour of some franks
                    potential, &amp; I on my part will make what speed I can to send you the continuation &amp; conclusion. &#8211; And if you send me some
                    money also it will not come before it is wanted. I feel the sudden defalc<hi rend="ital">ation</hi> of 400 &#163; a year from the
                    Edinburgh concern,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had severed his connection with the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register</title> and had therefore lost &#163;400 p.a.</note> &amp; if Roderic does not lend me a good lift shall be put to
                    some difficulties in the course of the next year &amp; half.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have written about 120 verses of an Ode which will run to some 30 or forty lines more.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s first official poem as Poet Laureate was extremely controversial and much altered prior to
                        publication. The final five stanzas were considered by Croker and Rickman to be inflammatory. Southey bowed to pressure and
                        deleted them from the version published as <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> in a quarto of 30 pages on 1 January 1814. He
                        incorporated the deleted stanzas into an &#8216;Ode Written During the Negotiations with Bonaparte&#8217;, published in the
                            <title>Courier</title> 3 February 1814.</note> It is somewhat stately, &#8211; &amp; I hope other people may like it better than
                    I do. <ref target="people.html#ParsonsWilliam">Sir William</ref> may cut out as much as he pleases. Three verses of <del>the
                            100<hi rend="sup">dth</hi>
          </del> &lt;a&gt; psalm are the regular allowance of <del>even</del> a congregation, &amp; I
                    suppose a Laureates ode ought not to overstep the modesty of four stanzas. This is <ref target="people.html#ParsonsWilliam">Sir
                        Williams</ref> business, &#8211; how much or how little he sets of it I care not, &#8211; as I am not to sing it. For its appearance in
                    print I ought to care I suppose, as it will be looked for with no common curiosity, &#8211; but in honest truth I care very little about
                    it. For be it good or bad, it will be but a weeks wonder. Tomorrow will perhaps see it finished, &amp; then I will send it to you.
                    &#8211; My purpose is to write a series of Inscriptions for our battles in the Peninsula, &amp; the officers who have fallen, &amp; to
                    print them with the ode, &amp; an Epistle to the <ref target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">Prince</ref> prefixed.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> This volume did not materialise. Only 18 of the proposed 30 inscriptions on the Peninsular War
                        were written.</note> This is volunteering gaily.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will write to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> concerning <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Robert Southey to Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn, 18 December 1813, Letter 2352.</note> My conviction is that if he be sent to Spain, he will very soon return to
                    his present way of life. Nevertheless I will readily act against conviction, if you &amp; he think that the trial ought to be
                    made. &#8211; About <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> &amp; my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> I feel exactly as he supposes, &#8211; &amp; he will relieve me from a burden upon my <del>xxx</del> mind, if he will
                    mention the subject.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The surrender of Davoust, the submission of Denmark, &amp; the recovery of Italy will be the next news.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The French Marshal Louis-Nicolas d&#8217;Avout (1770&#8211;1823) was besieged in Hamburg, but did not
                        surrender until the end of the war in April 1814. Denmark was increasingly isolated and withdrew from the war under the terms
                        of the Treaty of Kiel, 14 January 1814. There was no decisive victory for the Austrians in Northern Italy and the French Army
                        of Italy only surrendered at the end of the war in April 1814.</note> But the Netherlands also must be rescued, &amp; Down
                    down with the Tyrant!<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> i.e. Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821). The Netherlands had been
                        incorporated into France in 1810.</note> Vengeance for Toussaint,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The hero of Haitian
                        independence, Fran&#231;ois-Dominique Toussaint-Louverture (1743&#8211;1803), who died in prison in France.</note> for Pichegru, for the
                    Duc d&#8217;Enghien, for Wright, for Palm &amp; for Hofer! This is to be the burden of my Ode &#8211;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Early drafts of <title>Carmen Triumphale</title>, Southey&#8217;s first Laureate poem, included the accusation that the Bonapartist
                        regime had murdered: Jean-Charles Pichegru (1761&#8211;1804), who was found strangled in his prison cell after returning to France
                        to lead a royalist uprising; the British naval officer John Wesley Wright (1769&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), captured on the
                        French coast in 1804 and suspected of landing Pichegru and other opponents of the regime, he was found with his throat cut in
                        prison the following year, a reported suicide; the German bookseller Johann Philipp Palm (1768&#8211;1806), executed without trial
                        for publishing an attack on Bonaparte; and the Tyrolese patriot Andreas Hofer (1767&#8211;1810), executed for his leadership of a
                        failed rebellion against Bonaparte. Southey was persuaded to remove these sections from the poem published in the
                            <title>Courier</title> on 8 January 1814. This unused material was turned into the ninth stanza of a new poem, &#8216;Ode Written
                        During the Negotiations with Bonaparte&#8217;, published in the <title>Courier</title>, 3 February 1814.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>