<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2399</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3670</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2399" type="letter">
        <head>2399. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1814-04-05">5 April 1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: 5 April 1814; April 5.
                        1814<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> You are right about <hi rend="ital">days</hi> instead of <hi rend="ital">years</hi>, &#8211; &amp; I cannot now tell for
                    what reason I <del>was</del> chose to avoid the repetition. Yet there must have been some, which perhaps will strike my eye or my
                    ear in correcting the proof.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was correcting proofs of <title>Roderick, the Last of
                            the Goths</title> (1814). The bulk of this letter deals with his responses to Bedford&#8217;s critique of the MS of the poem.
                        These remarks probably refer to Book 12, lines 68&#8211;69.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Exalted as here used has a foreign shade of meaning akin to Enthusiastic. wa<hi rend="ital">r</hi> I wore &#8211; was
                    miswritten, it should be war<hi rend="ital">s</hi>.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 12, lines 50, 64.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Does the prospect of future danger heighten the sense of present security you ask. The danger here described is
                    distant, &amp; doubtful: &amp; evils of <del>those</del> this degree I think have that effect. The man who means to rise at eight
                    on a cold morning, &amp; wakes at seven, enjoys his bed the more for the prospect of leaving it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will find by a note upon the scale-armour that I have gone as far back as possible for authority, &#8211; which is to
                    Roland &amp; Oliver.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The note was appended to <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title> (1814), Book 13, lines 108&#8211;109. It referenced the French paladins Roland and Oliver, who were reputed to
                        have died at the battle of Roncesvalles in the Pyrenees in 778.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I write bends instead of bent,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 12, line 162.</note> because seldom as such a case can happen the
                        <hi rend="ital">s</hi> is required in that place for the sake of euphony, to smooth the line. As for the tenses it is mere
                    pedantry to suppose that they may not be used at libitum where no possible ambiguity can be produced by <del>passing</del>
                    &lt;going&gt; from an indefinite<del>-perfect to a</del> past, to a passing present.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What is a Cat looking out of a window &#8211; most like? &#8211; Like a Cat looking in &#8211; says the old jest. But my simily is
                    not of this description.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 12, lines 223&#8211;224: &#8216;like the voice/ Of waters in the stillness of
                        the night&#8217;.</note> The sound of water by day is very different from the sound of water by night, &#8211; as you may perceive
                    whenever you come &amp; make the observation out of my room-window. And <hi rend="ital">here</hi> it is that the simily fails in
                    philosophical, but not in poetical truth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not comprehend what you mean by asking if Lines 43&#8211;4 Book 13, are not rather dogmatick.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the published poem, <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 13, lines
                        43&#8211;44 read: &#8216;Therefore gave way to wonder, and dismay/ Effected what astonishment began&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By aiming the point of the scymitar against the neck I meant precisely to describe the <del>xxxx</del> way of
                    beginning to behead by a push.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 13, lines 56&#8211;57.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> 62. The battle is over, &amp; if you recollect that a valley in a mountainous country is the scene, you will see
                    that a <hi rend="ital">little</hi> eminence by the way side is just where Chiefs who had done their work should take their stand
                    at such a time. To go higher would be to climb a mountain.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the published poem,
                            <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 13, line 67: &#8216;a little rocky eminence&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Asturias is the antecedent. By duty I understand what every man in the common routine of life is called upon to
                    perform &#8211; by virtue (in this place) <del>that higher</del> the voluntary discharge of it when there would be no positive crime in
                    the omission. &#8211; This is not expressed with due precision &#8211; but you will understand me, &amp; I am too much in haste to hunt for
                    more accurate language. I meant to <del>imply</del> &lt;say&gt; that martyrdom political or religious is not to be demanded of a
                    man, &#8211; &amp; that in the then state of Spain they who took arms with Pelayo must be such men as were volunteers for it. &#8211; The last
                    half line of the speech is to my ear &amp; feeling a worthy finish; &amp; in dramatic verse, which this is, the break in the
                    measure adds to its rapidity &amp; passion.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pelayo&#8217;s speech refusing to make terms with
                        the invaders, <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), Book 13, lines 169&#8211;212.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent5"> _____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The necessity of the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Book you will see in the progress of the story wherein Florinda must
                    rejoin her father. The dog also has his use. If you do not like his anglicised name I have no alternative but to borrow one from
                    Ovid, &amp; suppose the Romans left it there.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In MS drafts of <title>Roderick, the Last
                            of the Goths</title>, Southey originally gave the name Whitefoot to a faithful dog. He later changed it to Theron (after
                        one of Actaeon&#8217;s hound&#8217;s in Ovid&#8217;s <title>Metamorphoses</title>) and reduced the dog&#8217;s role in the poem; for the significance
                        of this see Diego Saglia, &#8216;A Siege, a Dog, and Too Many Women: Refiguring the Epic in <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title>&#8217;, <title>Romanticism</title> 17.1 (2011), 52&#8211;62.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent5"> _____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have here a book &lt;the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>&gt; which is almost wholly descriptive. The reason
                        <del>th</del> is that this valley <del>&amp; this xxxx xx</del> is the scene of the final battle: the description is as much
                    to the life as it can be made from books, &#8211; which are however tolerably minute. I have spangled the book with a few classical
                    &amp; other allusions.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am disappointed at the nonappearance of both my articles in this Quarterly,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s reviews of James Montgomery, <title>The World Before the Flood</title> (1813), eventually published
                        in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 11 (April 1814), 78&#8211;87; and of Johann Gottfried Haensel (1749&#8211;1814), <title>Letters on the
                            Nicobar Islands</title> (1812), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 11 (April 1814), 57&#8211;72.</note> &#8211; for the supply would
                    have come seasonably. &#8211; The <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">printer</ref> gallops on. He has got thro the 12 book &#8211; 152
                    pages &#8211; &amp; I am beginning the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>! &#8211; 20 or 26 will be the extent.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Roderick, the last of the Goths</title> (1814) finally ran to 25 books.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How is <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">your father</ref>? this will be a trying month for him. I think
                    often of him &amp; of you with a concern which you will very well understand.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you my dear Grosvenor &#8211;</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1814-04-05">April 5. 1814.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>