<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1895</idno><idno type="nines">rce3166</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 3880.  Previously  published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 307–308
                        [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>corrections from proofing</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>TEI Encoding</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1895" type="letter"><head>1895. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, <date when="1811-04-02">2 April
                        1811</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Scott Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Edinburgh<lb/>Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>Postmark: AP/ 1811/ 4<lb/>Watermark: shield/ JW &amp; BB/ 1808<lb/>Endorsement:
                        Southey/ 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> April/ 1811<lb/>MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 3880<lb/>Previously published: Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), III, pp. 307–308
                        [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1811-04-02">April 2. 1811</date></dateline><salute>My dear Scott</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> You can probably tell me how I could transmit a copy of Kehama<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> to your friend Leyden,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The poet and
                        linguist John Leyden (1775–1811; <title>DNB</title>).</note> for whom tho I do not personally know him, I have always felt a
                    very high respect, regarding him with one only exception (which might be more properly expressed to any person than to you) as a
                    man of more true genius &amp; far higher promise than any of his contemporary countrymen.</p><p rend="indent1"> In your last you mention a probability of your going to London in the spring. I hope either to meet you there, or
                    to see you on your way. I thought to have been there early in May, but the year 1809 left behind it such a load of labour upon my
                    shoulders that I know not when it will be got rid <del>off</del> of, &amp; till it is done I am chained to the oar. The history
                    will sum to 700 pages, which is half as much again as that of the preceding year.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey
                        was not alone in his worries. <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantyne</ref> was concerned enough about the length
                        of the historical section to insist that Southey explained himself to the readers in a prefatory note; see <title>Edinburgh
                            Annual Register, for 1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), [v]–vi.</note> It could not be shortened without leaving undone those things
                    which ought to be done,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> A line from the ‘General Confession’ in the <title>Book of Common
                            Prayer</title> (1662).</note> &amp; yet I fear that the length will be urged against it as an objection, tho God knows it
                    is a greater inconvenience to me than it can possibly be to any body else.</p><p rend="indent1"> No doubt you have seen Pasley’s Essay,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Charles William Pasley
                        (1780–1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Essay on the Military Policy and Institutions of the British Empire</title>
                        (1810).</note> it will be in the main a book after your own heart as it is after mine – He talks sometimes of conquest where
                    he should talk of emancipation. – a system of unlimited conquest leads at last to the consequences which we have seen exemplified
                    in the fate of the Roman Empire. For ourselves I would wish no other accession of dominion than Danish Zealand &amp; Holland in
                    the North, with as many islands as you please in the Mediterranean. Italy to be formed into an independent state under our
                    protection as long as it needed it. – I have been reviewing Pasley (with some help upon statistic points).<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey received assistance from <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> in his review of Pasley.
                        The final product was deemed by <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> to be ‘perfectly incorrect and
                        dangerous’. The version published in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 5 (May 1811), 403–457, was, therefore, much altered
                        by <ref target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, in consultation with Gifford and <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>; see <ref type="l" target="/reference/qr/index/10.html">Jonathan Cutmore, <title>The Quarterly Review Archive</title></ref>.</note> – my object has been rather to spread his fame &amp; convert
                    unbelievers to the true faith than to dwell upon any points of difference between us, – for I am fully persuaded that if the war
                    be carried on with vigour &amp; the means which we so abundantly possess be <del>f</del> but fairly excited we may dictate a peace
                    under the walls of Paris. &amp; I believe also that the Ministry do not want the inclination to act vigorously, – but that they
                    want <del>the</del> public opinion to go before &amp; protect them against the opposition. These men &amp; their coadjutors the
                    Morning Chronicle<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The London daily newspaper, which ran from 1769–1862. At this time,
                        under the ownership of James Perry (1756–1821; <title>DNB</title>), it was firmly allied with the Whigs.</note> &amp; the Ed.
                        Review<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Edinburgh Review</title> (1802–1929) was a quarterly journal closely
                        allied to the Whigs.</note> – have neither patriotism, nor principle, nor feeling, nor shame to stand in their way. They go on
                    predicting the total conquest of the Peninsula with as much effrontery as if they had not predicted it two years ago, – nay even
                    asserted that it was then compleated: – &amp; they deliver their predictions in such a way, that it requires more charity than I
                    possess not to believe that they [MS torn]sh to see them fulfilled: – for this is the last &amp; worst. yet the ne[MS torn]ry
                    effect of party spirit when carried as far as thes[MS torn] politicians carry it.</p><p rend="indent1"> I do not know that I ever regretted being alone so much as when the news of Grahams victory<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Major-General Thomas Graham (1748–1843; <title>DNB</title>), had played a crucial part in the victory of an
                        Anglo-Spanish force at Barrosa on 5 March 1811.</note> arrived. It gave me more delight then I could well hold, &amp; I wanted
                    somebody to share it with me. We shall have great news too from Portugal. Massena<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        French commander André Massena (1758–1817) had commenced a retreat from Portugal into Spain on 13 March 1811.</note> has no
                    lines to fall back upon, &amp; if <ref target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> can but bring him to
                    action we know what the result must be. How happy his retreat must make <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord
                        Grenville</ref> who had just delivered so wise an opinion upon the state of Portugal in the House of Lords!<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Grenville had made a speech in the House of Lords on 18 March 1811 on the futility of British
                        intervention in Spain and Portugal. Southey noted laconically, ‘Two days after these opinions were delivered, the telegraph
                        announced the news of Massena’s retreat’, <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 264.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> new Review<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Longmans’
                            <title>British Review and London Critical Journal</title>, which ran from 1811–1825. Southey considered contributing, but
                        did not. It was owned by John Weyland (1774–1854: <title>DNB</title>).</note> will interfere with the Quarterly, &amp; so far
                    as it succeeds, so far will it prevent<del>xx</del> the extension of our sale. I have not learnt who are the proprietors of it. –
                    Not <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> himself, for he wrote to me some eight or ten weeks ago, <del>xxx</del>
                    wishing me to bear a part in it, &amp; giving me to understand that it was set on foot by some independent M.P’s. – so at least I
                    understood his language. Of course I returned a refusal upon the ground of my previous connection with the Quarterly.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey’s reply to Longman does not appear to have survived; see also Southey to Grosvenor
                        Charles Bedford, 14 January 1811, Letter 1853.</note> – They have set out better than we did, tho they have a considerable
                    portion of heavy matter, &amp; their first article ought to have been in a very different tone.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>British Review and London Critical Journal</title>, 1 (March 1811), 1–17, a review of Edward Copleston (1776–1849;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Advice to a Young Reviewer, with a Specimen of the Art</title> (1807).</note><ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> is to be considered in two characters. as a party-writer &amp; as a critic.
                    his strength is in the former character, &amp; if I were to grapple with him in that <del>it would be</del> no great exertion
                    would be required to serve him as Orlando did the <del>xx</del> prize wrestler in As you like it.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>As You Like It</title>, Act 1, scene 2, where Orlando overcomes Charles, the champion wrestler.</note> As a critic he
                    requires the same sort of treatment which <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> bestowed upon the Della Cruscans,
                    – fix the dunces cap upon him &amp; then flog away without mercy.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gifford’s <title>The
                            Baviad</title> (1791) and <title>The Maeviad</title> (1795) had attacked the political and poetic principles of the Della
                        Cruscan school of poets whose leader was Robert Merry (1755–1798; <title>DNB</title>). Southey had attempted his own Della
                        Cruscan parodies, see, for example, his letter to Thomas Davis Lamb, 17–29 May 1793, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert
                            Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 49.</note> – Remember me to <ref target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">Mrs
                        Scott</ref> &amp; believe me</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent2"> R Southey</signed></closer><postscript><p>I hope you received your copy of Kehama.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>