<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2436</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3707</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Pennsylvania State
                        University Library.  Previously  published: Eliza Beshero-Bondar, &#8216;Nine New Letters of Robert Southey&#8217;, The Wordsworth
                            Circle, 30.1 (1999), 48&#8211;49. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2436" type="letter">
        <head>2436. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HoggJamesEttrick">James Hogg</ref> [fragment], <date when="1814-06-07">7 June
                        1814</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. James Hogg/ Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Grieve &amp; Scott&#8217;s/ Edinburgh<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: B/ 9 JUN/ 1814<lb />MS: Pennsylvania State
                        University Library<lb />Previously published: Eliza Beshero-Bondar, &#8216;Nine New Letters of Robert Southey&#8217;, <title>The Wordsworth
                            Circle</title>, 30.1 (1999), 48&#8211;49. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1814-06-07">June 7. 1814.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> On the next leaf you will find an inscription written at the request of an E Indian officer, high in the service,
                    for his mothers monument,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Major-General John Pech&#233; (d. 1823), of the East India Company&#8217;s
                        Army. He had been a neighbour of Southey&#8217;s at Keswick.</note> &#8211; but which was too little in the fashion of epitaphs to suit
                    his purpose. I have nothing else among my papers, but what has appeared years ago in the newspapers, &amp; probably found its way
                    into the Poetical Register, &#8211; which I believe is the title of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Davenports<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The author and publisher Richard Alfred Davenport (1776/7&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>). His <title>Poetical
                            Register</title> commenced in 1801. It contained new poems (some by Davenport himself) and reviews (often highly critical)
                        of other poetic publications.</note> yearly volume. I wish you success, &#8211; &amp; hope that the critical part of your work will
                    display a better spirit than is to be found in any contemporary journal.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hogg had written
                        to Southey on 4 June 1814 and asked if he would contribute poetry or a review to a new &#8216;poetical repository in Edin. &#8230; to
                        consist of original poetry and the remainder to be filled up with short reviews or characters of every <hi rend="ital">poetical</hi> work published in the interim&#8217;; see Douglas S. Mack et al (eds), <title>The Collected Letters of James
                            Hogg</title>, 2 vols (Edinburgh, 2004&#8211;2006), I, p. 181. He also invited contributions from Scott and Byron, amongst
                        others. However, his original plan of soliciting contributions changed and instead he published parodies of his eminent
                        contemporaries in the <title>Poetic Mirror: or, The Living Bards of Britain</title> (1816). Southey was sent up in &#8216;Peter of
                        Barnet&#8217; and &#8216;The Curse of the Laureate, Carmen Judiciale&#8217; (pp. 231&#8211;256).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">Ballantynes</ref> is likely to be a good <hi rend="ital">representative</hi>
                        opinion.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hogg had reported Ballantyne&#8217;s opinion of <title>Roderick</title>, which was
                        at press: &#8216;he [Ballantyne] says that there are more instances of strength of mind and bold fancy in it than perhaps any former
                        one of yours but that the narrative is so much the leading feature of the poem that all depends upon it and that it gets
                        rather slowly on and the beauties are sometimes half lost&#8217;; see Douglas S. Mack et al (eds), <title>The Collected Letters of
                            James Hogg</title>, 2 vols (Edinburgh, 2004&#8211;2006), I, p. 182.</note> You &lt;who&gt; live <hi rend="ital">in</hi> the
                    public can perhaps hardly understand how little I who live <hi rend="ital">out</hi> of it, think of it, or care for it
                        <del>xx</del> [MS missing] <del>xxxx written</del>. The one thing which I [MS missing] </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have seen some comments upon <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrays</ref> last attack<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jeffrey&#8217;s highly critical review of <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (1814), especially its Notes
                        attacking the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, in <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 22 (January 1814), 447&#8211;454. This advised
                        him to &#8216;shake off his foolish bays, and return to his fresh water as speedily as possible &#8230; we earnestly hope
                            [<title>Roderick</title>] was written before he came to his Laurel and Butt of Sherry&#8217; (454).</note> in the Times,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Times</title>, 7 April 1814.</note> &#8211; not the article itself. He gives me credit for incredible <del>xxx</del>
                    industry in selecting the passages quoted in my notes. I never read his Review, &#8211; I desired a Lady of my acquaintance<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, with the assistance of Wordsworth&#8217;s sister-in-law, Sarah Hutchinson
                        (1775&#8211;1835): see Southey to Mary Barker, [c. 15&#8211;17 December 1813], Letter 2348.</note> to borrow <del>one</del> two or three
                    volumes &amp; select a few flowers for my <del>xxxx</del> &lt;purpose&gt;; &#8211; she with the help of a female friend performed the
                    task one evening after tea in the course of an hour, &#8211; &amp; sent me the extracts in question, with others equally choice which
                    are reserved for a second course. <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jeffray</ref> will find me what
                    the pugilists call an ugly customer. As a critic he is perfectly safe from any attack on my part; &#8211; but as a politician &amp;
                    prophet. &#8211; I am writing the history of the War in the Peninsula,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>History of the
                            Peninsula War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> with every possible advantage of documents &amp; authority, &#8211; &amp; he may
                    depend upon <del>being</del> having his due praise there. It is not likely that I shall ever <del>xxxx xxx</del> hitch him into
                    verse, &#8211; but I will certainly [MS missing]</p>
        <p rend="indent6"> Epitaph<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;Epitaph&#8217; had been completed by March 1811. It was first
                    published in Southey&#8217;s <title>Minor Poems</title>, 3 vols (London, 1815), II, pp. 129&#8211;130</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent6"> _____</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> This to a Mothers sacred memory</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Her son hath hallowed. Absent many a year</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Far over sea, his sweetest dreams were still</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Of that dear voice which sooth&#8217;d his infancy;</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And after many a fight against the Moor,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And Malabar, &amp; that fierce cavalry</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Which he had seen covering the boundless plain</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Even to the utmost limit where the eye</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Could pierce the far horizon, his first thought</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> In safety, was of her who when she heard</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The tale of that days danger would retire</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And pour her pious gratitude to heaven</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> In prayers &amp; tears of joy. The lingering hour</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Of his return, long-lookd for, came at length.</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And full of hope he reach&#8217;d his native shore: &#8211; </l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Vain hope that puts its trust in mortal life!</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> For ere he came the number of her days</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Was full. O Reader what a world were this, &#8211; </l>
          <l rend="indent3"> How unendurable its weight, if they</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Whom Death hath sundered, did not meet again!</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>