<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1769</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3040</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and
                        Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1769" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1769" type="letter">
        <head>1769. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1810-04-08">8 April
                        1810</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/
                        Surry<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmarks: 10 oClock/ AP 11/ 1810 FNn; [partial] 11 AP 11/ 1810<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and
                        Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1810-04-08">April 8. 1810.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Five tea-chests will set off by the next carrier for <ref target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.
                        Picart<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bernard Picart (1673&#8211;1733), <title>Ceremonies et Coutoumes Religieuses de Tous
                            les Peuples du Monde</title> (1723&#8211;1743).</note> is very carefully packed, the volumes have layers of act-of-parliament
                    between them, &amp; are compleatly bolstered on all sides. The stuffage must not be thrown out without examination, as a number of
                    odd things are wrapt up in different holes &amp; corners. The key of your writing-case is <del>with</del> &lt;in&gt; the
                    mathematical instrument case. You will find the bundle of precious stones, &amp; the little Japan-box of Roman coins. I have put
                    &lt;up&gt; one or two Spanish duplicates, among them is the Cronica del Rey D Alfonso,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Probably Juan Nunez de Villasan (dates unknown), <title>Chronica del Muy Esclarecido Principe u Rey Don Alfonso el
                            Onzeno</title> (1551), no. 3336 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s Library.</note> which is a valuable book. This removal
                        <del>xxxx</del> gives me room on my shelves, &#8211; &amp; I was straitened for it before. General Roys book<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Possibly one of the books of maps produced by Major-General William Roy (1726&#8211;1790; <title>DNB</title>),
                        military engineer and founder of the Ordnance Survey.</note> must make a distinct parcel, &#8211; the boxes not being wide enough to
                    receive it. The damp has done it no permanent injury, but it must go into a binders hands. One other book is sent because I could
                    not trust it to a country binder to repair, &#8211; otherwise I should have kept it, &#8211; it is the volume containing Nicetas,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jerome Drexelius (1581&#8211;1638), <title>Nicetas, or the Triumph Over Incontinence</title> (1633);
                        no. 860 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s Library.</note> of which one of the covers is broken off. It had better be divided
                    when it is rebound.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> had directions about <ref target="people.html#BellJohn">John Bells</ref>
                    copy, together <del>xx</del> with that for the Envoy.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Walpole (1736&#8211;1810), Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Portugal, 1771&#8211;1800. Southey
                        was later asked to write his life.</note> Whatever copies you may wish to send out should be placed by <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> to my account, &#8211; do not think of paying for a single one, it would be giving
                    the price to the booksellers. It or half of the two thirds might find its way to me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Arrowsmith<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Arrowsmiths were a well-known family of London
                    cartographers, based in Soho Square. This may refer to <ref target="people.html#ArrowsmithAaron">Aaron Arrowsmith</ref>.</note> has
                    got possession of a map which has perfectly delighted him. The title travelled here for a translation. It is dedicated to the
                        Prince<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John VI (1767&#8211;1826), Prince Regent of Portugal 1799&#8211;1816, King of Portugal
                        1816&#8211;1826. He had become heir-apparent with the title Prince of Brazil in 1788.</note> by Luiz de Albuquerque de Mello,
                    Pereiras e Caceres, Governor of Matta-Grosso<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Luis de Albuquerque de Melo, Pereiras e
                        Caceres (1739&#8211;1797), Governor of Mato Grosso 1772&#8211;1788.</note> &#8211; but including nothing of later discovery or observation than
                    the year 1789. When next you are near Soho you will probably call &amp; see it. I received a letter yesterday in consequence of my
                    advertisement for books,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), I, p. vi.</note> &#8211; <del>xxx</del> it was from a person who had not the
                    list of desiderata before him, &amp; offered me the Mercurio Peruano,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Mercurio Peruano</title> (1790&#8211;1795), the first newspaper published in Peru.</note> which by means of John Allen,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Allen (1771&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), political and historical writer, especially on
                        Spanish topics, in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>.</note> I saw when last in town. I have however good hope that some of
                    the works will turn up.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been grievously disappointed about a history of Junots proceedings<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey eventually received the <title>Observador Portuguez</title> (1809) and reviewed it in <title>Quarterly Review</title>,
                        4 (August 1810), 1&#8211;24. Jean-Andoche Junot, Duc d&#8217;Abrantes (1771&#8211;1813) was the commander of the French invasion of Portugal in
                        1808.</note> which <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> sent for, &#8211; his agent delivered it to Sealy<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Sealy (d. 1821), Lisbon merchant and father of Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s first wife.</note>
                    instead of sending it by the proper ship, &amp; God knows when it will arrive. I wanted it immediately. Our supplies seem to be
                    quite cut off from the peninsula. There is neither tale or tidings of those which you requested Sealy to look out, nor of a
                    commission which I sent to Seville.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Is the Brazil wood what we now call log-wood?<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> The two are not identical &#8211;
                        logwood is native to Mexico and northern Central America.</note> I am provoked with myself for not making this obvious enquiry
                    sooner.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your blue curtains, by the help of good care &amp; tobacco, have been preserved from the moths since they came to
                    Cumberland, &#8211; the linings had suffered grievously, &#8211; but the damask I believe is uninjured. They have never been made any use of
                    here; I send also the table-cloth. &#8211; It is well the Inquisition never thought of searching your house, &#8211; that mathematical
                    instrument would certainly have past for an implement of magic. Will you have your guns sent? they arrived here in a wretched
                    state. I had them cleaned of their rust, <del>greas</del> oiled &amp; hung over the kitchen fire place. One of them has been once
                    fired since, &#8211; &amp; that is all the use to which they have been, or are ever likely to be applied here, unless you come yourself
                    to shoot grouse on the hills, &amp; cormorants on the Lake.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> makes a noble report of <ref target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward the
                        ninth</ref>. I long to see him &amp; lay the foundation of a friendship upon the solid basis of barley sugar.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have begun a poem upon Pelayo,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> An early version of <title>Roderick, the
                            Last of the Goths</title> (1814).</note> &amp; want to see four books all of fabulous notoriety. The Chronica del R D
                        Rodrigo.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Chronica del Rey Don Rodrigo con la Destruycion de Espana, y como los Moros la Ganaron</title> (1587); Southey
                        eventually obtained a copy, no. 3341 in the sale catalogue of his library. Southey needed this, along with the other books on
                        his list, for his new poem.</note> Chro. de S. Isidoro.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Isidore of Seville (c.
                        560&#8211;636), archbishop who was later canonised. His <title>Chronica Majora</title> covers events from the creation to 615, with
                        particular emphasis on Spain.</note> Chron. Sarracina by Pedro de Corral.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro de
                        Corral (fl. C14th/C15th), <title>Cronica Sarracina</title>, written in the 15th century, it dealt with the Moorish occupation
                        of Spain.</note> &amp; the Conde de Moras Hist of Toledo.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro de Rojas, Conde de
                        Mora (c.1585&#8211;1658), <title>Historia de la Imperial Ciudad de Toledo</title> (1654&#8211;1663). Southey&#8217;s copy was no. 3630 in the
                        sale catalogue of his library.</note> Will you make enquiry for these when you see the <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Hollands</ref>. There is a copy of the second somewhere in this country, for I once mist it from a catalogue.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>