<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 4: 1810-1815. </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2125</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3396</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        47888.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 344&#8211;348 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2125" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2125" type="letter">
        <head>2125. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith
                    Southey</ref>, <date when="1812-07-23">23 July 1812</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To Mrs Southey/
                        Keswick.<lb />Endorsement: July 23 1812/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey to
                            M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47888<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 344&#8211;348 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>Settle.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1812-07-23"> July 23. 1812.</date> Thursday evening</dateline>
          <salute>My Dear Edith</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> We left S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Helens after an early breakfast on
                    Tuesday, with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> in company, looked
                    at Raby &amp; Barnard Castle, &amp; made our way to the porters lodge at Rokeby,
                    near that fine bridge over which we past in the rain. A sturdy old woman,
                    faithful to her orders, refused us admittance, saying that if we were going to
                    the Hall we might go in, but if not we must not enter the grounds, nor would she
                    let us in till we had promised to call at the Hall. Accordingly, against the
                    grain in observance of this promise to the house I went, having first enquired
                    if <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">W. Scott</ref> was there, requested
                    permission to see the grounds. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Bacon Sawrey Morritt (1771&#8211;1843;
                        <title>DNB</title>), traveller, classical scholar and member of the Society
                        of Dilettanti. He had gained the nickname &#8216;Troy&#8217; for his endeavours to prove
                        that the city had been a real place, not an invention of Homer. He owned the
                        Rokeby estate, where he entertained a large circle, including Humphry Davy
                        and Walter Scott.</note> was not within &#8211; but the permission was granted;
                    having received it I left my name, &amp; in ten minutes after the footman came
                    running to say we might see the House also &#8211; &amp; we might fish if we pleased.
                    I excused myself from seeing the House saying we were going on, &amp; returning
                    a due number of thanks &amp;c. But presently we met M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp;
                        M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> M.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Katherine Stanley (d. 1815), she had married Morritt on 19 November
                        1803.</note> in the walks by the river side; &amp; were as you may suppose
                    obliged to dine &amp; sleep there, &#8211; this hospitality being so prest upon us
                    that I could not continue to refuse it without rudeness. Behold the Lion there
                    in a den perfectly worthy of him eating grapes &amp; peaches &amp; drinking
                    claret. The grounds are the finest things of the kind I have ever seen. A little
                    in the manner of Downton<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Downton
                        Castle, near Ludlow, the gothic revival house built in c. 1774&#8211;1778 by
                        Richard Payne Knight (1751&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
          <del>a little</del> more resembling Lowther,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lowther castle, ancestral home of the Earls of
                        Lonsdale.</note> but the Greta at Rokeby affords <del>xxxx</del> finer
                    scenery than either. There is a summer house overlooking it, the inside of which
                    was ornamented by Mason<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Mason
                        (1725&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>), poet and garden designer.</note> the poet:
                    one day he set the whole family to work in cutting out ornaments in coloured
                    paper from antique designs, directing the whole himself. It is still in good
                    preservation &amp; <del>xxx xxx</del> will doubtless be preserved as long as a
                    rag remains. This river in 1771 rose in the most extraordinary manner during
                    what is still called the great flood. There is a bridge close by the summer
                    house, at least sixty feet above the water, against this bridge &amp; its side
                    the river piled up an immense dam of trees and rubbish which it had swept before
                    it. <del>xxx the water</del> At length down comes a stone of such a size that it
                    knocked down Greta Bridge by the way, knocked away the whole mass of trees,
                    carried off the second bridge, &amp; lodged some little way beyond it upon the
                    bank, breaking into three or four pieces. Playfair<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The mathematician and geologist John Playfair
                        (1748&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>).</note> the other day estimated the weight
                    of the stone at about 78 tons, &#8211; the most wonderful instance he says he had ever
                    heard of, of the power of water. Before this stone came down, one of the trees
                    had blocked out an old man &amp; his wife who inhabited a room under the summer
                    house, &#8211; the branches broke their windows, &amp; a great bough barred the door.
                    meantime the water, usually some 40 feet below, was on a level with
                        <del>them</del> it. The people of the house came to their relief &amp; sawed
                    the boughs off to let them out, &amp; the windows remain as they were left &#8211; a
                    memorial of this most extraordinary flood.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Morritts father<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Sawrey Morritt (1738&#8211;1791).</note> bought the house
                    of Sir Thomas Robinson, well known in his day by the names of Long Robinson,
                    &amp; Long Sir Thomas.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Thomas
                        Robinson 1st Baronet (1702/3&#8211;1777; <title>DNB</title>), collector and
                        amateur architect. A proponent of neo-Palladianism, in the late 1720s he
                        rebuilt the house at Rokeby (to his own design). However, financial problems
                        led him to sell the Rokeby estate in 1769. Robinson was extremely tall,
                        hence the nicknames.</note> You may recollect a good epitaph upon this
                    man.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> Unlike the Robinson shall be my song,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> It shall be witty, &#8211; &amp; it sha&#8217;nt be long.</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">Long Sir Thomas found a portrait of Richardson<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The novelist and printer Samuel Richardson
                        (bap. 1689, d. 1761; <title>DNB</title>).</note> in the house, &#8211; thinking
                        M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Richardson a very unfit personage to be suspended in
                    effigy among Lords Ladies &amp; Baronets, he ordered <del>xx</del> &lt;a&gt;
                    painter to put him on the <del>xxxx</del> star &amp; blue ribband, &amp; then
                    christened the picture Sir Robert Walpole.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Walpole, 1st Earl of Orford (1676&#8211;1745; Prime Minister
                        1721&#8211;1742; <title>DNB</title>).</note> You will easily imagine that <del>xxx
                        xxxxxx</del> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Morritt will not suffer <del>then</del>
                    the portrait to be restored. This however is not the most extraordinary picture
                    in the room. &#8211; That is one of Long Sir T&#8217;s intended improvements, &#8211; representing
                    the river, which now flows the finest rocky bed I ever beheld, &#8211; metamorphosd by
                    four dams into a piece of water as smooth &amp; as still as a canal, &amp;
                    elevated by the same operation so as to <del>xx</del> appear at the end of a
                    smooth shaven green. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M. <del>xxxx</del> &lt;shows&gt;
                    this with great glee &#8211; he has brought there from our country the stone fern,
                    &amp; the osmunda regalis.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        &#8216;royal fern&#8217;, a deciduous plant and one of the largest ferns found in
                        Europe.</note> Among his pictures is a Madonna by Guido,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Guido Reni (1575&#8211;1642), Italian Baroque
                        painter.</note> he mentioned this to a Master of a College at Cambridge,
                    whose name I am sorry &lt;that&gt; I have forgotten, for the gentleman in reply
                    pointed a picture above representing an Aunt of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Morritts
                    (I believe) dressd in the very pink of the mode, &amp; askd if that Lady was the
                    Madonna.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am sorry too that I forgot to ask if this was the Lady whose
                    needle work is in the house.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anna
                        Eliza Morritt (1726&#8211;1797). She created large needlework &#8216;paintings&#8217;, still
                        on display at Rokeby.</note> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M. had an Aunt who
                    taught Miss Linwood.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Linwood
                        (1755&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), artist in needlework.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> thought her
                    pictures quite as good. In one respect they may possibly be <del>xxxx</del>
                    better, &#8211; for she made her stitches athwart &amp; across, exactly as the strokes
                    of the original pictures. Miss L. (M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M says) makes her
                    stitches all in one way. This Lady had great difficulty about her worsteds,
                    &amp; could only suit herself by buying damaged <add>xxxxx</add> quantities,
                    thus obtaining shades which would else have been unobtainable. The colours fly,
                    &amp; in order to preserve them as long as possible, prints are fitted in to the
                    frames to serve as screens. The art cost her her life, tho at an advanced age.
                    It brought on a dead palsy <del>xx</del> occasioned by holding her hands so
                    continually in an elevated position working at the canvas. <del>xx xxx</del>.
                    Her last picture is hardly finished, the needle M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M. says
                    literally dropt from her hands, &#8211; death had been creeping on her for twelve
                    years.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Next morning we took chaise for two <del>xxx</del> stages &#8211; to
                    Richmond &amp; Leyburn. The former is in situation like Durham, with a little to
                    remind me of Ludlow, &amp; a little, in its air of antiquity, of Glastonbury: &#8211;
                    certainly one of the fine things of England. Easeby Abbey is near, on the banks
                    of the river, &#8211; a very fine ruin. To Leyburn over a large tract of newly
                    inclosed country, then we entered upon Wensley dale, one of the loveliest tracts
                    I ever saw. We walked up the dale 18 miles to Hawes, leaving Bolton Castle on
                    our right &amp; seeing the falls of the Ure at Aysgarth (which <ref target="people.html#ErskineHenry">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                    Erskine</ref> recommended us to see) &amp; leaving the little town of
                    Askrigg on our right. At the higher end of the valley, almost every field has an
                    out house in it, for housing the hay &amp; the cattle, &#8211; this gives a most
                    singular appearance to the country. Walked from Hawes a mile &amp; half to Ardra
                    Scar, &#8211; a waterfall which I have no room to describe here. Took chaise that
                    night 17 miles to Ingleton Walks, the morning a road of 13 miles to the caves
                    &amp; Thornton force. &amp; then 10 more to Settle. Tomorrow we walk to Malham
                    &amp; Gordale Scar a round of 14, &#8211; back to Ingleton (weather permitting) &amp;
                    chaise it to Lancaster. Our future movements depend upon the time for crossing
                    the sands, so that I cannot say where our sleeping place will be &#8211; only that we
                    shall go to Ulverston, see <ref target="places.html#FurnessAbbey">Furness Abbey</ref>, make for Irton, &amp; come home by
                    Wasdale over the Stye, &#8211; probably at home on Monday night. Our feet are sound
                    &amp; we are as well as could be wishd, &amp; have thus far been as fortunate. I
                    have finishd this since supper, having supt nobly. It was time, yesterday the
                    only animal food which I took was three quarters of a fish at supper, out of a
                    pie &amp; I had none today till supper: but eggs &amp; milk, &amp; tea &amp;
                    toast are little things to walk upon. God bless you. RS.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> will only stay three days I
                        believe.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> over ... I believe:
                        written at top of fol. 1r.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>